borrowed tomb, we're here today because he rose,
conquering sin, death, and the grave,
and only through that sacrifice
can your account be settled.
Only through that sacrifice can my account be settled,
can anyone's account be settled.
And I'm thankful that song said I settled it long ago,
it was on August 31st, 1997, for me,
that I recognized I was a sinner and I was guilty
and I was on my way to a Christless eternity
in a place called hell or the lake of fire,
and I understood that Jesus, he was the only savior,
and he loved me so much that he died for me,
he took my place, and he was willing to offer me
a free gift, that gift of eternal life,
through his precious blood, and I repented of my sin,
I confessed that Jesus is Lord,
and I asked him to be the savior of my life,
and on that day, something amazing happened,
the old account was settled.
It was settled long ago, it's under the blood, amen?
It doesn't mean that I've never sinned since then,
oh, no, no, no, it doesn't mean that,
it just simply means I'm forgiven, and I'm heaven-bound,
God is my father, I'm his child,
what a wonderful, wonderful truth.
Listen, if your account this morning,
you said, I didn't even know I had an account
when I got here this morning, well, you do,
and if you're not sure that your account's been settled,
you can have it settled today,
and that's a wonderful truth of God's word,
and in fact, Paul said to the believers in Corinth,
today is the day of salvation, don't put it off,
no man knoweth what might be on tomorrow, life is short.
I said to someone yesterday, we're out knocking some doors,
and I was talking to someone,
and I shared with them the truth of eternity,
and they said they weren't sure of heaven,
but they knew that death was certain,
and we actually referenced that catastrophe
that took place just a few days ago,
that bridge up in Baltimore, and I said,
you know, those people, they didn't think
they were gonna die that day, there's a lot of people,
they don't know, listen, you know not when you're gonna die,
our life is but a vapor, it appears for a little time,
and then, it's gone, it's gone, no man knoweth the hour
that we're going to die, no man knoweth the hour
that Jesus is coming again, but I tell you today
that if you're under the sound of my voice,
you can be saved today, if you're already saved,
I hope you're rejoicing in it,
and knowing that I'm heaven-bound,
and man, what a wonderful truth that is,
Matthew chapter 28, this morning,
that was all for free, amen,
no part of my sermon whatsoever, it was just free,
I was sitting there listening to that song this morning,
and God was just working in my heart,
and encouraging me, and I hope he encouraged you as well,
Matthew chapter 28, near the beginning
of the earthly ministry of the Lord Jesus Christ,
Jesus made this declaration,
destroy this temple, and in three days, I will raise it up,
you can read that in John chapter two, in verse number 19,
the context makes it abundantly clear
that Jesus is speaking about his body,
his body is the temple, he's speaking about his death,
and his glorious resurrection,
in fact, the gospel of John references back
all the way to chapter two, at the end,
after the resurrection, remembering what Christ said,
in fact, as we'll note here,
even in the passage of scripture
that we'll be studying this morning,
that even those that were against Christ,
they heard those words, and they understood
what he meant with regard to a resurrection,
we find that on three occasions here
in the gospel of Matthew,
that Jesus told his disciples that he would be put to death,
but then told them this,
on the third day, he would rise again,
we find in Matthew 28 is where our text is,
but I want you to quickly look at those three proclamations,
in Matthew chapter 16 is the first one
that we find in the gospel of Matthew,
again, three occasions here,
leading up to the death of Christ,
and in Matthew 16, and verse number 21,
we find it's in this text of scripture
that Jesus had asked the question,
whom do men say that I am?
Someone told Holly and Lena
when they're knocking doors yesterday,
they were a different world religion,
and they said, oh, we believe everything the same,
we believe everything the same,
we just don't believe what you think about Jesus,
well, that makes a world of difference, amen,
because Jesus said that he is God in flesh,
and that only through him, I, Jesus said,
in the way, the truth, and the life,
no man cometh unto the Father but by me,
and what a great declaration,
and so Jesus says, whom do men say that I am?
Some say that you're John the Baptist,
some say that you're one of the prophets,
and so on and so forth,
and Jesus then looks at his disciples,
and he says, whom say ye that I am?
Peter, I love Peter, we can relate with Peter,
in fact, Peter's the one that the one record
in the gospels, I think it's Mark's record,
says go and tell the disciples, and Peter, I love it,
because Peter was the one that denied the Lord,
and God still loved him, and God was still gonna use him,
and he did, he used him greatly,
but Peter stands up, and he says, thou art the Christ,
the son of the living God,
we find that great declaration that is made,
and Jesus, after giving some further instruction
in verse 21, it says, from that time forth began Jesus
to show unto his disciples how that he must go
unto Jerusalem, and suffer many things of the elders,
and chief priests, and scribes, notice, and be killed,
but notice, and be raised again the third day.
In Matthew chapter 17, in verse number 23,
we note the second reference here,
in verse 22, we'll read it, it says,
and while they abode in Galilee,
Jesus said unto them, the son of man shall be betrayed
into the hands of men, and they shall kill him,
and the third day he shall be raised again,
and they were exceeding sorry.
In chapter 20, and we notice this third record here,
I want you to begin reading with me in verse 17,
in Matthew 20, it says, and Jesus going up to Jerusalem
took the 12 disciples apart in the way,
and said unto them, behold, we go up to Jerusalem,
and the son of man shall be betrayed
unto the chief priests, and unto the scribes,
and they shall condemn him to death,
and shall deliver him to the Gentiles
to mock, and to scourge, and to crucify him,
and the third day he shall rise again.
As we come to our text of scripture in Matthew 28,
we're mindful of the resurrection morning.
Of course, every Sunday we gather
because we serve a risen Savior.
The reason that we meet on Sunday
is because it's the first day,
and it's the resurrection day.
Every Sunday we meet because we serve a risen Savior,
and what a blessing to understand that.
Not only did he rise, conquering sin, death, and the grave,
but he promised that he would come again.
We mentioned that a little bit
during the 7 a.m. service this morning,
and the promise of his soon return
is as sure as the promise of his resurrection.
We find that he made these statements
as we just looked at those three occasions
in the gospel of Matthew,
and then we come to resurrection morning, and guess what?
The tomb is empty.
Why?
Because he always does what he says he's gonna do,
and he said on the third day he would rise again,
and he says to us as New Testament believers
that we also understand that he will come again,
and I'm looking forward with great anticipation
to his imminent return.
Maranatha, they would say, in the New Testament.
We read it in 1 Corinthians 16.
The Lord cometh, amen?
The Lord cometh, and we see that to be the case.
The title for the message this morning,
the grave could not hold him.
The grave could not hold him.
I just wanna read verses five and six
in Matthew's gospel, the 28th chapter,
and then we're gonna consider three things this morning
about this wonderful resurrection of our Savior.
Notice in verse five,
and the angel answered and said unto the women,
fear not ye, for I know that you seek Jesus,
which was crucified.
Notice verse six.
He is not here, for he is risen,
and you see those three words, as he said.
See the place where the Lord lay.
He is not here, for he is risen from the dead.
And behold, he goeth before you into Galilee there.
Shall you see him, lo, I have told you.
We find that here on resurrection morning,
the ladies assemble and they go.
They have their spices for the preparation of the body,
and we find that they arrive,
and we didn't read the entirety of the text.
We'll go through it as we get
through the message this morning.
But we find that they arrive,
and the stone is rolled away, the tomb is empty,
and the angel announced the resurrection of our Savior.
It says, why seek ye the living among the dead?
In Luke's gospel,
we looked at that at seven o'clock this morning,
and we find this wonderful proclamation.
He is not here, for he is risen, as he said.
See, look at the invitation.
See the place where the Lord lay, and then go quickly.
Not only was an invitation to come and see,
but then there was an instruction of go and tell.
And we're living in that era of go and tell.
Go tell people that you serve a risen Savior,
and what a wonderful truth it is.
Let's consider three thoughts this morning
as we consider the burial and resurrection
of this glorious event of our wonderful Savior.
Number one, if you're taking notes this morning,
consider the sealed tomb.
Consider the sealed tomb.
In Matthew 27, I want you to begin reading with me
in verse 57.
We don't last week in Matthew 27, verse 27 through 50,
and we looked at the death of Christ,
and we said that the death of Christ.
was a violent death. We said that it was a vicarious death, but it was also a voluntary
death and a victorious death. We looked at that last week, and this morning as we look
at verse 57, we begin looking at the burial that is recorded for us in Matthew 27. The
Bible says when the even was come, there came a rich man of Arimathea named Joseph, who
also himself was Jesus' disciple. He went to Pilate, and he begged the body of Jesus.
Then Pilate commanded the body to be delivered. When Joseph had taken the body, he wrapped
it in a clean linen cloth, and laid it in his own new tomb, which he had hewn out in
the rock. And he rolled a great stone to the door of the sepulcher and departed. And there
was Mary Magdalene and the other Mary sitting over against the sepulcher. Now the next day
that followed, the day of the preparation, the chief priest and the Pharisees came together
unto Pilate.
Now let me pause here just for a moment. These ladies, they saw what took place, the tomb,
the place where Jesus was laid. They understood what Joseph of Arimathea did in putting that
linen cloth in verse 59 upon the body, and then putting that stone there. And the Bible
tells us that on the next day, the religious leaders, it says the Pharisees and the chief
priest, and understand this morning that religion never saves anyone. These people were religious,
the chief priest and the Pharisees. I mean, they knew the Old Testament. At least they
knew some of the Old Testament. They didn't understand because Jesus says, search the
Scriptures, for they are they which testify of me. And we find that Jesus, in Luke's gospel,
in the chapter 24, he begins with Moses and all the prophets, and tells those men, or
excuse me, those disciples on the road to Emmaus, all things concerning himself. These
religious leaders, they were lost. Religion never saved anyone. Their account was not
settled. They were trusting in their religion. You know, the same is true today. Many people
are trusting in a religion. Many people are disgusted with religion. You talk to people
today all around, listen, I'm glad I don't have religion. I have a relationship with
the Lord Jesus Christ. Amen? It's not religion. It's a relationship. And I'm so thankful for
that. These religious leaders, they come to Pilate. Notice what they say in verse 63.
It's almost hard to read it, to be honest with you, how they refer to my Savior and
my God. It says, saying, Sir, we remember that that deceiver said, while he was yet
alive after three days, I will rise again. I'm thankful this morning that our God cannot
lie. He's not a deceiver. Amen? That's how they refer to him. But it's interesting that
they refer to him as a deceiver, but yet they reference what they, what he said, what they
heard him say, and it brought great concern to them. Now, they call him a deceiver, but
they really think that what he said was going to come true. Isn't that interesting? It says
that they say to Pilate, command therefore, in verse 64, that the sepulcher be made sure
until the third day. Lest his disciples come by night and steal him away, and say unto
the people, he is risen from the dead. So the last error shall be worse than the first.
I know that they explain it this way, and this is the record that we've been given.
This is what they said to Pilate. But I think down deep, they really knew that it didn't
require the disciples to come steal him away. They could have just dealt with the disciples
if they chose, or thought that was the only concern. We find that Pilate says to them
in verse 65, ye have a watch. Go your way. Notice these words, make it. What's it? Well,
the sepulcher. Make it as sure as ye can. We're talking about here, considering the
sealed tomb. So they went, after they hear that response from Pilate, and they made the
sepulcher sure, sealing the stone and setting a watch. They did everything they could in
their power. But the grave, the grave could not keep him. It could not hold him. We sang
that last song. It's a wonderful song. I love the third verse. He tore the bars away.
Man, isn't that wonderful? Up from the grave he arose with a mighty triumph for his foes.
What a savior we have. And we find that when we consider the sealed tomb, and we see the
efforts of the religious leaders, and we see the fact that Pilate authorized them. He said,
you have a watch. Make it as sure as you can. And they did. They did everything in their
power to seal that tomb and to set a watch. But it was all in vain. It was all in vain.
Because we find, if we read into the 28th chapter, of course, that he rose. We'll deal
with that in just a moment. But we see the sealed tomb. I want you to consider not only
the sealed tomb, but I want you to consider number two, the saddened disciples. There's
a sealed tomb, but there are some sad disciples. I want you to consider, just for a moment,
all of the emotions that have taken place in these preceding days. I want you to understand,
as each gospel record gives us much information, really, with regard to the last week of the
life of Jesus Christ on earth, his earthly ministry. And we find, as the gospels provide
for us the record, and we come to those last moments of his physical life here on earth
before he would go to the cross of Calvary, that the suffering that he dealt with and
all that took place. And he said that they would be scattered. And guess what? They were.
We find that Peter was the one that was watching from afar. He was the one that denied during
the trials and all that was taking place. And we find that there were some saddened
disciples. These events that took place were impactful. You know, God's made us as emotional
people. There are times that we deal with various circumstances in life and there are
times that we deal with our emotions. And we might be sad with regard to a certain circumstance
that we're dealing with. And I notice that there's some saddened disciples. Look over
at Mark's gospel, if you will. Look at Mark 16. We find in Mark 16, again, verses 1-8
would record for us the record of the resurrection that morning when they went to the tomb. It's
in verse 7 where we see it says, go your way, tell his disciples and Peter. I referenced
that a moment ago. But I want you to look at verse number 9 with me. Now when Jesus
was risen early the first day of the week, he appeared first to Mary Magdalene out of
whom he had cast seven devils. And she went and told them that had been with him, notice
what it says, as they mourned and wept. There's some saddened disciples with regard to what
had transpired. They were there and they watched the trials, the mockings and all that
Christ suffered. They were there when he suffered on that cross at Calvary. They understood,
the Bible tells us, of those that watched as the tomb in which Jesus was placed. And
the Bible says that Mary Magdalene comes and it tells them, those that were there, and
they mourned and wept. They were sad. Luke chapter 24, the Bible tells us this, look
over in that passage if you will. We'll be in Luke 24 a couple of times here this morning
but I just want to look at the beginning and then we'll get to the end of Luke 24 as we
go through the message this morning. As we look at the beginning of this portion of scripture
after the resurrection is described for us in verses 1-12, we come to verse 13 and the
Bible says, behold two of them went that same day to a village called Emmaus, which was
from Jerusalem about three score furlongs. It's almost 7 miles, 6.8 miles. It says that
they talked together of all these things which had happened. All these things, that's these
last few days and the death and the burial and all of those things. And it says in verse
15, and it came to pass that while they communed together in reason, notice this, Jesus himself
drew near and went with them. But their eyes were holden that they should not know him.
Verse 17, it says this, that he, Jesus, said unto them, these two that are walking, what
manner of communications are these that ye have one to another as ye walk and are sad?
Notice what they say. Notice their response. And the one of them whose name was Cleopas
answering said unto him, art thou only a stranger in Jerusalem and hast not known the things
which are come to pass there in these days? And he, Jesus, said unto them, what things?
Isn't that wonderful? I love it. And they said unto him, concerning Jesus of Nazareth,
which was a prophet mighty indeed and word before God and all the people and how the
chief priest and our rulers delivered him to be
condemned to death and have crucified him.
But we trusted that it had been he
which should have redeemed Israel.
Beside all this, today is the third day
since these things were done.
Yea, and certain women also of our company
made us astonished, which were early at the sepulcher.
And when they found not his body,
they came saying that they had also seen a vision of angels
which said he was alive.
We find that the Bible tells us in verse 13
that it was that same day.
So they hear the announcement, but they walk back to Emmaus.
As they're walking back to Emmaus, they're sad.
They're talking, they're having these communications
and Jesus joins them.
They don't know that it's Jesus.
And he says what things and they explain it.
And see, you understand even as they said
that they had thought, they trusted
that it had been he, Jesus,
which should have redeemed Israel.
See, many of the Jewish people,
they were looking for deliverance from Rome.
They were looking for a kingdom
to be established at that time.
But see, they didn't recognize
that what they first needed to be redeemed from,
their greatest need of deliverance was not from Rome,
but was redemption from their sin.
And Jesus, through his death, burial and resurrection,
he was providing redemption for their greatest need.
They believe that their greatest need
was deliverance from Rome.
But in fact, their greatest need
was deliverance from their sin.
Today, the same is true.
There are many people that have ideas
of what they really need.
If I could just get this, or if I could just get that,
if I could have, if I could so on and so forth,
this is my greatest need.
Can I tell you, the greatest need of every human being
is to be delivered from their sin.
That's the greatest need.
And I tell you this morning
that if you're saved by the blood of Christ,
if you've been saved, you've been redeemed,
you have your need met in Jesus.
That's the only way to have that need met,
is through the Lord Jesus Christ.
And here we find that they had trusted,
they had a belief, but Jesus is walking.
We're gonna come back to Luke 24 here
in just a few moments.
But I want you to consider,
as we think about the emotional time for these disciples,
and I love the fact that even in the midst
of these emotional, sad times,
that Jesus comes along them, alongside them.
See, God knows everything that we deal with.
There are times in life,
see, these two are talking amongst themselves,
and they're sad.
Sometimes we talk amongst ourselves and we're sad, right?
We have problems, we have issues,
we have circumstances, trials, and so on and so forth.
And we can find somebody to talk to,
to confide in, whatever word we wanna use,
and we can have those communications amongst ourselves.
But I'm thankful that Jesus can come along
and he can help us.
See, we need to learn to tell it to Jesus.
Tell it to Jesus.
We have the privilege of going to God in prayer.
And we can do that at any moment for anything,
knowing that he hears us and that he'll help us
and he sustains us.
And Jesus comes alongside them and he's walking
and he's talking with them.
And we'll see some more of what this conversation holds
in just a few moments.
But I want you to consider, there's a sealed tomb.
There are some saddened disciples.
But I want you to understand this morning, number three,
I'm so thankful this morning to serve a risen Savior.
I know many have said it.
We've been singing about it.
We mentioned it during the 7 a.m. service.
We had some testimonies and several testified
of just what a blessing it is to know
that we serve a risen Savior.
And certainly it is.
You ask me how I know he lives?
Oh man, we could tell you on and on and on.
He is a very present help in the time of trouble.
Listen, he's a friend that's to get closer
than any brother.
He is my advocate, my intercessor.
He's my friend, my guide.
He is my shepherd.
I mean, he takes care of me.
He provides for me.
I pray to him.
I commune with him.
Man, he is alive.
He says in Revelation that he is the one that was dead,
but now is alive, and he is alive forevermore.
And we can rejoice and be glad in that truth this morning.
And we find as we consider his spectacular resurrection,
as we find that each gospel record records this for us.
We'll go back to Matthew chapter 28
and read those verses that lead up to the text
that I read to begin our message this morning.
But notice in verse number one of Matthew 28,
the Bible says this.
In the end of the Sabbath, as it began to dawn
toward the first day of the week,
came Mary Magdalene and the other Mary
to see the sepulcher.
And behold, there was a great earthquake,
for the angel of the Lord descended from heaven
and came and rolled back the stone from the door
and sat upon it.
His countenance was like lightning,
and his raiment white as snow.
And for fear of him, the keepers.
What were those keepers doing there?
Well, remember, that's the sealed tomb, remember?
Those are the ones that said,
the chief priests and the Pharisees,
hey, Pilate, we need to make this as sure as we can.
He said, you have a watch.
Make it as sure as you can.
And the Bible tells us that they sealed the stone
and then they set a watch,
but it tells us in verse number four,
for fear of him, the keepers did shake
and became as dead men.
The angel answered and said unto the women,
fear not ye, for I know that ye seek Jesus,
which was crucified.
He is not here, for he is risen, as he said.
Come, see the place where the Lord lay.
Go quickly and tell his disciples
that he is risen from the dead.
And behold, he goeth before you into Galilee.
There shall you see him.
Lo, I have told you.
And they departed quickly from the sepulcher.
Notice this, with fear and great joy.
There's some mixed emotions.
And did run to bring his disciples word.
As they went to tell his disciples,
behold, Jesus met them saying, all hail.
They came and held him by the feet and worshiped him.
Then said Jesus unto them, be not afraid.
Go tell my brethren that they go into Galilee
and there shall they see me.
We find that as we consider the spectacular resurrection
of our wonderful Savior,
that not only did he rise,
conquering sin, death, and the grave,
but we find that he appeared to many.
Acts says it this way, that many infallible proofs.
We read 1 Corinthians 15 this morning
in the 7 a.m. service.
And we mentioned in that text of scripture
of all of those that were eyewitnesses
of the resurrected Christ.
And Paul adds in there, and above 500 at once.
Many of whom were still alive
at the time of the writing of 1 Corinthians.
Some had died, but many were still alive.
But I wanna focus just for a few moments here
as we finish our message this morning
on three personal times in which Jesus appeared
to an individual, to a group of people.
And I want you to look at these,
and I want you to see how Christ ministers to his people.
The first one, we look in John chapter 20.
And I want you to see as Jesus had risen from the dead,
how he appeared to Mary.
To Mary.
In John chapter number 20, again,
the record of the resurrection is given to us
in verses one through nine.
But beginning in verse number 10,
we begin to see this text with regard to Mary
being there in the garden.
And the Bible says in verse number 10,
and the disciples went,
then the disciples went away unto their own home.
But Mary stood without at the sepulcher weeping.
And as she wept, she stooped down
and looked into the sepulcher,
and seeth two angels in white sitting,
the one at the head and the other at the feet,
where the body of Jesus had lain, past tense,
because he rose.
They said unto her, woman, why weepest thou?
She saith unto them, because they have taken away my Lord,
and I know not where they have laid him.
When she had thus said, she turned herself back
and saw Jesus standing.
But notice what the Bible says,
and knew not that it was Jesus.
Jesus saith unto her, woman, why weepest thou?
Whom seekest thou?
She, Mary, supposing him to be the gardener,
saith unto him, sir, if thou have borne him,
hence tell me where thou hast laid him,
and I will take him away.
And then Jesus says her name, Mary, Mary.
You see it in verse number 16.
Isn't it wonderful, he knows our name,
and he speaks her name.
And the Bible says that she turned herself
and saith unto him, Rabboni, which is to say, master.
Jesus saith unto her, touch me not,
for I am not yet ascended to my father,
but go to my brethren and say unto them,
I ascend unto my father and your father,
and to my God and your God.
Mary Magdalene came and told the disciples
that she had seen the Lord
and that he had spoken these things unto her.
Isn't that wonderful?
Mary was sitting in the garden there.
She's weeping and she's distraught.
She doesn't know, she can't make sense
of all of the circumstances,
all of the things that have happened.
And we find, as we've mentioned already,
as we looked in several of the gospels,
we mentioned this at seven o'clock service this morning
in Luke's gospel, remember that Jesus said this.
then they remembered his sayings."
All of those emotions that were taking place, listen, sometimes in the time of your greatest
difficulty, you are prone to forget the wonderful promises that God has given you.
You're prone to forget.
He said, remember.
We find that she's there and she's weeping and she's stooped down and she's looking in
and yes, there's some interaction and she explains, but then she sees who she thinks
might be a gardener and she asked this question, just tell me where you put them and I'll take
them away and then he speaks her name.
You know, Jesus knew what Mary was going through.
He knew where she was and he came to her.
Isn't that awesome?
And he spoke her name.
Listen, we have a God who is personal, who knows our very needs.
He knows your heart this morning.
He knows what you're dealing with.
He knows the heartaches that we have.
We don't have to get so consumed with those things.
No, we need to get consumed with our Savior.
And all of a sudden we get more consumed with our Savior.
The things of this world, even the problems and the trials, I don't pretend that they
go away, but they're not as significant.
They're not as big.
Why?
Because my God's in control.
My God has a plan.
My God knows where I am and he knows what I'm dealing with and he comes alongside and
he ministers.
What a blessing.
In Luke 24, we've mentioned already as we've read through part of this passage, but I want
you to notice the ministry of Christ to these two disciples on the road to Emmaus.
They had explained to him what they had anticipated.
Cleopas is speaking and we find that the Bible will pick up the text in verse 25 as Jesus
is now going to respond to them.
He says, O fools in slow of heart to believe all that the prophets have spoken.
Ought not Christ to have suffered these things and to enter into his glory?
And then the Bible tells us in verse 27, beginning at Moses, and all the prophets, he, Christ,
expounded unto them in all the scriptures the things concerning himself.
You know, sometimes when we think about the difficulties that we deal with, being sad
as we mention these, Jesus comes alongside them, but you know what he does?
He uses his word.
You know what we need in the time of difficulty?
We don't necessarily need to pick up the phone and just start calling whoever and talking
and trying to, no, no, we need to get into the word.
Let God minister to us.
He started in Moses and the prophets and he's going to expound to them all things concerning
himself.
Ought not Christ to have suffered these things and to enter into his glory?
Listen, you're sad because of these events, but these events were foretold.
It was known that Christ was going to suffer and bleed and die, but he was going to rise
again.
It had been told to them, not only in the Old Testament, but Jesus himself had spoken
these words to the disciples.
The Bible says in verse 28, and they drew nigh unto the village whither they went, and
he made as though he would have gone further.
Jesus was going to keep on going, but they constrained him.
Listen, there's a message there.
You have to invite Jesus in.
You have to desire, listen, he doesn't force himself upon anyone.
The Bible talks about the disciples in one of the miracles when they're toiling and rowing.
They're in the midst of a storm and they're toiling and rowing and Jesus is going to walk
by.
But they invited him into the ship.
It made all the difference when they invited him into the ship.
Listen, the Bible says that he would have kept on going, but they constrained him.
I'm so thankful that, listen, he's given us a free will.
And even as his children, you know, you can be saved here this morning, but it doesn't
mean, he don't make you read your Bible.
He didn't make you come to church today.
You came to church because you wanted to be here, amen?
If you read your Bible today, if you plan to read your Bible later today, you're only
going to read it because you want to.
He's not going to make you.
I will say this, there are times in which God will allow circumstances into your life
to bring you to a place of dependence on him, amen?
He'll bring you to the end of yourself.
He'll bring you to the place where you recognize, listen, I've gone away from God.
I've gotten far away from God.
I've neglected him.
I've neglected church.
I've neglected the Bible.
I've neglected prayer.
And then you look at your life and say, man, it's a mess.
It's a wreck.
And God will allow those things in your life to bring you back to him, amen?
There's some people that have testimonies of their salvation and some things that happened
that led up to how God brought them to the end of themselves.
But it says that they constrained him saying, abide with us for it is toward evening and
the day is far spent.
Notice this, and he went in to tarry with them.
I don't know how long he was there, but can I tell you that when you invite Jesus in,
he's not in a hurry to leave.
Isn't that good?
I mean, honestly, you can just spend time with the Lord.
You don't have to be in a hurry.
He's not in a hurry.
It says that he went in to tarry with them, to tarry with them.
You ever feel like you're somewhere and it's kind of rushed?
Doctors?
You say, man, I got two and a half seconds with the doctor.
It works that way sometimes.
But it says that he went in to tarry with them.
Listen, I'm thankful this morning that we can spend time with God as much time as we
want, as much time as we want.
What a blessing.
In his presence is fullness of joy.
Sometimes we just need...we've missed something in 2024.
It's really been a lot of decades that we've missed it.
We've missed the ability to be still and know that I'm God, and just spend some time in
the presence of God.
Not being in a hurry.
Not when is this going to end?
I got this, that, blah, blah, blah.
Just spending time with God.
It says in verse number 30, and it came to pass as he sat at meat with them.
You understand they didn't have crock pots back then that it was like already simmering
and ready, and they just kind of came in.
No, no, no, no, no, no.
It didn't work like that back then.
They were seven miles away.
They had been in Jerusalem for all the things that happened, and then they come, and they're
going to have a meal.
There was some time that was spent there.
I don't know how long, but there was some time that was spent there, and it says that
as they sat at meat with them, he took bread, and blessed it, and break, and gave to them.
Their eyes were opened, and they knew him.
Then it says he vanished out of their sight.
See he came, and he ministered.
He did for them what they needed.
It says that when he took that bread, and he blessed it, and they break, and he gave
it to them, how their eyes were opened, and then notice what they said after their eyes
were opened.
He vanished.
It says that they said one to another in verse 32.
Did not our heart burn within us while he talked with us by the way, and while he opened
to us the scriptures?
That's a good kind of heartburn, amen?
They were full of joy.
They said as Jesus were walking, and now they know that it was him, he vanished out of their
sight.
It says, did not our heart burn within us when he walked with us by the way, and he
opened the scriptures?
So what do they do?
Well, after walking 6.8 miles to where the village was where they dwell, they turned
around and walked 6.8 miles back to Jerusalem to announce to the others that Jesus is risen
indeed, hallelujah.
Now they'd be able to minister to others.
Let me share with you one final account of Jesus appearing.
It's in John chapter 20.
We dropped off with Mary in verse number 16 and following, we really read all the way
down to verse 18.
We're going to pick up in verse 19 and look at the disciples that were gathered together.
The Bible tells us in verse number 19 that they're gathered together on the night, the
same night of the resurrection.
It was evening and the first day of the week, and they're gathered there together.
The Bible says then the same day at evening in verse 19 of John 20, being the first day
of the week when the doors were shut, where the disciples were assembled for fear of the
Jews, came Jesus and stood in the midst and saith unto them, peace be unto you.
Isn't that awesome?
He comes and he appears to them.
They're assembled.
The Bible told us as we look back in Mark's gospel that they mourned and wept.
We find here that they're in this place.
The doors are shut and they're trying to be secure.
Why?
For fear of the Jews it tells us in verse 19.
Remember, there's a lot of stirring that's going on because of the resurrection, that
tomb that was set and sealed and all of that.
And so there's all kinds of things going on.
And so they're there and Jesus appears and says, peace be unto you.
And when he had so said, he showed unto them his hands and his side.
Then were the disciples glad when they saw the Lord.
Then said Jesus to them again, peace be unto you.
unto you, as my Father hath sent me, even so send I you."
What a great message of instruction that Jesus gave to the disciples.
We find that in Galilee, as you study the Gospel of Matthew, that Jesus will give the
Great Commission there, and we note that he says, as the Father hath sent me, even so
send I you.
Verse 22, and when he had said thus, he breathed on them, and saith unto them, Receive the
Holy Ghost, and whosoever sins you remit, they are remitted unto them, and whosoever
sins you retain, they are retained.
That wasn't that they had the ability to forgive sin, but they would preach the Gospel message
that is the power to forgive sin, amen, that's what he's telling them.
But Thomas, notice verse 24, one of the 12, called Didymus, was not with them when Jesus
came.
I always feel bad for Thomas.
I don't mean to be unkind, but don't miss church, you never know what God's going to
do, amen, they're assembled together.
I've often heard it said, I've thought it myself, you know, you miss what God has for
you, God has something for you, Thomas wasn't there.
So the other disciples of verse 25, they said unto him, We have seen the Lord, but
notice what Thomas says, Thomas gets that doubting Thomas, right, we refer to him that
way, because here's what he says in verse 25, but he said unto them, Except I shall
see in his hands the print of the nails, and put my finger into the print of the nails,
and thrust my hand into his side, notice, I will not believe.
I will not believe.
You know, there's some people today that still have this kind of attitude of Thomas,
they want God to, I just want God to speak to me, hello, he's giving us a Bible, I just
want God to appear to me.
You know, in Luke 16, that rich man that died, he said, Lazarus, Abraham, let Lazarus go
and tell my brothers, why?
Because he's in hell and he didn't want his brothers to come there, he had five brethren.
He knew that hell was a real place.
He was there, he was in torment.
He said, I don't want them to come.
And listen, if one come back from the dead, then they'll believe.
You know what the Bible says?
They have Moses, the prophets.
You know what they mean by that?
Moses and the law, the prophets, what does he mean by that?
They have the word of God.
If they won't believe that, they won't believe yet one rose from the dead.
That's Bible.
See, Thomas says, I will not believe.
Notice God is so gracious.
He really is.
He's more gracious than I would be, and He's more gracious than you would be, because we're
just human beings.
Amen?
Have you experienced the grace of God in your life?
Would you acknowledge this morning that God's more gracious than you are?
He's more faithful than you are?
I'm thankful that His grace to me is not dependent on my grace and that His faithfulness to me
isn't dependent on my faith.
So, God is gracious.
He's merciful.
I've experienced it, and I'm thankful for it.
And here, the Bible says, after eight days again, the disciples were within.
And notice these words, and Thomas was with them.
I guess so.
After he missed it, he was with them.
The Bible says, then came Jesus, the doors being shut, and stood in the midst and said,
Peace be unto you.
And notice this in verse 27.
Just like in Mark's gospel, when it says, tell the disciples, and Peter, again, our
God's an individual God.
He's the God of the universe.
He loves all people.
He wants all people to be saved, but He's an individual God.
He cares about you as an individual.
He knows you as an individual.
And it says that He came, notice, He saith to Thomas, then saith He to Thomas.
Thomas was the one that said, unless I see, unless I put my finger, unless I, I will
not believe.
And so Jesus says to Thomas, notice what He says, reach hither thy finger, and behold
my hands.
Reach hither thy hand, and thrust it into my side, and be not faithless, but believing.
Thomas answered and said unto Him, My Lord and my God.
Jesus saith unto him, Thomas, because thou hast seen me, thou hast believed.
Blessed are they that have not seen, and yet have believed.
Many other signs truly to Jesus in the presence of His disciples, which are not written in
this book.
Notice these things are written that you might believe that Jesus is the Christ, the Son
of God, and that believing you might have life through His name.
As we consider the spectacular resurrection, we rejoice in the truth that Jesus rose conquering
sin, death, and the grave, but then He appeared to many.
We didn't look at all those that He appeared to.
We don't even have record of all of the appearances that He made, but we notice in these three
records in John, Luke, and again in John, we find that Jesus graciously comes alongside
and He ministers to His people.
If you're saved this morning, if you've trusted Christ as your Savior, He wants to minister
to your needs.
He has a very present help at the time of trouble.
He said that He would never leave you nor forsake you.
We understand that as we get into His presence, as we abide in Him, that He abides in us,
that as we draw nigh to God, that He draws nigh to us, that He is a God who is seeking.
He doesn't force Himself, however.
He doesn't make you spend time with Him.
He desires that you spend time with Him, and He's always available, but He wants to minister
to you.
And I'm so thankful that we serve a risen Savior that knows our needs, and He comes
alongside and He ministers.
If you're not saved this morning, you say, I don't even know, you've talked about being
saved many times, I don't even know what it means, I don't understand it.
Let me put it this way, if you're not sure with 100% confidence that heaven is your home,
then today you need to be saved.
It was a glorious Easter morning.
What a great day to be saved if you're not saved this morning.
If you don't know, listen, I was baptized, that's not being saved.
I went to church when I was, that's not being saved.
I did, it's not being saved.
There's only one way to be saved.
Here's what Peter said, there's no other name under heaven given among men whereby
we must be saved.
Acts 4 and verse number 12, he's preaching that before the religious leaders actually
that are interrogating him.
As he preaches that message, he gives us the truth that salvation is only through Christ
Jesus.
You say, why do I need salvation?
Because you have an account, you have a sin account.
And honestly, until you get saved, that account is growing day by day, and you stand guilty
before a holy God.
The Bible tells us there's a sad scene in Revelation 20, but the Bible teaches us about
a great white throne judgment.
So we talk about the resurrection, everyone's going to rise.
Some to eternal life, some to eternal damnation, some, listen, I'm thankful that the second
death has no power over me because I've been saved by the blood of Christ, and I'm not
going to be at the great white throne judgment as a subject of that judgment.
I will stand before Christ, and so will you if you're saved this morning at the bema seat
of Christ, the judgment seat of Christ.
But at the great white throne, the Bible says the dead are raised, and the Bible says they
stand before God, great, small, and great, all men that have not trusted Christ as their
Savior.
And the Bible says the books are open, and they're judged out of those books, and it
says, whosoever is not found written in the book of life was cast into the lake of fire.
This is the second death.
But can I tell you this morning, Jesus loved you so much, and He died for you, and He rose
again so that you do not have to suffer that second death.
You don't have to spend eternity in the lake of fire.
You can be saved by the grace of God.
This morning, that message is for you.
If you're not saved this morning, it's for you.
Today is the day of salvation.
We're going to have an invitation in just a moment, and when we do, we never want to
embarrass anybody, but we'd love to have you come.
We'd take a Bible and show you how to be saved, to know for sure.
If you're a man, we'll have a man talk to you, if you're a lady, we'll have a lady talk
with you.
But then I think about the Christians that are here this morning, I wonder how often
do we live with the mindset that we serve a risen Savior.
It's not just on Easter Sunday, it's not just on any Sunday, but every day of our lives
that we remember that we serve a risen Savior.
The power of the resurrection, we're to live in that power.
We're to go, as the disciples were instructed, to go and tell, let it be known.
He is risen indeed.
Let's pray together.
Father, we love you.
We thank you for loving us.
We thank you, God, for the opportunity that you've given us to gather today.
We thank you for the early service, and we thank you, God, for the breakfast, and now
for this service.
We thank you for the opportunity to look at so many passages of Scripture this morning.
Thank you that the grave could not hold you, Lord.
Lord, as we consider this morning that sealed tomb and the saddened disciples, how we focus
and rejoice in the speculation.
spectacular resurrection. God, I pray that you would help each of us to live with resurrection
power. Lord, that we live each day knowing that you love us and that you come to minister
to us. Lord, if one's not saved this morning, God, I don't know everyone here. I don't know
the hearts, but God, you do. God, I know based on the authority of your word that you love
every single person, that you died for them and you rose again for them, and you offer
to them eternal life. God, if they're not saved, I pray they'd come today and get it
settled. That even as those young men sang that song, the old account was settled, they
said long ago, to be settled today. For Christians this morning, those that have been saved,
those that could say the old account was settled long ago, God, would you help us to live in
such a way that you'd be pleased, honored, and glorified with our lives. Lord, help us
to be your representatives, good representatives, ambassadors, Lord, representing the King of
Kings and Lord of Lords. We look forward to your soon return. I pray that you'd help us
to be found faithful. We pray that you'd work in these moments of invitation, that you have
your will and way, that you'd do what only you could do, and we'll thank you for it in
Christ's name we pray. Would you stand with me? I mentioned that we'd have a time of invitation.
There it is. What do we do this for? Well, we want to give you an opportunity to respond.
You've listened so well, and now you have an opportunity to respond. Maybe you just
want to come and thank God that He saved you and that He lives and that He's got a plan.
Maybe you're not sure of heaven. We'll all take a Bible, show you how you could know
for sure that you would not leave this place without knowing for sure that heaven's your
home. Kimberly's going to play quietly on the piano, and as she does, the altar is open.