to James chapter one, please, James chapter one.
And while you are turning there,
do you want to just say that I am grateful
for the opportunity that we have had
to be able to serve at Rapid Inn
over the last 14 summers or so.
And this summer is, I'm just gonna say it,
it's the weirdest summer yet.
And the reason why I say that
is because for the last 13 years,
all six of our family has been serving there.
And this year, it's myself, my wife,
and our youngest daughter, Lena,
who introduced herself just a little bit ago
and said she was from Pennsylvania.
And we have three other children
who aren't with us this summer at the camp.
God has called them to different ministries.
Our oldest daughter is in Pennsylvania.
Our son is in Indianapolis.
And our middle daughter is in New Hampshire.
And each of them are involved
in different ministry aspects this summer,
and we are grateful for them.
But we are kind of in that stage of life
where God is beginning to take them
as they are heading off to college to different places
and directing them to serve.
And so we are grateful that God has given us
the opportunity to be able to minister as a family.
But it's also exciting to be able to see God taking them
and using them in different places
and them being willing to follow God
and see what God has for their lives.
And they're learning to trust God on their own
as they follow Him in obedience.
And so we are grateful for that
and appreciate again the opportunity to be able to be here.
James chapter one is where we are going to be looking
in the scriptures this morning.
And as we go to James chapter one,
we're gonna begin reading in verse 22,
and we will read down through verse 25.
We're jumping into the middle of a paragraph here.
We'll look at some other parts of this paragraph
in just a minute, but let's start at verse 22
and we'll read down through verse 25.
The Bible says this or reads this way,
but be you doers of the word
and not hearers only deceiving your own selves.
For if any be a hearer of the word and not a doer,
he is likened to a man beholding his natural face
in a glass for he beholdeth himself and goeth his way
and straightway forgetteth what manner of man he was.
But whoso looketh into the perfect law of liberty
and continueth therein, he being not a forgetful hearer,
but a doer of the work,
this man shall be blessed in his deed.
You know, it's a classic story
that many of us are familiar with.
I don't know when you maybe first heard or saw this story,
but it's a story that has some basic elements in it
that still remain in some of the fairy tale stories
and things that we grew up with as children.
There is a particular story that comes to mind
or came to mind when I was reading
through this passage of scripture.
This story contains a wicked queen.
It contains a poisoned apple, seven dwarfs,
a glass coffin, a handsome prince,
and of course, the classic, they lived happily ever after.
If you're familiar with the story that I'm talking about,
this beloved fairy tale, which has these elements,
is known as Snow White.
And you know, as you consider the history
of the background of Snow White,
Snow White was actually a story that was published
all the way back in 1812 in a book
called Grimm's Book of Fairy Tales.
The brothers Grimm would continue to improve the story
until they had their final revision that came out in 1854.
Years later, it would be put into an animated movie
with music and things like that.
But as you go throughout that story,
one of the things that appears in that story
is that you have a queen who comes before a mirror
and she asks this question.
Mirror, mirror on the wall,
who is the fairest of them all?
And you know, when the queen comes before the mirror,
for quite some time, she is very content
to hear the answer and to see the result
or hear the result that the mirror gives to her.
You are the fairest in all of the land.
But then there comes a day
when the queen comes before the mirror
and she asks mirror, mirror on the wall,
who is the fairest of them all?
And the mirror finally tells her
that there is someone who is fairer,
someone who is more beautiful,
someone who has taken her place.
And the queen's response is very telling.
All is fine as long as the mirror is saying,
hey, everything is great, you're the fairest.
But when the mirror finally reveals
that there is something about her
that she didn't want to hear,
she has a completely different response.
So we come to this passage of scripture in James 1.
James is not speaking in fairy tales,
but he does use an illustration of a mirror
here in this passage of scripture
to teach us spiritual truth.
He likens the word of God as to a mirror.
And in so doing so, he teaches the importance
that the mirror ought to have in every one of our lives.
Not the physical mirror, but the mirror of God's word.
And so I want us to notice this morning
three important aspects of this,
what for many of us is probably
a familiar passage of scripture,
but I wanna break it down into three different aspects.
And I want us to consider this morning,
what is our response to the mirror of God's word?
How do you respond to the mirror of God's word?
Well, as we come to this passage of scripture in verse 22,
we see that God's word gives to us,
first of all, some instruction.
He gives us some very clear instruction in verse 22.
I mentioned that we are in the middle of a paragraph here
in verses 22 through 25.
And in order to be able to get the whole feel
of what is taking place,
we're gonna back up to verse 19.
In verse 19, the scripture reads this way.
Wherefore, my beloved brethren,
let every man be swift to hear,
slow to speak, slow to wrath.
You know, when you're working with children,
it is often best to keep instructions
brief, short, and simple.
As we come to this verse,
John is, or excuse me, James is sharing a truth
and he keeps it short and sweet, if you will.
He uses this phrase, he says,
but be ye doers of the word
and not hearers only in verse 22.
But he's referencing back to what he's talked about here
in verse 19, where he says that we need to be swift to hear,
slow to speak, slow to wrath.
You know, the word of God ought to play
a very important part of our lives.
The word of God ought to have a preeminence
that is there in our lives.
And here in these verses, in verses 19,
even down through verse 20 and 21,
he gives to us some instruction.
Now, we don't have the time to unpack each of these verses,
but I want us to consider something here
specifically in verse 19.
He gives us these short, simple instructions.
First of all, he says we are to be swift to hear.
The idea there is that there ought to be a delight
and a hunger for God's word.
And it's the picture of a person
who has their ears wide open while their mouth is closed.
You know, at camp, some of your young people
came to camp this week and we do at camp,
we teach them this at the very beginning orientation,
we teach them what we call the eyeballs click system.
And campers, where were you?
You didn't help me here.
I'm gonna go back a couple of seconds and repeat that, okay?
And so at camp, when they come to orientation,
we do what we call the eyeballs click system, okay?
And basically the system works this way
for those of you who are adults and have never been there.
Anytime that myself or Mr. Kelly
or someone is giving announcements,
if they say the word eyeballs, two of them are still awake,
okay, the campers should say click.
And I tell them on Monday,
there are a couple of things that need to take place
when you say click.
And what needs to happen is this,
as soon as you say click, your mouth needs to go closed,
your eyes need to look in the direction
of the one who is speaking
and your ears need to go wide open.
Have you ever noticed it's hard to listen to someone
when you're talking?
It's really hard to listen to someone
when the sound of our own voice
is really what we want to hear.
And in this passage of scripture,
God teaches us a very valuable lesson
well before he ever gets to the fact that we need to,
when we come before the mirror of God's word,
allow it to affect our lives.
He says, you wanna know one of the best ways
that you can allow God's word to affect your lives?
Is just simply be willing to listen.
Be swift, be desiring to hear what God wants to say to you.
And in order for that to happen,
we have to be quick to hear, slow to speak
and even consider our response being slow to wrath.
James would go on in these next few verses
and he would talk about as God's word does a work
in our hearts, according to verse 22,
that God's word does a work in our, excuse me, verse 20.
He says then that we need to lay apart all filthiness
and superfluity of naughtiness
or the abundance of naughtiness in our lives.
And instead, what we ought to do
is we ought to receive with meekness the engrafted word
which is able to save your souls.
Our response ought to be that I wanna be swift to hear
God speak to me.
My desire.
is to hear from God, and I want that engrafted word
which is able to save my soul.
I want it to affect my life.
Hey, is that your attitude when you come to God's word?
When your pastor preaches,
when the Sunday school teacher begins the lesson,
when you have your personal devotions in God's word,
do you come before God and say,
God, all ears speak to me?
Or do we come to God's word with our opinion,
with our thoughts and our desires and our feelings?
If the word of God is going to be able to have effect
on our lives, we must be willing to come to God's word
and allow it to change and affect our lives.
And that means that we must be willing
to resign our thoughts, to quiet our hearts
and come before God's word.
And the instruction is that we would not just be a hearer
of the word, but allow it to influence our lives so much
that we choose to do what we learn in God's word.
This is not the only place that God's word references
this idea of being a doer of the word.
In fact, God's word gives us multiple admonitions
to be a doer of the word.
One of those famous passages is in Matthew chapter seven
at the end of the Sermon on the Mount.
Jesus has been speaking, he's given the beatitudes,
he's confronted some false teachings and some false prophets
and as he gets to the end of chapter seven,
he closes with an illustration
and you're familiar with this illustration
though you may not know where it is in the Bible.
Many of you are probably familiar with this illustration.
It's a story about the wise man and the foolish man
who were building their houses.
We could sing the Sunday school song this morning,
but we won't take the time to do that.
But we know that through that story,
there is a wise man who builds his house on the rock.
Yeah, and all of a sudden the wind begins to blow,
the rain comes down, the flood beats upon that house
and because he dug and the Bible says
in another passage of scripture, I believe it's in Luke,
it says he dug deep and he had a solid foundation.
When all of that happened, his house stood.
But then there's this other person
who builds his house on the sand.
Doesn't have a very solid foundation.
And when the wind begins to come, the rains begin to fall,
the floods begin to beat on that house,
Jesus describes the result of that as it fell and great.
It was utter catastrophe.
You realize the difference between the wise man
and the foolish man?
We often talk about the foundation,
but you know what the foundation is?
The foundation there, the difference is
that there is someone who hears God's word and does it,
that's the wise man.
The foolish man is the person who hears but refuses to do.
That's the difference.
There are people who hear God's truth all the time
and they wonder why don't I have God's blessing
in my life?
The problem is you're hearing God's word,
but you're choosing not to do God's word.
And so the instruction that James follows up with here
in this passage of scripture at the very beginning
of his letter or not very far into it,
he says this, be a doer of the word and not just a hearer.
James is gonna come back to this idea
in James chapter four and verse 17 when he says this,
therefore to him that knoweth to do good.
How do you know it's good?
Well, you heard it at some point in time.
You've seen it in God's word.
God has shared with you what the good
or the right thing is to do.
Therefore to him that knoweth to do good
and doeth it not, to him it is sin.
This is where the mirror begins to point out some things
in our lives that we don't like to hear
and we start getting angry at the mirror.
Have you ever stepped in front of the mirror
and you didn't like what you saw?
Hair out of place, maybe some drool from the morning,
maybe you brushed your teeth and you didn't know,
you know, you had a little bit on the side of your face
and so your spouse points it out to you
or maybe, you know, a kid points it out to you
or something but you come before the mirror
and you see something there that you don't like.
Do you punch the mirror every time that happens?
Probably not.
If you do, you have a pretty expensive
mirror budget somewhere.
What do we do?
We take what the mirror reveals about us
and if we don't like it, we probably change
something about it.
We go and we wash it off, we comb our hair,
we do these things, why?
Because what the mirror reveals to us
isn't what we want to see.
Someone who's gonna be a doer of the word
is someone who has a desire to come before the mirror
of God's word and say, God, I want you to show me
truth from your word.
And so our purpose, when we come before God's word
is to hear it and it ought to be that we would
just not hear it but that we would be a doer of the word.
And so the instruction here really can't get any clearer.
Do what God's word says.
That then ought to cause us to step back
and ask this question, am I doing what God's word says?
Am I someone who is a hearer of the word
but not a doer of the word?
Perhaps we ought to ask it this way,
in what area of my life am I not doing God's word
and the truth that I've heard
or I know I ought to be doing in God's word?
And so as we come to this passage of scripture,
James says and uses the illustration of a mirror,
we're gonna get to that here in just a minute,
but he says, before we ever address that illustration,
you need to know God's expectation is this,
be a doer of the word.
God wants us to respond properly to his word.
Then there's a second aspect of this passage
that we're gonna look at in verses 23 through 25,
where we not only see the instruction,
be a doer of the word and not a hearer only.
And then he goes into this illustration
in verses 23 through 25.
Now we read down through this illustration.
We won't take the time to read this passage again,
but as he gives us this illustration,
basically James says this, James says,
I'm gonna present to you two different people.
Let's talk about exhibit A.
Exhibit A is the person who comes before the mirror
and we're just going to simply identify this person
as the looker.
This is the person who,
when they come before the mirror of God's word,
they're willing to look into the mirror,
see what God's word says, even hear it,
but then they go away and they forget what God's word says.
There's an interesting word in verse 22
and it's the verse 23, excuse me.
It says this, beholding his natural face in a glass.
The word beholding there is this,
it means to perceive clearly, to understand.
In other words, this person is presented
with the truth of God's word,
whether it's in reading God's word,
hearing God's word preached,
it could be done through godly music
that conveys the truth of God's word,
but somehow they hear God's word
and it isn't that they don't understand it.
It isn't that it's too high for them to understand.
God's word has been made clear.
It's been explained to them.
It's been made evident to them what needs to happen,
but they are just willing to look.
And then they purposefully go away
and they forget what manner of man they were.
The word forget there is the idea of neglect.
You ever forgotten something, forgotten keys?
Maybe you've forgotten your wallet or your purse somewhere.
Maybe you've forgotten something
even more important than that.
Maybe you've forgotten your child somewhere.
And you know, when something is important to you,
you try not to forget it, right?
Well, here he says for the looker,
the things that he's learned, read,
heard from God's word and knows he ought to put
into practice in his life,
the one who is the looker, exhibit A,
the one who ultimately when the storms arise,
the floods come, their life is gonna be a disaster,
they neglect, they forget.
They make really a choice
not to apply God's word to their life.
Why?
Because they're just simply a looker.
They're even willing to look into God's word
and find information to help other people.
They're willing to look into God's word
to hopefully find some sort of a life vest
that when trouble comes into their life,
they can maybe use God's word that way.
But to allow God's word to affect their daily life,
they're just a looker and not choosing to be a doer.
That's exhibit A.
Exhibit B, as we continue to go on in these verses then,
we see that there is something that is different.
We don't see this one who is exhibit A
not being exposed to God's word.
They've heard God's word.
They've heard truth presented.
That's not what really makes the difference.
The difference is exhibit B is someone
who hears the word of God,
comes before the mirror of God's word
and their choice is this.
I don't wanna neglect this.
I don't want this to just come in one ear and out the other.
I want to have God's blessing on my life.
So I'm going to choose to be a hearer of the word
and a doer of the word.
If we look at these two different people,
we classified exhibit A as the looker.
Exhibit B this morning,
I would classify him as this kind of a person.
He is a lingerer.
Notice the word as we read down
through this passage of scripture in verse 25,
it says, but who so looketh into the perfect law of liberty
and continueth therein.
My mind goes to that person who is lingering,
who is continuing,
who is seeking to stay with
or stand near something as long as they can.
And if they can't stay by that any longer,
then they can't.
They carry the thought, they carry the concept,
they carry the memory in their mind,
they take it with them.
I mentioned that half of our family
is not with us this morning.
But you know, there are different ways
that we can stay in touch.
There are different ways that we can think
about our children, and even though we may be
hundreds of miles apart,
we can still have the thought of them.
It's not like they're completely gone,
that they've disappeared, that we don't want
anything to do with them.
You wanna know something, we go around the campsite
and there are memories that begin to flash
into our minds all of the time,
of the things that our children have done
as they've grown up there at camp,
and we see them there, why?
Because the memory, the importance,
it's significant to us, and it lingers in our mind.
Hey, can I ask you this question this morning?
What is your habit when you hear God's word?
Do you come into God's word and you walk out
these doors and God's word is forgotten?
Kelly will often encourage the young people
before they leave to not let the gates
at the end of the road as they go out,
which is actually the entrance when they come in, okay,
that when they go out the front gate,
to don't let them be like giant erasers
where everything that they've heard at camp this week
from God's word and they learn in their devotions
from their counselors, from the preaching,
from the instruction, don't let it be like a magic eraser
that all of a sudden when you go out that gate,
that whew, it's gone.
Take the truth with you.
Are these doors like mental erasers,
spiritual erasers to you?
I've heard God's word, now I've gotta get back to life,
and you don't take God's word with you?
Or do you allow God's word to linger in your heart?
Can I give you a food illustration?
It's the idea of a marinade.
What do you do with a marinade?
You don't just pop it into a bag for five seconds,
take it back out, right?
If you really want that flavor to get into the meat,
you have to let it sit in there for a while
so that it begins to soak it up, it begins to permeate it.
Do you let God's word linger in your heart?
Do you let God's word begin to get in
and permeate your life, or do we respond
like the wicked witch in the Grimm's fairy tales
that when it tells us something we don't like to hear,
automatically we get shut off to God's word?
God, you can't penetrate that area of my life.
No, sir, you can't tell me how to thank God.
Say, does God really tell me how to thank?
Read Philippians chapter four in verse eight.
Whatsoever things are true, honest, just, pure, lovely,
if there's virtue, if there's any praise,
think on these things, God says.
Here's what you ought to be thinking.
So God's word addresses the areas of our lives,
and God applies his truth to different areas of our lives.
When he shows areas of our lives
that are in the mirror of God's word
that we need to change, do we get mad at the mirror
and we go away, being someone who is just a looker,
or are we someone who is willing to linger
and let God's word permeate, affect, and change our lives?
So we see in this passage of scripture
that God's word gives to us the instruction.
The instruction is this, be a doer of the word,
not just a hearer.
The illustration that he gives to us
is that of someone who comes before the mirror.
The looker is the one who says,
I'll look into God's word, I don't like it,
I'm gonna neglect it, I'll forget it,
I'll hear it, but that's about it.
And then exhibit B is the one who says,
I wanna be a doer of the word.
You say, why is it so important to be a doer of the word?
Well, you may have noticed when we went to verse 22
that I didn't read the final phrase.
The final part of verse 22 says this,
first part says, but be ye doers of the word
and not hearers only.
Notice these last four words, deceiving your own selves.
The last thing that I want us to notice
in this passage of scripture is James,
God really through James as he's writing,
shares with us what I call the illusion, the illusion.
You ever seen somebody do some sort of an illusion?
Might be a clown pulling a scarf out of a fake thumb,
so hopefully I didn't ruin that for anybody.
Maybe you've seen a magician do some sort of a magic trick
and you're trying to think, ooh, that's sleight of hand,
how did he do that?
I don't understand.
And there is this illusion that is there.
Sometimes the hardest thing for us to be willing
to accept from God's word is this,
you're deceiving yourself.
You're living an illusion.
The word deceive as we see it here is that,
it's the idea of someone who is miscalculating something,
mis-evaluating.
And so it's somebody who says, I'm gonna go to the store
and I'm gonna buy this, I have $20, but it's $50
and they still think that they should be able to get it.
You're mis-calculating.
You're not evaluating it properly
and so James puts in here this warning to his readers
of the very grave condition of self-deception.
Those who were at camp this week,
they are very well aware of the fact,
we hit this verse a couple of times,
that the Bible warns us in Jeremiah that we have a heart
that is deceitful above all things and desperately wicked.
You see, I think oftentimes, I know I've done this
and God has had to convict me about this.
We come before God's word and we think,
hey, I'm pretty good, but God's word says,
really, you need to be careful because we can get
into this illusion where we mis-calculate
our relationship with God.
We begin to make excuses for things.
When God's word points out sin in our lives,
we begin to excuse it and we would rather worship God,
live our lives on our terms rather than God's terms
and as a result, we're living an illusion.
Kind of reminds me of a man by the name of Cain
who comes before God and he's living the illusion
of worshiping God properly.
He found out that God had disrespect,
God didn't honor what he was trying to do with God
and as a result, he got mad at God and he killed his brother.
We go on in the scriptures and we see a man
by the name of Jacob.
Now, there are a lot of things that we could talk about
in Jacob's life, the deception that he had in his family,
in his brother, in his dad, in his uncle,
in all of the deception that was there
but God finally gets a hold of his heart
and he tells him this, he says,
Jacob, I want you to go down to Bethel.
He tells him that a couple of times
and as he tells him, I want you to go down to Bethel,
you know what Jacob does?
Jacob starts to live an illusion.
He packs things up, he goes but the problem is this,
the closer he gets to Bethel,
he remembers what Bethel is like.
Bethel is where he came to have a personal awareness
and an awesome perspective of who God is
and as he gets closer to that place,
he stops about 30 miles short and he says,
I'm gonna stay at Shechem for a while
and so God has to come to him again and says,
Jacob, you're not where I told you you need to be.
You're supposed to be at Bethel
but you're still dwelling in Shechem.
Hey, I wonder if there are some people in this room
this morning who we've gotten satisfied
with where we want to be and God says,
that's not where I want you to be.
It might be physically the location.
Maybe God is calling you,
asking you to take another step of faith
and follow him in obedience in some area of service
but maybe there is someone here this morning
who you're living an illusion.
I'm where I need to be but God is saying,
no, this is the next spiritual step that I want you to take.
Here's the next area of growth that I want you to take.
Here's the next area of surrender that I want you to have
and we step back from the mirror and we say,
God, I'm okay and God says, don't be just a hearer
of the word, be a doer of the word.
Otherwise, you're gonna fall into self-deception
and live in this illusion.
It's very possible that there is someone here this morning
who you've heard the gospel.
You've heard it from pastor.
Maybe he's shared with you verses from God's word
on a personal basis.
Maybe it's been someone else here in the church
who has knocked on your door.
Maybe they've shared the gospel with you.
Maybe you've heard it in a Sunday school class
or you've heard the gospel of Jesus Christ
and you've come before the mirror of God's word
and God says, you need to understand that you are a sinner.
Ouch, that hurts.
I don't like seeing that in the mirror.
I'm a pretty good person.
I'm a pretty good person who's not in jail,
who doesn't have this addiction,
who hasn't done this to people.
I'm a pretty good person.
You're living an illusion.
The Bible says that all of us have sinned
and fallen short of the glory of God.
Not only does the Bible tell us that we are sinners,
but the Bible says that the consequence of our sin is death
for the wages of sin is death,
but the gift of God is eternal life
through Jesus Christ, our Lord.
Here's where the illusion begins to change.
As God gives us truth
and he begins to open up our eyes to the reality
that though I am a sinner and I deserve death,
God loved me enough.
He sent Jesus Christ to die on the cross for my sins.
And if I'm willing to believe
in the finished work of Jesus Christ,
his perfect life, his death, his burial,
and thankfully, we don't have a dead savior,
we have a risen savior.
Because he lives, he can give to you eternal life.
God says, I've loved you.
That's no illusion.
But you have to make the choice to believe in Jesus Christ.
And the Bible says there is only one way of salvation,
one way.
to have eternal life. And Jesus put it this way in His own words. He says, I am the way
of the truth and the life. No man, no woman, no boy, no child, no teenager, no person cometh
unto the Father but by Me. And so I ask you to consider this question this morning. Are
you living an illusion? In your mind you think, I'm a pretty good person. I ought to be able
to get into heaven because of the things that I've done. There is no one who gets into heaven
because of the things that they've done. It's all because of what Jesus did on the cross
of Jesus Christ. And so if your faith isn't in Jesus Christ, if you haven't received or
welcomed Jesus Christ into your life as your Savior, then you do not have eternal life.
You say, preacher, that's harsh. Read 1 John. He that hath the Son hath life. He that rejects
or hath not the Son of God hath not life. That's not me. That's God's words. And there
may be someone here this morning who you're under the illusion, I have eternal life. But
all along you're rejecting Jesus Christ. You've never put your faith and trust in Him. You've
never trusted Jesus Christ as your Savior. Don't live in the illusion any longer. This
morning you can trust Jesus Christ. Would Jesus really accept me, you ask? He that cometh
to me I will in no wise cast out, Jesus says. And so this morning that illusion can be broken.
Don't stand before the mirror of God's Word and be deceived into thinking that you know
more than God. God this morning says you need to trust Jesus Christ as your Savior. Would
you be willing to do that? In just a minute we're going to have a closing time here at
the end of the service. I would encourage you, if you do not know Jesus Christ as your
Savior, maybe there's a person here that invited you, you came with them, you know,
you trust them, they would love to be able to take God's Word this morning, open it up
and share with you how you can know from God's Word how you can be saved. Nobody here is
going to force you into praying a prayer, making a decision. We just want you to see
the truth in God's Word so that you can make an informed decision about whether you're
going to receive Jesus Christ and receive eternal life or whether you're going to reject
Christ and reject eternal life. Our prayer is you would trust Him. Believer, you're here
this morning and I would guess that a majority of people in this room, you would say, I've
trusted Jesus Christ as my Savior. When you come before the mirror of God's Word, are
we quick to listen or are we quick to interject our opinion, our thoughts, our feelings and
so as a result of us still talking the truth that God's trying to give to us, it gets
drowned out. The instruction is be a doer. In order to be a doer, we have to be a hearer,
to hear what God's Word says and do we linger in the truth of God's Word or do we neglect
it in our lives? God says if you want my blessing, we didn't read the rest of this and spend
a lot of time on this, but take a look at the end of verse 25. It says, but whoso looketh
into the perfect law of liberty and continueth or lingereth therein, he being not a forgetful
hearer, but a doer of the work, notice this, this man will be blessed in his deeds. There's
no greater way to deny God's blessing from our lives as believers, as His children than
to say, God, I hear what you're saying, but I'm not going to do it. So God's instruction
today is that we might come to Him and say, God, help me not just to be a hearer, but
to be a doer of the Word. Let's pray. Father, we thank You so much for this time and we
thank You for the opportunity to be able to come and minister today. We thank You for
this church and their ministry here. We thank You for those who have been here and have
been able to hear the preaching of Your Word, but all of us this morning are at risk of
being merely hearers of God's Word. I pray that we would not make that choice this morning.
If there is someone here who has not trusted Jesus Christ as their Savior, I pray that
You would do a work in their heart that I am not able to do, and Lord, they would see
the need to trust Jesus Christ as their Savior today. For believers, Lord, help us not to
live deceived, being deceived by our own heart, being deceived, living the illusion
just simply because we hear Your Word. Help us to be doers so that we can have Your blessing
on our lives. And we ask this in Jesus' name. Amen. Pastor?
Amen. Would you stand?
Closed. The message has been clear. The challenge has been given. This morning, if you're not
sure of heaven, we'd love to take a Bible and show you how you could know for sure that
heaven is your home. Maybe God has spoken to you. You're saved. You've been born again,
but God spoke to you about something specific in your life. Kimberly's going to play on
the piano, and as she does, the altar is open.