This morning, the book of 2 Timothy,
the book of 2 Timothy, it'll be a theme verse
or a theme really message this morning,
kind of overviewing the entire thought for the new year.
And I'm thankful for the opportunity
to be looking forward to what God has in store for us.
In many ways, I believe that you would probably
echo the statement, it's hard to believe
that today is the last day of 2023.
And for many of us, as we flip the calendar tomorrow, 2024,
we think about just our lives
and we think about all that has happened
and see where we are.
And we certainly rejoice in the goodness of God,
the opportunity and privilege that he has given us
to serve him yet for another day.
And we look forward to what God will do.
Of course, we expect that God will continue
to do great things.
We look forward to a soon return,
and it could be that we never even flip
the calendar to tomorrow.
It could be that the Lord returns still today
and that'd be okay with me, amen.
And we certainly look forward to the imminent,
the soon return of the Lord Jesus Christ.
But each year, somewhere around September, October,
I begin to fervently seek the Lord
with regard to a theme for the next year.
And I've done that every year
that God's given me the opportunity
to pastor here at Fellowship Baptist Church.
And I have thanked the Lord for his guidance
and for his direction.
And I desire that God will provide us
with an annual church theme that will help us
to be encouraged and challenged throughout the entire year.
And very quickly, if you think back,
those some of you have been here
since the beginning of me being here.
And in 2012, I got here in August of 2011.
So the first full calendar year was 2012.
And our theme that year was Standing on His Promises.
And I'm so thankful for the promises of God.
And we were reminded each week of various promises
that God has given to us.
And we find that Peter said they're exceeding great
and precious promises.
And we can thank God for the promises
that he's given us.
In 2013, we turned to the book of Esther
and throughout the year preached from the book of Esther
dealing with the theme of for such a time as this.
And God no doubt has put us here for such a time
even as he did Esther.
And what an opportunity that God has given us
to serve him even as he did Esther.
In 2014, the book of John, he must increase.
What a great challenging statement
as John the Baptist is standing there in John three
and the discussion that takes place.
And he looks to Jesus and he says of Jesus,
he must increase, but I must decrease.
And really it's all about the Lord Jesus Christ.
And we studied through the book of John in 2014.
In 2015 and 2016, we looked at the book of Acts.
In the first part of the series in 2015,
we dealt with Acts one through 12.
And we dealt with the thought of boldness
to speak thy word and oh, how we need that boldness.
God's promised to be with us.
And we find that throughout the scriptures
that the disciples and Paul himself prayed for boldness
and how we ought to pray for boldness.
The latter part of the book of Acts in 2016,
we looked at Acts 13 through 28.
We dealt with the subject of I believe God.
I hope that you still believe God, amen.
God is trustworthy.
He's always done what he said he would do.
He's always going to do what he said he will do.
And he is a trustworthy God.
And Paul stands up at the end of the book of Acts
in the 27th chapter and he says, I believe God.
And oh, how we need some of God's people today
to have that same level of faith and confidence
in what God has said.
In 2017, increase our faith.
And we dealt with a number of things
throughout the calendar year that God would use
in our lives to increase our faith.
The Bible says, so then faith cometh by hearing
and hearing by the word of God.
And God will use his word to increase our faith.
And we desire, even as the disciples said,
Lord, teach us to pray, but then they said,
Lord, increase our faith.
And oh, that God would help us to believe him
and to trust him.
In 2018, count your blessings.
And in that particular calendar year,
we said that we desired to have a number of reasons
every week of the year, a new reason that we can rejoice.
Count your blessings.
The songwriter said, name them one by one
and it will surprise you what the Lord hath done.
And so often we think about the blessings,
even as we talked about, I mentioned it already
this morning, the Lord, he daily loadeth us with benefits
and he's been so good to us.
If we're not careful, we can focus on some challenges
and some difficulties and the obstacles.
But God says that we're to fix our attention
on the blessings and thank God for what he's done.
In 2019, we turn to the book of Ephesians,
be strong in the Lord and the power of his might.
Listen, we're engaged in spiritual warfare
and we need to understand that the battles
in which we're facing, the battles in which we're engaged in
as Tozer said, the Christian life can best be described
not as a playground, but as a battleground.
We are engaged in spiritual warfare
and the truth is that we must be strong in the Lord.
2020, looking unto Jesus.
Oh, 2020 was what a year that was.
And God gave me that theme about October 5th or so of 2019.
I had no idea of all that we would deal with in 2020,
but how encouraged I was personally
that as we develop that theme,
that we're to keep our eyes on Jesus.
He knows all things, he do with all things well,
and we're to keep our eyes on him.
2021, complete in Christ from the book of Colossians.
And I'm thankful that my identity first and foremost
is in Christ and I am complete in him.
And what a blessing to know the Lord Jesus Christ
as your personal savior.
I hope this morning that as we've gathered together,
that you know the Lord as your personal savior.
Last week, Ryan trusted Christ as his savior
right after the morning service.
And what a blessing.
He came in here not knowing the Lord,
but left here knowing the Lord
and being confident that heaven was his home
and his identity is in Christ.
And I'm so thankful to be complete in Christ.
2022, we went to the book of 1 John, walking in the light.
Aren't you thankful that we can have fellowship with God?
We can have fellowship with God.
And we walk in the light as he is in the light.
And what a blessing to know the Lord
and to walk with him daily,
to develop our personal relationship with him
and certainly a blessing.
Last year or this year, still 2023, great is the Lord.
And throughout the calendar year of 2023,
we dealt with examining, discovering, if you will,
why God is great.
Why do we say, why does the scripture declare
that God is great?
Why would the psalmist stand up and say,
great is the Lord and greatly to be praised?
Well, God has revealed, he's declared to us in his word,
his greatness and we study for a large portion
of this calendar year, reasons that God is great.
And then we said this, as we continue to look at the idea
of discovering his greatness,
then we're to declare his greatness
because not everyone knows how great our God is.
A lot of people in our world that have no idea
how great our savior is.
And what a blessing that God has given us
the opportunity to know him and then to declare
his greatness and then we finished up the calendar year
by dealing with the impact that his greatness will have
in our lives daily.
When I truly understand how great God is,
my belief, God is great, will impact my behavior.
How I behave reveals what I believe.
The way that we pray is going to be impacted
by how great we believe God is.
And we dealt with a number of things.
And so this year in 2024,
as we flip the calendar tomorrow,
as we have our vision Sunday today
and introduce the theme, the idea of continue.
And again, I mentioned 2 Timothy 3, 14,
you probably, some of you can read it from where you are.
Some of you say it's just blurry to me
because of the size of the font there.
But 2 Timothy 3 and verse number 14,
Paul gives this charge to Timothy and he says this,
but continue thou in the things which now has learned
and has been assured of,
knowing of whom thou has learned them.
The word continue means to persevere.
It means to be steadfast or constant in any course.
It carries this idea not to depart.
The idea of continue in Acts chapter 14 and verse 22,
you don't need to turn there.
But in that portion of scripture,
Paul has the opportunity to follow up
with those that had been saved
during the first missionary journey,
those that were reached with the gospel
of the Lord Jesus Christ.
And the Bible tells us in Acts 14 and verse 22
that when Paul followed up with those believers,
that he gave them this exhortation
that they would continue in the faith.
We find that each letter of this first and second Timothy,
these letters that we'll be studying this year in 2024,
we find that God would use the apostle Paul
to write to Timothy.
And we find that in each of these books,
there's a charge to continue.
We find that there are some that are in the scriptures.
In fact, some that are mentioned by name
throughout the scriptures,
who unfortunately they failed to continue.
They gave up, they went back and they did not continue.
And we find that as believers,
we understand this morning that we have an enemy.
I mentioned from a previous year in 2019,
when we spoke about be strong in the Lord,
that we are engaged in spiritual warfare
and spiritual battle.
And we have an enemy.
The ultimate goal of Satan.
is to devour you, to devour us.
The Bible says that he's walking about seeking
whom he may devour.
We understand that's in 1 Peter 5,
a book that's written to believers.
We understand that his work amongst lost people,
those that have not yet trusted Christ as their savior,
is to keep them blinded to the truth of the gospel.
The Bible tells us in 2 Corinthians 4,
in whom the God of this world
hath blinded the minds of them which believe not,
lest the light of the glorious gospel
should shine in unto them.
And we find that Satan is actively working along the way
with his ultimate goal of devouring you and devouring me.
He seeks to discourage and derail God's people.
He seeks to discourage you.
He'll use a variety of means.
In fact, as you study throughout the scriptures,
as you begin to look at life and even your own experiences,
the means that he uses are varied.
And unfortunately, he's been successful.
He's been successful far more often
than any of us would really like to acknowledge.
There are people that we can read of in the scriptures
that did not continue.
They gave up, they went back.
There are people that you know, that I know,
that did not continue.
They've given up, they've turned back.
And that's unfortunate.
But we understand this morning that we have an enemy.
And he uses a variety of means
in order to try to discourage the people of God
and to derail the people of God.
But I'm thankful that the Bible tells us
that greater is he that is in you
than he that is in the world.
I'm thankful this morning that God has given us a Bible
and he loves us as his people, as his children.
We spoke last week about the miracle of Christmas
and how that because of what he did and how he did it,
what has accomplished that we,
if we've trusted Christ as our savior,
that we are his sons.
His children.
And he loves us.
And in so loving us, he's given us a Bible
and he's revealed himself to us through his word.
But not only has he revealed himself through his word,
we find that he has exposed the enemy.
We are not ignorant of his devices.
We understand the tactics of the enemy,
but we also understand that in the Bible,
God has instructed each and every one of us
throughout this calendar year 2024,
it is my goal with the help of God
and by the grace of God
that we would have the opportunity to study
through 1 Timothy and 2 Timothy.
And as we do, that we would be challenged to continue.
To continue.
To not turn back.
Not give up.
In the midst of opposition, in the midst of difficulty,
in the midst of all the craziness,
that we would not throw in the towel,
that we would not turn back,
that we would not slow down,
but know we would continue,
that we would persevere,
that we would be steadfast or constant in this course,
the course of the Christian life.
See, one day, and we believe soon, Jesus is coming back.
The reality is that for me as a believer
and for you as a believer this morning,
the thought, the truth of his soon return is encouraging.
It's exciting.
The reality is that we, as David said,
there's but a step between me and death.
Not only do we have the promise of Christ's soon return,
but we have the awareness of the brevity of life.
David said there's but a step between me and death,
and James says that our life is but a vapor
that appears for a little time and then vanisheth away.
And we understand this morning that we have this opportunity
and as long as God would give us life and breath,
then our goal would be that we continue.
That we continue.
Notice as we look in 2 Timothy chapter number three
this morning, if you're taking notes,
a couple of thoughts for you this morning
as an introductory message to our theme for 2024,
number one, notice the explanation.
Paul begins in chapter number three in verse number one
and says this, this know also.
I think about those three words and I understand
that as we study the Bible that God wants his people
to be informed of some things.
He does not want us to be ignorant.
He does not want us to be in the dark.
He wants us to be aware of what's taking place
and we find that God has said through the Apostle Paul
as he's writing to Timothy, this know also.
He wants us to be aware of.
He wants us to be assured of.
He wants us to have a knowledge of something.
And what is that something?
He says that in the last days, perilous times shall come.
Brethren, I believe this morning
that we are in the last days.
I believe that we're living really if we'd be honest
and we look at the prophetic calendar of the Lord
and we look at the scriptures that are provided to us,
we'd find that I believe that we're living
in the very end of the last days.
And no, I'm not seeking to set a date.
No man knoweth the hour.
I would never seek to do that.
But what I'm saying this morning
is that we're living in the last days.
We're there.
And God says through Paul as he's writing to Timothy
under the inspiration of the Holy Spirit of God,
preserved by God for us this morning
and for believers throughout the history of the church,
he says this know also that in the last days,
perilous times shall come.
That word, that phrase perilous times,
it means harsh, it means fierce, it means dangerous,
it means troublesome.
Have you found this morning that we live in perilous times?
Have you found this morning
that we're engaged in spiritual warfare?
Have you found this morning that we live in a time,
in a society, in a culture,
in which they call evil good and good evil,
that we live in a time when they're anti-God,
anti-Christian, anti-Jesus Christ?
That's the time in which we live in.
And Paul says to Timothy, I want you to know this,
I want you to be aware of this.
God wants us to know the times in which we're living.
We see this explanation that Paul is providing to Timothy
and for us this morning, we continue to see it.
This morning, we'll just do a quick overview
of these next few verses in a later message
at the end of the year.
We'll begin to deal with each of these
particular characteristics, if you will, of the last days,
these perilous times that are provided for us.
But this morning, we'll just quickly go through
and read what God says with regard to the characteristics
of these last days, these perilous times.
Notice verse number two,
for men shall be lovers of their own selves.
You don't have to look real far to see that happening.
Notice covetous, boasters, proud, blasphemers,
disobedient to parents, unthankful, unholy.
I think about that disobedient to parents.
How many times you've been in a public place
and you've seen the behavior of some children,
you've thought this thought, man,
if that was me when I was a kid, I'd have got a whooping.
You say, well, that's not really appropriate
to say that this morning.
Well, you understand, there's a lot of disobedience.
The disobedience is a result
of a lack of respect for authority.
We see unthankful.
How many people today, we live in this era,
if you will, of entitled individuals,
and it leads to a lack of thankfulness,
a lack of appreciation.
We find that the Bible says unholy.
Notice verse number three, without natural affection,
truce breakers, false accusers, incontinent,
fierce, despisers of those that are good.
Verse four, traitors, heady, high-minded,
lovers of pleasure more than lovers of God.
Having a form of godliness,
but denying the power thereof from such, turn away.
And we find that in these few verses of Scripture
to begin the third chapter of the book of 2 Timothy,
that Paul is providing this explanation to Timothy
with regard to the days in which he would be living
and the perilous times that should come.
And listen, you understand that Paul is writing
under the inspiration of the Holy Spirit of God,
and he says this, they shall come.
He didn't say they might come.
He said they're going to come,
and he said here's how those days are to be characterized.
Here's what you're gonna find happening.
You find that in verse number 12, the Bible says this,
yea, and all that will live godly in Christ Jesus,
notice what the Bible says, shall suffer persecution.
So we find in verse number one that he says this,
know also then in the last days,
perilous times shall come.
He says in verse number 12 that all those
that live godly in Christ Jesus shall suffer persecution.
And so we find that as Paul is writing here,
he's wanting Timothy to understand,
he's wanting him to be aware of what he would face
and what he would deal with,
and that idea of persecution is to be harassed
or to be troubled, it really carries with it
the idea of to make one run or flee.
Now consider that within the context of our theme
for this year, the way that the enemy will use persecutions
in order to cause the people of God to turn back,
to flee, to not continue.
We find that as Paul is writing to his own son of the faith,
Timothy, Paul knows, in fact, in chapter four,
he will share the truth that he understands
that the time of his departure's at hand,
he understands that he will soon take
and he'll leave this earth, he'll die a physical death,
he understood that he would appear before the Lord
to be absent from the bodies, to be present with the Lord,
but he knew that when he.
would die that Timothy would continue to have the responsibility to live for God.
It's almost the idea as we read 1st and 2nd Timothy and we think about the
leadership roles and we think about Paul investing in and instructing Timothy, you
think about a relay race in which one runner finishes their leg of the race
and they have that baton in their hand and as they would take that baton and
they would pass it to the next runner, their teammate, who would run the next
leg of their race. And Paul understood that his race, his course, he was near the
end. He would put off his earthly tabernacle, the time of his departure's
at hand, but he wants to give this charge to Timothy, his son in the faith, and he
wants him to understand some things with regard to what he'll deal with. Honestly,
as you look at the explanation that Paul provides Timothy with and you see the
characteristics of these last days that shall come, when you understand the
persecution that will come for those that live godly in Christ Jesus, you
could understand why the next word in verse number 14 is continue. Continue. Why?
Because really the idea is, man, I'm gonna give up. I mean, why would I want to deal
with all of that? Why would I want all that hardship and difficulty? And Paul
says, listen, be aware, know what you're going to face, but continue. But continue.
We see, number one, the explanation, but now we see, number two, the exhortation.
The exhortation. The idea of an exhortation is an address or
communication that's emphatically urging someone to do something. We find that this
exhortation is given in verse number 14, and the Bible says, but continue thou in
the faith, in the things which thou hast learned and has been assured of, knowing
of whom thou hast learned them. He said to the believers there in Acts 14, 22,
continue in the faith, and here he says, continue thou in the things which thou
hast learned and has been assured of, knowing of whom thou hast learned them.
Begin to think about this particular charge, this exhortation, this communication that
Paul is giving to Timothy, emphatically urging him to continue. I understand, Timothy, that
the pressures are going to be great. I understand that the opposition is going to mount. I understand
you're going to deal with some really difficult things, but continue. Don't give up. Don't
give up. Don't turn back. Continue. Continue. So often, people will ask the question when
you deal with times of difficulty and great adversity as we've dealt with in our nation
in recent years, and they begin to consider, what is it that we should do? How is it that
we should respond? What should we do with regard to the current environment and the
current circumstances in one word? Continue. Continue. And really, as believers this morning,
we could say, what other option is there? Listen, I don't want to give up. I'm not a
quitter. I don't want to go back. I don't want to give up or go back. No, I want to
continue. Is it going to be easy to continue? No, it's not going to be easy to continue.
Are there going to be obstacles to continuing? Sure, there will be obstacles, but our God
is with us. And we find that this exhortation is given, the idea of keep on keeping on.
You've heard somebody use that phrase, no doubt. I want you to think about some other
things that Paul says. Turn back to 1 Timothy chapter 4, if you will, and I want you to
notice what Paul says here in this portion of Scripture as he's dealing with the idea
of what's taking place with regard to the ideas of difficulty and all that he would
deal with. And he says to Timothy in 1 Timothy chapter 4, in verse number 1, notice he says,
now the Spirit speaketh expressly, then in the latter times, notice what he says, some
shall depart from the faith, giving heed to seducing spirits and doctrines of devils,
speaking lies and hypocrisy, having their conscience seared with a hot iron, forbidding
to marry and commanding to abstain from meats which God hath created to be received with
thanksgiving of them which believe and know the truth. And so Paul, again, in 1 Timothy
chapter 4, is telling Timothy, listen, here's what's going to happen in the last days and
there will be some, notice in verse 1, some shall depart from the faith. Some shall depart.
But what's the exhortation to Timothy? Continue. What's the exhortation for us this morning?
I don't want to be part of the some that shall depart. In fact, if you look at the end of
2 Timothy in the 4th chapter, you find that Paul mentions about Demas, hath forsaken me,
having loved this present world, in 2 Timothy 4 in verse number 10. And we find that here
as we look to the truth of God's Word and we see that God has provided us with an explanation
of what we'll deal with, but the exhortation remains the same. He tells him this in the
beginning of 1 Timothy 4, but then skip down, if you will, to the very last verse of 1 Timothy
chapter 4 in verse number 16. He says this, take heed unto thyself and unto the doctrine.
Notice what he says, continue in them. Continue in them. For in doing this thou shalt both
save thyself and them that hear thee. And so we find that Paul continues to give this
exhortation. He's consistent in the message that he delivers to Timothy, both in 1 Timothy
and again in 2 Timothy, this message of continue. The pressures are great. The opposition is
great. But continue. Persevere. Continue to march forward, to be steadfast, to be constant.
I think about that word steadfast. Look at 1 Corinthians chapter 15. In 1 Corinthians
chapter 15 we see, as we're reminded of the great chapter of 1 Corinthians 15, that we
serve a risen Savior. The chapter that we would go to to speak about the resurrection
and to look at all the teaching here in 1 Corinthians 15, that we serve a risen Savior.
And what a great truth to know that He lives and that He lives and He reigns and He rules.
And here, at the end of the chapter, Paul is giving this exhortation, this admonition
to the church in Corinth and he says in verse 57, but thanks be to God which giveth us the
victory through our Lord Jesus Christ. Therefore, my beloved brethren, notice what he says,
be ye steadfast. To continue is to be steadfast. And so he says, be steadfast, unmovable, always
abounding in the work of the Lord. And then notice this great promise, for as much as
you know that your labor is not in vain in the Lord. Our labor is not in vain in the
Lord. God has given us promises. There are some that would look at the current environment
in which we're living and even looking at the Christendom, if you will, broadly speaking,
and looking even closer in if you would narrow down that scope and look at some evangelical
churches and even narrowing it down and looking at some Baptist churches and saying, why are
there less people coming in this generation than in the previous generation? Why are we
not seeing as many results and why are we not seeing all these things? Listen, don't
be discouraged by those things. Don't give up because of that. No, continue because God
said that your labor is not in vain in the Lord. God had said through Paul to the believers
in Corinth earlier in this book, some water or some plant, some water, but God gives the
increase. And there are times in our lives where we may be on that process of being those
that are picking fruit, so to speak, that we're seeing the results of the harvest and
we're seeing the fruit of the labor. But there are other times in which we're simply out
sowing the seed, sowing the seed. When you're sowing the seed, it takes time for that seed
to germinate, to produce. But we can understand that God said that His Word would not return
void. God said that His Word is powerful, that His Word is profitable. And we go forth
and we sow the Word of God, the seed of God's Word, and we try to be faithful. We seek to
please the Lord in what He's called us to do. And we understand that with all the oppositions
and all the difficulties and all that's taking place, that the one word for us is continue.
Continue. Continue. Continue what? Continue what? I'm going to give you 12 thoughts this
morning. Just two points and then 12 thoughts, amen? I'm going to give you 12 thoughts this
morning of in what areas we can continue. But here's my challenge for you. It's not
an exhaustive list. There may be some things that you're able to add to this list, maybe
immediately. There's some thoughts that you have and some areas in which you can continue
that you should continue, that we should continue. Maybe throughout this year as you are reminded
of our theme as we study through these books, 1 and 2 Timothy, as we are meditating on this
thought of continue that God would help us add to this list. Of in what areas should
we continue? Number one, we better continue praying. Continue praying. Never stop praying.
God hears and answers prayer. Prayer is a unique privilege for every child of God. What
a great truth.
God has given us direct access to the throne of God. He says that we can come boldly unto
the throne of grace. We can go to Him at any moment for any reason. Never stop praying.
Continue praying. Why? Because when we pray we get to see what God can do. Now unto Him
that is able to do exceeding, abundantly, above all that we ask or think. And ultimately
what's the purpose? That He would receive the glory. That He would receive the honor.
That it would be obvious to us and to those around us that God did it, that God worked,
that God answered the prayers of His people. God hears prayer and He answers prayer. His
answer may not always be immediate. But we must continue to pray. Praying is difficult.
Praying is challenging. Praying is battle. There's a great spiritual battle that takes
place when you and I enter into our prayer closet. Why? Because the enemy hates prayer.
Because the enemy knows that God has chosen to use prayer to move the hand of God, to
change the circumstances. We must continue to pray. Number two, we must continue rejoicing.
You know how easy it is to complain? You know how easy it is to murmur and to complain
about the circumstances and the issues? No, no, no. We must continue rejoicing. You know
God is pleased to hear the praise of His people. The Bible says that He inhabits the praise
of His people. We find that it is well pleasing in His sight when we lift our voices in praise
unto His name. We find that it's lovely, that it's comely, that it's appropriate for God's
people to exalt and praise His name. David says, come and let us exalt the name of the
Lord. Let us praise our God. We must continue rejoicing. You say, but pastor, do you see
the news? Do you see the things that are happening? Listen, continue rejoicing. Why? Because my
God is on the throne. My God rules and my God reigns. And listen, my God is victorious.
Your God is victorious. Thanks be to God which giveth us the victory. We too are victorious.
We sing the song victory in Jesus. I've read the back of the book, amen? If you read the
scriptures through in a calendar year, I typically read the Bible more than once a year, so it's
been a little while since I read the book of Revelation. I didn't finish it up this
morning as maybe some of you did on a calendar reading. Guess what? We win. We win. We're
victorious forever. I will be with my God. We have so many reasons to rejoice. Don't
allow the circumstances. Don't allow the perilous times. Don't allow the persecution
to keep you from rejoicing. No, we got to continue rejoicing. Number three, continue
reading your Bible. Continue reading your Bible. You say, well, I read it last year.
Read it again. I read it the year before. Read it again. You know what I do? I just
said this to Holly last night. In fact, the last several months I've been reading from
a different Bible, still King James Version. I don't have any other version of a Bible,
but from a different Bible because this is my preaching Bible. I've read through this
Bible I don't know how many times, and so I started reading probably four or five months
ago from a different Bible. Why? Because it doesn't have all my notes in it. It doesn't
have the underlines and things. Now it's starting to get marks in it, but I want to go fresh
and I want to look at it. Why? Because I want the Spirit of God to speak to me. The Bible
says of itself that his word is quick. That word doesn't mean that it's fast in the sense
of somebody winning a race. No, it's alive. God's word is alive. And God will use his
word in your life and in my life on the day in which we need what we need from God and
he'll speak to us. And what a blessing to be able to read and reread and reread. And
listen, as many times, I don't know, I've lost count. I wish I would have kept track,
but I never did. I don't know how many times I've read through the Bible. But can I tell
you? It never gets old. It just doesn't get old because God will teach you something new.
God will minister to you in a new way, in a fresh way. There's 1189 chapters in this
book. You don't know all of it, neither do I. You know how many times I preach through
a passage of Scripture and then a few weeks later I read through that passage of Scripture
in my daily devotions and I say something like this, I wish I would have thought about
that when I preached that message. Why? Because it's a living book. We sing the song with
the kids, read your Bible, pray every day. And you'll, Lydia, grow, grow, grow. Right?
Don't read your Bible, forget to pray. And you'll shrink, shrink, shrink. This is a little
song for the Sunday school kids, but what a great truth. We're going to be students
of the Word of God. Continue reading your Bible. Continue, number four, memorizing Scripture.
Wherewithal shall a young man cleanse his way, by taking heed thereto according to thy
word. Thy word have I hid in mine heart, that I might not sin against thee. Bible memorization
is something that has almost, in our churches today, it's almost been reserved for children.
We need to be memorizing Scripture. Memorizing Scripture. I've read accounts of people in
foreign nations that have had various people groups come in and occupy and try to destroy
and one thing that has been consistent, they take a Bible away from people. I wonder the
morning, if somebody took your Bible away, how much do you know? How much have you memorized?
How much can we rehearse? I remember when I was in Bible college one night, we had an
old-fashioned tent revival meeting and we're in that tent revival and there's all the sound
equipment out there so they had some of us college guys sleeping in the tent that night
so that, you know, nothing would happen to the materials and what have you. And we're
supposed to be out there for some security purposes and we're laying there trying to
get to sleep and we just began, the group of us that were there, just how many verses
can we memorize? How many verses can we quote? We just began quoting verses and each one
of us take a turn and quote a verse, quote a verse, quote a verse, quote a verse, quote
a verse, just keep going around. Man, it was encouraging. We need to continue memorizing
Scripture. Number five, we need to continue attending church. Listen, there's no place
like church. I'm thankful for church. Understand this morning that church is not the place,
it's not the building, it's the people. Understand this morning that we're the body of Christ.
Understand this morning that the church is not man's idea, the church is God's idea.
For Jesus Christ said, I will build my church and the gates of hell shall not prevail against
it. I'm thankful for a local church. I'm thankful for the opportunity to have, obviously, pastor
a local church, but I'm thankful that God gave me the opportunity to get plugged into
a local church right after I got saved. The local church means so much to me. The local
church. Continue attending church. Continue, number six, sharing the gospel. Continue sharing
the gospel. You say, no one wants to hear. You just keep continuing sharing the gospel.
The Lord told the disciples about going into a city and if they don't receive you just
shake the dust off and go on. Continue. He didn't say come up and give up or come back
and give up. No, he said just continue, just go on. And this morning I understand there's
a lot of people that aren't interested in hearing the gospel, but we must understand
this morning that we must continue to share the gospel. The gospel is the power of God
unto salvation to everyone that believe it, to the Jew first and also to the Greek. Listen,
we have, if we stop preaching the gospel we have no reason to really even be here. We've
been given, we've been entrusted to share the gospel. We've been given the gospel. We
must continue. Number seven, we must continue investing in eternity. Investing in eternity.
You say, pastor, the economy. You know how many people I've heard tell me things about
the economy in the last six months? I mean, this is going to happen and that's going to
happen and this is going to happen. It makes my mind go crazy. But we're going to invest
in eternity. We don't give because the economy's good. We give because it's Biblical. Amen?
Amen? We give because it's Biblical. We don't give because we get a tax break. We give because
it's Biblical. You know there's some countries, some nations in which they don't have the
kind of tax system that we have. They don't have the kind of economy that we have. But
you know what believers do each and every week? They worship the Lord through giving.
Some people they give grains because that's what they have. God's blessed us abundantly.
We must continue to invest in eternity. The greatest investment that we could ever make
is to invest in eternity. The Bible says, as we would look at the book of Philippians
in the fourth chapter, that my God shall supply all your need according to his riches in glory
through Christ Jesus. This offering that's mentioned in Philippians chapter 4 was really
missions giving as they would give to Paul as he would have the opportunity to go and
share the gospel as a missionary. And we find that there was an investment and Paul says
it's not that I desired a gift but fruit that would abound to your account. Wow! God's economy
is different than our economy. And I understand there's a lot of concern amongst a lot of
people with regard to what economic crisis we must face or we might face. But the reality
is that my God is still...
on the throne, and my God's still good.
One day, according to the, during the Tribulation, according to the book of Revelation, at some
point a day's wages are going to be necessary to buy a daily portion of food.
We're not there.
Thankfully, I'll never be there, I'm not going to live through the Tribulation.
But the reality this morning is that God's been so good to us.
So often we hear of people, and I don't seek to criticize anyone, I believe it's an important
aspect to be wise and to be prudent and to do some retirement planning, but not at the
expense of investment eternity planning.
Retirement is not a guarantee for any one of us.
The person that owned that property before they sold it to have two houses built there,
her plan was to move there and retire and build a house.
She bought that property in 1978.
You know why she's not building a house?
She never made it to retirement.
It's sad.
That was her plan.
There's a lot of people that don't ever make it to retirement, but can I tell you this
morning, we're going to make it to eternity.
We must be investing in eternity.
Number eight, continue obeying the Lord.
Just continue to obey.
Lord, I will obey.
Just simple obedience.
Simple obedience to what thus saith the Lord.
John chapter number two, Mary says to those servants, whatsoever he saith unto you, do
it.
Do it.
Just obey.
Number nine, continue serving the Lord.
Now is not the time to quit serving God.
It's time to continue serving the Lord.
It's time to serve Him more than we have in the past.
Why?
For we see the day approaching.
We know that we're living these last signs.
We know that Jesus is coming.
We know that we soon will put off our earthly tabernacle as Peter and Paul speak of, and
so we must continue to serve the Lord.
Continue singing.
I love to sing.
I don't always sing on tune.
Peter can tell you all about that.
But I love to sing.
I hope God's given you a song.
Just continue to sing.
You know, singing is something that's, it's amazing the impact that it can have on your
life.
You go through some difficulties, you go through some trials, you have some of these perilous
times.
Just begin to sing.
Sing songs that are biblical songs.
Sing songs that exalt the Lord.
Sing songs that help you to understand how great God is.
All of a sudden as you begin to sing those wonderful songs, those songs of Zion, if you
will, those hymns of the faith, how it will help you spiritually.
By the way, the Bible would tell us in the book of Ephesians in the fifth chapter about
being filled with the Spirit of God, and as we're filled with the Spirit of God, the evidence
of being filled with the Spirit of God is that we're speaking to ourselves in psalms
and hymns and spiritual songs, singing and making melody in your heart to the Lord.
That's an evidence of being filled with the Spirit of God.
Continue singing.
I love the old hymns.
We sang those songs this morning.
Man, I was encouraged.
I sing the mighty power of God.
Wow.
My Savior's love, oh, how marvelous, oh, how wonderful.
Man, it just does something for you.
Continue singing.
Number 11, continue loving people.
Continue to love people.
You say, but they don't love me.
They're not lovable.
Continue to love people.
We're filled with the Spirit of God.
He allows us to spread abroad the love of God.
Continue to love people.
I've said this before, I believe that it's biblical when you look at the book of 1 Thessalonians
in particular, a number of other areas you could look to.
We find in the book of 1 Thessalonians specifically that as Paul ministered to the believers in
Thessalonica, that those believers, they knew that he loved them, and then he was able to
minister to them.
He was able to teach them and even correct them and help them.
I've said this, you've heard it in various contexts, no doubt, people don't care how
much you know until they know how much you care.
Love people.
Love them to Jesus.
You know, I'm thankful that Jesus loved them unto the end.
His love is a perfect love.
John 13 verse 1 speaks about, He loved them unto the end.
This is a perfect love.
But as His children, not only would they love one another, but we're to love our enemies.
Love our enemies.
Number 12, continue trusting the Lord.
Look at a variety of things that are taking place, say, well, I can't see, I don't know
what's going on, just continue to trust the Lord.
He's trustworthy.
Great is thy faithfulness.
We sing the song and how encouraging that song is, but I want you to understand that
He's never failed you and He never will.
Continue to trust the Lord.
Again, that list is not exhaustive.
Things that you could immediately, no doubt, add to the list.
Things that the Lord will help you in the days and weeks and months ahead to add to
that list.
Where is it?
How is it that I need to continue?
Listen, there's a great danger in giving up, going back, throwing in the towel.
The midst of all of the circumstances in which we face, the difficulties, the perilous times,
the persecutions, the single word that Paul would exhort Timothy with, continue, continue.
I'm so thankful that God's given us the truth.
I'm thankful to have a Bible.
I'm thankful to know the Lord, and this morning, I want to encourage you, and throughout this
next calendar year, 2024, I want to be encouraged every single week to continue.
As we look at 1 and 2 Timothy, and we go verse by verse through these wonderful books, how
we'll see Paul using his own life as an example of one that continued in the midst of great
opposition.
He left an example, and then he says to Timothy, continue.
For each of us this morning, we've been admonished to continue.
The exhortation is plain, it's clear, continue.
This morning, I hope that you have a level of excitement as we look at this new calendar
year, 2024, to study these books afresh, to be challenged, to be encouraged, to be helped
in our walk with God.
Know that you have an enemy.
Oh, he's going to try to discourage you and derail you.
In fact, he may try even this afternoon.
It's just the way he works.
Have you found it to be so?
Just keep your eyes on Jesus, looking unto Jesus, the author and finisher of our faith,
and by God's grace and with God's help, we will continue.
We will persevere.
We will be steadfast in the work that God has called us to do.
We will not depart.
We will, there's no turning back, no turning back, no giving up.
We continue.
Father, we love you.
We thank you for loving us.
We thank you for the privilege, the opportunity that you've given us to gather together this
morning.
God, we thank you for the many blessings in which you've bestowed upon us.
We thank you for your Word, and Lord, we thank you for this text of Scripture, these two
books that we'll have the opportunity and privilege to study through here in 2024.
And God, I pray that you would help us to be aware, have the knowledge.
As Paul explained to Timothy the things that he would face, the things that shall come,
Lord, that we'd have that understanding.
And Lord, I pray that you'd help us to receive and respond to the exhortation to continue.
Lord, I pray that not one amongst us would turn back or give up.
Help us to, by your grace and with your help, help us to continue.
God, I pray that if there's one here this morning, one that's tuned in via live stream
this morning that's not sure of heaven, they've never trusted the Lord Jesus Christ as their
personal Savior.
In fact, they came here this morning, and the truth be told, they do not know for sure
if they were to die that they'd go to heaven.
God, I pray that the Holy Spirit of God would work in their hearts and lives, help them
to understand the truth of your Word, the power of the gospel.
I pray they'd understand that they're sinners and the consequence for sin, and understand
that you loved them and you died for them.
You rose conquering sin, death, and the grave.
You offer to them a gift.
The gift is eternal life.
And God, I pray that today they would not leave this place without knowing for sure
that heaven is their home, that they would receive the gift of God, which is eternal
life.
I pray for every child of God, Lord, I pray that you'd help us.
No doubt, we've experienced the attack of the enemy.
His methods are varied.
Maybe we're in the midst of a serious spiritual battle even at the moment.
Maybe the thoughts have crossed our minds.
of giving up or turning back. Maybe, Lord, we have contemplated that idea. I pray that
you'd help us this morning to be encouraged. Help us, Lord, to be determined that by your
grace and with your help that we will continue. We'll continue to serve you and to live for
you. God, I pray that you'd move and work in the midst of this invitation as only you
can. I pray that decisions would be made that would please thee. Well, thank you for the
work that you'll do, for it's in Christ's name we pray. Would you stand with me? Heads
are bowed, eyes are closed. At the end of our services, we have a moment of invitation
where we give an opportunity for folks to respond.