This morning the book of 2 Corinthians chapter number 8 will be back in our study through
the book of 2 Corinthians and we are making really good progress through the book on Sunday
mornings and then we got to chapter 5 and we really slowed down.
There was so much in chapter 5, spent a few weeks there and then it's been kind of getting
through this next little bit of the section and I've been mapping things out.
I do believe that by God's grace and with God's help we will finish the book here in
the calendar year of 2025 and so I've tried to map some things out and be prepared for
that and so we're looking forward to what God has in store for us.
Last time we were here in the book of 2 Corinthians chapter 8 two weeks ago, we looked at verses
16 and 17 and really asked the question, how is God working in your heart?
We noticed that in verse number 16 that Paul begins to rejoice and he says, but thanks
be to God which put the same earnest care in the heart of Titus for you.
And we mentioned that Paul understood how God was working but also who God was working
in and how God puts something in the heart of His people and I'm thankful that God knows
our hearts, I'm thankful that God wants to use us for His glory and I'm thankful that
if we would yield to Him and surrender to Him that God will do a great work in and through
us.
As we continue through this latter part of chapter number 8 we begin looking at verse
18 down through verse number 24 this morning and the Bible says this, and we have sent
with Him, speaking of Titus, the brother, unnamed child of God, it says that we've sent
with Him the brother whose praise is in the gospel throughout all the churches.
And not that only but who was also chosen of the churches to travel with us with this
grace which is administered by us to the glory of the same Lord and declaration of your ready
mind avoiding this that no man should blame us in this abundance which is administered
by us providing for honest things not only in the sight of the Lord but also in the sight
of men.
And we have sent with them our brother whom we have oftentimes proved diligent in many
things but now much more diligent upon the great confidence which I have in you.
Whether any do inquire of Titus he is my partner and fellow helper concerning you or our brethren
be inquired of they are the messengers of the churches and the glory of Christ.
For show ye to them and before the churches the proof of your love and of our boasting
on your behalf.
As we look at this text of scripture I've alluded to it the last couple of weeks that
we find that here at the end of chapter 8 the apostle Paul is communicating to the church
in Corinth about this offering that was being sent.
It's referred to as this grace also we see it here in the text of scripture to travel
with us with this grace.
In verse 19 speaking about this offering remember he starts chapter 8 by commending
the churches of Macedonia that though they were in deep poverty they gave liberally and
he mentions about they first gave their own selves to the Lord and we mentioned and we
studied through that we find that then the apostle Paul encourages and really challenges
the church in Corinth.
He commends them in all that they had going on and all that they were doing but he wants
them to be complete in Christ to be mature and he says to abound in this grace also in
verse number 7 and they were not to be engaged in these things and leave this thing undone
or to be engaged in these things and leave this thing undone but to be complete and to
be mature and Paul challenges them with regard to their walk with the Lord.
As we enter the latter part of chapter 8 we find that this offering is now being sent
and delivered and Paul will once again in verse number 24 provide one additional charge
if you will to finish up the chapter to the believers in Corinth to get involved.
It is not explicitly stated within the text of scripture that there was some concern on
the part of the Corinthians on whether or not the offering if they were to give an offering
what would the security and safety measures be of that offering actually being delivered
and all of the things that could go awry.
It's not explicitly stated in the text of scripture but we find that as Paul is giving
an explicit detail with regard to how this offering is being transported that he's answering
those questions whether they're verbalized or otherwise we find that they're being answered.
We look at this text of scripture I've titled the message meet for the master's use and
you say that term sounds familiar.
It's a verse that we find in 2 Timothy chapter 2 and verse number 21 and there the Bible
says this a man therefore purge himself from these he shall be a vessel unto honor sanctified
and meet for the master's use and prepared unto every good work.
The word meet there in 2 Timothy 2 and verse 21 and we use the title for this text of scripture
this morning meet for the master's use that word meet carries with it the idea of being
easy to make use of being useful and we find that our master the Lord Jesus Christ our
savior he is looking for people human beings that he can use to carry out his purpose in
this world.
You know it's an amazing truth that we find throughout the entirety of the Bible that
God uses people.
He uses his people and I ask the question as we look at verses 16 and 17 what is God
doing in your heart and as we finish looking at the text and we consider meet for the master's
use we find that here in 2 Corinthians chapter 8 this latter portion of this text that God
provides us with a record of this offering being sent but we read of Titus and other
unnamed brethren that were entrusted with this task and we find that these though the
scriptures do not say it I believe that as we look at this text of scripture that we
could say of these individuals that they were meet for the master's use.
They were used of God to complete a task that God had for them.
What does God want to do through you?
What does God want to do in your life?
How does God want to use you for his honor and for his glory as we examine our lives
as we examine this portion of scripture we ought to rejoice in the fact that God has
used people but recognize this morning that God wants to use me.
Maybe it's exciting to read of the people that God has used.
It's exciting to read of the people that are recorded in the scriptures that God has used
and often times we think of some of the most prominent characters and we can rattle off
their names and we can think of their prominence and maybe they fill many pages of scripture
with their name being on it and all that God used them to be but then at times even in
this text of scripture there's some unnamed brethren that God used.
You know there's a lot of people in the scripture that God used that we really don't know about.
Like the details of their name and who they were and all those kind of things and the
reality is that we could look at church history over the last couple thousand years and we
could read biographies and autobiographies and we can read of individuals that God used
and we ought to rejoice in that but we also must recognize that God wants to use me.
God wants to use me.
Paul's with the Lord, amen?
Titus is with the Lord.
These unnamed brethren they're with the Lord.
You start naming some people that we've known in recent history that God has used to accomplish
much many of them are with the Lord but God has us.
He always has a remnant, He always has a people and we find that in every generation
it is our responsibility to make ourselves useful to the master.
As we look at the text of scripture we find a few things that are mentioned to us that
we could gain from this text that we could look and apply in our lives.
Notice number one if you're taking notes as we think about these that were meant for the
master's use we notice first of all that they were recommended.
Notice they were recommended.
In verse 18 the Bible says this and we have sent with him the brother whose praise is
in the gospel throughout all the churches and notice in verse 19 and not that only but
who was also chosen of the churches to travel with us with this grace.
And so we notice in verse number 19 that this unnamed brother that is referenced here that's
going to go with Titus and Paul and others we find here that the Bible says in verse
number 19 who was also chosen of the churches to travel with us with this grace.
They were recommended.
The Bible would reveal to us that this individual again whose name we do not know there were
the churches there they recommend.
Now think about a recommendation.
ever been asked to give a recommendation for someone?
Have you ever asked someone to be a reference for you
to make a recommendation on your behalf?
And the reality is that it is not a light thing
to make a recommendation.
It is not a light thing to recommend someone for a task.
Before making a recommendation,
there are some things that you need to know.
Would you agree?
And before you take that step
and go out on the limb, so to speak,
and put your name attached to someone else
that you're going to recommend,
you wanna know some things about their character.
You wanna understand some things about who they are,
and your name is on the line.
See, there are some times that I've had experiences
in the past in various contexts where someone would say,
well, if you recommend them, then I'll take it,
I'll trust it.
Man, that means that they're taking
my recommendation seriously.
That means that they trust me, right?
Now, I don't want that trust to be violated,
so therefore I'm not going to make a recommendation lightly.
Does that make sense?
Because I don't wanna make a recommendation
and someone say, okay, I'm gonna trust you,
and then it's a disaster.
And then who do they look at?
They look at the one that made the recommendation.
And we see that in life, we understand that.
We've had a couple of instances here in our church
where we have taken individuals on for support,
only two that I can remember that we took on for support
before they ever came here to present their ministry
to our church.
And it was based upon a recommendation.
And it was based upon some circumstances
where they could not travel to be here.
And the most recent one is actually one
that's a missionary of the week this week,
the Huckaboe family, they cannot come here
to present their ministry.
If they did, if they were able to travel and be here,
they would need an interpreter.
And yet we had the opportunity to minister alongside them
in Panama last summer, and what a blessing,
and God is using them in a great way.
And we find here in our text that this brother,
these brothers, it seems as if there's two of them
if you look at verse 19 and verse 22,
and I'm not gonna argue whether there was one or two
if it's the same person being spoken of,
but we noticed they were recommended.
Notice number two with me, they were reputable.
They were reputable.
I understand that this goes hand in hand
because of their reputation, because they were reputable,
they were recommended for their task.
But I want you to understand that the Bible says this
in verse 19 that they were chosen of the churches
to travel with us.
But then notice back in verse number 18
where the Bible says, and we have sent with him the brother
and then notice this phrase with regard to the reputation
that they were reputable, whose praise is in the gospel.
Notice this, throughout all the churches.
Wow, what a reputation.
I mean, this is an individual that's reputable.
This reveals to me that these individuals were engaged
in the work of the Lord.
They were doing God's work.
They were busy doing what God had entrusted them to do.
They were not sitting on the sideline.
They were not sitting on the premises.
They were not waiting for that perfect opportunity.
No, they were rolled up the sleeves and get engaged
in the work of the ministry and do what God
had given them to do.
You know, the reality is those that are faithful
and little will be entrusted with much.
Is it not a biblical truth, a biblical principle?
And we find that we look here at the text of Scripture
and we find that they had this great testimony.
They had this praise throughout all the churches,
but we notice whose praise is in the gospel
throughout all the churches.
See, they were engaged in the work of the Lord.
I believe that through looking at the phraseology
that is used in verse 18, that these people had a burden
for lost people because it specifically says
whose praise is in the gospel throughout all the churches.
You know, we need to have a burden
to reach people with the gospel.
The gospel is the power of God unto salvation.
Amen, do we believe that?
Do we believe that you're to preach the gospel
to every creature?
I know Brother Cottle, dear friend of mine,
he's preached here a couple of times in the past
and he says, ye means me.
And I like that because the reality is that
we're to be engaged in preaching the gospel
of the Lord Jesus Christ.
The Bible tells us, continue to look at the fact
that these men were reputable.
Notice with me in verse number 22, the Bible says this,
and we have sent with them our brother.
Then notice this phrase, whom we have oftentimes
proved diligent in many things.
So you find that as you look at that phrase
right in the middle of verse number 22,
that the Apostle Paul as he's writing back
to the church at Corinth and he's challenging them
and encouraging them to be engaged in this offering
and we find that he's speaking about those
that have participated, now those that are going
to carry the offering.
And he says that these that are going to go with Titus,
that we have proved them.
Notice, we have oftentimes, not just one time,
but we have oftentimes, there's this pattern of behavior
that has been observed, this diligence,
this serving the Lord, this integrity of character.
The Bible says that we have oftentimes proved diligent,
but then notice this, in many things.
You ever feel like you're so busy,
so many things going on?
Listen, it's exciting to be busy in the work of the Lord.
Amen?
A preacher friend sent me a text a couple weeks ago
and asked how things were going.
I said, man, we just got back from Idaho,
we did this, this, this, blah, blah, blah.
Here's what we got coming up on the calendar.
He said, it sounds like you're busy.
I said, listen, I'd rather be busy serving God
than busy doing anything else.
Amen?
I understand we got a lot of things to do.
I understand, I was in the work world,
in the corporate world.
I understand what it is to work a job.
I understand all of those things.
And I understand, and some of you may not understand,
and that's okay, I understand how much it takes
to be able to deal with the business side of a church.
It's a lot of work.
But I like being engaged in the work of the Lord.
And they prove diligent in many things.
The Apostle Paul, as he's writing here
to these believers in Corinth,
he says that these that are going and taking this offering,
this grace, that they are reputable.
They have this reputation that they're busy
serving the Lord, that they've been diligent,
that they've been proved.
And I believe that's so important as we look
at those two aspects by way of starting this passage
of Scripture, that these individuals,
that they were recommended, they were reputable.
This morning, what kind of reputation do I have?
What kind of reputation do you have?
In the workplace, in the community?
How do people view us?
What do people think of us?
And the reality is that we ought to have a reputation
that is God-honoring.
I understand they may not like our God,
they may not know our God, they may not serve our God,
but they ought to be able to understand
that we're upright people, that we're honest in integrity,
and we operate in such manners
and that we've proved diligent, amen?
I've often said this, the best employee at any company
ought to be the Christian employee, amen?
What's over thy hand find it to do?
Do it heartily, as unto the Lord, right?
Not unto men, but as unto the Lord.
And the Christian ought not be the lazy worker, amen?
Ought to be the most diligent.
You say, that means I get more tasks.
I understand, it's how it works.
We've experienced that, but the reality is
that this reputation that these individuals had,
that they were entrusted with taking this offering.
There was not, we live in a different environment
and society, culture than what they lived in.
We have means of doing things very differently
than what they had means of accomplishing tasks
in this particular era.
There was no safe way for them to really transport
this offering that had been collected
other than individuals that were trustworthy individuals
from the churches taking that offering
and delivering it by hand.
So we have banking systems, we have all kinds
of things today, we, most of our, well,
all of our monies that we send to our missionaries,
they either go to a mission board or to a local church.
And we send those monies and many times it's a check
and you think about the transfers that can be made,
it's super simple.
But in this era, they'd have some trustworthy people.
And by the way, the task wasn't easy.
You know, it's really easy to sit down at a computer,
it takes time to do it, but it's really easy
to sit down at a computer and type in some things
and print out a check compared to taking an offering
and walking or getting on a boat
and then getting on some donkeys
and you understand what I'm saying.
And the fact that they were recommended for this task,
that they had this reputation speaks volumes
of their character.
We ought to be the kind of people that someone would be willing to make a recommendation
for us.
You know what?
I know that person.
They're honest.
They're going to do a good job.
They're trustworthy.
They've been proved to be diligent in many things.
Notice with me as we continue looking at the text of scripture, I would say this.
Number three, they were resolved.
I was beginning to think about their resolve of these individuals and the way in which
they made themselves available.
Again, meet for the master's use.
Someone who is easy to be used, to make use of.
Someone that is useful.
We find that they were resolved.
They were entrusted with this task.
But understand with me that this task would take them away from their normal activities.
Think about this.
They would have to travel, be apart from if they had families, their job responsibilities,
whatever their duties and responsibilities were for a season.
They would have to be separated from those things in order to carry out this task.
And yet they were willing.
They were willing to be engaged in the work of the Lord at that level.
And they were resolved to do some things.
Number one, I believe they were resolved to honor the Lord.
You know in all that we do, we ought to seek to bring honor and glory to God.
Whether therefore you eat or drink or whatsoever you do, do all to the glory of God.
And we find that these individuals, notice again in verse number 19, and not that only,
but who was also chosen of the churches to travel with this grace, which is administered
by us, notice this, to the glory of the same Lord and declaration of your ready mind.
In verse 23, whether any do inquire of Titus, he is my partner and fellow helper concerning
you, or our brethren be inquired of, they are the messengers of the churches, notice
this, and the glory of Christ.
And so we find that there's this desire, there's this resolve on the part of these individuals
that they're resolved to honor the Lord.
You know, how is it that God wants to use you to bring honor to His name?
What is it that your hand can find to do that God can entrust you with a task that you would
make yourself available and useful to Him, and you're resolved through this task, through
this work, through this call that God has placed on my life, my desire, my only desire
is that God would receive honor and glory.
You know, it's amazing what can be accomplished when individuals only care that one receives
the glory, and that's God.
You know, all of a sudden, when people start trying to get the honor and recognition and
glory for themselves, and I did this, or they did that, and all that sort of thing, man,
it just kind of gets all kinds of sideways.
But the reality is that as I look at this passage of Scripture, and I think about these
that were meant for the Master's use, what was it about them?
We see their character, they were reputable, they were recommended, but then they had some
resolve, we want to honor God.
This task was presented to them as an opportunity that they would have to honor the Lord through
fulfilling this task.
I believe that they were resolved, number two, to operate with integrity.
You know, integrity is so important, so vital, that we operate with integrity.
We find in verses, in this text, in verse 20 and 21, notice what Paul says, avoiding
this, that no man should blame us in this abundance which is administered by us.
And so what is he trying to avoid?
Well, he has these brethren that are going to accompany Titus and him, and they're going
to go with this offering, and he wants to avoid any blame.
He wants to avoid someone bringing accusation against them, that it wasn't handled properly,
that there was a lack of integrity or honesty, and Paul says, no, no, we're going to avoid
all this.
And then we read in verse 21, providing for honest things, then notice what he says here,
not only in the sight of the Lord, but also in the sight of men.
Listen, we know today that God sees everything and knows everything, and we ought to live
our lives in the presence of God, and we ought to live with integrity, but we understand
there are human beings that are watching us, and we need to understand the importance of
living a life of integrity before them as well.
You know, it's a tragic thing, and we read it so frequently.
It's a tragic thing when a church is in the news, in the media, on the highlights of the
news for wrong reasons, for embezzlement that has taken place, for improprieties that have
taken place, for adulterous relationships that have taken place.
I mean, you fill in the blank, we see it in the news all the time, and it's a tragic thing.
Why?
Because it gives opportunity for the enemy to, to really mock our God, it really does.
You know, as Christians, followers of Christ, there's got to be a resolve that we're going
to operate with integrity.
We're just going to operate with integrity.
What's right is right.
I talked to someone in my office a while ago, and they had visited our church, they were
asking some questions, and it was a good conversation, and part of the conversation evolved into
talking about some ethical kind of things, and I said, listen, it's real simple.
Right is right, and wrong is wrong.
You ever hear people talk about situational ethics?
No, no, no.
There's just ethics.
It's right, it's right, it's wrong, it's wrong, amen?
There's no put me in this situation, and we're going to determine what's right or wrong,
or put me over here in this situation.
No, no, no.
It's just right or it's wrong.
I understand that we live in a society where they call evil good and good evil.
We live in that society, but that's nothing new under the sun.
Isaiah and Jeremiah were writing about that stuff a long time ago, twenty-five, twenty-seven
hundred years ago, they're writing about that stuff, amen?
And here we are, and we understand we're living in that kind of society, but we ought to be
the kind of people that, that have a resolve.
We're going to operate with integrity, we're going to honor the Lord, we're going to operate
with integrity.
Paul says this is so important, that we're taking this because we want to avoid something,
we want to avoid that no man should blame us in this abundance which is administered
by us.
We're taking precaution, we're going the, you ever hear somebody say we're going to
take the extra mile?
Why?
Because we want to be above board, we want to be a completely transparent.
Integrity, integrity is important, honesty is important.
And he says providing for honest things not only in the sight of the Lord, but also in
the sight of men.
And so we begin to look at these, that we're going to take this grace, that we're going
to, to fulfill this task, they were resolved to first honor the Lord, to number two operate
with integrity.
I believe that as we look at the text of scripture, they were resolved to cooperate
one with another.
You know, cooperation is so important, here's another word that we could use for it, teamwork.
You know, we are laborers together with God, and it's a joyful thing, we're on the same
team, amen?
Listen, if we're brothers and sisters in Christ, we're on the same team, we're not in competition
one with another, amen?
We all have our own callings and our own gifts, and we're all to fulfill and to do what God
has called us to do for the honor and glory of God, and we see that we're on the same
team, we're on the winning side, as the songwriter said.
I had a pastor friend that's not far from here, and he says, listen, if you have a good
day, I'm rejoicing with you.
Why?
Because we're on the same team, we're not in competition.
I don't, listen, I don't have the kind of pastor friends, and I know there's some guys
out there like this, and the Lord bless them, and that's fine if they want to be that way,
but I'm not, I don't get on the phone with pastor friends, how many did you have yesterday,
how many decisions did you have, how many this, how many that, no, no, man, look, if
God blessed, man, I'm excited for you, I'm rejoicing with you, why?
Because listen, we can't reach the entire world by ourselves, and God has different
lighthouses and different communities that are seeking to do the same thing that we're
seeking to do, and we find that not only are we to cooperate one with another, but
did you see the plurality of the name?
They were recommended of the churches.
Is that what it, is that what it says?
So that's plural, right?
I know I'm not an English scholar, but it's plural.
So listen, I believe that as you look at this text of Scripture, there's a few people at
a minimum that are taking this offering, they're not all from the same church, but
they're all cooperating for the same purpose, and ultimately what's the purpose?
Listen, if you think it's to deliver the offering, you've missed, because the ultimate purpose
is to bring glory to God.
Yes, through that offering, God was going to use that.
He was using all those people, and listen, all the people that gave the offering weren't
able to go and travel to deliver the offering, right?
And there were some people that had to give the offering, and I would guess, I can't prove
it biblically, but I would guess that the people that are carrying it also contributed
to the offering.
Right because I don't think they'd be counted to deliver it if they weren't participating in it
but but they gave
They collected and then it had to be delivered
There's cooperation notice what the text says read it with me and see how they're cooperating one with another in verse 23
notice what Paul says whether any do inquire of
Titus now Titus is the one that we started this section with in verse 16 that Paul is
Rejoicing because God put something in the heart of Titus
But we find that there's others that are gonna go with Titus unnamed brethren
And so he starts in verse 23 whether any do inquire of Titus. How does he describe Titus? He is my
Partner and
fellow helper
Concerning you aren't those good words
Partner fellow helper listen iron sharpeneth iron
We need each other
God designed it that way
Amen
You said I'm just kind of I like to be to myself. Listen, you need godly encouragement
Edify one another pray one for another
We need that and he says that that he is my partner and fellow helper concerning you
You know what? Paul is saying. Listen, there were some amazing things that Paul was used of God to do
But then there were other times that God
Used other partners like Titus to help fulfill something that Paul was not going to personally be able to do
and he says here's here's the the testimony of Titus and then he says this notice at the end of verse 23, or
our
Brethren be inquired of so if anyone's gonna inquire about Titus, I want you to know that he's my fellow helper
He's my partner and then he says this or our
Brethren be inquired of that's why I think it's more than one because it's plural again. He says our brethren be inquired of they are
notice what it says the
messengers of the churches and
the glory of Christ
So ultimately it's to bring honor and glory to God that's the purpose
But they're resolved to work together to cooperate one with another and let me encourage you this morning
That we need to cooperate one with another
That we need to understand that we're partners that were fellow helpers
you read throughout the God or throughout the the New Testament and you read of people that God has used and that our
Fellow helpers of the of the ministry. I want you to turn over quickly to the little book of 3rd. John
Look at the little book of 3rd. John
And in this little book
There are three different characters
That are all very different one from the other
we read in this little epistle 3rd John of
the one that I want to mention this morning of Gaius and
Gaius is referred to as being the well-beloved
Notice in verse number one the elder under the well-beloved Gaius whom I love
in the truth
Beloved I wish above all things that thou mayest prosper and be in health notice what he says even as thy soul
Prosperous, you know, I'm thankful that though the outward man perish that our inner man can be renewed day by day
Amen, he talks about his soul
Prospering he says I pray that you would be in good health that you would prosper and be in health
Even as my soul prosperous in the same way that you have that that inner strength and that soul
Prospering I I desire that you would prosper
Physically in in health that way for I rejoice verse 3 greatly
When the brethren came and testified of the truth that is in thee even as thou walkest in the truth
You know what's interesting about verse number three the first two points that we looked at this morning from 2nd Corinthians 8
Recommended and reputable. Do you see what it says in verse 3?
I rejoice greatly why when the brethren came and testified of the truth that is in thee
Even as thou walkest in the truth
So what was he there was a recommendation these brethren came and testified and said that he was walking in truth. He had a reputation
Notice in verse number 4. I have no greater joy than to hear that my children walk in truth beloved in verse number 5 thou
Doest faithfully
Whatsoever thou doest to the brethren and to strangers
I love verse number 5 and I'm challenged by it because the reality is that this man Gaius
He was not just doing faithfully the things that he loved
Sometimes we might be assigned a task that may not be exactly what we really want to do
How do we do it do we do it faithfully as under the Lord what's over thy hand finder to do
Do it heartily as in the Lord not unto men
And he said that thou doest faithfully whatsoever thou doest
To the brethren and to strangers which have borne witness of thy charity before the church
Whom if thou bring forward on their journey after a godly sort thou shalt do well
Because that for his namesake they went forth taking nothing of the Gentiles
We therefore ought to receive such notice this last phrase here in verse number 8 that we might be fellow helpers
to the truth
Fellow helpers Paul says Titus
He's my partner and my fellow helper these other unnamed men. These are the messengers of the churches
There's a commitment to cooperate one with another there's a resolve that we're going to cooperate with one another
Some plant
Some water, but God gives the increase you ever find yourself in the position where?
You're planting it's hard work
Hard work planting
Going out there and sowing the seed
Going faithfully so in the seed
Then sometimes you get to water
Maybe there's a good contact. Maybe there's a follow-up
There's a an opportunity to be able to engage in deeper
conversation go further with the gospel and there's some some watering that takes place and every now and then God will give you the
Opportunity to be in a place where you get to see fruit
It's God that gives the increase
But sometimes as we would experience our working with the Lord and cooperating with him being laborers together
That we see that fruit we see God working
Remember what Paul said and he's writing to the same people here at the church in Corinth
But he says this in the book of 1st Corinthians who then is Paul
Right. Is that what he said now Paul? I mean sometimes when we think about Paul we think of him in a very high
Position and he's the Apostle Paul
You know, Paul was a humble man
He didn't want others to think more highly of him than they should
Not only did he not want to think more highly of himself than he should he didn't want other people to think more highly of
Him he refers to himself as being the chief of sinners
And he says who then is Paul we're just ministers
What's our resolve? Are we resolved to honor the Lord?
Are we resolved to to operate with integrity we resolve to cooperate one with another and then let me say this finally I
Believe that they had resolve to complete the task
No turning back and no quitting
It requires focus it requires resolve I do not pretend to understand all that they would experience on this journey
But I understand that a journey in this era of human history
And the task that was entrusted with them was a challenging journey
It was a journey that could be met with much opposition and difficulty
And we find that as they would engage in this work as they would be
Entrusted and as they would trust God to use them. They were they were resolved that they were going to complete the task
They they didn't get into the work to get out of the work, you understand I'm saying
Remember in verse 22 Paul says that we have oftentimes proved
That that whom excuse me. We have oftentimes proved diligent in many things
But then notice he continues but now much more diligent upon the great
Confidence which I have in you and so we find that the Apostle Paul
As as it's been communicated to these brethren that would be entrusted with this task
There had to be this resolve that that that they're gonna complete listen life gets challenging sometimes
You say sometimes I mean life's challenging all the time. I understand some of us have that law. Amen
You say pastor just seems like has been challenged after challenge after challenge after challenge after challenge. I get it
But God's with you
You know the world faces challenges I told you about that guy on Thursday
He was
You ever you ever meet somebody and you can just tell by looking at them there they're dealing with something. It's just all over him
This guy was dealing with some stuff. I can't sure he shared some stuff with me
But he said
The God that I believe doesn't even care
Listen, I'm thankful that
On my journey with my God that when I face difficulties that God's with me
me. He said, I'll never leave thee nor forsake thee. He said, My grace is sufficient for
thee. And we find that, listen, there's going to be some difficulties. There's going to
be some opposition. There's going to be when, listen, Nehemiah, I'm going to go build. I
want to rise up and do something. And then what happens? Man, you got Sanballat and Tobias
and you got everybody that's coming against you. Right? You understand. But the resolve
to finish, to complete. See, God wants us to finish. He wants us to finish well. The
enemy wants to distract us. He wants us to lose our focus from finishing. I think about
a couple of verses of scripture. Look at Hebrews chapter 12, if you will, just very quickly.
It's a text that's familiar to us. As you're turning to Hebrews 12, let me remind you of
1 Corinthians 15, 58, as Paul is writing to the same group of people. Therefore, my beloved
brethren, be ye steadfast, unmovable, always abounding in the work of the Lord. For as
much as you know that your labor is not in vain in the Lord. You know that's at the end
of Paul writing to the believers in Corinth about the truth of the resurrection. This
mortal shall put on immortality. Amen? Praise the Lord. And he says, because we have this
hope and this assurance, therefore, my beloved brethren, be ye steadfast, unmovable. Listen,
God wants us to start the race, but He wants us to finish. He doesn't want us to just start.
He wants us to finish. To complete the task. Wherefore, in Hebrews chapter 12 and verse
number 1, wherefore, seeing we also are compassed about with so great a cloud of witnesses,
let us lay aside every weight and the sin which doth so easily beset us and let us run
with patience the race that is set before us, looking unto Jesus, the author and, what,
finisher of our faith, who for the joy that was set before Him endured the cross, despising
the shame and is set down at the right hand of the throne of God. For consider Him that
endured such contradiction of sinners against Himself, lest ye be wearied and faint in your
minds. Remember what Jesus told the disciples before He'd go to the cross. He says, listen,
they're going to hate you, but they hated me before they hate you. We're going to deal
with opposition, but we've got to have a resolve to finish. Put our hand to the plow and not
looking back. We're going to serve Jesus. We're going to complete the task He's given
us to do. Not under my own strength, but trusting in His strength. Because I can't overcome
all of the opposition, but greater is He that is in me that He that is in the world.
Amen? And with Him, we are more than conquerors. And we can have the ability as we yield ourselves
to Him to, for God to use us. No turning back, no quitting. I remember growing up, and my
dad wouldn't let me quit anything. And I appreciate that. You know, sometimes things get tough
in life. It's easy to quit when it gets tough. But you know, when you just persevere, push
forward, have that resolve, you learn some things. From a spiritual perspective, you
learn some things about God. When you feel like you can't go on, but God can. God can
work through you. God can do what you cannot do. There's a story, it's a true story, of
a Tanzanian runner, Akari, from the Olympics in 1968. It's an interesting story. The Olympics
that year were held in Mexico. He was representing his country, Tanzania, and he was representing
his country to run the marathon. I've never run a marathon. I thought about it once. I
began training for it. I looked at the number of, the population of the world that has ever
run a marathon. It's super small percentage. And I thought, I'd like to be in that category.
And then I got up to running about 10 miles, and I thought, this is silly. And I never
went further than that. I was training and training and training. I got to 10 miles.
I said, I don't have time for this. You've got to run 26.2 miles. Amen. And this man,
he was going to run the marathon, and he went to represent his country, 1968. You can look it up.
And he finished the race about one hour after the winner finished the race. He was battered,
hurt, injured, had fallen, various things had taken place, and he barely limps across the
finish line, an hour. Many had not finished the race that had started the race. He's being
interviewed afterwards, and he said something that's so, so vital. Here's what he said when
he was being interviewed. He said, my country didn't send me 5,000 miles to start a race,
but to finish a race. They didn't send me 5,000 miles to start a race, but to finish a race. You
know what I'm thankful for in the Christian life, in our race? We're not competing against one
another like they are in a marathon. There's not a first place and a last place like there
is in a marathon. I don't know where your finish line is, and I don't know where my finish line
is. But by the grace of God, we're going to be resolved that we're going to complete the task
that God has given to us. And we're going to have that resolve. God used me. See, Paul comes to the
end of his life, and I know it's such an important, familiar text of Scripture, but he says, I am now
ready to be offered. The time of my departure is at hand. I have fought a good fight. I have
finished my course. I have kept the faith. That's not only finishing, but that's finishing well.
Because he said, I finished and I kept the faith. Hallelujah. He finished well. But you know, Paul
himself had resolved. You don't need to turn there. I'll read in closing this morning what he says in
Acts 20 and verse 24. He says, But none of these things move me, neither count I myself dear unto
myself, my life dear unto myself, so that I might finish my course with joy in the ministry which I
have received of the Lord Jesus to testify the gospel of the grace of God. Listen, when you
acknowledge, as I believe these brethren in 1 Corinthians, 2 Corinthians chapter 8 had to
acknowledge, that God is the one who entrusts to us the spiritual gifts, and he gives us the
opportunities to serve him. Listen, God's looking for some people. I'm thankful for those that have
gone before us. I'm thankful for Paul and for John and Peter, and you named the apostles, and I'm
thankful for those that came up through the ranks over the centuries and those that were faithful to
stand for the truth of God's word. I'm thankful for those that invested in me personally that are
nearing the end of their race, some that have already finished their race. I have professors
that I had in seminary and Bible college who are with the Lord now. God used them, but God wants
to use us, and are we meet for the Master's use. God used these folks in 2 Corinthians chapter
number 8 for a task that was specific for a time and a purpose, but God has a task for you today.
What is it? Are you meet for the Master's use? Are you desiring, Lord, use me? God, I want you to use
me for your glory, for your honor, because God is looking for some people to use for his glory.
One of the saddest verses I've ever read in the book of Ezekiel specifically says that the Lord,
he sought for a man, but it finishes this way, but I found none. Man that would stand in the gap
and make up a hedge, but I found none. I hope this morning that God would look at your life
and my life and say, I can entrust them with something to do for me, because we desire nothing
more but for God to be honored and glorified, and we're resolved to finish, to work together,
to operate with integrity. God, use us for your glory. Let's pray. Father, we love you this morning.
We thank You for loving us, thank You for the record that we have in this text of Scripture
of how You use these individuals.
And as we can rejoice at what You did in and through their lives, and we can learn various
aspects of their character because of what we read, we are challenged this morning and
we are recognizing this morning that God today, in September of 2025, that You're desiring
to use us to fulfill Your purpose and Your will.
God, I pray that we would be the kind of people that are meet for Your use.
Lord that You would take our lives, that we would be fully consecrated to Thee, that God
You would use us to make an impact in this world, that Your name alone would be honored
and glorified.
I pray that You'd move and work in hearts and lives as only You can, and we'll be careful
to give the glory for it's in Christ's name we pray.
Would You stand with me?
Heads are bowed, eyes are closed.
This morning, if you're not sure of heaven, I didn't preach the gospel much this morning,
we spoke about it briefly.
If you're not sure of heaven, we'd love to take a Bible and show you how you can know
for sure that heaven is your home.
This morning, maybe during the invitation, you just need to come to the altar and say,
God, I'm available, I want You to use me.
God, I'm resolved, as these individuals were in this text, I want to be used of Thee.
As Kimberly plays, the altar is open.