worthy, and he is worthy of our praise,
and we ought to thank him for it.
What a wonderful song,
and glad to have some folks visiting with us this morning.
We do trust the service to be a blessing to you,
and certainly thank you for being here,
some for the very first time,
some who have been here before,
and we thank you for coming again.
Galatians chapter number four this morning,
Galatians chapter number four,
and I'll be looking at a couple of verses of scripture
here from the book of Galatians this morning.
We'll look at a number of other portions
as we get through the message this morning,
but we've been dealing with all year our great God,
great is the Lord, and greatly to be praised,
and we started the very first Sunday of the year
with this statement that God is great,
and why is God great,
and how is it that we would describe the greatness of God,
and it's one thing for us to stand and say
we serve a great God,
but then when we begin to put some meat on that statement,
God is great because of,
and we have some biblical truth
as to what makes our God so great,
and I'm thankful that he's declared to us
that he's a great God,
and we can discover his greatness
as we study the pages of scripture.
We find that God has given us,
just as he's done to so many others
throughout the centuries,
the revelation of his greatness.
Over the past couple of weeks,
we've dealt with the truth that God is great
because of his great care for us,
and I'm so thankful to be a child of the Lord
and to know that he cares about me.
He knows everything about me,
and he still cares about me,
and he cares about you.
He cares about all of us collectively and corporately,
and what a great God that we serve.
Over the next few messages,
I'm gonna deal with the subject matter
that God is great because of his plan,
and you say, what do you mean because of his plan?
Well, God has a great plan,
and today, we're gonna deal
with his great plan of redemption,
but we find that we'll go through,
and the last message that we'll deal with
with the subject matter of God's plan
is his plan for the ages,
and I'm so thankful that God has a great plan.
Maybe you say, how is it that God's plan
reveals God's greatness?
Well, no doubt in my mind,
you, like myself, have made plans before,
and there are times in which we've made plans,
and we thought they were just the best plan
that's ever been ever been made,
and it's failed.
That ever happen to you?
You plan something, it just doesn't come to pass.
There are extenuating circumstances.
There are obstacles.
There are hindrances that come up
that prevent your plan from being executed,
and you say, man, that was a great plan,
but it's not executed,
and I look at the scriptures.
I look at God's precious word,
and I find that God developed a plan,
specifically with the plan of redemption
that we'll look at this morning.
He developed a plan,
and though that plan had been opposed
by the devil and his angels,
we find that the plan of redemption was completed.
It was finished,
and what a blessing to understand
that God has a plan for you.
He has a plan for me.
God has a plan for the ages,
and though the world might stand in opposition to God,
and though the devil and all of his angels
might try to oppose the plan that God has for the ages,
we can be confident in knowing this morning
that God's plan will come to pass.
It's a great plan with regard to the content of the plan,
but it reveals the greatness of God
because he's able to bring it to fulfillment,
and what a blessing to consider that this morning.
We look at this portion of scripture,
and I'm reminded of what William Scroggie said years ago
in a book that he wrote,
and he summarized the Bible,
the totality of the Bible.
He summarized it this way,
that God's word is the unfolding drama of redemption.
It was a single statement that he made
in summarizing the content of this great book.
I happen to like the summary statement.
I'm thankful for all that God has contained
within his word,
but if you were to draw one precious truth
from God's word,
I'm thankful that it's God's word
that contains within it the plan of redemption,
and what a blessing to know that we can be redeemed.
We didn't sing the song this morning,
but often we sing the song about being redeemed,
and we're familiar with the song Redeemed,
how I love to proclaim it.
Redeemed how?
By the blood of the lamb.
That's the only way to be redeemed,
and the songwriter said in another song,
I stand redeemed by the blood of the lamb,
and what a blessing to understand
God's great plan of redemption.
The word redemption from a theological perspective
is the purchase of God's favor
by the death and suffering of Christ.
It's the ransom or the deliverance of sinners
from the bondage of sin,
and the penalties of God's violated law
by the atonement of Christ.
As we begin to think about this truth
of God's great plan of redemption,
I wanna draw your attention here to Galatians 4,
and verses four and five,
actually look at verse number three,
the Bible says this,
even so we when we were children
were in bondage from the elements of the world,
but when the fullness of the time was come,
God sent forth his son,
made of a woman, made under the law.
Why?
To redeem them that were under the law
that we might receive the adoption of sons.
We're gonna deal with this great plan
of redemption this morning.
I would ask this question with our first point
is why this great plan was required?
Why was this great plan required?
Well, we see in verse number five,
the answer to the question
as to why God sent forth his son,
it is to redeem them that were under the law.
The reason that this great plan of redemption was required
is because we are lost in sin.
We find that the Bible tells us that we are sinners,
and we understand that God has developed
this wonderful plan of redemption,
and it's important for us to recognize this morning
that this plan of redemption
was developed in eternity past.
In eternity past, God who is eternal,
who has no beginning and no ending,
God developed this great plan of redemption.
Why?
Because he knew that there would be sin
that would enter the world through Adam and Eve.
And though he created Adam and Eve
in a perfect environment without sin,
we know that the Bible records for us
in Genesis chapter number three,
the events leading to the entrance of sin into the world.
And we find that God in his knowledge,
his infinite wisdom,
his all-knowing transcending time from eternity past,
he knew that would take place,
and therefore he created,
he developed this plan of redemption.
It was required because of sin.
It's interesting, some have said to me over the years,
I remember one individual that was just in great opposition
and very angry over the fact that
because of the transgression of Adam,
because of the sin of Adam,
then I have to pay a consequence
because of something he did,
and just so angry over that.
And the fact of the matter is that this morning,
you understand that God,
before Adam and Eve ever sinned in the garden,
God developed this plan.
If you were in the garden,
guess what you would have done?
You would have sinned.
And by the way, we're not guilty because of Adam's sin,
we inherit a sin nature because of Adam's sin,
and we are guilty on our own.
There's not one amongst us that could stand and say,
I'm without sin.
We're all guilty.
It's not hard this morning.
Typically, it's not challenging to speak to someone
and to get them to agree to the truth that they've sinned.
Now, the degree of their sin,
the understanding of the consequence of their sin,
that's a different story,
but there are times I've spoken with people.
In fact, just on Thursday, I said to someone,
I said, listen, have you ever sinned?
They just kind of chuckled and said, of course,
everyone has.
That was their response.
Now, they didn't think they were that bad of a sinner
because they didn't do that many really bad things.
They acknowledged that they were a sinner.
The problem was they had a difficulty acknowledging
the penalty for their sin,
understanding the payment that was made for their sin.
But as we begin to think about this truth of God's plan
of redemption and the requirement,
why this was required, look over the book of Ephesians,
if you will, in the first chapter,
and I want you to see what God says here
in Ephesians chapter number one.
With regard to the plan of God,
this plan of redemption being developed by God
in eternity past.
The Bible says in the book of Ephesians,
just a few chapters over a few pages from where you were
there in the book of Galatians,
we find the Bible says this in beginning in verse number four
of Ephesians one,
according as he has chosen us in him,
notice what the Bible says before the foundation
of the world,
that we should be holy without blame before him in love,
having predestinated us under the adoption of children,
Christ to Himself, according to the good pleasure of His
will, to the praise of the glory of His grace, wherein
He hath made us accepted in the Beloved, in whom we have
redemption through His blood, the forgiveness of sins,
according to the riches of His grace. We just sang about
God's amazing grace just a few moments ago, and we see
here that the Bible talks about the riches of His grace
in Ephesians 1 and verse number 7, and we find that in
eternity past, before the foundation of the world, before
sin ever entered into the world, that God developed a
plan for man to be redeemed. And that plan required that
Jesus Christ, God in flesh, go to a cruel cross, be
crucified for you and for me, be buried and rise again.
And we find that that would be the only way for man to
be redeemed. That's the plan that God developed. It was
required because man was separated from God because of
our sin, and God in His grace and His mercy, He comes and
He says, I'm going to provide a way so that you can be
redeemed, so you can be reconciled to God. See, because
we were at enmity with Him, the Bible says that all are
sinners, and because of that, we are separated from God
and we're in need of redemption. We're in that
bondage to sin. I said this when we were teaching
Vacation Bible School just several weeks ago to the
class that I was teaching. I said to those young people,
I said, listen, you don't become a sinner because you
sin. You sin because you're a sinner. It's our sin
nature. And this morning, we find that this truth is
universal, that all are born sinners. And therefore,
this great plan of redemption was required because man
was separated from God. We find that this plan includes
the very way in which man would be redeemed. There's
only one way. Jesus said this, I am the way. He didn't
say I am a way. If He said He was a way, then certainly
it would be open for us to say, well, there are many
ways by which we can reach God. But we find this
morning that the Bible tells us that Jesus boldly
declared, I am the way. The one and only way. One way,
God said to get to heaven. Jesus is the only way. But
I'm a pretty good person, but I've done this and I've
done that and I'm working to do this and so on and so
forth. Jesus said, I am the way. For by grace are you
saved through faith, and that not of yourselves. It is
the gift of God, not of works, lest any man should
boast. No doubt today there are many people in our
world that are sincere in what they believe. They're
sincere in believing that they could be a good person
and somehow they could attain salvation. But the
reality is that we cannot attain salvation. We simply
obtain it. And we are given the gift of God, which is
eternal life through Jesus Christ our Lord. We can't
work for it. We can't earn it. And those that hold to
that belief, though they might be sincere, I would say
with great compassion, but with certain conviction
that God's Word plainly and clearly states to us that
you can be sincerely wrong. This morning the plan was
required because man sins. Man is a sinner in need of
redemption. I want you to notice with me not only why
the plan was required, but number two, what this great
plan reveals. What does this plan reveal to us? This
plan of redemption that God developed before the world
began, before the foundation of the world. He says, and
again if you look at Ephesians chapter number one,
help me, or I want to help you to understand that He's
not speaking about the who of salvation, but He's
talking about the how of salvation. Again He said that
we should be holy without blame before Him in love. And
verse number five, having predestinated us unto the
adoption of children by Jesus Christ to Himself. That's
the only way to be saved, to be redeemed is through the
Lord Jesus Christ. And He's dealing with the how. God
developed this plan of redemption and He says this is
how man can be saved, can be redeemed. But I want you to
notice what this plan reveals to us. Look over at First
Timothy chapter number one if you will. In First
Timothy chapter number one, Paul is writing here into
the inspiration of the Holy Spirit of God. And as he's
writing, he's speaking about his own testimony. He's
rejoicing in the opportunity that he has to serve God. But
in that same section he reveals to us something with
regard to the plan of redemption that we see God's
abundant grace. Notice in verse number 12 of First
Timothy one, the Bible says, And I thank Christ Jesus our
Lord, who hath enabled me, for that He counted me
faithful, putting me into the ministry, who was before a
blasphemer, and a persecutor, injurious. Notice where he
says, But I obtained mercy, because I did it ignorantly
in unbelief. And the grace of our Lord, notice how it's
described, was exceeding abundant with faith and love
which is in Christ Jesus. And so God's great plan of
redemption reveals to us His abundant grace. It says in
verse number 15 of First Timothy one, This is a
faithful saying and worthy of all acceptation, that Christ
Jesus came into the world to save sinners, of whom I am
chief. Understand this morning that Jesus came with a
singular purpose. He came with a singular purpose. There
are many things that Jesus did while He was here upon
this earth during His earthly ministry. We can read of
the gospel accounts, and we can read of the great
miracles, and we can read and understand even as Peter
would tell us later that He left us an example that we
should follow His steps. And no doubt we can look at the
life and ministry of the Lord Jesus Christ, and we can
learn some very valuable lessons with regard to living
for Him and pleasing Him. But understand that the
singular purpose by which Jesus came was to save
sinners. To save sinners. That's why in the book of
John He so often reveals to us that phrase with regard
to the hour, the reason, the purpose by which He came to
this earth. And so we find that here in First Timothy
chapter number one, this great plan of redemption, it
reveals to us God's exceeding abundant grace. I'm so
thankful for God's exceeding abundant grace. I know that
we just sang amazing grace, and it is amazing, and we
sing, and they played for the offitory today, and can it
be, and that leads us to the second thought as to what
this plan reveals to us is not only His abundant grace,
but His amazing love. So thankful for God's love. We're
familiar with the verse in John 3, 16, for God so loved
the world that He gave His only begotten Son that
whosoever believeth in Him should not perish, but have
everlasting life. Amazing love, the songwriter said,
how can it be that thou, my God, shouldst die for me?
Amazing love, indeed. And this plan that God developed
in eternity past reveals to us His abundant grace, reveals
to us His amazing love. We need to think about this plan
of redemption, and it's required because we're sinners.
It reveals to us God's grace and God's love. But we
understand that this plan that God developed had to be
fulfilled. And I want you to understand this morning that
the enemy tried to do everything he could to thwart
the plan of God. Satan and all of his angels did everything
he could to thwart the plan of God. I want you to consider
with me just a few thoughts with regard to the opposition
to the plan of God, with regard to this plan of redemption,
this great plan of redemption. I want you to understand
that it was opposed even during His birth. Think about
His birth, and if you were to precede the account that's
given to us in the Gospels with regard to the birth of
Christ, and even go back to the Old Testament, you'd
understand that the enemy was active even during that
time to try to thwart the plan of God. How? One way was
by eliminating the messianic line. You read the book of
Esther, and there's so many wonderful truths in the book
of Esther, but you understand that the hatred of Haman
towards the people of God was a demonic hatred. And it
was no doubt in my mind a plan of the enemy to try to
eliminate the messianic line. Because if he could have
all Jews killed, the Messiah was to come through that
seed of Abraham. He said, I didn't say the promise was
a seed in the book of Galatians, not seeds, but seed,
speaking of Jesus Christ. And so why is Haman so hatred,
such hatred toward Mordecai?
But we find that he says,
I want all the Jews to be destroyed.
The enemy seeking to eliminate the messianic line.
We can read how that many attempts
throughout the Old Testament
that were made to defile the messianic line.
I want you to think about the truth
in Matthew chapter number two,
when those attempts by the enemy
to thwart the plan of God
through eliminating or defiling the messianic line.
I want you to see that after the Lord Jesus Christ was born
that there was one by the name of Herod.
And we're familiar with the text,
we're familiar with what took place,
but I want you to read it with me this morning.
We read so often verses one through 12,
and really even backing up into the first chapter
of the book of Matthew, beginning in verse 18,
and reading about the announcement of Christ's birth
and the adoration of the Lord Jesus Christ
and those that would come and bring the gifts
and all of those things.
But we find that the Bible tells us
in Matthew two in verse number 13,
and when they were departed,
that's these men that came that were bearing these gifts.
It says in verse 13,
behold, the angel of the Lord
appeareth to Joseph in a dream saying,
arise and take the young child and his mother
and flee into Egypt and be thou there
until I bring the word for Herod
will seek the young child.
Why?
To destroy him.
Why was Herod gonna destroy Jesus?
Preventing Jesus from going to the cross of Calvary,
seeking to thwart the plan of God
that was developed in eternity past.
Notice in verse 14, when he arose,
he took the young child and his mother by night
and departed into Egypt.
And was there until the death of Herod,
that it might be fulfilled,
which was spoken of the Lord by the prophet saying,
out of Egypt have I called my son.
Notice in verse 16, the Bible says then Herod,
when he saw that he was mocked of the wise men
was exceeding wrath and sent forth
and slew all the children that were in Bethlehem.
Can you imagine?
Such wicked behavior.
So all the children that were in Bethlehem
and in all the coast thereof from two years old and under,
according to the time which he had diligently inquired
of the wise men.
You're gonna think about the hatred.
This is the enemy seeking to thwart the plan of God.
How do we keep Jesus from going to the cross of Calvary?
We'll kill him in his infancy.
Think about this, during his life,
we find that this attempt to defile
and to eliminate the messianic line,
this attempt to kill Jesus in his infancy,
these are not successful.
And so therefore, during the life and ministry
of the Lord Jesus Christ,
you'll read right after his ministry commences
where Satan tempts him.
Then you'll read multiple times throughout
the gospel records.
We don't have time this morning to look at the examples,
but you'll read of those that tried to kill Jesus.
What was the significance of killing Jesus,
of stoning him or throwing him over that precipice
or any other manner in which they would kill him?
Well, the issue is that the Bible tells us
that Jesus would go to a cross.
That Jesus would go to a cross.
That's what God's plan of redemption required,
that Jesus go to a cross,
that he shed his precious blood for you and for me.
And we find that the enemy sought
to prevent that from happening.
I find that at the end of the life and ministry
of the Lord Jesus Christ,
that even there at the cross,
turn to Matthew 26, if you will,
I believe that leading up to the cross,
I believe that the enemy sought to oppose Jesus
to ever make it to the cross.
When you read of what takes place
in the Garden of Gethsemane,
I believe that all of the forces of evil,
that Satan and all of his fallen angels
were doing everything within their power
to keep Jesus from going to the cross.
In fact, the Bible tells us in Matthew 26,
notice what the Bible says in verse number 38.
It says this,
then saith he unto them,
my soul is exceeding sorrowful,
even unto death.
Tarry ye here and watch with me.
So often as we read this portion of scripture,
and perhaps you've heard someone say this before,
and I don't seek to argue with anyone
or to cause controversy,
but so often people will come to this passage of scripture,
and as they read where Jesus says,
to let this cup pass from him,
nevertheless not as I will,
but as thou wilt,
that so often people will say that Jesus was praying
that he would not have to go to the cross.
I don't believe that for one second.
Why don't I believe that?
Well, because Jesus said it was for that hour
that he was born.
It was the purpose.
By the way, Hebrews chapter 12 says that for the joy
that was set before him,
he despised the shame, right?
He went to the cross willingly.
He was not praying in the garden of Gethsemane
after his life and ministry,
after he had announced to the disciples
and to all those that he ministered to
that this was the purpose by which he came to save sinners.
In that hour, he was not praying to be released from that.
I believe in that hour that Satan
and all of the power of the enemy
was trying to kill Jesus in the garden
so that he could never get to the cross.
But guess what?
Jesus went to the cross.
He was arrested in the garden.
He went and he stood before the high priest
who was beaten, tortured,
delivered to Pilate,
and went to that cross.
Why?
Because the plan of redemption required it.
And though the enemy sought to do everything possible
to thwart the plan of God,
God's plan is great and reveals to us his greatness.
Why?
Because the plan came to pass.
The plan was fulfilled.
It was executed just as God prophesied it to be
after Jesus is on the cross.
Matthew chapter number 27.
Notice the opposition continues.
We sing the song typically during resurrection Sunday.
Up from the grave he arose.
The bars, they could not hold him, right?
He tore the bars away.
Up from the grave he arose.
But notice what happens in Matthew 27 in verse 64.
Look at verse 62.
The Bible says, now the next day,
that followed the days of the preparation,
the chief priests and Pharisees came together
and to Pilate saying, sir,
we remember that that deceiver said,
what a horrible way to refer to God as being a deceiver.
God cannot lie.
But notice what they said.
While he was yet alive, after three days I will rise again.
Command therefore that the sepulcher be made sure
until the third day, lest his disciples come by night
and steal him away and say unto the people,
he is risen from the dead.
So the last hour shall be worse than the first.
Pilate said unto them, you have a watch.
Go your way, make it as sure as ye can.
So they went and made the sepulcher sure,
sealing the stone and setting a watch.
Let me help you understand this morning.
Jesus didn't need his disciples to come
and steal him away by night.
Amen.
Jesus is gonna rise from the dead,
conquering sin, death and the grave.
And by the way, when we understand the truth
of the gospel, it is the death, the burial
and the resurrection of Jesus Christ.
It's the resurrection that proves that the sacrifice
at Calvary was acceptable by God.
Accepted by God.
We find that as you study that great prophecy
in Isaiah 53, the Bible talks about not only
the death of Christ, but it talks about
the resurrection of Christ.
You can read in the Psalms about the resurrection.
In fact, we find that the apostle Paul,
as you read Peter, is preaching and he talks about
this day have I begotten thee, referring to the Psalms.
That's not about the birth of Christ,
but about the resurrection of Christ.
You see that in the book of Hebrews.
And this morning, we find that though this plan
was opposed by the devil and all of those
that had power, that the plan was fulfilled,
revealing to us his greatness.
Finally, this morning, if you're taking notes,
not only why was this plan required,
because man has sinned, we are sinners
and we need to be redeemed.
What does this plan of redemption,
what does it reveal to us?
It reveals God's abundant grace.
It reveals to us his amazing love.
But number three, who does this great plan reach?
Who does this plan reach?
Who does it affect?
Who does it impact?
Well, very simply put, all people of all times.
Aren't you thankful for that?
The Bible says this, what a wonderful truth,
for whosoever shall call upon the name of the Lord
shall be saved.
That word whosoever is so precious,
because it means anyone.
This morning, as we begin to think about this truth,
we read in 1 Timothy 1 and verse 14 and 15
just previously about God's abundant grace
and how the apostle Paul says that this is a faithful saying
and worthy of all acceptation
that Christ Jesus came into the world.
world to save sinners. He then says of whom I am chief, but I
want you to notice that in chapter number 2 of 1st
Timothy as the Apostle Paul is giving instruction with
regard to prayer, then in 1st Timothy chapter number 2
there's a connection that we see in verse number 15 where
the Bible says that Christ Jesus came into the world to
save sinners of chapter number 1. And in chapter number 2
the Bible says this in verse number 4, who will have all
men to be saved and come unto the knowledge of the truth?
How many men? All men. All men. The plan reaches all
people of all times. The gospel is the hope of any
people. I preached a message at the beginning of this
month that the only hope for America is Jesus. But I said
this in the introduction to that message that this
message was being preached in the United States of
America on that particular day on July 2nd, 2023. But
the message that I was preaching on that day could
be preached anywhere around the globe because the only
hope for any people is Jesus. Why? Because God's great
plan reaches all people of all times. Now that's
amazing to me. That reveals to me an aspect of God's
greatness that He's developed this wonderful plan and
eternity past. He knew that man would sin. He knew that
man would be separated from God. But He developed a plan
that through Jesus Christ man could be redeemed. Man could
be reconciled through the blood of the Lamb. It was the
only way for man to be redeemed. And He offers this
plan and He's revealed to us this plan. And He says all
people of all times can receive this precious gift of
redemption. Isn't that wonderful? It's absolutely
just astounding as we look at this wonderful plan this
morning. We find that the Bible says this in 2 Peter 3
in verse number 9, that the Lord is not slack concerning
His promises. Some men count slackness. But His long
suffering to us we're not willing that any should
perish, but that all should come to repentance. And we
find this amazing God that we serve He's developed this
amazing plan, this plan of redemption. And He's so great
that He was able to bring this plan to pass, to
fulfillment that He says on the cross of Calvary, it is
finished. Hallelujah. This morning God's greatness is
revealed to us through His plan, specifically this
morning His plan of redemption. I wonder as we
speak about this plan of redemption this morning, I
wonder to make it personal have you been redeemed? Have
you been born again? Saved by the blood of the Lord Jesus
Christ? Understand this morning I've said this plenty
of times from this pulpit over the years that false
teachers will use our vocabulary, but they use a
different dictionary. What do I mean by that? They'll use
the term born again, but they mean something entirely
different. So let me make it crystal clear this morning.
Jesus in John chapter number 3 has an interaction with a
man by the name of Nicodemus. And Jesus says to Nicodemus,
ye must be born again. And Nicodemus in a time of
confusion and uncertainty as to what does this mean to be
born again? He says this, how can a man be born again when
he's old right? How can I as a grown man, how can I be born
again? Can I enter into my mother's womb a second time?
That's what he asks in John 3 specifically. He's not
tracking, he's not understanding. And Jesus says
except a man be born of water, physical birth, and of the
Spirit, second birth, being born again. Jesus did not say
to Nicodemus, ye must be born again. And Nicodemus inquires
and says, how can a man be born when he's old? And Jesus
says you need to be baptized. No, that's not what Jesus
said. There are some that would tell you that would say
to be born again is to be baptized. In fact there are
people that have told me as I've asked them before, are
you saved? Are you sure of heaven? Have you been born
again? Yes, I've been baptized. No, no, no I'm not
asking if you've been baptized. I'm asking if you've
been saved by the blood of Christ. This morning it's a
wonderful thing to be redeemed. To know that our
sins have been paid for, not by anything that I could do,
but all because of what Jesus did. Why? Because he loved
me. Because I deserved it? No, because he's gracious and
he's merciful and he loves and he offers us this free
gift. The Bible says, as you study the pages of
Scripture, that the gift of God is eternal life, but
prior to that it says the wages of sin is death. The
wages of sin is death. There's a great contrast
between a wage and a gift. What I earn for my sin is
death. Separation from God for all of eternity. That's
what I deserve. That's what you deserve for your sin.
That is the just judgment of God for your sin and my sin.
But God in his mercy and his grace, he says, but I offer
you a gift and the gift that I offer you is eternal life
through Jesus Christ our Lord. That's amazing to me. I
mean, listen, I know several this morning, you've been
saved, you've been born again, you have a testimony of
salvation, but I hope this morning that we are
overwhelmed with gratitude to understand this great plan of
God and to see how God's great plan of redemption was
opposed through the ages and Satan and his enemies did
everything they could to thwart the plan of God, but
God's plan was fulfilled so that we could be redeemed. So
that we could have a right standing with God. When we
sing the song redeemed, how I love to proclaim it, when we
say redeemed, we always make it clear that we're redeemed by
the blood. By the blood. It's not by any works that any
person could do. It's a gift. If you could work for it, it's
no longer a gift. It's something you've earned. It
would give you reason to boast. That's what he says in
Ephesians 2, verse 8 and 9. So I wonder this morning, have
you been redeemed? Could you stand here this morning with
100% confidence to sort of die today and go to heaven? Not
because of anything I've done, but because I'm redeemed by
the blood of the Lamb, because Jesus is my Savior. He came
into the world to save sinners. Paul says, of whom I am
chief. But I stand here this morning and say, I'm saved.
I've been redeemed by the blood of the Lamb. I wonder this
morning, will we praise Him for this great plan of redemption?
Will we praise Him for this wonderful, fascinating plan of
redemption? That God has infinite wisdom. He said, I
have to die for man. Think about that. He left the throne
room of heaven, all of the splendor and all of the glory
of heaven to die for you, to die for me. Oh, how we should
praise Him. How shall we escape if we neglect so great
salvation? Hebrews chapter number 2. It ought to be a song
in our lips every day of our lives that we're praising Him
for this truth of redemption. And then this morning I would
ask finally this question, will you tell someone about this
great plan? I mean, honestly, it's a wonderful plan. It's the
greatest plan ever, developed by God, fulfilled, finished. And
we can stand this morning with great confidence and with
biblical authority and say to anyone that we come into
contact with, Jesus died for you because He loves you. And
Jesus wants to redeem you. He wants to save you. We can stand
with confidence and with biblical authority, not just
with a thought that we have that we just want to be, you
know, reaching everyone. No, no, this is what God says. This is
what God's plan includes. And I'm so thankful for that. He
included me. He included you. Whosoever will may come. And
this morning, this plan of redemption needs to be shared.
You need to tell other people about it. It reveals God's
greatness. And this morning...
I hope that if you've never been redeemed, you're either here personally or you're watching
via live stream, oh, I would tell you that the Bible says today is the day of salvation.
The Bible says, boast not thyself of tomorrow.
We don't know what's on the morrow.
I would tell you that today is the day of salvation.
If you're not sure, man, we'd love to take a Bible and show you how you can trust Christ
as your personal Savior, how you can be redeemed, and have that confidence.
But for those of us that have been redeemed, oh, would we rejoice if we tell somebody?
Because this plan of redemption reveals how great our God is.
What a wonderful God we serve.
Let's pray together.
Father, we love you.
We thank you so much for loving us.
As we look at these truths this morning, I pray, God, you'd work in hearts and lives.
Maybe there's one, maybe there's several that are in the sound of my voice today that have
never trusted Christ as their Savior.
They could not stand and say, I've been redeemed, but I pray that they'd understand this great
plan of redemption was developed in eternity past.
Why was it required?
Because we're sinners.
It reveals your great love and grace, and it reaches every individual.
God, I pray that today they would accept the free gift of eternal life through Jesus Christ
our Lord.
They'd be saved, redeemed.
I pray for every child of God, Lord, many that are here this morning that I've heard
their personal testimony.
God, would you help us to rejoice?
Would you help us to share this wonderful truth with someone?
God, I pray that we would look for opportunities, pray for opportunities, and then seize those
opportunities to declare this wonderful truth of redemption.
Would you move and work in hearts and lives as only you can?
I pray that as we've been ready to receive truth from your Word today, that we would
be equally ready to respond, as we have this moment of invitation that we would be doers
of the Word and not hearers only, that we'd not delay, that we'd not put off.
I pray that you'd be honored and glorified through every decision that's made.
For it's in Christ's name we pray.
Would you stand with me?
Heads are bowed, eyes are closed.
Kimberly's going to pray.