given us a Bible, we have an opportunity to be in church
and to study His word, to be encouraged,
sing the great hymns of the faith.
It's wonderful, isn't it?
You know it's wonderful to be a Christian.
Amen?
Come on, it is wonderful.
We used to sing that chorus.
So it's wonderful to be a Christian.
How many of you know that chorus?
I'm not gonna sing it for you right now,
but you know it, amen?
Maybe we'll sing it at the end of the service tonight.
Somebody remind me, and we'll sing that chorus.
It's a good one.
It's wonderful to be a Christian.
Listen, it's the best life.
It really is, man, to know the Lord Jesus Christ,
your personal Savior.
Know that you're going to heaven, amen?
And all the blessings He daily loadeth us with benefits.
Have you found it to be so?
And what a joy and what a blessing.
Matthew chapter 12, I'm gonna read the 14 verses
that open this particular chapter,
get into the message this evening.
I want you to notice that in our text,
and I want you to make note of it in verse three
and also in verse number five,
the text says, have ye not read?
And this text of scripture provides us
with an interaction between the Lord Jesus Christ,
our wonderful Savior, and the Pharisees.
We see that it's repeated twice, have you not read?
And this phrase has captured my attention.
It's caused me to do some reflection
and also some meditation.
And for a little bit this evening,
I wanna just focus on this thought, have you not read?
And before we get into reading the text,
let me say this about the Pharisees,
the ones that Jesus would have this interaction with.
These Pharisees were religious leaders who were separatist
and they had a high view of themselves.
And I mean, they just really thought that they were,
and they considered themselves
to be the experts of the Old Testament.
They were the most devout
and the most knowledgeable interpreters of Jewish law.
And they'd be glad to let you know that.
I mean, that's just how they functioned, how they operated.
They considered themselves to be spiritual authorities.
And so when you begin to understand that backdrop
of who these Pharisees are
and what the opinion of themselves is,
it really kind of opens up a little bit here
of what's going on.
Notice the text begins and it says,
at that time Jesus went.
Notice it says specifically on the Sabbath day
through the corn.
Can I say this by way of introduction this evening?
God always moves with purpose.
He went through the field on the Sabbath day
on purpose and with purpose.
And we see that he always moves.
During his earthly ministry,
he was always moving on purpose and with purpose
in your life and in my life,
he's moving on purpose and with purpose.
And we find that it says that at that time,
Jesus went on the Sabbath day through the corn
and his disciples were in hungered
and began to pluck the ears of corn and to eat.
But when the Pharisees saw it,
they said unto him, behold,
thy disciples do that which is not lawful to do
upon the Sabbath day.
But he, Jesus said unto them,
have you not read what David did when he was in hungered
and they that were with him,
how he entered into the house of God
and did eat the showbread,
which was not lawful for him to eat,
neither for them which were with him,
but only for the priest.
Verse five, or have you not read in the law
how that on the Sabbath days,
the priest in the temple profaned the Sabbath
and are blameless.
In John seven and verse 22,
he'll mention about the circumcision,
really what he's talking about here in Matthew 12
and verse five, the circumcision had to be on the eighth day
and if it was a Sabbath day,
they still carried it out because it's on the eighth day
and so Jesus is making that reference.
Notice in verse six, but I say unto you
that in this place is one greater than the temple.
But if you had known what this meaneth,
I will have mercy and not sacrifice,
you would not have condemned the guiltless
for the Son of Man is Lord even of the Sabbath day.
And when he was departed thence,
he went into their synagogue.
Behold, there was a man which had his hand withered
and they asked him saying,
is it lawful to heal on the Sabbath days?
And it's interesting because the scriptures tell us
in verse number 10, their motive for asking the question
that they might accuse him.
Notice what Jesus says in verse 11,
what man shall there be among you that shall have one sheep
and if it fall into a pit on the Sabbath day,
will he not lay hold on it and lift it out?
Now, I think all of them could relate to that.
Jesus is dealing with their heart,
he's dealing with what they knew,
he's dealing with something that they could relate to,
they have a sheep and the sheep falls into the pit
and which one of you, if it's on the Sabbath day,
are you gonna go get that sheep out?
You're gonna go, notice, lay hold of it and lift it out?
And then Jesus says, how much then, verse 12,
is a man better than a sheep?
Aren't you thankful that man is created in the image of God?
Man has value because man is created in the image of God.
If Darwinian evolution is true,
and it's all just a chance, a random chance,
and we have no value and life doesn't really matter,
but we know that God created man
and we look at the creation account on day number six,
let us make man in our own image.
Aren't you thankful?
And then God so loved the world
that he gave his only begotten son to do what?
To die for the sins of humanity.
Man is valuable.
And here, Jesus says, how much then
is a man better than a sheep?
Wherefore, it is lawful to do well on the Sabbath days.
Then saith he to the man, stretch forth thine hand.
And he stretched it forth and it was restored whole,
like as the other.
Isn't that awesome?
The power of the Lord.
Then the Pharisees went out and held a council against him,
how they might destroy him.
It's always interesting when you read the interactions
between the Lord Jesus Christ
and the religious leaders of the day.
Here, specifically, the Pharisees.
And there's two separate interactions that take place.
One there, of course, is they're walking through the field
on the Sabbath day there and they begin to,
his disciples pluck the ears of corn and eat it
and they bring an accusation
and Jesus is going to speak to them about,
have ye not read?
And he references an account from the life of David
that's recorded in the book of 1 Samuel.
And he's referring back to a biblical truth,
something that they claim to be scholars of,
the Old Testament, experts in the Old Testament.
And then he says this in verse number seven.
He mentions, again, in verse number five,
going back to really numbers
and about the Sabbath day and the circumcision.
But then you read in verse number seven, he says,
but if ye had known what this meaneth,
oftentimes these religious leaders,
they would wear on their person,
they would wear scripture, scripture references.
And I often believe,
and you can look back at Matthew nine and verse 13
and see a similar interaction where Jesus says,
if you had known what this meaneth,
they seemed as if they outwardly knew all of this stuff,
but it was just kind of letter of the law.
And Jesus tells them a great truth in verse number eight,
that the son of man, the Lord Jesus Christ,
he is Lord even of the Sabbath day.
We find that it continues.
And there's a man that has this hand that's withered.
And he, of course, is going to heal that man.
And when they should have rejoiced
for seeing such a miraculous healing,
no, they talked and tried to figure out
how they might destroy him.
That's the heart of these Pharisees.
And we see contextually kind of these conversations,
these interactions, but I wanna zero in
for a few moments this evening on that question,
that really the four word statement there
that's given in verse three and again in verse number five,
have ye not read?
Have you not read?
Begin to meditate upon that,
begin to muse upon that statement,
that question that Jesus asked
when he is having this interaction.
And as I begin to really just allow the truth
to saturate in my heart and my mind
and begin to think about how important it is
that we have a Bible,
how important it is that we read the Bible
and we know the Bible.
Listen, I'm thankful that we have a Bible.
I'm thankful that all scripture
is given by inspiration of God, amen.
I'm thankful that God's word
has been providentially preserved for us,
that we hold in our hand a Bible
that is reliable, trustworthy.
Listen, you can trust this book.
I'm so thankful for that.
I'm thankful that God's word is profitable
and we can talk about all that God's word is,
but can I tell you this evening
that God's word is not gonna help you
by just having a copy of it.
I was teaching with the children, the teenagers,
I should really make sure I say teenagers, not children,
but they're kind of kids to me,
but I'm teaching the teenagers.
and we're talking about the situation there
when they found the book of the law
in the house of the Lord.
Isn't that awesome?
So what do you think they did with that?
Listen, they didn't take that
and put it on some pedestal
and put glass over top of it
and put a light on it and have a monument.
No, they took it and they read it.
Amen?
That's what they did.
And we find that as Josiah hears God's Word written,
he has got a tender heart and responsive
and he's broken and he rinses clothes
and all that takes place.
And we find that then,
after the interaction with the prophetess,
he says, gather all the people.
We're going to read it to them also.
Why? Because God's Word is powerful.
And God's Word needs to be read
and applied and understood.
And here Jesus says, have ye not read?
Now, I believe that these Pharisees,
they obviously had read.
They would tell you how often they read.
They'd memorize it.
I mean, have it memorized.
But they didn't really know it.
And this evening as I've meditated
upon the thought of have you not read,
we're going to look at a number of verses,
but I want to just give you a couple of thoughts this evening.
Number one, let me say this.
Reading the Scriptures is expected.
What do I mean by that?
God didn't give us a word.
He didn't give us a Bible
that it would just sit on a shelf somewhere.
God's expectation is that God's people
would read God's Word.
Does that make sense?
Have you ever sent somebody a letter?
I know we're not in the era of letters.
I understand that we're in the era of text messages
and instant messages and all of that sort of thing.
But you think about letter writing
or even if you do send someone a digital message,
the purpose of you sending that message,
you intend, you expect that it will be read.
Right? I mean, that's what the expectation is.
And so God is God.
Amen? Last Sunday night,
only God is great.
Thou art God alone.
Nobody told God that he had to write a Bible.
No one told God how long the Bible had to be.
God wanted to give us his Word.
He desired to reveal himself to us
not just through creation,
but through the written Word.
Yes, I'm so thankful that the heavens
declared the glory of God.
And you can see that truth as we read it in Psalm 19,
but it very quickly goes into the law.
The Lord is perfect
in all that God deals with there in Psalm 19.
And so God gave us a Bible.
He gave us his Word so that we would read it.
It's an expectation.
By the way, I would say it's a reasonable expectation.
It is reasonable that God would expect.
God loves us so much.
Some have referred to the Bible
as being God's love letter to his people.
And it's reasonable that God would expect us to read it.
And it's sad how often you talk to individuals
that they've not read the Bible.
They don't read the Bible regularly.
They have no plan for reading the Bible.
There are times, and you've heard me say it,
that people have this,
I'm going to read a psalm and a proverb every day.
That's wonderful,
but there's 64 other books in the Bible.
I love the book of Psalms,
and I love the book of Proverbs.
You say, well, I don't want to read Leviticus.
You should. It's good for you.
Amen?
Listen, it's important that we understand that God's Word...
Some people say, well,
we don't really need the Old Testament anymore.
We're in the New Testament.
Listen, the New Testament says
that the Old Testament was written for our learning
and for our admonition.
So how could we say that the Old Testament
isn't really important?
You can't understand the New Testament
without the Old Testament.
And so we begin to understand this evening
that the reading the Scriptures is expected.
And I believe it's a reasonable expectation.
We read it here, as we've noted in Matthew 12,
in verse 3 and verse 5,
where he says, have you not read?
Notice in Matthew 19, if you will,
and look at a couple of verses here
in the book of Matthew.
We'll be looking at a few other places
as we go through the message this evening.
But look in Matthew 19 and verse 4.
Matthew 19 and verse 4.
It says this.
I'll read verse 3.
The Pharisees also came unto him, tempting him,
and saying unto him,
It is lawful for a man to put away his wife
for every cause.
And he answered and said unto them,
Have ye not read,
that he which made them at the beginning
made them male and female?
And said, For this cause shall a man leave
father and mother, and shall cleave to his wife,
and they twain shall be one flesh.
That's going all the way back to Genesis 2.
Amen?
I mean, by the way,
when Jesus refers to the Old Testament,
he's authenticating the Old Testament.
And so we find that he says,
Have ye not read?
He asks that.
He has that interaction again with these Pharisees.
Verse 3 tells us, again,
another interaction with the Pharisees.
In Matthew chapter 22, notice in verse 31.
Notice what Jesus says in verse number 31.
Again, this statement,
Have ye not read?
And I'm going to jump right in the middle.
We're going to come back to this same passage
in just a moment.
But notice in verse 31,
but it's touching the resurrection of the dead.
Have ye not read?
That which was spoken unto you by God,
saying, I am the God of Abraham,
the God of Isaac, and the God of Jacob.
God is not the God of the dead,
but of the living.
When the multitude heard this,
they were astonished at his doctrine.
By the way,
it really leads us into our second thought this evening.
But we see number one,
reading the scriptures is expected.
And before I share the second thought,
let me just say this.
Have you ever read in the book of Acts?
Have you read Peter's message in Acts chapter number two?
Have you read Stephen's message in Acts chapter number seven?
It is absolutely full of Old Testament truth.
Both of them.
Messages that are just references back
to the Old Testament,
and just systematically walking through
and coming to a point of decision
for the hearers of those particular messages
and how well and how skillful they were
in using the scriptures.
And so they obviously,
if you think about Peter and Stephen,
those messages that are recorded for us in Acts two
and in Acts chapter number seven,
they knew the Old Testament.
They obviously spent time in it,
reading it and understanding it and studying it.
And so we see that reading the scriptures is expected.
I think God has every right to expect us to read his word.
I've heard some say,
nowhere in the Bible does it say you should read the Bible.
And Paul tells Timothy
that he is to give himself to reading and to exhortation.
And I think that definitely deals
with the reading of the scriptures,
the public reading, yes.
I think also we'll look at the book of Nehemiah here
in just a little while
as we get through the message this evening,
but they read the Bible.
Yes, there's the truth of meditation,
but we need to read God's word.
And as we read it and we saturate our minds
and our hearts with the truth of God's word
and we allow ourselves to become biblically learned
and we're able to interact
and to deal with things biblically.
Here it is, reading the scriptures, number two,
not only is it expected,
but number two, it exposes error.
Reading the scriptures exposes error.
You know how many people today have ideas
that are not right?
Because in the Bible quickly,
very quickly exposes the error.
And I understand, I'm not suggesting this evening
that we argue only from a perspective of Bible
because I understand that the apostle Paul says
that the natural man receiveth not the things
of the spirit of God
for their foolishness unto him,
neither can he know them
because they're spiritually discerned.
And so the reality is that
when I'm having a conversation with a lost person,
they don't accept the Bible as being God's word.
They don't accept it.
So I have to start at salvation for them.
I have to understand that the spirit of God
is going to convince them of the truth of God's word.
But I'm talking about Christians
that are living in error,
that have beliefs that are not right.
The Bible exposes error.
And when you're given some teaching and some thought,
you say, no, the Bible exposes error.
So as I'm reading the scriptures,
I'm able to be sound in the faith.
Bible talks about sound doctrine
and we need to be sound in the faith.
Notice if you will, I still have you here in Matthew 22.
Go back to verse 23.
We're going to catch the whole context here.
We read verse 31 down through the end
when he talks about have you not read,
but I want you to catch the whole thing in context.
In verse 23, the Bible says this.
Matthew 22, verse 23,
the same day came to him the Sadducees.
Now this is a different group of religious leaders.
In fact, the Pharisees and Sadducees oftentimes
would debate and argue and all sorts of things.
People say this, they didn't believe in angels
and they didn't believe in a resurrection.
And so everyone that says about the Sadducees,
they don't believe in the resurrection.
That's why they're sad, you see.
And so you can remember it that way.
They don't believe in the resurrection.
So it's important to understand
that it says it in the very next statement,
which say that there is no resurrection.
And it asked him.
So they themselves,
this sect of religious leaders in Judaism,
they didn't believe in the resurrection.
They do not believe in the resurrection.
Okay, are we clear? We got it.
The Scriptures tell us that.
You can read that in antiquity.
You can understand that in verse 24.
Here's what they say.
Master, Moses said,
if a man die having no children,
his brother shall marry his wife
and raise up seed unto his brother.
Now there were with us seven brethren.
The first, when he had married a wife,
deceased and having no issue,
left his wife unto his brother.
Likewise, the second also,
and the third unto the seventh.
And last of all, the women died also.
Therefore, in the resurrection..."
Still the Sadducee is talking.
They don't believe in a resurrection.
Are you tracking?
They don't believe in a resurrection,
but they say,
"...therefore, in the resurrection,
whose wife shall she be of the seven?
For they all had her."
Jesus answered and said unto them,
notice the answer in verse 29,
"...ye do err."
Why?
Not knowing the Scriptures
nor the power of God.
You know where they erred?
In the truth of the resurrection.
Because Jesus immediately deals with that first.
He says this in verse 30,
"...for in the resurrection..."
He answers the question,
but when he says,
"...ye do err,
not knowing the Scriptures
nor the power of God.
For in the resurrection,
they neither marry
nor are given in marriage,
but are as the angels of God in heaven."
Now that truth that's given to us
in Matthew 22 and verse number 30,
that's not a truth you're going to read
in the Old Testament.
But you do read about the resurrection.
Are you tracking with me this evening?
And so when we read the Scriptures,
it exposes error.
And so Jesus says,
"...ye do err,
not knowing the Scriptures
nor the power of God."
He then talks to them and says,
"...in the resurrection..."
Answers their question.
They neither marry nor are given in marriage,
but are as the angels of God in heaven.
And then he goes back to the subject
of the resurrection in verse 31.
"...but as touching the resurrection of the dead.
Have you not read that which was spoken unto you
by God saying,
I am the God of Abraham and the God of Isaac
and the God of Jacob?"
God is not the God of the dead,
but of the living.
And when the multitude heard this,
they were astonished at his doctrine.
As we look at this interaction here
with the Sadducees,
Jesus is exposing their error,
but he's doing it with giving them biblical truth.
The error is that they don't believe in the resurrection.
But why don't you believe in the resurrection?
The Bible clearly teaches that.
The Old Testament clearly teaches this
and he tells them,
you do ye do err not knowing the scriptures
nor the power of God.
And so this evening,
as we understand this interaction
that takes place in Matthew chapter 22,
he'll then say,
have you not read?
And he gives them reference with regard to God
being the God of the living
and not the God of the dead.
He's driving home this truth.
The reality is you look at this passage of scripture,
they didn't believe in the resurrection.
They're just trying to get Jesus tripped up on something.
Some hypothetical,
listen, that's what people will do to you as well.
They will.
How many times I've been trying to share the gospel
with somebody and they ask me
some crazy off the wall question.
I had somebody say,
well, how many Adams were there?
There's one man, Adam and Eve.
Yeah, but how many do you think he created
on different planets?
And just go through all this nonsense kind of nonsense.
And listen, you can answer some questions.
Acts talks about God has given us what our habitation is.
And listen, I believe this evening
that as we look at the scriptures,
we can answer those questions,
but it exposes error.
And we need to know the Bible.
Can I tell you there's a lot of crazy teaching
out there tonight?
I mean, crazy teaching.
And God's word exposes error.
Notice over in Psalm 119.
And then I'm gonna come right back to the New Testament.
But Psalm 119, notice what the psalmist says.
Of course, the Psalm dealing with God's word
and how wonderful God's word is
and how the psalmist loves the law of the Lord.
In fact, in verse 97 of Psalm 119,
oh, how love I thy law.
Notice he says, it is my meditation all the day.
I wonder this evening,
as you read the Bible this morning,
I wonder, do you recall what you've read?
Do you have, is it in your heart,
is in your mind, do you meditate?
Is there something that you take away with you?
Right now I'm reading through the book of Acts.
I just finished up this morning,
that first missionary journey
and kind of the interaction there.
And man, it's just exciting to read
and to have understanding of what God has done
and how God is working.
And here the psalmist says, I love,
oh, how love I thy law.
It is my meditation all the day.
Notice in verse 99 of Psalm 119.
Notice when he says,
I have more understanding than all my teachers.
For thy testimonies are my meditation.
You know, the Bible talks about
in the book of 1 Corinthians
that God uses the foolish things of the world
to confound the wise.
The Bible says in the book of Romans,
professing themselves to be wise,
they became fools.
Listen, the understanding and wisdom
that you get from this book
is far superior to anything that the world offers.
Far superior.
And it's the Bible that will correct academia.
We're not looking for academia to correct the Bible.
Amen?
God's word is true.
Sometimes every once in a while you'll hear somebody say,
hey, I heard this report
and they had this scientific study
and you know what they found out?
They found out the Bible was true.
Really?
It's always the case.
100%.
God's word is true.
Amen?
And notice in verse number 100,
he says, I understand more than the ancients
because I keep thy precepts.
This is not a prideful, arrogant type of an approach
and attitude in verse 99 and 100.
It's just simply that I meditate upon God's word
and I keep God's word
and therefore God gives me this understanding.
You know, we're to glory in the things
that God has revealed to us
that we can understand him and know him.
And what a joy.
You know, the answers to life's questions
are all answered in this book.
And this book exposes error.
Look over, if you will, at 2 Peter in chapter number three.
2 Peter chapter number three.
The reality as you're turning there
is we need more of God's word, not less of God's word.
We need to read more of God's word, not less of God's word.
It's the only book that I've ever read
that I continually read.
The only one.
There's no other book that I've ever read
that I've continually read.
There are some books that I've read more than once,
but never with those books have I finished the last page
and the next day started on the first page, never.
There would be years in between
reading it for a second time.
This book, I end reading.
I read it through.
I finished the book of Revelation on June 28th.
On June 29th, I started reading Genesis one.
I like reading Genesis to Revelation.
That's just what I like.
Some people like a little old, a little new.
Some people, whatever your preference, just read it.
Amen?
And then do it.
Obey it.
In 2 Peter chapter three in verse number 17,
the Bible says this,
ye therefore beloved, seeing you know these things before,
beware, lest ye also being led away
with the error of the wicked,
fall from your own steadfastness.
Anytime you see the word beware,
you should take note of that.
I always take note of it when I'm door knocking
and I see a beware of dog sign.
Amen?
Ronnie and I were door knocking a few weeks ago
and there were four very large German shepherds
in the front yard.
And they were very young and aggressive.
I'm not saying young like puppies.
They were like full grown, but they were going crazy.
And you know what they had, Pierre?
They had an invisible fence.
You know how much I trust invisible fences?
Because I'm like, I got the thought process
that if that dog just feels like, you know what,
it's worth the shock, I'm toast.
And Ronnie's like, what do you want to do?
I want to go on the other side
and we're going to mail something to that house.
Because I am not even trying to go to that door.
You say, I can't believe that.
You have no faith.
I'll give you the address, amen?
And you can go there.
But I'm just saying that I take note of the warning.
God's word is full of warnings.
Beware.
Notice what he says in verse 18.
The warning in verse 17 is being led away
with the error of the wicked.
So what is the antidote?
What is the remedy?
What is it that we should do?
Notice in verse 18, but grow in grace
and in the knowledge of our Lord and Savior, Jesus Christ,
to him be glory both now and forever, amen.
How do you grow as a Christian?
Help me.
Read the word, right?
I mean, you don't grow as a Christian
just because you had another spiritual birthday.
Like I'm.
in the Lord, and so therefore I should be at this." No, you grow by reading.
As newborn babes desire the sincere milk of the word that ye may grow thereby.
1 Peter 2 and verse number 2. And so now he's writing at the end of 2 Peter,
the second epistle that he writes to these folks, and he says to them that
they're to grow in grace and in the knowledge of our Lord and Savior Jesus
Christ, because the answer to error is always truth. And so as we read the
Scriptures, not only is reading the Scriptures expected, but understand it
exposes error. I don't want to be tossed to and fro with any wind of doctrine. I
just really don't want to be that way. I don't want to come in and this week I
believe this, and next week I believe this, and the following week I believe
this. No, God's Word gives us truth and we can be settled, and it exposes error.
Number three, reading the Scriptures is essential. It's essential. Anemic
Christianity, it's a problem. Weak Christianity, it's a problem.
Because we don't read God's Word. We're not growing. We're not walking in the Spirit.
We're quenching the Spirit. We're grieving the Spirit. Notice what God
tells Joshua. Joshua had a great task in Joshua 1, and you're familiar with the
passages, off-quoted verse of Scripture. Joshua had a monumental task ahead of
him as the human leader to lead the children of Israel into the land of
promise. God, of course, would do the work, but Joshua's the human leader. And as God
is encouraging and commissioning his man in Joshua chapter number one, he tells
him this in verse number eight, this book of the law shall not depart out of thy
mouth, but thou shalt meditate therein, notice what it says, day and night, that
thou mayest observe, notice it says, to do according to all that is written
therein. For then, how many of you want the then? Do you know that the then
is the result of the process? For then thou shalt make thy way prosperous, and
then thou shalt have good success. I know that we don't use the word success and
prosperous very often, but it's biblical. We'll have God's favor and God's
blessing as we read and meditate and do the Word that God has given to us, and
we're looking for the then, but sometimes we try to get then without
following the process. We want the result without the process, but the result, the
then, is given to us that we are in God's Word. We're meditating in it day and
night. We're observing to do all, not some, not the easy things, but all. Lord,
whatever you say I'm going to do, I submit to you. It's essential. Let's look at the
book of Nehemiah. We'll look at just a few more verses this evening, but look at
the book of Nehemiah, and I want you to look here in Nehemiah chapter number
eight, and as we look at this passage, it's really just a very prominent few
verses of Scripture with regard to the reading of God's Word. Yes, the public
reading here that is given to us, and I'm going to read the first eight verses of
Nehemiah chapter number eight. Notice what the Bible says,
And all the people gathered themselves together as one man into the street that
was before the water gate. And they spake unto Ezra the scribe to bring the book
of the law of Moses, which the Lord had commanded to Israel. And Ezra the priest
brought the law before the congregation, both of men and women and all that could
hear with understanding, upon the first day of the seventh month. And he read
therein before the street that was before the water gate." Notice what it
says, from the morning until midday. Is that what your Bible says? From the
morning until midday, before the men and the women and those that could
understand. By the way, that's referencing to children that were of age
to understand. Continue reading there in verse three. And the ears of all the
people were attentive unto the book of the law. You know, we constantly are being
told today in the 21st century, in 2025, you know, we need to preach
sermons that are shorter because people don't have attention spans and they
can't handle it and so on and so forth. From the morning until midday. Listen,
this book is prosperous. There was a huge video that some guy from a mega church
in Texas put out about preaching a message that was too long and he was
going on it too long of a video to try to criticize preachers for preaching too
long. And it was absolutely bizarre to listen to the fellow given all of his
criticisms. But listen, this book, if somebody's just standing up giving
their opinion, man, I got you. Like, okay, I'm checked out. I heard enough. But this
book, this is God's Word. He says in verse number four, and Ezra the scribe stood
upon a pulpit of wood. I'm never gonna stand on this pulpit. I don't like
heights. I'm getting older. I don't need to fall. But he stood upon a pulpit of
wood which they had made for the purpose and beside him stood
Matthiah and Shema and Ananias and Uriah and Hilkiah and Massiah on his right
hand and on his left hand Paddaiah and Mishael and Malachiah and Hashem and
Hashabadana, Zechariah and Meshulam. And Ezra opened the book in the sight of all
the people for he was above all the people and when he opened it all the
people stood up and Ezra blessed the Lord, the great God, and all the people
answered, Amen, Amen, with lifting up their hands and they bowed their heads
and worshiped the Lord with their faces to the ground. Also, Yeshua and Bani and
Sharibiah, Jamin, Aqab, Shabbathiah, Hodijah, Messiah, Kelita, Azariah,
Josabath, Hanan, Peliah, and the Levites caused the people to understand the law
and the people stood in their place. Verse 8, so they read in the book in the
law of God distinctly and gave the sense and caused them to understand the
reading. Reading the Scriptures is essential, absolutely essential. You need
it. I need it. I need it every day of my life. You need it every day of your life.
And listen, we don't read the Bible like we read the newspaper, like we read the,
I don't know why I said newspaper. I don't even know the last time I saw a
newspaper. I hate the newspaper. It gets your hands all black and I just, my
grandparents used to get it all the time, but I'm talking about you don't just
look for a headline. You don't just look for a, no, no, you systematically read the
book. It's God's Word. You say, I can't pronounce some of these words. I can't
this and what is this about? God gave it to us for a purpose. He wants us to know
it. He wants us to understand it. And reading God's Word, reading the
Scriptures, the essential. Notice, and you're familiar, Psalm 1. Notice in Psalm 1
in verse number 1 through verse number 3, and then we'll look at one New
Testament verse and be done this evening, but in Psalm 1, Psalm 1, beginning in
verse number 1, the Bible says,
Blessed is the man that walketh not in the counsel of the ungodly, nor standeth
in the way of sinners, nor sitteth in the seat of the scornful. The focus of me
reading this passage is verse number 2, not verse number 1, but let me just say
this about verse number 1. We better check who we're associated with.
Amen? Blessed is the man that walketh not in the counsel of the ungodly, nor
standeth in the way of sinners, nor sitteth in the seat of the scornful.
It's interesting when you note the progression in verse number 1. Walking,
standing, sitting. It's a progression. You say, well, they're not going to influence
me. Yes, they are. Be not deceived. Evil manners corrupt good
communicate, or evil communications corrupt good manners. But notice verse 2,
But his delight, his delight is in the law of the Lord, and in his law doth he
meditate day and night. And he shall be like a tree planted by the rivers of
water that bringeth forth his fruit in his season. His leaf also shall not
wither, and whatsoever he doeth shall prosper. Isn't that a precious truth?
Reading God's Word is essential. Can I tell you this evening, you can't do what
you don't know. You can't do what you don't know. If you don't read the
Scriptures, you can't do what God commands you to do. How can you please
God if you're not in the Scriptures? If you're not reading it, if you're not
having that understanding, it's absolutely essential. And then let me say
this, when I think about this truth of it being essential, in Ephesians chapter
number 6, God goes through the whole, put on the whole armor of God, and he deals
with all of that, and he gets to verse 17.
and he says this in verse 17, I'll give you just a second to turn there, in
Ephesians 6 and verse number 17, he says this, and that and take the helmet of
salvation and the sword of the Spirit which is the Word of God. Can I tell you
this evening that we need to learn how to use our sword skillfully. The Bible is
referred to here as being the sword of the Spirit. I mentioned this morning
about being able to say it is written. Memorizing verses that specifically deal
with areas of weakness or vulnerability as we identify sin in our lives or those
areas of weakness and we memorize Scripture that pertains to those
particular topics or subjects. And that's part of using God's Word skillfully. And
we must get into the Scriptures, we must understand what God's Word says. A
chapter earlier in Ephesians in chapter 5 and verse number 10, this is proving
what is acceptable unto the Lord. How do I prove it? Here's something, and it's
just something that started to kind of bother me recently. It seems like a lot
of people will ask this question and they want to do something and they'll
say this, what's wrong with it? Here's my question. What's right with it? Instead of
you making me give you an answer as to why it's wrong, why don't you tell me why
it's right? Does that make sense? Because if the onus and responsibility on the
person, the child of God, is to prove what is acceptable in the sight of the
Lord, then you ought to be able to tell me what's right about what you want to
do. Does that make sense? And sometimes we look here and say, listen, we got to know
God's Word. It is essential. I want to think and I want to act biblically. But
the only way I'm gonna think and act biblically is I get into this book.
Someone said this, I have no idea who it was, Bart asked me this morning, who says
these quotes? I don't know, I don't write down their names, I just write down the
quotes. Sometimes I write down their names. Oftentimes I just remember the
quote. But here's what this person said, I don't know who it was. Thumbprints in
the Bible are more important than footprints on the moon. Thumbprints in
the Bible are more important than footprints on the moon. Now we get into
God's Word. Jesus said, have you not read? Reading God's Word is expected. Reading
the Scripture, God expects us to read it. He gave it to us so that we'd read
it. It exposes error. It's essential. You cannot live, you will be anemic, weak
spiritually, if you don't read this book. You need more than what you get at
church. Amen? How many of you like to eat three meals a day? Just a couple of you.
How many of you like to eat at least once a day? All of you probably, right? How
many of you ate more on Thanksgiving than you should have, right? Listen, we
gotta have an appetite for God's Word. Job said it was more necessary to him
than his food. I want to feast on the manna from heaven, as the songwriter
said. I need God's Word. Let's pray. Father, we love you. Thank you for giving us a
Bible. It's not enough that we have it. It's not enough that we have the King
James Bible. It's not enough that we know that it was given by inspiration and
providentially preserved. We need to read it. We need to meditate upon it. We need to
know it. We need to do it. God, I pray that you would help us as we just
ponder this thought for a few moments this evening, have you not read. God, I
pray that you would help us not to be ignorant biblically, to be unlearned, but
Lord, help us to be biblically knowledgeable, that we would think and we
would act biblically. I pray, Father, that you would help each of us to have a
desire to have more of your Word. Help us to make commitments to spend more
time in your Word, that we might know you, that we might please you. I pray that in
the moment of invitation, that you'd have your will and way in the lives of your
people, and we'll thank you for what you'll do. For it's in Christ's name we
pray, we just...