And we are thankful for the opportunity
to be gathered together this evening.
And I got some friends from South Carolina
watching tonight, Gene and Ruth Boyce,
and not related to Holly,
it's actually spelled differently
than what her maiden name is.
But I haven't seen Gene and Ruth for years and years.
And Gene just recently had hip replacement
and they're friends of my parents.
We met them down there years ago
and they go to Harmony Baptist Church as well
and they're supposed to be tuned in tonight.
And so welcome to them.
I trust they're doing well.
Tongues Shall Cease.
That is the title for the message this evening.
On Sunday nights here for several weeks now,
we've been dealing with this Ask the Pastor series.
And as we have had the opportunity
for you to submit questions,
and as I've mentioned, as we have this series,
this is the third time that we've done this,
is that we take your questions
and they become the sermon series through the summer.
I thoroughly enjoy it and I trust that you do as well
and it gives us an opportunity.
I found this in life,
many times if one person has a question,
there are many people that have a question.
And we, of course, have an opportunity
to be able to learn what God says.
And so the subject of tongues is before us this evening.
We find that the subject of tongues
is commonly brought up.
Unfortunately, I would say that there is much confusion
with regard to the subject of tongues.
And it's sad to me because I believe that the Bible
provides us with such clarity.
And so there's so much clarity that God gives us
in his word with regard to the subject of tongues,
and yet there's so much confusion in our world
with regard to tongues.
And so we seek, as we've said many times over the years
as Baptists, the Bible is our sole authority
for faith and for practice.
And so we must understand what does God tell us in his word.
The question that was submitted specifically has to do
with when will tongues cease or when did tongues cease?
And so that's why we find ourselves here
in 1 Corinthians 13 and verse number eight,
really as a springboard into the message this evening.
We'll be looking again, as we did this morning,
we'll be looking at a number of different portions
of scripture within the Bible
in order to answer the question.
But here in 1 Corinthians 13 and verse number eight,
the Bible says, charity never faileth.
But whether there be prophecies, they shall fail.
Now understand that it's not speaking about prophecies
not coming to pass,
meaning that they're going to cease to be given
in the manner in which it's speaking here
of these sign gifts.
And then it continues and says,
whether there be tongues, they shall cease.
Whether there be knowledge, it shall vanish away.
For we know in part and we prophesy in part,
but when that which is perfect is come,
then that which is in part shall be done away.
When I was a child, I spake as a child,
I understood as a child, I thought as a child,
but when I became a man, I put away childish things.
For now we see through a glass darkly,
but then face to face, now I know in part,
but then shall I know even as also I am known.
And now abideth faith, hope, charity, these three,
but the greatest of these is charity.
And so we see right in the midst of verse number eight,
the Bible says specifically,
whether there be tongues, they shall cease.
In order to answer the question
with regard to tongue ceasing,
I believe it's important for us to understand two things.
Number one, I believe that we need to understand
the purpose of tongues,
and then we also need to understand
the biblical usage of tongues.
If we can understand the purpose of tongues
and the biblical usage of tongues,
then it helps us to be able to answer the question
with regard to what it says here in 1 Corinthians 13, eight,
whether there be tongues, they shall cease.
So we begin to dig in and we understand this evening
that within 1 Corinthians 13,
really beginning in chapter 12
and all the way through chapter 14,
the apostle Paul is addressing the church in Corinth
about spiritual gifts.
As he's addressing the church in Corinth
regarding spiritual gifts,
it's important for us to understand
some fundamental truths.
Number one, I would say that as we have
an understanding of the audience to whom Paul is writing,
this is a carnal church,
this is a church that's dealing with
all sorts of carnality and competition
and saying, I have this spiritual gift
and so I'm better than you are,
and there's all of this comparison and competitiveness
and all of this carnality.
And he says that he can't speak to them as unto spiritual.
Why?
Because they're carnal.
And so we understand the audience that Paul is writing to
and we find that as Paul is giving them the truth
with regard to spiritual gifts,
there was obviously some matter, excuse me, of confusion
because he starts in 1 Corinthians 12 in verse one
and says, now concerning spiritual gifts, brethren,
I would not have you ignorant.
And so what is Paul saying?
He wants them to be informed.
He wants them to understand these spiritual gifts.
He wants them to have an understanding
of how God is working and what God is doing
and the purpose of these spiritual gifts.
He tells them in the first chapter,
in chapter one in verse number seven,
so that you come behind in no gift.
And so we find that the gifts, they were gifted,
they had spiritual gifts, they'd receive them.
Just as we'd understand from 1 Peter
that the Bible says, as every man hath received the gift,
even so let him minister.
And so we find that if you're saved this evening,
you've been given a spiritual gift.
Now, Paul is going to give them instruction
because there's an element of ignorance
that they have with regard to spiritual gifts.
So fundamentally, it's important
that we have an understanding of spiritual gifts
generally, and then as we speak about tongues specifically,
it will enable us to answer the question
with regard to when tongues will cease.
I do not think that it's a matter of arguing
whether they will cease, for the Bible plainly says
that whether there be tongues, they shall cease.
So the question that arises is when will this take place?
Has this already taken place?
And we try to again, answer that question
by understanding the purpose and the biblical use of tongues.
Now, let me say this, the Bible gives us three books
that deal with, that Paul touches on spiritual gifts.
1 Corinthians is one of them,
the book of Romans and the book of Ephesians.
Those are the three books that you study
within the New Testament that deal with spiritual gifts.
And as those three books deal with spiritual gifts,
and as we understand in 1 Corinthians 13 and verse eight,
whether there be tongues, they shall cease.
Paul deals in 1 Corinthians much with the subject of tongues
but as you study the book of Romans
and as you study the book of Ephesians,
you will notice immediately
that the reference to tongues is omitted.
It's not even addressed in either one of those books.
Now, as we understand that truth
and then begin to try to process,
what does that mean to us?
Well, we understand that the Bible was not,
the way that we have the Bible,
the way that the canon of scripture is organized
is not given to us chronologically, all right?
So in other words, we look at the New Testament
and although Romans is in the Bible
before 1 Corinthians,
the reality is that 1 Corinthians was written
before the book of Romans.
Is everyone tracking on that?
Sometimes when we read the New Testament,
we read it as if,
and in fact, any of the portion of the Bible,
we read it as if it's chronological
that the book of Romans must have been written
before the book of 1 Corinthians
because it's in our Bibles in that order.
But the reality is that the book of 1 Corinthians
was written about 55 AD.
The next book to be written
with regard to these three
that deal with spiritual gifts
is the book of Romans
that was written two to three years later
between 57 and 58 AD.
And then you go to the book of Ephesians
which was written in AD 61.
So there's six years
in between the writing of 1 Corinthians
and the writing of Ephesians.
Why do I bring that out?
Well, when Paul says whether there be tongues,
they shall cease
and tongues is addressed in the book of 1 Corinthians,
but it's omitted in the book of Romans
and the book of Ephesians.
It seems as if it was already beginning to fade away
as the scriptures were coming into completion, all right?
Is everyone tracking with that?
So we find that as we study the scripture.
So what is the purpose of tongues?
In 1 Corinthians 14,
you're here in chapter 13,
turn to chapter 14 if you will
and look at verse number 21.
We'll read a few verses of scripture here
as we seek to answer the question,
what is the purpose of tongues?
Again, it's gonna be difficult.
It's gonna be challenging for us to answer
when tongues will cease
if we do not understand the purpose of tongues.
In 1 Corinthians 14 and verse 21,
the Bible says in the law,
it is written with men of other tongues and other lips,
will I speak unto this people.
And yet for all that, will they not hear me, saith the Lord?
Wherefore, tongues are for a sign,
not to them that believe, but to them that believe not.
But prophesying serveth not for them that believe not, but for them which believe.
If therefore the whole church be come together into one place,
and all speak with tongues, and there come in those that are unlearned or unbelievers,
will they not say that you are mad?
But if all prophesy, and there come in one that believeth not, or one unlearned,
he is convinced of all, he is judged of all,
and thus are the secrets of his heart made manifest.
And so falling down on his face, he will worship God,
and report that God is in you of a truth.
In verses 21 and 22, God makes it plain,
the purpose of tongues, that tongues are given as a sign.
Notice in verse 22, wherefore tongues are for a sign.
Who are they assigned to?
Well, according to verse number 21, they are assigned to the Jewish people.
It says in verse 21, in the law it is written.
Who is the law written to? It is written to the Jewish people.
It says with men of other tongues and other lips.
You can go back to Isaiah and read this prophecy in chapter 28.
Well, I speak unto this people, and yet for all that will they not hear me sayeth the Lord.
And not only when we understand the purpose of tongues is for a sign,
to whom, verse 21, this people, the Jewish people,
but in verse 22, it says them that believe not.
Wherefore tongues are for a sign, not to them that believe,
but to them that believe not.
And so we begin to understand the purpose.
Why is it that God has given the sign?
To whom is this sign given?
Well, it's given to the Jewish people, this people, verse 21,
and it's given to them that believe not, verse 22.
Then we say, why?
Why tongues?
Why did God allow for these apostolic sign gifts?
I taught a series in Sunday school a while ago,
and as I taught that series, I mentioned that as we studied through the book of Acts,
we looked at a number of things in which God gave us
with regard to the growing of the church, the foundation of the church,
and we used as a foundation from the book of Mark,
where the Bible says in Mark 16 and verse 20,
and they went forth and preached everywhere,
the Lord working with them and confirming the word with signs following.
Amen.
So I want you to just think for a moment,
as the apostle Paul would go on a missionary journey,
as they were preaching the day of Pentecost,
as Peter gets up to preach,
we find that they're preaching, but they don't have a Bible like we have a Bible.
I stand up here this evening, I stood up here this morning,
I stand up here week after week after week,
and I preach the Bible, I preach the word of God,
but you can go back because you have a Bible as well,
and you can read and you can tell if these things be.
Amen.
The Bible tells us in 1 John that we're to try the spirits,
and so we find that because God has given us a whole Bible,
you can go back and you can verify whether these things be so.
Peter stands up and preaches, Paul stands up and preaches,
they don't have a Bible like we have a Bible.
And so God, until the Bible was completed,
He allowed for these sign gifts,
He's confirming the word with signs following.
So as they're preaching the word,
these signs that follow are confirming that the word that's being given is true.
And that's the purpose that God would use these apostolic sign gifts.
You look at the Apostle Paul where he would heal people,
you look at Peter where he would heal people,
and you look at that situation,
but then later on down the road of ministry,
you find that Paul mentions people by name that he left sick.
He didn't heal them,
because healing them was not just his own volition of,
bam, I want to heal you.
No, the healing was confirming the word that was being preached.
The same is true with tongues.
So what was the purpose? Why did God use this?
And I want you to understand this distinction.
It's important in 1 Corinthians 14
that we understand to whom the sign is given,
because it helps us to understand why.
The Jews are always looking for a sign.
That's what the Bible tells us.
The Bible tells us, in fact,
in this very book that we're looking at in 1 Corinthians,
the Bible speaks about the truth that the Jewish people are looking for a sign.
In verse 22 of chapter 1, it says,
for the Jews require a sign,
and the Greeks seek after wisdom.
So the Jews require a sign.
God's given them this sign of tongues.
So I want you to consider what's taking place.
The Jewish people, and as we study the Scriptures,
we find evidence of this in an abundance.
There was a great disdain for Gentiles.
The Jewish people, by and large,
they hated Gentiles.
They viewed them as dogs.
Biblical. We see it. We understand it.
Jesus was breaking down those barriers
because in John chapter number 4,
he said, I must needs go through Samaria.
The Jewish people would go around Samaria
because of their view of the inhabitants of Samaria.
And Jesus went through and he talked to a woman at the well,
which obviously was also something that was not culturally acceptable
for a Jewish person to do.
And he is breaking down that barrier. Why?
Because for God so loved the world.
Amen?
And he talks about the church.
There's neither Jew nor Gentile.
There's neither circumcision nor uncircumcision.
We're all in Christ.
So understand that as the church is moving forward,
the Jewish people as a nation,
they rejected Messiah.
They said crucify him, crucify him.
The church in Jerusalem begins the day of Pentecost,
all that takes place.
But Jesus said that after,
but you shall receive power after that
the Holy Ghost has come upon you
and you shall be witnesses unto me both in Jerusalem
and Judea and Samaria and unto the uttermost part of the earth.
So the gospel, because of the Jewish rejection,
the nation rejecting Messiah,
the Gentiles are grafted in.
There's an amazing truth of God's word
and we find that the gospel is given to the Gentiles.
Peter is the first one.
Turn over to the book of Acts in the 10th chapter if you will.
He's the first one that God uses
to speak to a Gentile man by the name of Cornelius.
Now, as we begin to understand
and look at this truth with regard to the purpose of tongues,
there was this disdain that the Jewish people had of the Gentiles.
But now God is offering repentance to the Gentiles
and yet there's going to be some Jewish people
that are going to say, wait, hold on a minute.
They're Gentiles.
They're not allowed to be part of this.
So it becomes a real problem.
So in Acts chapter 10, God gives Peter a vision.
I don't have time to study all of it
and read through all of chapter number 10 this evening,
but God gives Peter a vision.
In that vision, he tells him, rise and eat,
and he says, not so, Lord, for I have never eaten anything
that is common or unclean.
And what God was giving to him in this vision
was not so much about food
as much as it was taking the gospel to the Gentiles.
He tells them that someone's going to come
and he's going to bear witness
and Cornelius had sent some people, so on and so forth.
I'm going to pick it up in verse number 33 of Acts chapter number 10.
Peter has already traveled from where he was
over to where Cornelius is.
And the Bible says this in verse 33,
This is Cornelius speaking.
Peter had been in Joppa.
It says,
This is an awesome opportunity.
See, Cornelius had seen a vision,
but in his vision it was sent for Peter,
and Peter's going to tell you what you need to know.
And we find that Peter,
because God was working in Peter's heart,
Peter obeys the Lord and he goes to the house of Cornelius
and Cornelius says, I'm glad you came.
It's good that you came. We're all here ready.
What do you got for us? Isn't that awesome?
I mean, what an opportunity.
And we find that the Bible says in verse 34,
Then Peter opened his mouth
and said of a truth I perceive that God
is no respecter of persons.
Aren't you thankful
that our God is no respecter of persons?
Praise the Lord.
It says this,
The word which God sent unto the children of Israel,
preaching peace by Jesus Christ,
he is Lord of all.
That word, I say, ye know,
which was published throughout all Judea
and began from Galilee after the baptism which John preached,
how God anointed Jesus of Nazareth
with the Holy Ghost and with power,
who went about doing good and healing all
that were oppressed of the devil,
for God was with him.
And we are witnessing
which he did both in the land of the Jews and in Jerusalem,
whom they slew and hanged on a tree.
Him God raised up the third day and showed him openly."
This is the gospel.
The gospel is the death, burial, and resurrection of Jesus Christ.
In verse 41,
"'Now to all the people, but unto witnesses, not to all the people,
but unto witnesses chosen before of God even to us,
who did eat and drink with him after he rose from the dead.'
And he commanded us to preach unto the people and to testify
that it was he which was ordained of God to be the judge of quick and dead.
To him give all the prophets witness that through his name
whosoever believeth in him shall receive remission of sins.'"
You ought to underline verse 43 in your Bible
and rejoice greatly for that Bible truth.
The Bible says that through his name,
there's no other name under heaven given among men whereby we must be saved.
Jesus said,
"'I am the way, the truth, and the life. No man cometh unto the Father but by me.
Through his name whosoever believeth.'"
I'm so thankful that the gospel is a whosoever gospel.
I'm so thankful that because of my heritage, my lineage, my nationality,
that I've not been excluded from being able to be a recipient of God's grace.
I am a whosoever and you are a whosoever.
"'For whosoever shall call upon the name of the Lord shall be saved.'"
And Peter says that through his name,
"'Whosoever believeth in him shall receive remission of sins.'"
Every single person has an issue with sin.
It's a universal condition.
It's a sin problem.
And because of our sin, there is a penalty.
We understand this.
The Bible says the wages of sin is death.
But the gift of God is eternal life through Jesus Christ our Lord.
And so he says that you can receive remission of sins,
that forgiveness that is only through the blood of the Lord Jesus Christ.
Hallelujah.
So Peter's preaching the gospel.
Cornelius and all these are gathered.
These are Gentiles.
They're gathered together and Peter's preaching the gospel.
And the Bible says in verse 44,
"'While Peter yet spake these words, the Holy Ghost fell on all them which heard the word.'"
Because they were believing.
They didn't pray a sinner's prayer.
They were believing it already.
Sometimes we think that salvation is in praying a prayer.
But I'm telling you, these people, they received the word and they received it with gladness
and they were saved by the grace of God.
And the Holy Spirit fell on them.
"'And they of the circumcision.'"
Now who are those?
Those are the Jewish people that accompanied Peter on this journey.
It says, "'And they of the circumcision which believed were astonished.'"
"'As many as came with Peter.'"
Why?
"'Because then on the Gentiles also was poured out the gift of the Holy Ghost.'"
But how did they know?
Somebody can tell you, I have the Holy Ghost.
How do you know?
Now Ephesians reveals to us as now having the whole canon of Scripture.
But remember, at this point in Acts 10,
at the point in 1 Corinthians, Ephesians hasn't been written yet.
Ephesians chapter 5 reveals to us when the Bible says,
"'But be not drunk with wine, where it is in excess, but be filled with the Spirit, speaking to yourselves.'"
It gives us what the evidence of being Spirit-filled is.
But here, why were these Jewish people astonished that on the Gentiles,
the Holy Ghost, the gift of the Holy Ghost was poured upon them?
How did they know that?
Verse 46, "'For they.'"
Who's they?
That's the circumcision, the Jewish people.
"'They heard them speak with tongues and magnify God.'"
So God allowed those Gentile believers to speak in tongues
to show the evidence that they too had been saved,
that they received the Holy Spirit.
Are we tracking?
Now, in verse 47, "'Can any man forbid water, that these should not be baptized,
which have received the Holy Ghost as well as we?'
And he commanded them to be baptized in the name of the Lord.
Then prayed they him to tarry certain days.'
Chapter 11, "'And the apostles and brethren that were in Judea
heard that the Gentiles had also received the word of God.'"
Now, these people in Judea, they're rejoicing.
I mean, the Gentiles got saved. No way.
They're not rejoicing.
They're saying, hold on a minute.
Jewish, Gentile, what's going on here?
It says, "'And when Peter was come up,' in verse number 2,
"'to Jerusalem, they that were of the circumcision,' Jewish people,
"'contended with him.'"
They've got a problem.
What's their problem? Well, verse number 3,
"'Thou wentest into men uncircumcised and didst eat with them.'"
Not only did he eat with them, but he gave them the gospel,
and they got saved.
Hallelujah.
But they weren't happy in Jerusalem.
They said, hold on, what's going on here?
We're Jewish. They're Gentiles.
It's a problem.
Do you understand the mindset?
I understand that we're living in America.
We don't really think that way,
of the Jewish mindset with the Gentiles and all of that.
But it's plain in the Scriptures to understand
the culture and the historical truth of what's going on.
So what happens? They're upset with Peter.
So in verse number 4, the Bible says,
"'But Peter rehearsed the matter from the beginning
"'and expounded it by order unto them, saying...'"
Now, Peter's going to rehearse everything.
We don't have time to read it.
But you read chapter 11, and Peter's going to rehearse
the vision, the instruction that God gave,
his arrival to the house of Cornelius,
his preaching, all that takes place.
Pick it up with me in chapter 11,
in verse number 15.
The Bible says, "'And as I began to speak,
"'the Holy Ghost fell on them as on us at the beginning.'"
Now, they remembered that.
"'So he tells them the Holy Ghost fell on them,
"'then remembered I.'"
Peter says, "'I remember the word of the Lord,
"'how that he said, John indeed baptized with water,
"'but you shall be baptized with the Holy Ghost.
"'For as much then as God gave them the like gift
"'as he did unto us who believed in the Lord Jesus Christ,
"'what was I that I could withstand God?'
Peter says, "'Listen, it was obvious
"'that they were saved the same way we were saved,
"'and the evidence was there.
"'The people that accompanied me saw it, they heard it.
"'It's evidence that they were saved.'"
And so notice in verse 18, "'When they,'' who's they?
Well, that's the circumcision that we're contending with Peter.
"'When they heard these things, they held their peace
"'and glorified God, saying,
"'Then hath God also to the Gentiles
"'granted repentance unto life.'"
God's way is perfect.
Do you agree with that this evening?
God doeth all things well.
He knows.
And so God chose to allow this situation
to be the way that it was
so that the Jewish believers that would have rejected
the idea of Gentiles being part of the body
being part of the church,
that they hold their peace and glorify God.
Why?
Because the evidence was so overwhelming
that the Gentiles also have remission of sins,
that the Gentiles also have been granted life eternal.
Isn't that awesome?
And God knows.
And so God allowed for this sign.
Notice, if you will, in Acts chapter 15.
We're going to fast forward a couple of chapters here.
There's a few things that take place there in Antioch
and the situation with Peter going to be put to death
and then the missionary journey
that takes place in chapters 13 and 14.
We come to chapter 15,
and this is after the first missionary journey.
Paul goes into the region of Galatia.
There are churches that are established,
but there's some Judaizers.
What are Judaizers?
Well, they're Jewish people
that are trying to make these people Jewish.
The idea is not becoming Jewish.
The idea is trusting Christ as your Savior.
Since I have been born again,
since Jesus came into my heart,
we sang that song this evening.
So notice in Acts chapter 15,
this is the council at Jerusalem.
The Bible says this in verse number 1.
And certain men which came down from Judea
taught the brethren and said...
Here's what they're teaching.
Except ye be circumcised after the manner of Moses,
that is, ye cannot be saved.
Now that's an error.
That is not true Bible teaching.
You do not have to be circumcised
after the manner of Moses
in order to be saved.
Amen?
This was something they were adding.
This was not true.
By the way, this caused a great stir.
It caused a big problem.
We were at dinner on Monday night.
We got to Tennessee.
We drove down there on Monday.
We go to dinner.
Maybe you've been there.
Maybe you know that place.
They have great potato soup.
And that's why we went to the apple barn.
And we go to the apple barn.
And our waitress notices on a shirt that I'm wearing,
I'm wearing a polo shirt,
and it has Hebrews chapter 6 on there
that Jesus is the anchor of my soul.
Mady made it for me a few years ago for my birthday.
And I was wearing that particular shirt.
And she says,
Are you Christians?
Praise the Lord.
Open door.
We sit down and I say,
it's kind of interesting you ask us if we're Christians.
She says,
Are you a Christian?
Well, yeah, I believe in God,
but I haven't been baptized.
That's what she said.
That was her answer.
So she's busy.
She's a waitress.
We're there in the...
the restaurant, we place our order, she comes back, it's kind of slowing down, it's getting
close to closing time, and she comes back over and I'm looking for that opportunity
and I say to her, I say, ma'am, I say, let me ask you this, when I asked you if you were
a Christian, you said you believed in God but you haven't been baptized.
What do you mean by that?
What is the significance in your mind of being baptized?
She provided an answer and basically in her mind, she believed that it was important for
her to believe in God but that she had to be baptized in order to be saved in order
to go to heaven.
That's not true.
Amen?
That's not biblically true.
So I'm going to ask her questions and I'm going to say to her, well, if that's true,
and I gave her Bible verses, I'm going to share with her truth with regard to works
and so on and so forth, boil everything down.
Basically she thinks, if I'm a good person, then I'll go to heaven, but if I'm a bad person,
I'm not going to go to heaven.
Now, a lot of people think that.
That's just not true biblically because we're all bad people.
We've all sinned.
For all have sinned and come short of the glory of God.
So we understand this universal condition of sin.
So I have this conversation with this lady, and as we're sitting there and we're supposed
to be having dinner, I finished eating earlier because I was hungry, and they're finishing
up and I'm talking to the waitress and I'm sharing with her and giving her Bible truth
and sharing Bible verses with her.
And I went to Galatians and I said this, I didn't have my Bible with me, but I was just
quoting scripture to her.
And I said, listen, the Bible says, Paul says, that if righteousness came by the law, then
Christ is dead in vain.
I said, I believe this night that as you're standing here, that you do not believe Christ
died in vain.
And she said, not a bit.
No way.
I said, and he died so that you could be saved.
He died so that I could, because being baptized isn't going to save me.
Being circumcised isn't going to save these people.
This was, these were the Judaizers.
So what happens, verse two, when therefore Paul and Barnabas had no small dissension
and disputation with them is a big deal.
They determined that Paul and Barnabas and certain other of them should go up to Jerusalem
and to the apostles and elders about this question.
So they, they convened this, this council and they're going to answer the question.
These guys are running around saying you got to be circumcised after the matter of Moses
or you cannot be saved.
And this is not true biblically.
And I mean, that's a big deal.
So what happens?
Well, Peter stands up and he makes some comments.
Notice with me in verse number eight, I'll back up in verse number seven.
And when there had been much disputing, Peter rose up and said unto them, men and brethren,
we know how that a good while ago God made choice among us that the Gentiles by my mouth
shall hear the word of the gospel and believe.
What is Peter referring to in Acts 15 in verse eight, seven?
He's referring to what we just read in the life of Cornelius.
It's exactly what he's referring to.
He says that God determined, made choice among us that the Gentiles by my mouth should hear
the word of the gospel and believe.
So Peter is standing after much disputation or disputing takes place and he says, listen,
we all know what happened.
God sent me to the house of Cornelius and they believed, notice in verse eight, in God,
which knoweth the hearts, bear them witness, giving them the Holy Ghost, even as he did
unto us.
How do we know that he gave them the Holy Ghost?
They spoke in tongues.
It was a sign for the Jews.
So it says in verse number nine, and put no difference between us and them, purifying
their hearts by faith.
By the way, I'm thankful there's no difference between us and them.
There's only one way to be saved and it's Jesus.
There's only one way to be saved.
There's not many ways that lead to heaven.
There's not just be sincere about what you believe and everything's going to work out.
No, there's one way.
Jesus said, I am the way, the truth and the life.
No man cometh unto the father, but by me.
Verse 10, now therefore, why tempt ye God to put a yoke upon the neck of the disciples,
which neither our fathers nor we were able to bear?
But we believe that through the grace of the Lord Jesus Christ, we shall be saved even
as they.
Hallelujah.
But understand that in Acts 10 and 11 and 15, that in each of these passages of scripture,
we see the purpose of tongues and how it gave evidence that these Gentiles were saved.
So here's what happens.
Oftentimes, people say, okay, well, then you have to speak in tongues if you get saved.
That's the evidence of being saved.
No, no, no.
Back up.
Hold on just a minute.
It happened in the book of Acts.
But understand that there were many people that got saved in the book of Acts that never
spoke in tongues.
So you can study through the book of Acts.
We don't have time this evening.
It's already 6.50.
But you can study through the book of Acts and you can read of other people that trusted
Christ as their Savior that did not speak in tongues.
Were they saved?
Absolutely.
They were saved.
But they didn't speak in tongues.
Why?
Well, maybe there were no Jews there.
Sometimes you see that to be the case and you find that there was no need for that evidence
to be displayed to the Jewish people because there were no Jewish people there.
And so you look at each of the situations independently and understand the reason, the
purpose.
So we answer the question, what's the purpose of tongues?
Then we answer the question, the biblical usage of tongues.
Turn to our 1 Corinthians 14.
I know I've given you a lot this evening, but look here in 1 Corinthians 14, if you
will.
People that talk about, well, when will tongues cease or have tongues ceased.
Those that would argue that tongues have not ceased and that they're still an active, valid
sign gift for today, they still have to answer the question, when are they going to cease?
So here's what I've often said to people, okay, if you believe that tongues are still
for today, which I don't, I believe they've ceased, I'll give you that in conclusion this
evening.
But if you believe that they're still in existence today, then you have to agree that they have
to follow the biblical principles that God has set forth for how tongues were to be utilized.
Because God put forth regulations, if you will, in 1 Corinthians 14 for how tongues
were to be utilized.
Understand with me that in 1 Corinthians 14, the instruction that's given in verse 26 through
40 is almost always violated in the modern charismatic Pentecostal movement today.
There are many times that I've said, hey, okay, so you believe that speaking in tongues
is for today.
Do you believe that there needs to be an interpreter?
Well, it depends if the Spirit wills.
Sorry, the Spirit has already willed.
How do I know that?
God told us in His Word that if they're going to speak in tongues, there has to be an interpreter.
So it's not if the Spirit wills at that moment, He already has.
Does that make sense?
And so we begin to find that if they're violating the regulations that are laid forth in the
Scripture for the proper biblical usage of tongues, we have to say, hold on, is that
appropriate?
Is that biblical?
Does that make sense?
So notice in verse 26, how is it then, brethren, when you come together, every one of you hath
a psalm, hath a doctrine, hath a tongue, hath a revelation, hath an interpretation.
Let all things be done unto edifying.
What was the purpose?
In 1 Corinthians 12, He gives us two purposes of these spiritual gifts.
Number one is to honor God, and number two is to edify the believers.
Those are the two purposes of spiritual gifts.
He continues in verse 27, if any man speak in an unknown tongue, let it be by two or
at the most by three, and that by course, and let one interpret.
But if there be no interpreter, let him what?
Keep silence in the church, and let him speak to himself and to God.
Let the prophet speak two or three, and let the other judge.
We go through, I don't have time to deal with all of this regulation because I need to get
to the end, but in verse 33, God is not the author of confusion, but of peace, is in all
churches of the saints.
Let your women keep silence in the churches.
You know what you find in the modern charismatic movements?
Oftentimes, it's primarily women.
But the regulation is let the women keep silence in your churches within the context of tongues.
Verse 40, let all things be done decently and in order.
You find that in the modern charismatic apostolic ministries today that there's a lot of chaos
and confusion.
There's a lot of lack of order and decency, and so we find that the regulations are provided.
Turn back to chapter 12 just for a moment, and I want you to look at two verses with
me because some say, well, it's a, you speak in tongues, it's an evidence of salvation.
We disagree because of what I've looked at in the book of Acts already.
Then others say, well, speaking in tongues is evidence of being spirit-filled.
We disagree because of what Ephesians says, because Ephesians 5 gives the evidence of
being spirit-filled in verse 18 through 20.
But then I want you to look at what the Bible says in 1 Corinthians 12 within the context
of tongues specifically.
In verse 13 of 1 Corinthians 12, notice the Bible says this, for by one spirit are we
all baptized into one body, whether we be Jew or Gentiles, whether we be bond or free
and have been made, and have been all made to drink into one spirit.
Now if you're saved, we look here at 1 Corinthians 12, we look at what the Bible says in Ephesians
1.
deals with it as well.
If you're saved, at the moment of salvation,
the Holy Spirit of God indwells you.
At the moment of salvation,
The Bible says that our bodies are the temple
of the Holy Ghost, which is in you,
which you have of God, you're not your own.
1 Corinthians 6 deals with that.
And so he talks about, why does he use the terminology,
all of us are baptized?
Well, he's writing to a church,
a church made up of saved people.
But notice in verse number 29 and 30,
when Paul begins to list, and it really starts in verse 28,
about all of the particular gifts
and all of the differences of gifts,
he says, are all apostles, in verse 29?
Are all prophets, are all teachers,
are all workers of miracles, verse 30?
Have all the gifts of healing?
Do all speak with tongues?
Do all interpret?
You know what Paul's saying?
He's speaking with a level of,
here, dealing with this situation,
and really being somewhat sarcastic of saying,
listen, not everybody has the same gift.
We've all been baptized by the Holy Spirit,
we all have the Holy Spirit of God if we're saved,
but we don't all have the same spiritual gifts.
So therefore, for someone to say that speaking in tongues
is the evidence of being filled with the Spirit of God,
you have a problem with 1 Corinthians 12.
So the Bible, again, as I mentioned by way of introduction,
there's much confusion, but the Bible gives us much clarity
with regard to the subject.
Now that we understand the purpose and use of tongues,
we can attempt to answer the question
of when tongues will cease.
I believe that it's clear that the Bible teaches
that tongues will cease.
It says in 1 Corinthians 13, eight,
whether there be tongues, they shall cease.
Obviously, everyone that would even believe
in the practice of tongues has to agree
that they have to cease at some point.
I believe that the scriptures reveal
that tongues would cease when the New Testament was complete.
In verse number 10 of 1 Corinthians 13, it says,
but when that which is perfect is come,
then that which is in part shall be done away.
Now, I believe, and he talks in verse number 11,
when I was a child, I spake as a child,
I understood as a child, I thought as a child,
but when I became a man, I put away childish things.
He's talking about the church,
and he's talking about the infancy of the church
versus the maturity of the church.
And in those infant stages,
God allowed for these sign gifts to confirm the word
because they didn't have a whole Bible.
So then when the whole Bible was given,
there was no need for the temporary sign gifts
because the Bible had been completed.
Now, Hebrews chapter two and James chapter number one
give us some evidence to deal with this truth
of 1 Corinthians 13, 10 being the Bible being complete.
And there are some that argue
that that's the return of Christ, the rapture.
I disagree as you compare scripture with scripture,
and I'll answer that question in just a moment,
but in Hebrews chapter two and verse number three,
the Bible says, how shall we escape
if we neglect so great salvation,
which at the first began to be spoken by the Lord
and was confirmed unto us by them that heard him?
How was it confirmed?
Verse four, God also bearing them witness
both with signs and wonders and with diverse miracles
and gifts of the Holy Ghost according to his own will.
And so we find that God was working with the disciples.
He was confirming their word with signs following.
And Hebrews two deals with that subject
and helps us to understand that sign gifts
were given to confirm the message that was being delivered.
James one in verse number 25 tells us this
as we compare that with first Corinthians chapter 13
in James one and verse number 25,
but who so looketh into the perfect law of liberty,
that's the Bible, and continueth therein,
he being not a forgetful hearer, but a doer of the work,
this man shall be blessed in his deed.
So if we understand the why,
to whom is the sign gift given?
And we begin to answer the question, when would it cease?
I believe that the scriptures are clear
that even within the context
that it's when the Bible is complete.
The argument, and some have said,
that it's no, it's when Jesus returns.
So then we would, and that's their validation
for why this speaking in tongues consists
or continues until the present day
because Jesus hasn't returned.
The problem with that is that we have to have
an understanding properly of what takes place
at the rapture and what the purpose of the tribulation is.
If the rapture is the removing of the church,
but tongues was a gift given to the church,
then at the rapture it would automatically cease
and God would not have to say
whether there be tongues they shall cease.
Does that make sense?
Because if the gift is given to the church,
and it is, that's who the gift is given to,
to believers, that makes up the church,
then as the church is raptured,
everything pertaining to the church ceases at that point
because the church is raptured.
There's no more church in the book of,
in the tribulation as we know it today in this church age.
The church ceases to exist in the same manner
that it exists today during the tribulation.
And so therefore, if God says whether there be tongues
they shall cease, I don't, it makes zero sense in my mind
why he would tell us it would cease
if that time of ceasing is at the rapture.
There's gotta be a different time.
And that time, I believe,
according to 1 Corinthians 13, verse 10,
is when the complete canon of scripture is given.
I'm so thankful to have a whole Bible.
And so I believe this evening that it's clear.
I know that there are people that differ on this teaching.
I believe, even as I shared with someone this morning
that asked a question about it,
as they saw the title, they said,
man, I'm not gonna be able to make it back this evening
but it's a subject that I'm very interested in.
And I believe that tongues,
one of the issues with tongues today
and still becoming somewhat of a dispute, if you will,
as to why people think that it continues until today
is because tongues can be manufactured.
Do you know that in the Bible
no one was ever instructed on how to speak in tongues?
No one ever desired, except for the carnal people in Corinth
to speak in tongues.
And we find that Paul said,
I'd rather speak five words of understanding
than 5,000 words with an unknown tongue.
And so we find that as we study the scriptures
that today there's,
hey, we're gonna teach you how to speak in tongues.
No one ever was taught how to speak in tongues
in the New Testament.
No one was coveting after that.
No, the spirit gives as he will to every man.
And we find that tongues can be manufactured.
What do I mean by that?
Well, someone can stand up
and say they're speaking in tongues
and you don't know if they are or not.
But no one's walking around healing somebody
without you knowing whether they were healed.
Am I right?
No one's drinking poison
without you knowing if that poison affected them or not.
People trying to handle snakes,
crazy people trying to handle snakes outside of their mind.
They're not shaking it off like Paul did.
What happened when he shook that beast off, that serpent?
They went from saying he was a murderer
to saying he was a God.
And you know what that allowed him to do?
Preach the gospel and those people got saved.
That was the purpose of the...
Paul wasn't walking around playing with snakes
and letting them bite him and showing that he's immune to it.
No, it was a sign to confirm the word.
Amen.
And so tongues so often today can be manufactured
in people looking at the fact that,
oh, I spoke in tongues
and some elevation of a position
of being spirit-filled or otherwise,
and you don't know if they are or are not.
But you know one thing that's interesting
about speaking of tongues in the Bible?
It was always a known language.
It was a known language.
Every man heard them in Acts 2 in his own tongue.
That's why they marveled.
How is it that all of us are hearing in our own tongue?
We're gonna go to Panama in two weeks.
I don't speak but about 20 words of Spanish.
I'm gonna need an interpreter.
Why?
Because I don't speak the language.
I'm not gonna hear them in my language.
They're not gonna hear me in their language.
We're gonna need an interpreter.
This evening, we see the answer to the question,
but I say tonight as well,
it's so awesome that in the plan of God,
he allowed for this sign gift of tongues to be given
so that the Jewish people would know
that the Gentile people were saved the same way.
We sang to start the service this evening
since Jesus came into my heart.
I hope you know tonight that you're saved,
that you know for sure that heaven is your home,
that you understand that you're a sinner.
There's only one savior.
His name is Jesus.
For all have sinned and come short of the glory of God.
I mentioned that on Saturday,
this upcoming week will be 27 years
since I trusted Christ as my savior.
I'm so happy and so thankful to know Christ.
And I was saved the same way anybody else
and anyone else will ever be saved.
And that's through trusting the Lord Jesus Christ.
and has finished work on the cross of Calvary.
It's not by any merit of my own.
There's no righteousness that I could do.
There's no good work that I could do or that you could do.
It's only through Jesus Christ
and to God be the glory for that wonderful truth.
Let's pray together.
Father, we love you.
We thank you for loving us.
We thank you for your word.
And this evening, we've covered a lot of territory.
And God, I pray that there's a measure of clarity
that's been given,
that God, you'd help us to understand
the truth of your word.
I pray, God, that if there's one here tonight
that's not saved,
they've never trusted Christ as their savior.
I pray that tonight would be the night of their salvation.
I pray the Holy Spirit of God would convict of their sin,
of Christ's righteousness and of judgment to come.
Pray that you'd give us an opportunity to take a Bible
and show them how they could know for sure
that heaven is their home.
I pray, God, that if there's some
that are struggling with this area of tongues,
that, Lord, they would understand the simplicity
and the truth of your word,
the clarity that you provide us with.
I pray that you'd move and work
in the moment of invitation as only you can,
and we'll thank you for it in Christ's name, we pray.
Would you stand with me?
As you know, at the conclusion of our services,
we have a time of invitation,
not intended to embarrass anyone or to pressure anyone,
but to simply give you an opportunity to respond.
Kimberly's gonna play quietly on the piano,
and as she does, the altar is open.
If you're not sure of heaven,
we'd love to take a Bible and show you
how you can know for sure that heaven is your home.
Maybe this evening, you wanna come and just thank God
for his word and the clarity that he provides.
Maybe you wanna thank God for saving you.
As Kimberly plays, the altar is open.