Different times we live in, aren't they?
And sometimes we can allow a negative spirit
to kind of sweep over us.
And we just have to be careful that we don't do that.
Our God is great and he can speak to our hearts
whether we're in a room or whether we're at home,
we're listening on live stream, God is able.
I was thinking to myself, God could speak to Jonah
when Jonah was in the belly of a whale.
God found Peter on a rooftop, spoke to his heart.
He found John in exile on the Isle of Patmos
and spoke to John there.
So I think God is able even in 2021
to allow us to be in our living room
or somewhere on live stream,
some in the auditorium, very few.
And he is able to speak to our hearts.
It really is about our attitude.
And so my prayer is, is that you will
just for these next few moments,
allow the Lord through his Holy Spirit to take his word
and speak to your heart.
And let's just see what God can do in our lives.
It'll be a wonderful thing.
Take your Bible if you would and turn with me to Psalm 89.
I appreciate pastor allowing me to be here.
We are friends and for some period of time
pastored in the same area.
And I'm glad for all the years that we had in the DC area.
We moved to Charlotte, North Carolina,
where we have two sons,
but I will always be a Virginian at heart.
I love Virginia, even the traffic of Northern Virginia.
Maybe not so much that part.
Psalm 89, and let's notice beginning in verse one.
I will sing of the mercies of the Lord forever.
With my mouth will I make known thy faithfulness
to all generations.
For I have said, mercy shall be built up forever.
Thy faithfulness shalt thou establish in the very heavens.
I have made a covenant with my chosen.
I have sworn unto David, my servant.
Thy seed will I establish forever
and build up thy throne to all generations.
Selah.
And the heavens shall praise thy wonders, O Lord.
Thy faithfulness also in the congregation of the saints.
For who in the heaven can be compared unto the Lord?
Who among the sons of the mighty
can be likened unto the Lord?
God is greatly to be feared in the assembly of the saints
and to be had in reverence of all them that are about him.
O Lord God of hosts, who is a strong Lord like unto thee
or to thy faithfulness round about thee?
Let's pray and ask God to help us.
Father, we're so grateful for this morning
that you've given us to be together
in whatever way you've allowed us to be
in tune with this service.
Lord, we're not gathering because we are people
who have it all figured out.
We're gathering because we are needy people.
We need your Holy Spirit's help.
We need your word.
Lord, we need your touch upon our lives.
And we offer ourselves in these few moments
for you to speak to us, to teach us.
Lord, there are so many that need encouragement
and I pray that you would encourage them today.
But Lord, we also need to be convicted.
And where we need conviction and where we need
to change attitude, action, words,
I pray that you would impress that upon our hearts
and help us not to be stiff-necked,
but to be willing to hear you and make the changes
with the help of your Holy Spirit
that would please you in our lives.
So work in our hearts.
Thank you for this moment.
We pray in Jesus' name, amen.
If you were to ask me,
what is the highest Christian virtue?
Of course, I would say love,
because I believe love is the abiding great virtue.
But one of the virtues that I would rank very, very highly
is the virtue of faithfulness.
I love faithfulness.
I love the testimony of preachers, if you will.
I am one and so allow me to be self-interested for a moment.
I love preachers who have been at it and stay at it
in the way that they have energy to do,
but for a long time.
I love that.
I love Sunday school teachers who teach for a long time.
I think the greatest crown to be given in heaven
will be given to teachers who taught junior high boys
for 40 years.
They deserve a crown for sure.
I love faithfulness in marriage.
And I'm an older fellow.
I listened to Paul Harvey when he was on the radio
and I used to love a segment that he had.
It was called the Tournament of Roses.
And when he would talk about the Tournament of Roses,
he would mention a couple who had been married 60, 70 years
and he would just honor them.
And I think that's praiseworthy.
I just love the thought of faithfulness.
And as much as we could talk about the faithfulness
that we see in men and women, here's the truth.
Our faithfulness, if any,
is only evidence of God's faithfulness to us.
And when we praise faithfulness,
may we first understand that it is God's faithfulness
in our lives that allow us to move, to do,
and to have the privilege over years of pleasing him.
When I come to this great psalm,
I understand something about faithfulness.
I want you to notice some things in introduction.
If your Bible has ascriptions for the psalm,
mine says that it is a maskial of Ethan the Ezraite.
That word maskial just simply means
that it is a psalm written to instruct,
a psalm written to instruct.
So when we come to Psalm 89,
we know that God's intention is to teach us something.
Now, notice in verse one, the latter phrase,
thy faithfulness to all generations.
Notice verse two, latter phrase,
thy faithfulness shalt thou establish in the very heavens.
Verse five, thy faithfulness also
in the congregation of the saints.
Notice verse eight, or to thy faithfulness round about thee.
I am not the brightest bulb in the pack, I assure you.
But when God says I've written a maskial,
which has the intention of instructing us,
and four times in the first eight verses,
we're told about the faithfulness of God, I get it.
This is a psalm to instruct God's people
about his faithfulness to his own.
Well, second, I want you to notice who wrote this psalm.
It's important to understand a little bit
about Ethan the Ezraite.
I won't take you there for the sake of time,
but if we went to 1 Chronicles 15, verse 17,
we would learn that Ethan, of course, is a Levite,
and Ethan was put in charge of worship.
Now, as a Levite, he was to study and care about
and teach the word of God,
and he and his family have this special calling,
or special responsibility of teaching and leading in worship.
One of the other things I learned about Ethan
was in 2 Chronicles, I'm sorry, 1 Kings 4, verse 31,
that his wisdom is compared to the wisdom of Solomon.
Now, it doesn't say that he is as wise as Solomon,
but I would suggest to you that if you're even mentioned
in the same verse, you're a pretty wise guy.
I don't know about you, but I do know about me.
I do not know one word of Hebrew other than shalom, okay?
But I have a strong concordance,
and it often makes me dangerous.
And I love to understand names,
especially as they are in the Old Testament,
because God often will communicate an important thought
or a trait about that person through their name.
And so, as I was studying this passage,
it occurred to me I'd love to know
what that name Ethan means.
I looked it up in my strong concordance and was amazed.
It means literally to be permanent, to be constant.
Now, I wanna put that together for just a moment.
Here's God wanting to instruct his people
about his faithfulness.
So he chooses a man to inspire through his Holy Spirit
to write about his faithfulness to God's people,
and that man is a Levite
who is a teacher of the people of God.
He is a man who is wise.
And he is a man whose character,
I believe God is communicating to us,
is one of faithfulness.
Now all of that I find very interesting,
but I'll tell you the thing in my study
and introduction that really amazed me.
It is when the psalm was written.
When did God decide to inspire Ethan
to write a psalm about his faithfulness?
I could have understood it if it was written
during the reign of David,
because David was the sweet singer of Israel.
He was the man after God's own heart.
He was a flawed man, but he was a man after God's own heart,
and we so identify that kingdom of Israel with David.
But it wasn't written when David was king.
I could have even understood if it was written
when Solomon was king,
because under Solomon, the kingdom reached its zenith.
The greatest cities were built.
The greatest armies were in the field.
There was just a great sense of prosperity and blessing,
but it wasn't written when Solomon was king.
Do you know when God inspired Ethan to write Psalm 89?
Right after the kingdom split, when Rehoboam,
the son of Solomon, had made such an unwise decision
following the counsel of the young men
rather than the elders, and the kingdom was split,
and Jeroboam came back from Egypt and took 10 tribes
and went to the north and Samaria, made his capital.
That is now called Israel or Ephraim,
and Rehoboam is left with two tribes in the south,
Judah and Benjamin.
It is called Judah, and in the midst
of the kingdom being rent,
in the midst of the greatest chaos
Israel had ever experienced,
in the midst of when you would wonder,
does God even know where we are?
Does God even care about who we are?
That's when God said to Ethan,
Ethan, I want you to remind my people about something,
that regardless of the circumstances,
regardless of what they think they see,
regardless of what they're experiencing,
my faithfulness never changes.
I know where they are, I know where I'm taking them,
I know what they're experiencing,
and I am utterly faithful.
And when I understand that, to be honest with you,
the thing that occurs to me is this,
because the rest of the psalm is not necessarily
about God's faithfulness,
it speaks to what our response to God's faithfulness
should be, even in difficult circumstances.
I want you to notice several of them this morning.
Here's number one.
Our response to God's faithfulness
ought to be to have a rejoicing spirit
that celebrates God's faithfulness.
I'll say it again.
Our response to God's faithfulness
ought to be to have a rejoicing spirit
that celebrates God's faithfulness.
Go with me to verse one again.
I will sing of the mercies of the Lord forever.
With my mouth will I make known
thy faithfulness to all generations.
I think somebody ought to write a song like that,
don't you?
Oh, wait a minute, they did.
A chorus, it's a wonderful chorus
that we sing as children,
but it has one of the greatest truths
that too often as adults we forget.
You see, we as adults can be so quick to be grumbling,
so quick to complain in all that God has done for us
and in all that God is presently doing for us.
There are times that out of the mouths of believers,
God does not hear praise and God does not hear rejoicing.
Instead, God hears complaining
and it is not an innocent thing.
I'm reminded of the time that Israel was in the wilderness.
They had come up out of Egypt
and oh, how they rejoiced when they came up out of Egypt
and oh, how they loved God
and God brought them to the edge of that Red Sea
and almost instantaneously the beginning complaint began.
God parted the Red Sea and they went across the Red Sea
and then of course we know the story of the spies
and the wrong decision made and here's the truth.
Because of that wrong decision, that unbelief,
they were destined to spend 40 years
in the wilderness of Sinai.
I don't know if you've ever been to the wilderness of Sinai
but it's not a garden spot, it is truly wilderness.
You can't grow crops there to sustain a million people.
You can't find enough water
to sustain your flocks and your herds.
It's not a comfortable place to dwell
and yet during those 40 years, think with me for a moment,
their sandals never wore out,
their clothes never deteriorated
and every day they had flocks out there,
there was enough water for their herds
and their flocks and for them
and oh yeah, every single morning other than Sabbath morning
they would wake up and they would see out there
what appeared to be dew at first
but when you walked up on it,
it was of a white coriander seed,
it looked like coriander, it had the taste of fresh oil,
it was manna and for every day of 40 years
in a wilderness that could not sustain you,
they ate, they had nutrition, it was tasty,
it was provided of God for his people
and can I remind you of what they did in Numbers 11?
They complained about the provision of God
and they said we loathe this white bread
and God did not hold them innocent for it.
Now I don't believe we live in the Old Testament
and I'm not predicting that God will do with us
what he did with them but of all people on the earth,
it ought to occur to us, God is good to me.
Even when the circumstances are difficult,
God is good to me and I think we ought to join with Ethan
and say, I will sing of the mercies of the Lord forever,
I will sing, I will sing, I will sing of the mercies
of the Lord forever even as I sit on 66 or 95
or even as there's no supplies at Costco
and even though there's a pandemic
and even though it seems like all is changing
and all is falling apart, my God is good and able to supply
and you and I right now, listen, it is so easy
to have a grumbling, complaining spirit
and as believers, it ought to stop in our lives
and rejoice because God knows where we are,
God knows what we need, God knows where he's taking us
and God will deliver us to that place
because God is utterly faithful.
Here's number two, our faith can rest on God's faithfulness.
Look at verse two, for I have said,
mercy shall be built up forever,
thy faithfulness shalt thou establish in the very heavens.
There's not a lot that we can count on in these days.
How many of you notice that politicians
will often disappoint you?
What is popular today will be forgotten tomorrow.
Our own bodies and lives seem like they're always moving,
always moving, always changing.
What I could do yesterday, I can't do today
and I don't know about you but sometimes
I just wanna holler, let it stop, let it just stay here.
I'll never forget years ago, I was in a hospital room
where a husband and wife had just had a little baby
and I loved those visits, it's a time of real joy
and mom was attending to the baby and I was talking to dad
and as we were talking, I overheard her whisper
to this little baby, I want it to just stay like this.
She's holding her child, the child is not crying
and it's all peaceful, almost like a little halo
resting over the child's head and I thought to myself,
I wanted to turn to her as a fundamental Baptist preacher
and say, well it ain't gonna stay there
but I decided to be nice that day but it doesn't stay,
it always moves, it always moves
and to be honest with you, we're not promised.
easy or comfortable or pleasant circumstances all our lives.
But what we are promised is this,
that as our lives are always and ever changing,
and as the circumstances that surround us
are always and ever changing,
we have a sovereign God who is sovereign
over the change in our lives.
And I don't mean to be too elementary,
but God says, God says, look to the heavens
and comfort yourself when it is swirling around you
and you don't know what tomorrow's gonna bring,
you don't know what you're gonna do,
look to the heavens and remind yourselves, I do, God says.
I don't know if you noticed it,
but at about six o'clock last night, the sun went down.
I follow the science, I am deeply scientific.
How many of you noticed this morning
at about six o'clock, the sun came up?
Did you know that's gonna occur again today
and again tomorrow and again the next day?
And you say, well, yeah, preacher,
because the earth goes around the sun
because God did it on purpose.
Because God wanted us to look at that and say,
wow, has this thing changed,
but wow, does God know and does God have control
and God knows what happens in the night, in the dark,
and God knows what happens in the day
and God knows how to get me there.
We're getting ready to experience my favorite season, fall.
I love the chill in the air,
I love the leaves getting ready to change.
My favorite thing in the world is apples.
I am the world's greatest apple connoisseur
and it is harvest season for apples.
And sadly, it's going to give way
to my least favorite season of the year, which is winter.
You say, don't you love the beauty of the snow?
No, you have to shovel it.
But it's gonna give way to spring
and it's gonna give way to summer.
You say, preacher, we know that.
You said you wouldn't be elementary.
It's elementary, but it's vital for us to understand
that God is in control
and God is able to bring life
where there doesn't seem to be life.
He is able to handle transition
and he is able to move us through it.
I love how the songwriter put this, and forgive my singing.
♪ Summer and winter, springtime and harvest ♪
♪ Sun, moon, and stars in their courses above ♪
♪ Join with all nature in manifold witness to what? ♪
♪ To thy great faithfulness, mercy, and love ♪
And I love what the songwriter does.
♪ Great is thy faithfulness, great is thy faithfulness ♪
♪ Morning by morning, new mercies I see ♪
Now, you remember this line?
♪ All that I've needed, thy hand hath provided ♪
Regardless of the circumstances.
♪ Great is thy faithfulness, great is thy faithfulness ♪
♪ Lord, unto me. ♪
Boy, these are uncertain times, aren't they?
Honestly, we don't know what a day will bring forth.
I almost don't turn the news on
because the news cycle is like 12 minutes, not 12 hours.
But in all of this mess and all of this chaos,
there is a God who can make night turn into day.
There is a God who controls
and by whom all these things consist
and he moves us from summer to fall to winter to spring.
God is utterly faithful.
Here's number three.
No human faithfulness can be compared
to God's faithfulness.
Look at verse eight.
Look over at verse eight.
Oh, Lord God of hosts, who is a strong Lord like unto thee
or to thy faithfulness round about thee?
I love, as I began this sermon,
faithful men and women and their testimonies,
but can I tell you the truth?
Men and women, to include myself, will fail you.
I told my congregation for years and years,
hang around me long enough and I will disappoint you.
There'll be something that I do, something that I say,
I will disappoint you.
And my friend, you cannot build your faith on a man.
You can't build your faith on a political party.
You can't build your faith on an IRA.
You can't build your faith on a career.
There is only one who never, ever fails us.
That is God Almighty.
Put your trust in him.
Since I've been retired the few weeks that I'm home a year,
one of the things I love to do
is go with my wife grocery shopping.
She does not love it when I go with her grocery shopping,
but I love it.
And we only shop at the finer stores, so we go to Walmart.
And as we go into Walmart, there is a person there
whose purpose in life is to make me feel good
about myself being at Walmart.
She's got, he or she's got a blue vest on,
they've got a smiley face.
Their job is to welcome me to Walmart.
Not long ago, I went with my wife.
We walked in, I pushed the cart, that's my job.
And be careful not to hit her in the back.
As we're going through and we're coming up to that door,
I see her, she's there.
This is gonna be great, I love people.
I'm gonna greet her, she's gonna greet me.
It's gonna make life wonderful.
She makes eye contact with me and turns and walks away.
Now can I tell you something?
I will never go to Walmart again
because of what that woman did.
You take me too seriously, okay?
I don't go to Walmart because I need somebody
to make me feel good about myself.
I go to Walmart because the Jif peanut butter is cheaper.
I am so weary of people who use what is universally known
that men will disappoint us as a reason
to not worship and serve the Lord
who will never fail them.
Listen, I'm not making light that people have been hurt
by Christians and in significant ways.
Please do not think that's what I'm doing.
But you and I have to understand that it is a devil's tactic
to use the failure of men to cause us
not to want to have fellowship and faithfully worship
the one who is utterly faithful to us,
who has never failed us.
I don't come to church for somebody
to make me feel good about myself.
I come to church and sing and listen to preaching
and learn of him to worship the one
who is utterly faithful to me.
And I pray that if somehow your life is marginalized
by the failure of a person in your life,
I'm not diminishing it.
I'm just saying, beg God for the grace to get over it
because he has never failed you.
And you are harming your own spiritual walk.
You're allowing the failure of failing men
to keep you from serving and worshiping and loving
and enjoying your walk with the Lord
who has never, ever failed you.
Notice this very quickly.
Your sin does not change God's faithfulness.
Turn over to verse 31 with me, would you?
Here, Ethan says, if they break my statutes
and keep not my commandments,
then will I visit their transgression with the rod
and their iniquity with stripes.
Nevertheless, my loving kindness
will I not utterly take from him,
nor suffer my faithfulness to fail.
This psalm, if we had time to really study it in depth,
you would understand was to reassure Israel
of the promises that God had made to David,
that one of David's lineage would reign in perpetuity
over Israel.
That will be realized in the millennium
when Jesus, the son of David,
reigns literally from Jerusalem for 1,000 years.
But now in the midst of this chaos,
it looks like Israel's sin has broken the covenant
and now God has forsaken them
and he's not going to fulfill his promises to them.
But that is never true.
Yes, God is going to chastise them.
He's going to deal with them.
but in truth there is a remnant and God will bless them and God loves them even
through the chastising. You say preacher how does that relate to me? Well I've
been in ministry long enough that I've met a lot of people who use their
failure as a reason to not be restored and be used of the Lord. Hey David was a
flawed man. David committed adultery. I would suggest that's a very serious sin.
David actually conspired in the murder of Uriah. David was a man who had was
filled with pride at times and and numbered his armies because he wanted to
see how great his empire was. David was as flawed as you and I. But can I remind
you that God only has flawed people to work with and that God is able and God
loves us so much that even when we fail, when we sin, that God's desire is for us
to be restored and he convicts our hearts about what we've done and if we
will repent and if we will look to him that you and I can be restored.
Sometimes we have the image of God that he is in heaven and he's a God with a
thunderbolt who's just waiting, just waiting for one of his kids to step out
of line so that he can dash them with that thunderbolt. And I want to tell you
that is not the accurate picture of who our God is. The accurate picture of our
God comes from that great parable of the prodigal. A son takes what his father has
given to him, the blessing of his father, and takes it to the far country and then
wastes his his life in that place, finds himself in the pig pen having fed the
hogs and hoping to eat a little bit of what he has fed to the pigs. And I love
how simply the Bible puts it, it says he came to himself. And when he came to
himself, he said to himself, what what am I doing in a hog pen? And he gets up and
he makes the decision, I'm going back to my father. Now understand, when he goes
back to his father, he doesn't know what the reception will be. He doesn't know
whether his father will be there with a clenched fist, ready to beat him for his
sin. He doesn't know if his father will completely ignore him, and he'll have no
entrance to his father. He has no clue what it's going to be. But I want you to
understand, on that day when he's approaching home and perhaps very
nervous about what father is going to be, when he sees his father standing in
the road because he was waiting and watching and hoping his son would come
home, and his arms are wide open, that's the picture of our God. And I don't care
whether we have failed him or not, I'm not minimizing sin, I'm maximizing the
graciousness and the mercy of our God. And God says come home. One of the
moments that has just burned into my mind, I preached a sermon somewhat along
those lines, and a man came forward and he motioned to me, would you come down?
And of course I would come down and speak with him and pray with him, and he
said to me, I shouldn't be here. I said, well what do you mean you shouldn't be
here? He said, well you've preached on this probably ten times in the years
that I've been in this church, and he said, I've tried to get this thing
squared away, and I've tried to do it, and every time I failed, and here I am
back down here now. I've failed at this. And he said, I know God doesn't want me
to be here, but I wanted you to know that I know God doesn't want me to be here.
I said, what are you talking about? I said, of course God wants you to be here.
God's message to the disciple was seven times seventy, and he wasn't teaching up
to 490 times you can be forgiven. He was saying as long as you'll come, I'll work
with you, I'll help you, I'll restore you. And look, I'm not trying to get people to
run it out to 490 times to fail. What I'm telling you is, is the devil will
keep you from experiencing fullness in Christ, because he will convince you that
your failure disqualifies you for the love of God, and the blessing of God, and
to be used of God, and restored. And I'm telling you, God says you come, because
though your sin may have to be chastised, and though you must confess and repent
of your failure, God says I will never utterly forsake you. One last thing and
I'm done. You know what God is faithful to do? He is faithful to call upon those
that will call upon him to be saved. I'm sorry, he's faithful to save those who
will call upon him. I don't know about you, but I know about me. I wasn't
raised in a Christian home. My mother and dad were not Christians. Mother may have
been, but dad was definitely not a Christian. And he got saved when a
soul winner came by the door at 63 years old, and they started serving the Lord. In
70, he became a deacon. My mother determined that she didn't raise her
boys as Christians, but now that she was serving the Lord, they were going to know
about the Lord. And so she determinedly would witness to us to the point where I
finally had to say, I was married, we had children, and I finally had to say, mother
you've made a decision. I'm glad for you and dad. You go the direction that he
wants. God wants you to go. But for Nancy and I, we're content with our
life. We're decent people, good people. We're going to do what we do. Long story
short, she knew that I had an affinity for cobbler, blackberry cobbler. And she
said to me one day, she said, Mike, do you do you want that blackberry cobbler?
You're coming over for it. I said, well of course I want that blackberry
cobbler. And she said, I left my dish at church, and you go right past that church.
Could you just stop and pick that dish up? She had it set up, and the custodian,
who was a tremendous soul winner, had the dish in his hand. And it wasn't coming
out of his hand until I listened. And for 45 minutes he cornered me between a
water fountain and a wall, and he told me I was a sinner, and he told me I deserved
to go to hell. He told me that God loved me, my parents loved me, that yes, my mom
did this so that he could talk to me about the Lord. I was under conviction. I
got out of there without bowing my head and trusting Christ. I got home, thought
back and play with the baby, and I'll forget this, and I'll feel better. And I
got home, and my wife was gone with the baby. And my mother had given us a little
ward Bible, $2 Bible, no red letters, no notes, no maps, just a Bible. And she had
taken a red pen and a ruler and underlined Romans chapter 10, verses 9
and 10 and 13. And deeply under conviction, I took that Bible down from a
shelf. We'd put it on a shelf. We didn't, we were glad to have it, didn't need it.
And I opened that Bible to Romans chapter 10, verses 9 and 10 and 13, and
read them. And that man had just talked to me about the gospel and about Jesus's
resurrection, about his death, his resurrection, about his substitutionary
death for me. And I knew in my heart, I did believe that. And I knew I had to
confess that. And I came to Romans chapter 13, I'm sorry, chapter 10 and
verse 13, for whosoever shall call upon the name of the Lord shall be saved. I
took that Bible over to our sofa. I laid it on the sofa. I kneeled down before the
sofa. I prayed the most deeply theological prayer you've ever heard. It
went something like this, God if you can save somebody like me, will you save me?
And he did. Because God is utterly faithful. God is utterly faithful. That
whether it is 1200 AD, 70 AD, or 2021 AD, if a man or a woman or a child will
acknowledge that indeed they are sinners, and that their only hope of salvation is
the gift that is given to us in the Son of God, Jesus Christ, who came and loving
us, lived on this earth for 33 years, and as the Bible says, was yet without sin.
And gave himself to die on the cross, and in a transaction that I will never
understand fully until I get to heaven, my sin is placed on him, and his
righteousness is placed on me because of what he did.
and because of my acceptance of that truth, and when God sees me, he no longer
sees sinful Mike Edwards. He sees the righteousness of his Son, Jesus Christ.
That is available to every person on this globe, because God is faithful to
save all those who, understanding their need and confessing the truth of Christ,
will call upon him. So a series of questions and I'm done. Have you developed
a complaining spirit in the chaos and the confusion, the sadness of our world,
the anger that surrounds us? Have you developed a spirit of grumbling? It's not
an innocent thing, and you and I must be the testimonies of God's mercy and grace
in this dark time, and our grumbling does not accomplish that. We may well
have been handed the greatest soul-winning evangelism tool the world
has known in hundreds of years in this pandemic, but if all our workmates here
is our complaining about a mask, or our complaining about this and complaining
about that, that will never draw people to the God that is so much
bigger than all this. Are you fearful? There's a lot to be fearful about in
this world, but you and I don't have to live fearfully. Our faith can rest on a
God who knows where we are, what we need, where he's taking us, and how to get
there. Have you been hurt, disappointed by someone? Don't let that marginalize
your walk with the Lord. And how about this? Have you failed? Boy, a revival this
time in our lives is a moment when we can say, God, I want to get back into it.
Back into what? Back into serving you, back into pleasing you, back into loving
you, back into sharing the truth, and Lord, will you help me? And he will. And then
last, if you're here or under the sound of my voice on livestream, if you're not
sure you've trusted Christ as your Savior, please, it is a matter of knowing
your need because you are a sinner, knowing God's provision of his Son who
willingly died on the cross without sin, not guilty, without sin, taking our sin
upon him so that we could be made the righteousness of God in him. If you'll
call upon the Lord, he'll save you. Would you pray with me? Father, we thank you so
much for these few minutes you've given us, and thank you for the patience of
people to listen to me. And I pray just now, whether folks are here or at home,
whether they need to kneel at their sofa or kneel at their chair or at their
table, whatever it is, God, a grumbling spirit is not an innocent thing, and I
pray they deal with that. And Lord, being fearful in this time, it's understandable,
but it's not acceptable for the Christian. We've got a God, you, who are
able to care for us in the midst of this chaos. And for those who have been hurt
and use that hurt as a reason not to serve and live for you, deal with them
and help them with that hurt. Lord, for those who have failed, they've sinned,
they have broken fellowship with you, would you convince them that you love
them, that you want to restore them? And for those who are unsaved, Father, if they
will but make this simple acknowledgment that they are indeed sinners, and then
believe that your Son, Jesus Christ, came to earth, lived sinlessly, died on a
cross for them, and rose from the dead, and is coming again, if they will confess
that with their mouth, you are utterly faithful to save. So Lord, work in our
lives and accomplish these things, I pray, in Jesus' name, amen.