And we kind of ended up getting bogged down a little bit, but that's okay.
And dealing with this subject and doing what we ought to do.
And in 1 John chapter number 2, in verse number 6,
we're given this truth, and we've been looking at it now for
the last two Wednesday evenings. Tonight will be the third part.
And I thought originally we would get through it in about three weeks,
but it's going to probably be five or six weeks.
And we're not in a hurry, and I'm thankful for the truth of God's word
and the opportunities that we have to study it.
And here in 1 John 2, in verse number 6, it says,
He that saith he abideth in him, ought himself also so to walk, even as he walked.
I'm thankful for the example that the Lord Jesus Christ gave us during His earthly ministry.
Of course, we know several things about the earthly ministry of the Lord Jesus Christ.
And after His baptism and how He made Himself known and through all the miracles
and all that took place that eventually would lead to that trip to Jerusalem,
where He went to after the interrogations and all that took place,
going to a cruel cross to suffer and to shed His blood for your sin and for mine.
Of course, He rose, conquering sin, death, and the grave.
He's alive forevermore, and we rejoice in that.
But we think about those years in which He walked upon the earth.
John says that if all the things were written, the world itself couldn't contain the books.
And so we know that we don't have all that Christ did during His earthly ministry,
but God gave us a record through the gospel accounts.
We find that Peter tells us in 1 Peter that He left us, speaking of Christ,
left us an example that we should follow His steps.
And we find that many times through the life and ministry of the Lord Jesus Christ,
as you study and you examine the portions of Scripture,
and you can see the miracles that are performed and the power of God that's on display
and the proof of deity and all of those things,
but you begin to trace His steps and you see that He walked in a certain manner.
And the very first week that we started this little mini-series within the series,
I said this, that Jesus walked wisely.
And how important it is that we also walk in wisdom,
understanding that we need the wisdom that is from above.
We don't need the earth's, the world's wisdom.
We need God's wisdom.
I'm so thankful that we serve a God who is the all-wise God.
And He said that if any lack, let them ask, right?
And He'll give to all men liberally, abrade it not.
He'll give us wisdom.
If any man lack wisdom, let him ask of God.
And so often what I found in my life and even in ministry over the years
and working with individuals, a lot of times we don't acknowledge our lack of wisdom
and therefore we never ask for wisdom.
And oh, how desperately we need wisdom so that we could walk wisely in this world.
We find that number two, He walked humbly.
And the truth of humility, God says that He resisted the proud,
but He gives grace to the humble.
And how important it is that we as Christ walk, that we too would walk humbly.
Last week we said that He walked purposefully.
And everything He did, He did on purpose and with a purpose.
And there are times in which we can see very specifically the purpose
by which God was moving and working and why He delayed
and why He went to certain places and all of that.
It's a joy and a blessing to think about the life and ministry of the Lord Jesus Christ
and how He lived, He walked with purpose.
And we dealt with this last Wednesday evening and said that we too,
we ought to walk purposefully.
We ought to have some purpose.
We ought to understand what our purpose is.
I'm thankful that as a New Testament believer,
I do not have the difficulty that so many in our society have today of saying,
why am I here?
What is my purpose?
Why am I?
No, no, we know why we're here.
We're here to bring honor and glory to God.
And so we walk purposefully with that idea in mind
that He must increase and we must decrease.
This evening, I want to use this one as our next thought here and deal with it tonight.
Jesus walked courageously.
He walked courageously.
And let me share a couple of passages of Scripture.
Go to the Gospel of Mark, if you will.
And as our custom has been for these last couple of weeks here on Wednesday evening,
we'll examine a couple of portions of Scripture from the Gospels
to see how Christ walked in a particular manner this evening courageously.
And then we'll look at the instruction for us.
We see that Christ walked courageously.
Okay, I am also to walk as Christ walks, so therefore I should walk courageously.
What does that mean?
What does it look like?
So on and so forth.
And so the idea of courage is that quality of mind
which enables men and or women to encounter danger and difficulties.
Notice this with firmness, bravery.
I like this one, boldness and resolution.
And that's what it means to have courage or to be courageous.
And we find that this evening as we consider the life and ministry of the Lord Jesus Christ here in Mark,
if you turn to Mark chapter number 11, Mark chapter number 11,
and notice we find that as we look here at this text
that Jesus was walking, I believe, with courage.
He was walking courageously.
In verse number 27, the Bible says this,
And they come again to Jerusalem, and as he was walking in the temple,
there come to him the chief priests and the scribes and the elders.
And notice what they say to him in verse 28,
By what authority doest thou these things?
And who gave thee this authority to do these things?
Now, I find it quite interesting, of course, in Mark's gospel,
chapter number 11, it only goes to chapter 16,
he's nearing the end of his earthly ministry
and soon going to the cross and all that will take place.
But we find that he's walking and he's there,
the Bible tells us in verse 27, in the temple,
and he's walking there, he's walking out in the midst,
the Pharisees, the scribes, the Sadducees, all the religious leaders,
they all at this point in Christ's ministry,
they were looking for any opportunity that they could possibly come up with to kill him,
they hated him, they were, every time they were around,
they were trying to find something to accuse him of,
and we find that they take this approach in Mark 11,
and they say, By what authority doest thou these things?
Now, it's an interesting question because we know who Jesus is.
Now, they're asking the question, of course,
they're denying the truth that was right before them.
Jesus had made it abundantly clear, in fact, John,
when there's another situation in the Gospel of John
where they come and they say, Tell us plainly, are you the Christ?
And he says, I have, but you didn't believe.
And the reality is that he's made it abundantly clear who he is,
they've already attempted to kill him on more than one occasion
because they knew that he was claiming to be God,
but then they ask the question, By what authority are you doing these things?
Well, he's God, he's the creator.
In the beginning was the Word, and the Word was with God,
and the Word was God, and we find that they ask him this question,
and then they say this, Who gave thee this authority to do these things?
And notice in verse 29, the Bible says this,
And Jesus answered and said unto them,
And I just begin to see the courage of the Lord standing before these that are questioning me,
and he says, I will also ask of you one question, and answer me,
and I will tell you by what authority I do these things.
And then notice where he says, Jesus, just the wisdom,
we could look at this passage as well with Jesus walked wisely,
it says, The baptism of John, verse 30,
Was it from heaven or of men? Answer me.
Now can you see Jesus? Now they think they have authority, right?
These religious leaders, and they were in a place,
and oftentimes these, notice it tells us, they come to him,
the chief priest, the scribes, and the elders, in verse 27,
these individuals, they were used to having a level of power and authority over the people,
and if they ask a question, they expect an answer.
And Jesus says, Well, I'm actually going to ask you a question,
and I'm going to ask you, and you answer me.
And he says at the end of verse number 30, answer me.
But notice verse 31, And they reasoned with themselves.
That's just comical to me, because you know what they did?
Jesus put them in a place where they couldn't give an answer,
because whatever answer they gave was going to really put them in a position
where they were going to be exposed.
And so Jesus, again, if you think about the wisdom of God and what he's doing here,
it says, They reasoned within themselves, saying,
If we shall say from heaven, then he will say, Why then did ye not believe him?
Verse 32, But if we shall say of men, they feared the people.
For all men count it John, that he was a prophet indeed.
And notice verse 33, And they answered and said unto Jesus, We cannot tell.
We cannot tell. And notice what Jesus said,
Neither do I tell you by what authority I do these things.
I see a measure of courage as he stands there to those that were the authority.
from a physical, from a human perspective,
the religious leaders of the day,
the chief priests, the scribes, the elders,
they come and they ask Jesus, and he says,
actually, I'm gonna ask you a question first.
If you answer me, then I'll answer you.
And he gives them the question, says, answer me.
They refuse to answer.
And then Jesus says, and I'm not gonna answer you either.
Wow.
The courage of the Lord.
We find in John chapter seven, turn over if you will,
and I want you to see in John chapter number seven,
we looked at this passage a couple of weeks ago,
and as we talked about the wisdom of the Lord,
and where he said that he was not going yet,
but in John chapter number seven,
we find here that he says to those, his brethren,
he tells them to go, verse six,
then Jesus said to them, my time has not yet come,
but your time is always ready, in verse eight,
he says, go ye up unto the feast.
I go not up yet unto this feast,
for my time is not yet full come.
But we find that it's interesting,
because the Bible says when he had said these words
in verse number nine unto them, he abode still in Galilee.
Again, we could look at what we dealt with last week,
the purpose, he walked purposefully.
We begin to see these things weave together
as we study through this here, this little mini-series,
how that it's not independent that I walk wisely,
but not courageously, or I'm walking courageously
and not wisely, or I'm walking purposefully,
but not wisely, no, no, no, it all gets weaved together.
And we find that what happens is it says here,
in verse number nine, that he abodes still in Galilee.
Notice in verse 10, but when his brethren were gone up,
then went he also up unto the feast,
not openly, but as it were in secret.
Then the Jews sought him at the feast and said,
where is he?
Now, why were they seeking him?
Because they knew he was gonna be there,
and they wanted to kill him.
Why was it that they knew he was gonna be there?
Well, because he's a Jewish man,
and by the law, he was required to be there.
And so they knew that he would be there,
and they're seeking him, but they're not seeking him
because they wanna learn of him, or they have,
no, no, they're seeking him because they wanna kill him.
It tells us in verse number 12,
and there was much murmuring among the people
concerning him, for some said, he is a good man,
others said, nay, but he deceived the people,
how be it, no man spake openly of him for fear of the Jews.
Now, about the midst of the feast,
Jesus went up into the temple and taught.
That's public, that's courage.
He knew that they wanted to kill him.
If you go back into the text of scripture in verse number one
and after these things, Jesus walked in Galilee,
for he would not walk in Jewry
because the Jews sought to kill him.
And then we find that as they were searching for him,
and as they were looking for him,
they knew that he would be there,
that he goes, and according to verse number 14,
about the midst of the feast,
he went up into the temple and he taught.
And notice in verse 15 that the Jews marveled,
saying, how knoweth this man letters, having never learned?
Jesus answered them and said, my doctrine is not mine,
but his that sent me.
If any man will do his will, he shall know of the doctrine,
whether it be of God or whether I speak of myself.
He that speaketh of himself seeketh his own glory,
but he that seeketh his glory that sent him,
the same is true and no unrighteousness is in him.
Notice in verse 19, did not Moses give you the law
and yet none of you keepeth the law?
Why go ye about to kill me?
He approaches it head on.
Why are you going about to kill me?
The people answered him, verse 20, thou hast a devil,
who goeth about to kill thee?
Jesus answered and said unto them,
I have done one work and ye all marvel.
Moses therefore gave unto you circumcision,
not because it is of Moses, but of the fathers,
and ye on the Sabbath day circumcise a man.
Why does Jesus say that?
Well, because they were always criticizing
the fact that he was working on the Sabbath.
What was he doing though?
He was healing people on the Sabbath.
He was showing that he is the Lord of the Sabbath.
And we find that that was always a contention.
In fact, as you trace the steps of Jesus,
many miracles that he performed were on the Sabbath.
And so we find that he says, but you on the Sabbath,
you circumcise a man.
Why?
Because of the law of Moses and he deals with that.
Verse number 23, if a man on the Sabbath day
receives circumcision, that the law of Moses
should not be broken.
Are you angry at me because I have made a man
every whit whole on the Sabbath day?
Judge not according to the appearance,
but judge righteous judgment.
Do you see the boldness and the courage of the Lord?
We find that in the midst of facing,
knowing that individuals were desiring to kill him,
that Jesus went and he's teaching publicly.
He's right there.
I then notice in John chapter 18,
quickly if you turn there,
I want you to see in John chapter number 18.
Now Jesus knew all things.
We find that Jesus in John 17 said the hour has come.
We find that Jesus had been preparing the disciples
for a period of time, especially in the Gospel of John,
as you trace kind of the chronological order
of the Gospel of John.
Jesus had been preparing the disciples for what?
I'm gonna go to Jerusalem, I'm going to be tried,
I'm going to die, and I'm gonna rise again.
And they weren't getting it, they weren't getting it,
but he's giving them the truth.
He knows what's going to happen.
He knew that it was for this hour that he was born.
He understood the plan.
And we find that in John 18,
this is the arrest in the Garden of Gethsemane.
We find that the Bible says in verse one,
when Jesus had spoken these words,
that's chapter 17, the hour's come, so on and so forth,
he went forth with his disciples over the Beuchatron,
where was a garden into the which he entered
and his disciples.
And Judas also, which betrayed him, knew the place,
for Jesus oft times resorted thither with his disciples.
Now remember, what did he tell Judas to do
after they had the last supper?
He said, what you're gonna do, do it quickly, right?
Did Jesus know that he was gonna betray him?
Yes, he made it known.
Now the disciples didn't get it, why?
Because they're too busy arguing
about who's gonna be the greatest, right?
That's what's going on,
they're arguing about who's gonna be the greatest,
but Jesus knew that Judas was going to betray him,
and Jesus made it known, he to whom I give the sop,
and so on and so forth,
but he tells them what you do, do quickly.
Now they thought, oh man, he's got the bag,
he was in control of the money,
and therefore, whatever it was
that he was gonna go buy supplies or whatever it was,
they totally missed it, all right?
And so Jesus knew that Judas was gonna betray him,
and Jesus goes to a place,
a place that was very well known,
a place that Judas knew,
a place that Judas would be able to easily go to
and lead the religious leaders
that wanted to kill Jesus to betray him in that place.
But guess what Jesus did?
He went there anyway,
because he was walking courageously.
Notice it says this in verse number two,
and Judas also, which betrayed him,
knew the place, for Jesus oft times
resorted thither with his disciples.
Judas then, having received a band of men
and officers from the chief priests and Pharisees,
cometh thither with lanterns and torches and weapons.
Now can you see in your mind's eye the scene?
I mean, I see this scene of this group of people coming,
I mean, this mob of people,
and they're coming with perceived power, right?
They're gonna take and arrest Jesus,
and Jesus, notice what it says in verse number four,
therefore, Jesus therefore,
knowing all things that should come upon him,
went forth and said unto them, whom seek ye?
That's courage.
This whole group of people come.
We know as we read the other gospel accounts
that when Judas comes and betrays them how?
With a kiss, that he says to Judas, friend, friend.
And Jesus knew all things,
and yet he goes out to this band of people
and says, whom seek ye?
And notice they answered him, Jesus of Nazareth.
Now, I've said this before,
I don't have time to deal with all of it tonight.
In the beginning of the calendar year of 2024,
we dealt with like 15 weeks of why
we should continue using the King James Bible,
but one of the lessons that I taught,
we talked about the italicized words.
The italicized words are not in the original language,
they're put in for the ease of readability.
There are some verses of scripture
that if you remove the italicized words,
you can understand why it's hard to follow the flow
because of the language differences
between the Greek and the Hebrew and the English,
and so they're entered in, they're inserted,
and they're put in italicized words
by the writers of the King James
because they're being transparent and they're saying,
hey, these are not in the original language
and we want it to be known.
They're not doing the deceitfulness kind of stuff
that the modern versions are doing
where they just take and change and remove and add
and so on and so forth,
and I want you, the reason that I say this
is because this passage is so powerful.
In John chapter 18 and verse number five,
they say that they're seeking Jesus of Nazareth
and Jesus said unto them, I am.
Now, your Bible says I am he,
and I understand it, I get it, he is italicized, all right?
But he says, I am.
What's the significance of that?
Exodus.
Moses says, whom shall I say sent me?
I am.
that I am, right?
What did Jesus say in John chapter number eight,
when he says, before Abraham was, I am.
And so Jesus, when they say, I'm searching,
we're looking for Jesus of Nazareth,
he goes to these group of people and he says, I am.
And Judas also, which betrayed him, stood with them.
And then notice what it says,
as soon then, in verse number six,
as he said unto them, I am,
they went backward and fell to the ground.
The power of his word,
but the courage by which he walked.
He knew why Judas was coming.
He knew why that band of men were gathered together.
He knew what their evil intent was,
but he knew I was born for this purpose.
This is the hour by which I'm going to pay
for the sin of the world.
He knew all of that.
And he walked with courage.
We could go on and on this evening through the gospels
and look at various examples of Christ walking with courage,
but let me give some instruction for us
as the people of God,
that today we too are to walk with courage.
Not only are we to walk with courage,
but I would say it this way, we must walk courageously.
We must have courage.
We must have this firmness and this bravery
and this boldness and this resolution.
It's not being ugly.
It's not being unkind.
It's not running people over,
but it's just simply having a courageous approach
to how we live our lives,
that I'm living for Jesus.
I'm serving the King of Kings and Lord of Lords.
I've been given authority from him,
and I'm gonna carry out what he's given me
the responsibility of doing,
and I'm gonna do it with courage.
Amen?
And we find, notice if you will, Joshua.
Great passage of scripture.
Joshua chapter number one,
we see the word courage used repeatedly
in Joshua chapter number one,
and I wanna read those verses
because I think they're so powerful.
Moses, of course, is not gonna be able to enter
into the land of promise,
and Joshua would be the next human leader
of the children of Israel,
and we find that in Joshua chapter number one,
if I could sum up the first nine verses
of Joshua chapter number one,
I would sum them up this way.
God encouraged his servant.
God was encouraging Joshua for the work,
for the task that was at hand,
and the Bible says this in verse number six.
Notice we're just gonna kind of pick our way through.
In verse number six,
be strong and of a good courage,
for unto this people shalt thou divide for an inheritance
the land which I swear unto their fathers to give them.
Only be thou strong and very courageous
that thou mayest observe to do according to all the law
which Moses, my servant, commanded thee.
Turn not from it to the right hand or the left
that thou mayest prosper,
whithersoever thou goest.
Verse number eight,
this book of the law shall not depart out of thy mouth,
but thou shalt meditate therein day and night
that thou mayest observe to do according
to all that is written therein,
for then thou shalt make thy way prosperous,
and then thou shalt have good success.
Have not I commanded thee?
Be strong and of a good courage.
Be not afraid, neither be thou dismayed,
for the Lord thy God is with thee,
whithersoever thou goest.
You know, we have a promise,
just as Joshua had a promise,
for the Lord Jesus Christ said this
when he gave the great commission
that's recorded in Matthew,
and lo, I am with you always.
He said, I'm with you.
He tells Joshua to be courageous, why?
Because I'm with you.
He tells us that we're to have that courage, why?
Because he's with us.
And I have a mandate.
I have a command.
I have a commission from my God,
from my Savior, from my Lord,
to live courageously, to live obediently.
We find that in Matthew chapter number 10
and verse number 16, the Bible says this.
Behold, I send you forth as sheep in the midst of wolves.
Be you therefore wise as serpents and harmless as doves.
You know what?
If we're sheep being sent forth into the midst of wolves,
we need to walk with courage.
We need to live courageously.
We need to understand that in this text of Scripture,
notice what the Bible says in Matthew 10 and verse 16.
It's not that I'm just choosing
to walk in the midst of sheep.
No, Jesus says, I send you forth.
Do you notice that?
He says, behold, I send you forth as sheep
in the midst of wolves.
Therefore, be you therefore wise as serpents
and harmless as doves.
And so I didn't just arbitrarily make a decision,
a choice, neither did you, that we're just gonna be sheep
that are gonna go walk amongst the wolves.
No, no, Jesus said, I'm sending you forth.
And therefore, I must have courage
because it requires courage to carry out the work of God.
Why?
Because there's opposition.
There's adversity.
There's people that are gonna say,
you're not allowed to do that.
You can't talk about this.
You can't, no, no, I'm having courage.
Again, I'm not trying to be ugly.
I'm not trying to be unkind.
I'm not trying to plow people over,
but I wanna have courage
because I've been given a mandate from God.
It's amazing to me how people can have such courage
when it comes to certain causes.
And yet as the people of God so often were timid,
we need to have courage, bold as a lion, amen?
I mean, seriously, we need to have boldness.
We find that in the book of Acts,
where does this boldness come from?
This courage, where does it come from?
Is it something that,
well, they're just naturally born courageous.
That's just in their DNA, that they're just courageous,
and I'm just not.
You ever hear somebody say,
well, they just naturally can,
they have a knack for talking,
and it's just not really my thing.
And no, no, no, we've been commanded to do things
that sometimes are within how we are designed
as far as what our natural tendencies are,
but not having the natural tendency
is not an excuse for disobeying what God told us to do.
And so we find that the Bible tells us
in Acts chapter number one, but ye shall receive power.
Now, if you're receiving power,
that means because you don't have power, am I right?
If I have a drill up here that's a power drill,
that's a corded drill,
and I have that thing in my hand
and I'm gonna try to do something,
that drill is absolutely useless
until I plug it into that outlet.
And then all of a sudden,
when I plug it into that outlet
and the current goes through,
all of a sudden my drill has power, am I right?
But without the power source, it's kind of useless.
What did Jesus say, without me you can do nothing.
And so we find here that the Bible tells us,
but ye shall receive power.
Oh, how we need power.
After that, the Holy Ghost is come upon you.
And ye shall be witnesses unto me, both in Jerusalem
and all Judean and Samarian
under the uttermost part of the earth.
I fear sometimes that we have allowed the Pentecostals
and the Charismatics to steal from us
Biblical truth with regard to the Holy Ghost
and the ministry of the Holy Ghost.
There is clear Bible teaching
about what it means to be indwelled
by the Holy Spirit of God,
what it means to be filled with the Holy Spirit of God
and what the ministry of the Holy Spirit of God is.
And sometimes we get so worked up
over the Pentecostals and the Charismatics
and the speaking in tongues and all of the scientists,
we can deal with all of that biblically.
It's very easy if you just study the scriptures
and you can address all of it and you can understand it,
but we can't get so far over correcting from it
that we shy away from talking about the ministry
of the Holy Spirit of God in the life of a believer.
I'm thankful to be sealed with the Spirit of God.
It's the earnest of our inheritance.
Listen, my spirit, his spirit,
it's gonna commune with my spirit.
And we understand that Paul,
he has said to go into Asia and Bithynia
and so on and so forth,
but the Spirit suffered him,
the ministry of the Holy Spirit of God.
I read recently, and this is kind of a rabbit trail,
but I'm gonna get the rabbit and kill him
and we're gonna get back.
But I read recently, these Pentecostals,
they got all this crazy stuff about the Holy Spirit
and it was tongues and it was this and it was that.
They said now, I just read this about three weeks ago,
that there was this new movement,
this is absolutely crazy, it blew my mind,
that to prove that you're filled with the Holy Spirit,
you start throwing up, okay?
Now that, Doc starts laughing.
Here's my immediate, Bart, my immediate thought was this.
Who's gonna clean all that mess up?
That was my immediate thought, all right?
It makes zero sense.
Where are you finding that in the Bible?
It's bizarre.
Back to the passage, back to the thought.
We're to have boldness so that we can walk courageously.
Notice in Acts chapter number four,
I think about Peter standing here in Acts chapter number four
and the Bible tells us in Acts chapter number four,
they'd already been imprisoned and they're kept in ward.
Why?
Because of the miracle that took place
in John chapter number, excuse me, Acts chapter number three
and we find that they're kept overnight
and they begin to get interrogated
and in verse number eight, Peter, the Bible says this,
filled with the Holy Ghost.
He said.
unto them, ye rulers of the people and elders of Israel."
And we can read what he says.
It's not very long, but we don't have much time.
He ends it by saying in verse 12,
neither is there salvation in any other,
for there's none other name under heaven given among men
whereby we must be saved.
Now, when they saw, notice what they saw, the boldness.
What did I say courage was?
Courage was having the quality of mind,
which enables an individual to encounter danger
and difficulties with firmness,
bravery, boldness, and resolution.
They saw the boldness of Peter and John.
See, they were used to having authority.
These that gathered, these religious leaders
that gathered John and Peter together,
and they're going to begin to interrogate them.
They're used to people being timid and shying away,
but Peter stands up filled with the Holy Ghost,
and he gives them an answer.
He's got courage.
He's got courage, and it says that they saw
the boldness of Peter and John
and perceived that they were unlearned and ignorant men.
They marveled, and they took knowledge of them,
noticed this, that they had been with Jesus.
I said this, I believe it was on the Sunday afternoon
service of our friend day this year.
You can't pretend when it comes to spending time with Jesus,
and people can tell if you've spent time with Jesus,
and we find here that they saw the boldness,
and how do they get that boldness?
Well, it's the key is in verse number eight
that they're filled with the Holy Ghost.
Notice, if you will, in Acts chapter number four,
as we continue to go through,
we don't have time to look at every verse of scriptures.
We dig through this very quickly tonight,
but we find that after they stand and they preach
that these religious leaders, they're stuck
because they don't know what to say.
They don't know what to do because guess what?
The man that was healed in Acts chapter number three
is standing there, and everybody saw him.
Everybody knew that he was lame, and he sat at the gate.
They saw him yesterday, and last week, and the week before,
and now he's leaping and praising God,
and they don't know what to do.
It actually says at the end of verse number 16
that a notable miracle was done, and we cannot deny it.
Listen, it was impossible for them to come out there
and say, hey guys, look, it's just a fake.
It's just a fraud.
No, they could not deny it, so what do we do?
How do we handle this situation?
Well, here's what we're gonna do.
We're gonna threaten them.
We're gonna tell them you can't talk
in the name of Jesus anymore.
We're gonna forbid you to speak about the name of Jesus.
That's what happens.
I can't read it all, but that's what happens
in the next several verses.
In verse number 23, being let go,
they went to their own company, and what do they do?
They prayed.
In verse 24, the Bible says, and when they heard that,
they lifted up their voice to God with one accord,
and notice they say, Lord, thou art God,
which hast made heaven and earth,
and seen all that in them is.
They recognize, as you study the prayer of the disciples
in Acts chapter number four, they knew who God was,
and their prayer revealed it.
I wonder when we examine our prayers,
how much does it reveal that we know about God?
It says to us in verse number 29,
and now, Lord, behold their threatenings,
and grant unto thy servants that with all boldness
they may speak thy word.
You know what they prayed for?
They prayed for boldness, but can I say it?
I don't think it's a stretch to say they prayed for courage,
because to have courage is to have boldness,
and we find that they pray, God, they didn't.
Now, could God have removed the enemy?
Sure.
Could God have dealt with them?
Absolutely, but they don't pray that way.
They say, God, you heard what they said.
You heard their threatenings.
You heard what they commanded us,
so now we're asking that you would give us boldness
to speak thy word, and the Bible tells us
in verse number 31, and when they had prayed,
the place was shaken where they were assembled together,
and they were all filled with the Holy Ghost,
and they spake the word of God with boldness.
Several more verses that I have in my notes.
We won't take time this evening.
We need to pray, but I want you to know
that there's an example after example after example
in the book of Acts of the disciples
really walking with Christ and walking courageously
in the midst of great adversity,
in the midst of great opposition.
They walked with courage.
They had boldness, and they're living in such a way
that they're making a difference,
so much so that they say you filled Jerusalem
with your doctrine.
They say that you've turned the world upside down.
They were courageous.
They were walking just like their Savior walked.
In Ephesians three and verse 12,
I'll close with this verse of Scripture.
The Bible says in whom we have boldness
and access with confidence by the faith of him.
Listen, God has given to each of us this evening
a mandate, a responsibility to walk in such a manner
that we would bring honor and glory to his name,
that we would walk with courage,
that we would live courageously,
that we would understand this evening
that our God is on his throne,
that we would understand tonight
that he's given us a responsibility,
and if I'm going to look at my life,
if I'm going to examine my life and say
am I walking as Christ walked?
Well, how did he walk?
Well, one way that he walked was courageously.
Then I have to examine my life and say
how many times have I shied away?
Have I had a measure of being timid
as opposed to being bold and not having the courage
because I was afraid of what maybe somebody would think
or somebody would say or what they would think of me?
No, no, no, we need to have courage
because can I tell you this evening
it matters a whole lot more what God thinks of me
than what any man thinks of me,
and the same is true of you.
Oh, that God would give us some courage tonight,
courage to stand for truth and for right,
courage to proclaim the gospel of the Lord Jesus Christ.
Let's pray together.
Father, we love you.
We thank you for loving us.
Thank you for your word, the truth contained therein.
I pray, Lord, that you bless our time of prayer.
We thank you for the privilege.
Pray that you'd be honored and glorified
for it's in Christ's name we pray, amen.