Ezra chapter number 8 this evening, you say, I thought we were studying the life of Elisha.
We were, but we're not tonight.
And on May 17th, a couple of Sunday nights ago, we had the opportunity to consider the
testimony of Ezra, and I preached on that Sunday evening about Ezra, and really from
the seventh chapter of the book of Ezra, and we talked about the fact that Ezra, he was
a ready scribe, and as we looked at the truth about his life and we understand the things
that he did, we mentioned from Ezra 7 and verse number 10 that he prepared his heart
to seek the law of the Lord.
We understand that he purposed to obey it.
It says there, and to do it, and then he planned to influence others.
He said, and to teach in Israel statutes and judgments, and what a great testimony Ezra
has and had, of course, and we had the opportunity, as we studied a couple of Sunday nights ago,
the life of Ezra, to look at his testimony, and then we went over to the book of Nehemiah
and had the opportunity to see the ministry of Ezra and how he was preaching the Word
of God, and he was declaring the truths of the Word of God, and helping the people to
understand that which was written and contained therein, and what a blessing to see the life
of Ezra and his testimony.
This evening, we're going to take a few moments to study this portion in Ezra chapter number
eight that really is going to provide us with an account of their journey to Jerusalem.
The first 20 verses of Ezra chapter number eight, we're not going to even read them.
Those first 20 verses really provide us with a record of the families who would accompany
Ezra to Jerusalem, and we'll look at a few verses of Scripture here in Ezra chapter number
eight, but I want you to look at verse number 31.
I'll give you the title and we'll get into the message this evening.
In Ezra eight, in verse 31, the Bible says this,
"'Then we departed from the river of Ahava on the twelfth day of the first month to go
unto Jerusalem, and the hand of our God was upon us, and he delivered us from the hand
of the enemy, and of such as lay in wait by the way.'"
I want to preach a message this evening that I've simply entitled, I've adopted the title
here from verse number 31, the hand of our God was upon us.
The hand of our God was upon us.
It's interesting that verse number 31 begins with that word, then.
There were some things that took place before you get to the departure that is recorded
in verse number 31, because really, in verse 31, we read of the departure from the river
Ahava.
We read in verse number 32 of their arrival to the city of Jerusalem, but we begin in
verse number 31 by noticing that word, then, and if we go back into the passage of Scripture,
we begin to find some things that Ezra and the children of Israel did before they left
and traveled to Jerusalem.
If you're taking notes this evening, I want you to notice, first of all, the danger they
faced.
We understand as we read the Old Testament, or we read portions of Scripture with regard
to the times in which Ezra is being written, of course, the captivity, the remnant that
would return to the city of Jerusalem, and God had prophesied that through His prophets,
and of course, many had been faithful, and the Bible gives us the record here in the
book of Ezra, we read again in Nehemiah as well, of the return of that remnant.
What a blessing to see the fulfillment of God's prophecies, and to understand, however,
that there was opposition, there was danger that they would certainly face.
In fact, as we read the passage of Scripture, both in Ezra and in Nehemiah, we understand
that the Lord gives us names specifically of those that were the adversaries of the
work of God, and those that were opposing the work of God.
Throughout the history of the world, we find that God's work has always been opposed.
There's always a certain amount of danger that someone would face in serving God.
We find that as you look at the New Testament, you read the life and ministry of the Apostle
Paul, and we reference some things about his life on Sunday evening in our message, and
as we consider the life of the Apostle Paul, he was aware of the danger that he faced,
and he was aware of those things that he would encounter along the way.
In fact, he gave truth to his followers, and specifically to Timothy.
He said, yea, all those that live godly in Christ Jesus shall suffer persecution, and
he tells them that, and we find here in the passage of Scripture that there was some danger
that they faced.
Notice if you will, back up into the text of Scripture, and look at verse number 22.
The Bible says, for I was ashamed to require the king, a band of soldiers, and horsemen
to help.
Notice what he says, us against the enemy in the way.
So there was a certain knowledge that Ezra had with regard to the danger that they would
encounter as they would make their journey to Jerusalem.
He understood the danger that was there.
He mentions about the enemy that was in the way.
If you read in verse number 31, as he's giving and rejoicing as to the protection of God,
that he says there, then we departed from the river of Ahavon, the twelfth day of the
first month, to go into Jerusalem.
Notice what it says, and the hand of our God was upon us, notice, and he, God, delivered
us from the hand of the enemy.
So again, we see that the enemy is mentioned in verse 22, again in verse number 31.
Then notice how he ends the verse, and of such as lay in wait by the way.
Now if you're like me, you read a verse of Scripture like this, and you, in your sanctified
imagination, you can kind of perceive what it was that they would encounter as they would
take this journey.
Traveling in these days was quite different than it is to travel here in the United States
of America.
We have the privilege to be able to travel, and we travel freely often throughout the
state, and throughout the states.
Of course, during this pandemic, there have been some limitations to travel and what have
you, but we many times do not fully understand some of the dangers that were common to those
that would travel in these particular days.
There would be some considerable danger that they would face.
And so as we look at the text of Scripture, we notice, we understand that Ezra was aware
of the danger that they would face.
But as we look at the passage of Scripture, we don't only notice the danger that they
would face, but we notice their dependence is declared.
Notice what Ezra says in verse number 22.
It's interesting to me.
The Bible tells us that he was ashamed to make the request for a military escort.
Notice what he says in verse 22.
For I was ashamed to require of the king a band of soldiers and horsemen to help us against
the enemy in the way.
I almost in my mind's eye begin to think about this dilemma, if you will, that Ezra is facing.
He's understanding the journey that's going to take place.
He understands there's a band of families that are going to travel with him.
He knows there's a danger and there is the possibility of speaking to the king and requesting
a military escort.
And yet the Bible tells us that Ezra says of himself that he was ashamed to make this
request.
It's interesting that he acknowledges the fact that he could have made the request,
but he says that he was ashamed to make the request.
The question that we ask ourselves, and thankfully it's answered for us in the text of Scripture,
we would say, why is it that Ezra was ashamed to request this military escort?
Why was it, Ezra, that you were not willing when you see all that took place and you see
in the beginning of chapter number 8, it says, these are now the chief of their fathers.
This is the genealogy of them that went up with me from Babylon in the reign of Artaxerxes
the king.
But you find that if you were to read in chapter number 7, in verse number 27, the Bible says,
blessed be the Lord God of our fathers, which hath put such a thing as this in the king's
heart to beautify the house of the Lord, which is in Jerusalem.
Well, guess what the king, Artaxerxes, had told Ezra.
He told him in verse number 20, and whatsoever more shall be needful for the house of thy
God, which thou shalt have occasion to bestow, bestow it out of the king's treasure house.
In verse number 26, the Bible says, and whosoever will not do the law of thy God and the law
of the king of judgment be executed speedily upon him, whether it be unto death or to banishment
or to confiscation of goods or to imprisonment.
And that's where Ezra then declares the blessing and seeing how God was working through the
heart of the king.
But Ezra says, I'm ashamed to ask for a military escort.
I'm ashamed.
Why, Ezra?
Well notice what it says in verse number 22, he was ashamed because of what he had previously
declared to the king regarding his God.
See, the Bible tells us in verse number 22, notice, for I was ashamed to require the king,
a band of soldiers and horsemen to help us against the enemy in the way, because, here's
the reason, we had spoken unto the king.
And here's what we said to the king saying, the hand of our God is upon all them for good
that seek him, but his power and his wrath is against all them that forsake him.
So Ezra.
And those, he says, he uses the plural,
we had spoken to the king,
but we know that Ezra is part of that.
And what he had previously proclaimed to the king
was that our God is able.
He had previously declared to the king
that we believe that our God,
that the hand of our God is upon all them
for good that seek him.
So Ezra was mindful of what he had previously
proclaimed to the king about his God.
And then he says, therefore, I'm ashamed
to go ask him for a military escort
because I've already told him that my God is able.
I've already told him that my God's hand
is upon them for good that seek him
and that his power and his wrath
is against all them that forsake him.
So Ezra's in this dilemma, if you will,
of I'm not gonna ask for an escort from the king.
We could say it this way today.
We know that we serve the king of kings
and the Lord of lords,
that he is the Lord God omnipotent,
that safety is of the Lord.
We understand as many biblical truths
with regard to the ability and work of our God.
And we'd say, I'm not looking for
what some human can provide for me
because I know what God can provide for me.
And here's the thought.
It was time for Ezra and the children of Israel
to live what they had proclaimed,
to live what they had proclaimed.
See, sometimes it's easy for us to make some proclamations.
There's another thing to live it, amen?
It's easy for us to say, but God said he's gonna do this
and he's gonna do that and he's this and he's that.
He is.
This book is not just a book of theory.
This book is a book of practice.
And we find that everything that God has revealed
to us in this book about himself is true.
And he's dependable, he's trustworthy, he's faithful.
In Ezra, we find that his dependence is declared.
We find that he has this moment of revealing to us
the dilemma, if you will, but notice in verse number 21
and also in verse number 23,
notice what they were depending upon.
They weren't depending upon the king's escort.
They weren't depending upon the military escort,
the band of soldiers and the horsemen
that could be provided from the king.
No, the Bible tells us in verse number 21,
then I proclaimed a fast there at the river of Ahava
that we might afflict ourselves before our God
to seek of him a right way for us and for our little ones
and for all our substance.
Verse 23, so we fasted and besought our God for this
and he was entreated of us.
Isn't that good?
Perhaps there were some within the group that said,
hey Ezra, why don't we just ask the king for an escort?
I understand the Bible doesn't say that.
That's why I said it could be.
I'm not saying dogmatically that they did,
but I'm saying today that when a leader makes a decision,
when somebody is going to trust the Lord
and take that step of faith,
there are times in which somebody says,
well, we could do this or what about relying on this?
But the reality is that Ezra says,
no, it's a shame to do that.
Why?
Because I know what my God is able to do
and I've declared it to the king.
I've told Artaxerxes what God is able to do.
We look here, we find that the Bible says that after,
if you read the first 20 verses
and you see all of the names of those that are mentioned
that are going to accompany Ezra on his journey to Jerusalem,
we find that when they got there to the river of Ahava,
he proclaimed a fast.
What did he do?
Specifically, they were seeking direction from the Lord.
Notice, to seek of Him a right way for us
and for our little ones and for all our substance.
We find that not only were they seeking direction
from the Lord,
but they were seeking protection from the Lord.
Notice, to help us against the enemy in the way.
He said, I was ashamed to ask the king
for a band of soldiers and horsemen
to help us against the enemy in the way.
So what do they do?
They seek the Lord.
It says in verse number 23,
so we fasted and besought our God for this.
And I love the last words of verse 23.
And he was entreated of us.
This evening, we believe that God hears and answers prayer.
I quoted the verse to someone earlier today on the phone.
I've quoted it many times from this pulpit.
Many of you could quote it as well.
The truth of Ephesians 3 in verse number 20.
He is able to do exceeding abundantly
above all that we ask or think.
It's not just a cute cliche
that Christians run around and say, it's Bible truth.
We serve the Lord God omnipotent.
He is able.
We sing the song.
I preached a message many weeks ago now
from the life of Daniel.
And you read in Daniel chapter six
and you read all that's taking place with the writing
and the fact that they could not make any petitions
of any kings or gods and so on and so forth.
And you find that Daniel's going and he's praying
and he's seeking the Lord.
And of course they come and they accuse him
and he's going to go into the den of lions.
And the Bible tells us that the king Darius,
he says, I know that your God is able.
We sing the song.
He is able to deliver thee.
See what had to happen
for Ezra and the children of Israel
is it was time for them to live what they had proclaimed.
To be doers of the word.
To live by faith.
To believe that God was able.
Would it have been easy and maybe comfortable
to make the request of the king for a band of soldiers?
I can't even say to you that it would have been wrong
for him to ask of that.
I believe that he felt that way.
But if you look in the book of Nehemiah,
the Bible tells us that they sent horsemen with him.
If you look in Nehemiah chapter number two
and you think about Nehemiah and his journey,
the Bible says that when they came to the,
look in chapter two in verse number nine,
then I came to the governors beyond the river
and gave them the king's letters.
Now the king had sent captains of the army
and horsemen with me.
So I'm not telling you that it would have been wrong
for Ezra as we see that Nehemiah did have an escort.
But Ezra says for himself and for those that were with him,
I was ashamed to ask this thing.
I'm gonna trust my God.
I'm gonna trust that he is able.
That he will safely bring us to the place
of where we're planning to go, to Jerusalem.
We read of the danger that they face.
We read of their dependence that is declared.
We read number three of their departure
from the river Ahava.
We mentioned as we read for our text
to open the message this evening, verse 31,
after the fast was proclaimed,
after they sought the face of God,
after they spent time there seeking the face of God
and pleading with God for direction and for protection,
the Bible says, then we departed.
There was a time that they moved on by faith.
Their departure.
See, it was an act of faith.
They trusted the Lord to give them the direction
and the protection that they sought.
They believed that He was able
and they then stepped out by faith
and trusted that God would deliver them.
God did not miraculously put them in some kind of a vacuum
and just transport them from the river Ahava
and put them in Jerusalem.
No, no, they had to take the journey.
The enemy was in the way.
There were some that were laying in wait by the way.
There was an enemy, the danger was there,
but God was working and God is to be glorified
as we notice that after they prayed,
after they sought the face of God,
after they fasted, then we departed.
It says, they departed from the river of Ahava
on the twelfth day of the first month to go into Jerusalem.
Notice, we use this as our title this evening,
and the hand of our God was upon us.
Notice, and He, the Lord God Almighty,
by the way, He is the same yesterday and today,
the same yesterday and today and forever.
Right?
The God that Ezra served, same God I serve.
Amen?
He's as able today as He was then.
Notice, and He delivered us from the hand of the enemy,
and of such as lay in wait by the way.
And we came to Jerusalem and abode there three days.
They got to Jerusalem because they left the river Ahava.
You're never getting to Jerusalem if you don't leave the river.
They didn't leave the river until they fasted and prayed,
and sought direction and protection from God.
But at some point after they had fasted and prayed,
it was time to go.
Faith. Believe in God.
We see that God did.
He's able.
Our God is able.
I love the Bible.
I really do.
I read it every day. I love it.
I preach it with passion.
Why? Because I believe it.
I want to live it.
I love reading the accounts in God's Word
of these great heroes of the faith
as we refer to them as.
Reading through Hebrews 11
and other portions of Scripture,
and reading about the great things
that God accomplished through His people.
But one thing that we notice
in every one of those accounts
is that there was some point
that those Bible characters
stepped out and lived
what they had proclaimed.
Otherwise, there's no Bible account.
There's no David and Goliath
if David's hiding with all the other people
behind the rocks every time Goliath comes out.
You're not going to read of it.
1 Samuel 17 is not going to be there
in the manner in which it is.
There's not going to be a 1 Kings 17 and 18
where you see the miracles
and then you see the situation
in 1 Kings 18 with the showdown at Carmel
with all of the worshipers of Baal.
You don't see Elijah doing that
if he did not practice what he proclaimed.
And at some point in our lives,
we've got to practice what we proclaim.
We've got to do what we believe.
We've got to say this book is not theory.
It's practiced.
This is a book that's to be lived.
And we show that our God is real
and that our God is able.
And He is able to do exceedingly abundantly
above all that we ask or think.
I believe it.
Does it mean that nothing bad's ever going to happen?
No!
Absolutely not.
We'd never preach that because it's not true.
All those that live godly in Christ Jesus
shall suffer persecution.
I told you about a story about a conversation
that I had with someone that called
to do a survey many years ago.
I was, I don't know, it was probably four or five years ago.
I was in the office and someone called
and they wanted to conduct a survey.
And quite honestly, typically,
99.9% of the time when that happens,
I just say I'm busy, I don't have time,
I'm just not interested in surveys.
And on this particular day, I don't know,
something must have happened
and I was just in one of those kind of rare moods
that you're just like, you know what?
You want to ask some questions?
Bring it on.
And they started to ask some questions
and I began to give some Bible answers
and they were asking me all kinds of things
about the progressive movement in our churches today
and the prosperity gospel and so on and so forth.
And they were a student down, I think, at UVA
and they were doing this survey
and I gave them straight answers.
I said, the Bible says,
yea, all those that live godly in Christ Jesus
shall suffer persecution.
We can't pretend that that's not in the book.
It is in the book.
The Bible also says,
for we know that all things work together for good.
Did Joseph encounter some problems?
Yeah.
Did he spend time in prison?
Was he forgotten in prison?
For two years.
But guess what?
Joseph is second in command of all of Egypt.
He didn't go to the palace
without first ending up in the pit and in the prison.
Then he goes to the palace.
See, we serve a God that is awesome.
And at some point in our lives,
we have to put in practice what we proclaim.
We have to live it.
The Christians, they were first called Christians in Antioch.
Why?
Because the behavior of those people was observed.
They said, man, these people, they live like Christ.
We believe a lot of things about this book
and we should,
but I've often said belief impacts behavior.
It has to.
And the other side of that coin,
and it's the same coin,
is that behavior reveals belief.
It's a two-sided coin.
Belief impacts behavior.
Behavior reveals belief.
In this evening, if we look at Ezra in Ezra 8,
we would have to conclude from his behavior
that he believed God.
He believed what he had proclaimed to the king.
He believed that the good hand of God would be upon him
and them as they sought the Lord.
And guess what?
God protected.
We see in this passage of Scripture
as we kind of bounce back and forth
between these verses of Scripture,
there was a danger that they faced.
It was real.
There was a dependence that they declared,
and it was this.
We're not gonna trust the king
to send some military escort to protect us.
We're gonna trust our God.
We're gonna fast and pray, seek the face of God.
And then they departed from the River Ahava.
They got done praying, fasting.
It was time to go.
It was time to live by faith and to believe God.
The Bible tells us, then they departed,
and then it tells us in verse 32,
they arrived in Jerusalem.
Praise the Lord for someone that would live by faith
and believe God.
This evening, I don't know what it is in your life.
I know that there's several things in my life
and several things that we deal with.
You can make the application.
I could make applications
in so many different ways this evening.
But for us tonight, we gotta live what we believe.
If it's in this book, it's true.
Dependable, trustworthy.
Oh, that we'd live it.
Father, we love You.
Thank You for loving us.
Thank You for Your Word.
We thank You for the many accounts
that we get to read and study through Thy Word
to be encouraged, strengthened, and challenged
through the accounts of Your hand at work.
Many of these accounts that we would say
are maybe our favorite Bible account
or however we would use the terminology.
They never would have happened
if someone didn't live what they had proclaimed.
Lord, I pray that You'd help us today in 2020.
It's our hour.
It's our turn.
I wonder what the book would say of our lives.
What would it say of our lives
if someone were to look at us
and to chronicle our behavior in our lives?
Would someone walk away after reading that
by saying, man, they believed God.
They lived what they proclaimed.
Often, as Christians were criticized
for being hypocritical.
It's a criticism that comes far too often.
And we are to be doers of the Word.
We're to practice what we preach,
practice what we believe.
Paul said, the things that you've heard of me
and seen in me do in Philippians chapter number four.
Oh God, we pray that You would help us
to have the faith of Ezra,
to declare our dependence upon Thee,
knowing there are dangers that we face.
God, I pray that You'd help us to live by faith,
to use the terminology of our study this evening
from the life of Ezra,
that You'd help us to leave the river.
God, that we take that step of obedience
and step of faith, believing.
And then God, we can see You do what only You can do.
You just said revival.
We need revival in our nation.
I pray God that You'd help us to be faithful.
We'll thank You for it.
In Christ's name we pray, amen.