10 this evening, as I mentioned, we will have a little shorter of a message this evening.
We have three update videos to have the opportunity to watch.
I want to look really at verses 13 through 17 this evening, and as we look at this passage
of Scripture, it's a familiar passage.
In fact, a couple of verses from this passage of Scripture are extremely familiar to us
in verses of Scripture that we hold dear, in fact, verses that we've probably, many
of us, committed to memory.
And really, as we look at the passage this evening, I would look at those, verse 13 and
verse 17, as being really bookends to the message this evening.
And two wonderful promises that we find in these two bookends.
Notice the Bible says, for whosoever shall call upon the name of the Lord shall be saved.
How then shall they call on Him in whom they have not believed?
And how shall they believe in Him of whom they have not heard?
And how shall they hear without a preacher?
And how shall they preach except they be sent?
As it is written, how beautiful are the feet of them that preach the gospel of peace and
bring glad tidings of good things.
But they have not all obeyed the gospel.
For Isaiah saith, Lord, who hath believed our report?
So then faith cometh by hearing, and hearing by the word of God.
As we think about the passage of Scripture that is before us, of course, the emphasis,
the focus this evening, from our perspective, will be that on missions.
We're gonna look at these mission videos and have the opportunity to see how God is working
and what God is doing in various parts of the world and the privilege that we have as
a local assembly to be involved in what God is doing globally.
We understand that the Great Commission has been given.
We understand that the Lord Jesus Christ, before He ascended up into Heaven, He gave
that Great Commission and He said that we're to go into all the world and we're to preach
the gospel to every creature.
We find that as you read it in the book of Acts, and very interesting as you look at
the passage there in Acts chapter number one, as Jesus gives that Great Commission and then
the ascension is recorded, and you find that no doubt the impact of what the angels said
to those disciples that were there that observed the ascension of Jesus Christ had a great
impact on them fulfilling those last words that they heard from Jesus Christ, and those
words that were to be filled with the Holy Spirit of God and were to be witnesses, and
the idea that we're to be witnesses both in Jerusalem and Judea and Samaria and unto the
uttermost part of the earth.
And the idea of that both, when He uses that terminology, is at the same time.
And so as we're reaching our Jerusalem, we are to be engaged in seeing the rest of the
world reached.
And I'm thankful for the modern aspect of missions, of course, as you read through the
book of Acts and you see the gospel going out, and you find that really until Acts chapter
number eight, when you're looking at all of that which is taking place, you see the gospel
in Jerusalem, and you see the church in Jerusalem, and it's growing, but the persecution is intensifying.
And in Acts chapter number eight, the Bible speaks of a scattering, and when it speaks
of that scattering, it tells us that they went everywhere preaching the Word.
And what a blessing to think about the persecution and the intent of the enemy to stop the gospel
from going forward, but through that disbursement, if you will, through the group of people there
in Jerusalem being spread abroad, they went everywhere preaching the gospel.
You get to Acts chapter number 13, and you have the opportunity to read of the first
missionary journey, and you find that in Acts chapter number 13, the church at Antioch,
what a great church, and they're ministering and they're serving, and God is using them,
and God says through His Holy Spirit to separate unto me Barnabas and Saul for the work that
I've called them to.
And you find that in Acts chapter number 13 is that first missionary journey, and the
men of God that God called for that journey, they went to the region of Galatia.
There were four churches that were established on that first missionary journey, and as those
four churches were established, you find that the book of Galatians would later be written
to the churches that are in the region of Galatia, and you find that you receive further
insight as to what God did and how God worked.
But while they were out doing the work of the ministry, while they were out planting
churches and preaching the gospel, there was a church, the church in Antioch, that was
the sending church, if you will, that had the responsibility of reaching Antioch.
Yes, one of the regions that was, or cities that was reached in that first missionary
journey was Antioch in Pisidia, a different Antioch, and we find that the church is there,
and at the end of that journey, Paul returns and they have this great reunion and rejoicing
of all that God has done and how God has worked.
Now they didn't have the opportunity to send back information and data the way that we
do today, and the technology that exists, and just up-to-date updates that we're able
to receive and urgent prayer requests, and I mean, I'm thankful for technology, and there's
some things about technology I don't like a whole lot, but I'm thankful for the opportunities
to be able to know what's going on, and for these missionaries that we support, they're
not always able to come home and report to us and show us pictures.
Of course, when they come on furlough, we try to get them scheduled in.
We have the opportunity to see these update videos.
It's encouraging because you get to see how God is answering your prayers.
You get the opportunity to see how God is using your dollars as we collectively give
to the work of missions.
We have the opportunity to support all of these missionaries that God has graciously
enabled us to support, and to see that the work is going forward.
Listen, God is working globally.
It is absolutely exciting to see what God is doing.
I understand sometimes we can get under it here in America, and you can see all of the
difficulties that we face, and all of the hardships, and they're trying to stamp out
God and His Word, and all of those things, and the pushback and the opposition, but God
is working.
He's working here in America, and we get to see that, and what a blessing, but man, when
you begin to see what God is doing globally, it's exciting.
As we look at this passage of Scripture, I've titled the message this evening, How Shall
They Preach Except They Be Sent?
Of course, you see that in verse number 15.
I want to look just for a moment at these bookend promises, if you will, in verse 13
and verse number 17, and then I want to look at the questions that are asked in between.
Notice this truth in verse number 13, what a precious promise this is, for whosoever
shall call upon the name of the Lord shall be saved.
Isn't that wonderful?
Are you thankful for that promise?
I remember when I first heard the Gospel, I remember when I first was exposed to the
truth of God's Word, that somebody showed me this verse of Scripture, and they said,
for whosoever shall call upon the name of the Lord shall be saved, and they said something
like this, and I've said it hundreds of times as I've spoken to people over the years.
I've said that word whosoever, that means anybody.
That means any human being.
If you're alive and breathing, you're a whosoever.
Aren't you thankful for that?
And I've encouraged people over the years to put your name in there, take out the whosoever
and put your name, because if you, and have the person say their name, if you call upon
the name of the Lord, it says that you shall be saved.
Now we like the word shall.
It's an old English word, but it's a word of certainty.
It doesn't say that you might be saved.
It doesn't say that you could be saved.
It says that whosoever shall call upon the name of the Lord shall be saved.
And that's a promise that God Almighty has given us.
And we think about this precious promise of Romans 10 and verse number 13, and we understand
this evening how grateful we are to know that promise.
Many of us, again, have the ability to quote this verse of Scripture.
Many of us, someone has encouraged us to hide the word of God in our hearts, perhaps even
we've gone through some outreach classes and they've encouraged us to commit to memory
some verses from the book of Romans, and sometimes we call it the Romans Road, and memorize these
verses of Scripture, and this is one of them.
And again, we have it in our minds and we're familiar with it and we hear it often.
What a precious promise it is.
I'm so thankful that I'm a whosoever, and I'm so thankful that God allowed me to hear
the gospel, and that when I place my faith and trust in the Lord Jesus Christ, He saved
my soul.
What a blessing.
But look at verse number 17, another great promise, one, again, that we are very familiar
with, one that we have committed to memory, one that we've often rehearsed and recited.
The Bible says, so then faith cometh by hearing, and hearing by the word of God.
Have you ever heard somebody say, I just don't have enough faith?
Received a phone call not long ago, just a couple of weeks ago, and the person on the
other end of the phone said, I just don't have any faith, preacher.
And I asked this question, I said, how's your time in God's word?
I don't ask that to be unkind, but the Bible says that faith cometh by hearing, and hearing
by the word of God.
And if you have acknowledged and admitted that you have no faith, that your faith is
small, that your faith is weak, you need to get into the book, amen?
So that our faith would
would be increased.
We find that the Word of God increases our faith
as we go through and read the pages of Scripture,
how it encourages us and how it reveals to us
the nature and character of our God,
that He is the Lord God omnipotent,
that He rules and that He reigns
and that He is able to do exceeding abundantly
above all that we ask or think.
And when we think about the truth of God's Word
and His nature and character revealed to us,
it increases our faith and it causes us to trust Him
and to depend upon Him,
that He is the God of the impossible.
The just, the Bible tells us, are to live by faith.
The Word of God tells us in Hebrews 11,
that great hall of faith chapter,
a chapter that we cherish,
a chapter in which you go to and you see,
so by faith, you fill in the character,
Noah and Abraham and Sarah,
and you fill it in and you see
all of these great accomplishments
because the people of God took God at His Word.
But in verse number six of Hebrews 11,
it says that without faith, it is impossible to please Him.
For he that cometh to God must believe that He is
and that He's a rewarder of them that diligently seek Him.
And so we have to have faith.
That faith comes from this precious book.
The Bible tells us for by grace are you saved through
faith, right?
Ephesians two and verse number eight.
For by grace are you saved through faith.
We understand that it's not a works salvation.
It's not of works lest any man should boast.
I'm thankful for salvation entirely dependent
upon the Lord Jesus Christ.
Because if it was dependent upon you
or if it was dependent upon me, we'd mess it up.
Amen?
If I could lose it, I'd have lost it.
And so would you.
But the reality is that these two precious promises,
verse 13, for whosoever shall call upon the name
of the Lord shall be saved.
Verse 17, so then faith cometh by hearing
and hearing by the Word of God.
Precious promises for us as the people of God.
Bookend promises, if you will,
for this short passage of scripture.
But I want you to notice the questions
that are given in between.
The questions that are given in between
are really important questions.
Questions that we must not skim over.
Questions that we must allow to impact us.
It says in verse number 14,
how then shall they call on Him
in whom they have not believed?
But then it says this,
and how shall they believe in Him
of whom they have not heard?
And how shall they hear without a preacher?
When you look at verse number 14,
there are three questions that are asked
in this verse of scripture.
And if we take it and look at what's happening,
we understand that they're not going to call on Him
in whom they've not believed.
They're not gonna believe in Him
of whom they have not heard, right?
How are you gonna believe in Jesus
if you've not heard of who Jesus is?
Is that fair?
We understand that, correct?
We can't expect someone that's never heard
the name of Jesus Christ,
that does not know the Gospel,
that has had their minds blinded
by the God of this world
to call out and trust Christ as their Savior.
If we look at this in reverse order
in verse number 14,
the reality is how are they gonna hear
without a preacher?
A preacher shows up, a missionary.
These missionaries that we're going to look at
these videos this evening
and many missionaries that we support.
And I was speaking with someone just yesterday actually
about one of our missionaries
in a really a field that is a brand new field.
And it is a hard work.
I mean, the ground is hard.
It needs to be prepared.
It needs to be turned the soil, right?
I mean, it is a difficult work
and it's a difficult place.
But someone needs to go
because how are those people gonna hear
without a preacher?
And if they don't hear,
then they can't believe in Him
because they've not heard of Him.
And if they can't believe in Him,
then they're not gonna call on Him.
And you read that great precious promise
in verse number 13,
for whosoever shall call upon the name of the Lord
shall be saved.
How many whosoever's aren't calling
because they've never heard?
Right?
It continues in verse number 15.
Notice it says this,
and how shall they preach except they be sent?
Really as we think about this
and using it as the title this evening
and looking at verse number 15
and understanding the work of missions
and understanding as I've mentioned already
in Acts chapter number 13,
where they're sent out from that church.
And yes, they're called by the Lord
and God Almighty places a call
upon the lives of these individuals,
but they're sent out.
And how shall they preach except they be sent?
The Lord Jesus Christ sent out witnesses, did He not?
He sent them two by two.
And you find that they were sent
and you find that in Acts 13, they were sent.
And you find that as we look at modern missions,
if you will,
and you begin to think about the mission work
that takes place
and you see how that they are sent
and we desire to hold the ropes
and be behind them and pray for them
and try to encourage them and yes,
give so that they can have the financial resources
that are necessary in order to go
and to preach in those particular areas.
You understand in many countries of the world,
in fact, many of our missionaries,
I've chatted with them personally,
the countries in which they serve,
not all of them, but a majority of them,
you are not permitted to enter into the country
unless you can prove that you have enough financial backing
that you will not be dependent upon their society.
Before you can ever get any entrance into the country,
you must be able to prove
that you're not going to take any of the jobs
that are supposed to be for their people of that country.
It's how it works.
I know it doesn't work that way in America,
I understand that.
But that's how it works in a lot of these countries
where these missionaries serve.
Because the countries are saying,
no, we don't want you to come here and take a job
that could be for someone from a national.
And so the only way we're gonna grant you permission
to come here is if you have the financial wherewithal
to sustain yourself independent
of anything that you would receive from our country.
So that's why missionaries go to all these churches
and try to raise support.
Brother Michael told us
about a brand new missionary this morning.
I don't know the fella, I've never heard of the fella
until I read the email last week from Brother Hamilton.
But what a blessing to think about a new servant of the Lord
that God called that's gonna go out and raise support.
When we pick these missionaries up for support,
it's more than just that we're gonna send them money
monthly, that's part of it.
That's how today in our modern society
and the cultures and the climate in which we must deal,
that's how they have to go.
But it's so much more than just money.
Every missionary that I know,
every missionary that's on our board,
they would tell you as they have told me,
and many of them have stood on this platform
and they've said it publicly,
more than your money, we need your prayers.
Now they need the money.
If they don't have the money, they can't go.
I've already explained that.
But oh, how they need the prayers of God's people.
That's why we have these missionary directory booklets
that we put together.
That's why we update those.
That's why Deborah spent time to put the format together
and we pay to have them print it,
to get a resource into the hands of the members
of our church and the attenders of our church.
Why?
So that we can pray for our missionaries.
I sent out that email on Thursday evening
about Brother Day Carvalho,
and I got a response from one of our members
on Friday morning saying,
you know, God put him on my heart yesterday.
And I was praying for him in the afternoon.
I don't know why God put him on my heart,
but I was praying for him.
They were gonna send an email to Mrs. Day Carvalho
to try to encourage her.
As soon as I received the email,
I responded to Mrs. Day Carvalho.
I wanted to alert the church family.
Why?
So that we can pray.
Because God answers prayer.
And we think about the opportunity that we have,
we understand how shall they preach except they be sent,
that we have this privilege of being part
of that sending process.
Being one of those churches
that is partnered together with these missionaries
to see them go to the place where God has called them.
And then as they go, what do they go to do?
They go to preach.
They go to preach the gospel.
And then all of a sudden,
people that have never heard,
in verse number 14, the last question,
they now have a preacher.
And the preacher comes in and he begins to preach.
They've never heard this message.
They've been blinded by the religious world system.
They've been blinded by the culture in which they're living.
They have state religious organizations
and state-run, government-run churches
and all of these fields
and all of the darkness and the blindness.
And a preacher shows up and begins to preach.
Why?
Because he's been sent.
The family's been sent.
And now...
The preaching.
The preaching of let me tell you who God is.
Let me tell you who Jesus is.
Let me tell you what Jesus did for you.
Let me tell you how much God loves you.
They begin to preach,
and the Bible tells us
that now as you think about them
having a preacher,
now they can hear.
And now that they hear,
remember v. 17,
so then faith cometh by hearing,
and hearing by the Word of God.
So now they're hearing.
The faith is there.
And the Bible tells us in v. 14,
how shall they believe in Him
of whom they have not heard?
Well, now they're hearing,
so now they can believe.
What is faith? Believing.
Believing.
And so now, obviously,
I wish 100% of the people
that heard the Gospel got saved.
We know that's not the case.
In fact, I told an individual yesterday,
I cannot say it in the same way
that the Apostle Paul said it
in Acts 20,
that I'm free from the blood of all men.
I can't say that.
And I believe that he looks at that
from the parallel truth
in the book of Ezekiel,
and Ezekiel being a watchman,
and so on and so forth,
in chapter 3,
and I think in chapter 33.
And you find there,
but I told this individual,
I said, listen,
I just want you to know
that personally between you and I,
I can say that your blood
is not on my hands.
I have given you
the truth of the Gospel,
and I have explained it to you
to the best of my ability,
and I've shown you
the Word of God.
I've answered your questions.
The choice is yours.
The decision is yours,
but I have a clear conscience.
I have done what God has called me to do.
They don't always believe
on whom they have heard,
but now they have the opportunity to believe.
Now the preaching of the Word of God,
now they've heard who Jesus is,
and it says,
how shall they call on Him
in whom they've not believed?
But you notice the truth of verse 13,
and what a blessing
when these missionaries
have the opportunity
to see souls saved.
Lives changed,
because they went to a place
because they were sent.
How shall they preach
except they be sent?
Because God's moved and worked
in your heart and my heart
to give of our resources,
understanding that God has blessed us.
All that we have
is because of the good hand of God.
Amen?
All that we have
is because of God,
and that He would privilege us,
He would allow us
not only to give of our tithes
and our offerings,
but to give to the work of missions,
and to take a portion
of what God has blessed us with
and say,
I'm going to designate for mission work
that these funds,
I'm going to take time
and pray for these missionaries.
Paul said this
in the book of Philippians,
turn over there if you will,
Philippians chapter number four,
and I want you to notice,
and I'm going to close with this thought
because we have the opportunity,
how shall they preach
except they be sent,
that we have the opportunity
because of your giving
and because of our giving collectively
to support these missionaries.
And they're going
and souls are being saved
and lives are being changed,
and I want you to notice
that Paul was speaking
at the end of the book of Philippians
and he's speaking about
how the church at Philippi
had communicated with him,
how they had given to him
an offering once and again.
Notice in verse number 14,
notwithstanding you have well done
that ye did communicate
with my affliction.
Now ye Philippians know also
that in the beginning of the Gospel
when I departed from Macedonia,
no church communicated with me
as concerning giving and receiving,
but ye only.
For even in Thessalonica
ye sent once and again
unto my necessity.
Isn't that a blessing?
The church at Philippi,
they were investing in something
beyond themselves.
They said we want to invest in this.
We want to be part of this.
The Bible tells us
that Paul says,
not because I desire a gift,
but notice this,
but I desire fruit
that may abound to your account.
You know, there are going to be
some people in heaven
that we're never going to meet
on this earth.
But there's a missionary
that we pray for,
that we give to,
that's preached the word of God
because they've been sent.
And people have heard.
People have believed.
And people have called.
People have been saved.
And it's fruit.
It's fruit on our account.
Isn't that amazing?
That's how God's designed it to be.
And we're co-laborers together
with God.
And what a blessing.
Paul continues and says,
but I have all and abound
in verse 18,
I am full having received
of Epaphroditus,
the things which were sent from you
as an odor of a sweet smell,
a sacrifice acceptable
well-pleasingly to God.
God is pleased with this giving
of the church of Philippi.
He's pleased with their investment
in the work that God has called Paul to.
And then notice this great promise,
but my God shall supply
all your need according to His riches
in glory by Christ Jesus.
That's a promise that we can claim.
As we have the opportunity
to see these videos this evening,
I hope that you're encouraged
about the work of missions,
the opportunity that we have
as a local church.
Yes, we have a missions conference
that's coming up in May.
I love missions.
I love missionaries.
I love the privilege of being able
to receive these reports
and every week having at least four updates,
one that Brother Michael provides us with
on Sunday morning,
three on Wednesday evenings
on our prayer bulletin.
Man, it's encouraging.
I hope that we never get bored
with hearing what God is doing
and how God is working.
Because how are they gonna preach
except they be sent?
And unless we in churches like ours
give and pray, the work's not going on.
They're not getting there.
And people aren't calling on
because they've not heard of
the Lord Jesus Christ.
It's a great opportunity, great privilege.
So I hope tonight as we watch these videos
that you're encouraged,
that you have the privilege
of seeing your missions dollars at work.
Amen?
So let's pray.
And then we're gonna look at these videos.
Father, we love you.
We thank you for loving us.
Thank you for the privilege
of being involved in world missions.
I thank you for our church.
Lord, the heart of our church family
to give to the work of missions.
God, to pray for our missionaries.
Lord, I pray that you'd continue
to use our church.
We thank you for the many, many missionaries
that you give us the opportunity to support.
This evening as we take a few moments
to look at these videos,
I pray that you'd encourage us.
I pray, God, that if there'd be one
that maybe you'd call to the ministry,
to the work of missions,
that you'd place your call upon their life,
that, Lord, they'd respond in obedience.
Perhaps, Lord, we've not been
as faithful in giving to missions.
Perhaps we've not been as faithful
in praying for our missionaries.
God, would you help us to increase more and more
in these areas?
Again, we ask that you'd encourage us,
help us to rejoice in that which you're doing.
For it's in Christ's name we pray.
Amen.