a song of surrender. It's my prayer. I was sitting there thinking and listening to them
sing and I pray that they will live their lives the way that they just sang, to do the
will of God. Amen? Isn't that wonderful? And what a blessing. And I appreciate Kimberly
working with the kids and appreciate the parents helping and all of that. What a blessing.
And it's been good. Amen? And now we get to open God's word. 2 Corinthians chapter
number 12. I'm thankful that God's given us a Bible and what a blessing for the instruction
that God has given to us. And I'm going to have you here in 2 Corinthians 12, but I'll
let you know that we will look at a couple of other passages in the beginning here this
morning as we set the foundation for the message. And one of the most familiar verses in all
the Bible I think is probably John 3, 16. For God so loved the world that he gave his
only begotten son that whosoever believeth in him should not perish but have everlasting
life. Aren't you thankful for that Bible truth? And you find that the love of God for humanity
is revealed. It's declared there in that wonderful verse of Scripture in John 3 in verse number
16. You'll find that as you study throughout the life and ministry of the Lord Jesus Christ
that you see God's love displayed. You see it demonstrated. It's declared in that wonderful
verse and then it's demonstrated through the life and ministry of the Lord Jesus Christ.
I believe and I think that you would agree with me that the greatest display of love
is when the Lord Jesus Christ went to that cruel cross to suffer and to bleed and to
die to pay for your sin and for my sin and for the sin of the world. But God commendeth
his love toward us and that while we were yet sinners, Christ died for us. And what
a blessing to consider the display, that greatest display of love when the Lord Jesus Christ
went to Calvary's cross. I'm thankful that he rose conquering sin, death, and the grave.
He's alive forevermore and what a tremendous blessing to know him as our personal Lord
and Savior and to know that he's coming again. And we're thankful for that. I believe that
as you study the Old Testament, you find that God teaches us to love and we see that
very plainly. But it's interesting in John chapter number 13 that the Lord Jesus Christ,
before he would go to the cross of Calvary, he's instructing his disciples and he says
this that he gives them a new commandment. And this new commandment was that they would
love not in a fashion that would be kind of what we could understand as humans, but that
we would love like Christ loved. Begin to understand that as you look through the scriptures
that God has given to us as New Testament believers, a responsibility to love and that
passage in John 13, it's interesting for in verse number one of that chapter, the Bible
says that Jesus loved them unto the end. And then in the passage of scripture, he says
a new commandment I give unto you that you love one another. And then he says this, as
I have loved you, that you love all that you also love one another. And then verse 35 of
John 13 says this by this, by what? By our love one for another by this shall all men
know that you are my disciples. If you have love one to another, the gospels give us this
truth as you begin to study through the epistles and you find that there's instruction given
and there's demonstration of those that would love the brethren and the love that is to
be displayed. And we find that here as we come to 2 Corinthians chapter 13 and look
at our text of scripture this morning, that I find that here the apostle Paul is going
to really develop even further something that he's already taught the church in Corinth.
Remember in 1 Corinthians chapter number 13, it's the great love chapter, the chapter
on charity. And we find that in that portion of scripture, this same audience, we find
that the apostle Paul is used of the Lord to teach the people the importance of charity
or love. And we understand that as you read that chapter, there's so many wonderful truths
that God gives us. And now as he's writing to that same group of people, and he's going
to rehearse some things here in this text of scripture, I believe that really what we're
seeing is Paul's love for the Corinthians. One of the things that I love as you study
the scripture, and especially as you study the New Testament and the epistles and you
study the life of the apostle Paul, is that many times God would use him to give instruction
to the local church. And as he would give the instruction to the local church, in everything
give thanks. That's good instruction. But you understand that as you look at the life
of the apostle Paul, that he was a man that was giving thanks in everything. And you can
study his life and you can see that he was not just preaching a truth, but he was living
a truth. And I believe that's why God used him in the way in which he did, obviously.
But we find that as Paul would tell the believers in Corinth and as God would tell us as a local
church that we're to love one another, that Paul was not only teaching that, but he was
living that. And we find in our text of scripture really the illustration of this, Paul's love
for the Corinthians. Notice, if you will, beginning in verse number 11 of 2 Corinthians
chapter 12, notice the Bible says this, I am become a fool in glorying. Now remember,
he started this back at the beginning of chapter number 11. We've studied over the last several
weeks about this. And he says, ye have compelled me. It was like this requirement that he had
before the Corinthians to be able to really try to distinguish himself versus these false
teachers and these Judaizers and to be able to prove to them that he indeed is an apostle.
And so he says, I am become a fool in glorying, ye have compelled me. Then notice this, for
I ought to have been commended of you. For in nothing am I behind the very chiefest apostles,
though I be nothing. Truly the signs of an apostle were wrought among you in all patience
and signs and wonders and mighty deeds. For what is it wherein ye were inferior to other
churches, except it be that I myself was not burdensome to you? Forgive me this wrong.
Verse 14, behold, the third time I am ready to come to you, and I will not be burdensome
to you, for I seek not yours, but you. For the children ought not to lay up for the parents,
but the parents for the children. And I will very gladly spend and be spent for you, though
the more abundantly I love you, the less I be loved. But be it so, I did not burden you.
Nevertheless, being crafty, I caught you with Guile. Did I make a gain of you by any of
them whom I sent unto you? I desired Titus, and with him I sent a brother. Did Titus make
a gain of you? Walked we not in the same spirit? Walked we not in the same steps? Verse
19, again, think ye that we excuse ourselves unto you? We speak before God in Christ, but
we do all things dearly beloved for your edifying. As we look at this text of Scripture, I believe
that Paul's love for the Corinthians is on full display. As we begin to unpack the passage
of Scripture, and before we really get into the points of the message this morning, I
want you to understand that the Apostle Paul is loving as Christ loved. And that's the
instruction that we've been given. Remember John 13? I read it just a moment ago. This
new commandment that I give you, that you love as I have loved you, right? And this
idea that we're to love as Christ loved. And we find that the Apostle Paul is doing that,
and we understand that right away. Listen, there's some times in which we deal with circumstances
in life, and we have relationships in life. We say, I don't really like that person, or
they didn't really do me right. They didn't really do, so I'm excused. I'm not required
to do this. And we find that in the text of Scripture that Paul points out right in the
beginning in verse number 11. He says, for I ought to have been commended of you. You
know what Paul is saying to these believers in Corinth here in verse number 11? That as
they were really criticizing him and critiquing him, and they were saying, are you really
an Apostle? And they were having all these things that they're saying against him. The
Judaizers are speaking against him. In fact, at the end of verse 16, he's rehearsing and
recounting what they would say. And they were saying of him that he was being crafty and
that he was trying to take advantage of them. And even in this offering that he was sending
to collect, that really he was being deceptive and deceitful and all of these things. But
Paul says to these believers in Corinth at the very beginning of this passage, he says,
for I ought to have been commended of you. What is Paul saying? Paul's saying, you know
what, you believers in Corinth, you should have been commending me. That's not a prideful
thing. It's an understanding of the fact that Paul, by God's grace and by God's leadership,
went to the city of Corinth and he preached the gospel of the Lord Jesus Christ and he
labored there and he invested in these people. And he was in a place where he says here in
verse 15, I will very gladly spend and be spent for you. And that was his behavior.
And when the church in Corinth should have stood up when those Judaizers attacked Paul
and said, no, no, no, that's not the Paul that we know. This is the Paul that we know.
This is how Paul lived. This is what Paul did.
When you ought to have commended me, you didn't.
So therefore, I don't love you, and I'm going to do..."
No.
We look at the past and we say, he loves like Christ loved.
Do you remember when Judas came in to betray the Lord Jesus Christ?
Betrayed him with a kiss.
And do you remember what Jesus called him?
Friend.
We find that as we begin to look at the text of Scripture that's before us, and again,
by way of points, but really just building the whole truth this morning, when we think
about Paul's love for the Corinthians and the responsibility that we have to love, and
sometimes we're of this mindset that, well, they didn't do me right, and so that gives
me the card, the pass.
I don't have to do right to them.
And I can be...
No.
We're to love like Christ loved.
When those very people that were crucifying the Lord Jesus Christ, he said, Father, forgive
them, for they know not what they do.
As we look at the truth this morning, we find, number one, if you're taking notes, that Jesus
gave us the example to love.
I mentioned already in John 13, turn over to John 15, if you will, and in John chapter
13, the Bible says that he loved them unto the end, and I'm thankful for that truth.
It really, many times, has just gained my attention and my time of meditation upon that
very truth, that Jesus, his love was a continuation and it was a continual love, and we find in
the Old Testament that the Bible speaks about the fact that we're loved with an everlasting
love, and I'm so thankful for that truth, and we understand, I read the passage last
week at the end of the sermon from Romans, nothing can separate us from the love of God.
We find in John chapter number 15, it's the great passage of Scripture dealing with the
truth that we are the branches and he is the vine, but if you will, look down at verse
number 12, notice the Bible says this, this is my commandment, that you love one another
as I have loved you.
So at the end of chapter number 13, Jesus gave that commandment, a new commandment,
give I unto thee, and he says here again in John chapter 15 in verse number 12, this
is my commandment, that you love one another as I have loved you, and then notice verse
13, greater love hath no man than this, that a man lay down his life for his friends.
I'm so thankful that the example, if you're taking notes, Jesus gave us the example to
love that he is the greatest example and that as we look at the declaration in that familiar
verse of Scripture in John 3, 16, and that declaration of God's love that as you study
the life of the Lord Jesus Christ, you see that love displayed and demonstrated in the
example that's given to us.
Look if you will at John chapter 17, and as we look at John 17, we understand here that
just before he would be arrested and go to the cross of Calvary, that Jesus is praying
and he comes to the end of the passage, and I love how he mentions this truth for us in
verse number 26, and I have declared unto them thy name, and will declare it, that the
love wherewith thou hast loved me may be in them, and I in them.
As we look at this end of the prayer of the Lord Jesus Christ in John 17, he mentions
about this love, and it's a love that's, it's God's love, and it's the example that he gave
us, and he says that the love wherewith thou hast loved me may be in them, and I in them.
We're to love as Christ loved, and we understand this morning that Jesus gives us the example,
but then let me say this, number two, the Holy Spirit is the one who enables us to love.
We can't love like Christ loved without the power of the Holy Spirit.
It's just absolutely impossible, but we understand that the Holy Spirit of God enables us to
love as we have been commanded to do so.
I love the truth, and it's not just applicable here with regard to the love and the way in
which we're to love, but the truth of God's word, broadly speaking, that where God gives
us a command, he also enables us to fulfill that command, and I'm thankful for that.
There's no command that God has given us in his word that he will not enable us to be
able to fulfill, and I'm thankful for that.
He is the one that enables us.
You say, I can't do this.
Well, you can't in your own power, in your flesh.
Why?
Because your flesh is weak, and without him we can do nothing, but when we understand
that he's commanded us to do so, that he will enable us to perform it.
We find over in the book of Romans, in chapter number 5, notice what the Bible says.
I quoted a few moments ago Romans 5 and verse number 8, but look earlier, if you will, in
the text of Scripture.
In Romans chapter number 5 and verse number 5, we read this truth about the way in which
the Holy Spirit of God enables us to love.
In Romans 5 and verse number 5, the Bible says, in hope maketh not ashamed, because
the love of God is shed abroad in our hearts by the Holy Ghost, which is given unto us.
Now, there's much teaching from verse number 5 that we could focus on this morning.
We find, number one, that hope maketh not ashamed.
Aren't you thankful for the hope that we have in the Lord Jesus Christ?
God is our hope.
He is our hope.
We think about the truth that we're looking for the blessed hope and glorious appearing
of our great God and Savior, the Lord Jesus Christ, and we understand that this hope that
we have as believers is this confident expectation that God will do what he said he will do.
And it says, hope maketh not ashamed.
Listen, don't be ashamed of God or his word.
Don't run around thinking, well, not everyone's gonna believe this and I'm the, no, hope maketh
not ashamed.
I believe the book, amen?
And praise God for it.
Notice he says, because the love of God, remember we're supposed to love as Christ loved, because
the love of God is shed abroad, notice what he says, in our hearts by the Holy Ghost,
which is given unto us.
Let me remind you this morning that at the moment in which you trust that Jesus Christ
is your personal Savior, in the moment in which I trust that Jesus Christ is my personal
Savior, the Holy Spirit of God indwelled me and indwelled you at that very moment.
And I'm so thankful that the Holy Spirit has been given unto us.
It is the, he is the earnest of our inheritance.
And we find that we look here and we find that the Holy Spirit has been given unto us,
and we can study the Scriptures broadly and we can understand many things with regard
to the ministry of the Holy Spirit, but within this verse of Scripture here in Romans five
and verse number five, we find that one of those ministries is that he, the Holy Spirit,
the love of God is shed abroad in our hearts by the Holy Ghost, which is given unto us.
It is the Holy Spirit that enables you and enables me to love as Christ loved.
I can't love as Christ loved apart from the work of the Holy Spirit of God in my life
and neither can you.
We find that in Galatians chapter number five, the Bible speaks about the, the fruit
of the Spirit and the fruit of the Spirit is the very first one, love, love, joy, peace,
so on and so forth.
And we find the truth, listen, this morning, if you say, I just have a hard time loving,
maybe it's because the Holy Spirit doesn't have control in your life like he ought to.
Maybe it's because we're not walking in the Spirit as we ought to, because the reality
is that it's the Holy Spirit of God, the Holy Ghost that enables us to love as Christ
loved.
And when we have a hard time loving, it's not necessarily God's problem, it's not the
other person's problem, it's my problem, amen?
It's my problem, why?
Because God said that his love is by the Holy Ghost, it's shed abroad in our hearts.
And we find here this morning that the fruit of the Spirit, listen, if you walk in the
Spirit, you shall not fulfill the lust of the flesh.
This really begins to start dealing with the truth of the filling of the Holy Spirit.
Yes, we understand the indwelling of the Holy Spirit, that at the moment of salvation, I
got all of the Holy Spirit that I'm ever going to have, and so did you.
But day by day, the Holy Spirit of God doesn't have all of you or all of me.
There are times in which self wants to sit upon the throne, amen?
And all of a sudden, we're not filled with the Spirit because we're filled with self,
and we find here that he says that the fruit of the Spirit is love, joy, peace, longsuffering,
gentleness, goodness, faith, meekness, temperance, against such there is no law.
And they, notice verse 24, we often don't read the entire passage, but in Galatians
5 verse 24, it says this, and they that are Christ have crucified the flesh with the affections
and lust.
See, sometimes what happens, we have a hard time crucifying the flesh, right?
I was having discipleship this week, and we're talking about being a disciple, being a follower
of Jesus Christ, and oh, how we understand the call, follow me.
sometimes we're trying to follow Jesus
and we haven't died to self.
We've not first denied ourselves and taken up our cross
and we've avoided the first two points of instruction
that Jesus gave.
And we're saying, well, I'm trying to follow Jesus,
but I'm not denying myself, I'm not taking up my cross.
And you're gonna find it extremely challenging
and difficult to try to follow Jesus
when you've not denied yourself.
He says, they that are Christ,
aren't you thankful to belong to him?
I'm so thankful that I belong to Jesus.
They that are Christ, I am known, he knows my name,
he knows me, he saved me, he loves me.
And it says, they that are Christ have crucified the flesh
with the affections and lust.
If we live in the spirit, let us also walk in the spirit.
And this morning, we understand it's the Holy Spirit of God
that enables us.
Yes, Jesus is the one that gave us the example to love,
but the Holy Spirit of God enables us to love.
The Bible tells us in Ephesians chapter number five
and verse number two, that we're to walk in love.
We're to walk in love.
By this, Jesus said in John 13 and verse number 35,
shall all men know that you're my disciples
by your love one for another.
As we build all of that foundation
to go back to 2 Corinthians chapter number 12,
we find that yes, Jesus is the example.
Yes, the Holy Spirit is the one that enables us,
but number three, the evidence of Paul's love
for the Corinthians.
How do we know?
When we look here at the text of scripture
and we begin to understand Paul's love for the Corinthians
and the evidence of his love,
we look at this text of scripture and we see it so obvious.
Notice again in verse number 11, the apostle Paul says,
I am become a fool in glory, ye have compelled me,
for I ought to have been commended of you.
For in nothing am I behind the very chiefest apostles,
though I be nothing.
The apostle Paul had a proper view of himself.
He understood that he was nothing,
but he understood that God called him to be an apostle
and that God gave him this responsibility.
It was God who led him to Corinth in the first place,
to plant the church, to preach the gospel,
to invest in people.
And we find that he says,
I in nothing am I behind the very chiefest apostles.
Interesting really is he's kind of playing on words there
because what these Judaizers were saying
is they were elevating themselves
as really he uses the word chiefest apostles
that carries with the idea of being a super apostle.
The apostle Paul says, I come behind none of them.
In fact, they're false teachers.
But Paul then begins to explain in verse 12.
Notice he says, truly the signs of an apostle
were wrought among you in all patience,
in signs and wonders and mighty deeds.
Turn back, hold your place here.
Turn back to Acts 18, if you will.
And as we look at Acts 18,
and I'm gonna read the portion
because I think it's helpful for us to understand
as the ministry in Corinth first begins
and what's taking place in Acts 18.
And we visited this portion of scripture
back in the beginning of the year
as we spoke about the church at Corinth.
But notice with me in Acts 18,
during this missionary journey,
the Bible says after these things in verse number one,
Paul departed from Athens and came to Corinth
and found a certain Jew named Aquila born in Pontus
lately come from Italy with his wife Priscilla
because that Claudius had commanded all Jews
to depart from Rome and came unto them.
Verse three, and because he was of the same craft,
he abode with them and wrought for by their occupation,
they were tent makers.
Notice in verse four,
and he reasoned in the synagogue every Sabbath
and persuaded the Jews and the Greeks.
Now, oftentimes this verse of scripture
is taken out of context and people develop false teaching
based on verse number four, about one,
Paul going to the synagogue
and about number two, that it was on the Sabbath.
But understand with me
that he went to where the people were.
All right, he's going to where the people were
and it says that he reasoned in the synagogue
in previous portion of scripture in chapter 17,
the Bible says that he reasoned with them
out of the scriptures opening and alleging
that Christ must needs have suffered
and risen again from the dead
and that this Jesus whom I preach unto you is Christ.
And so we find that he's using the Old Testament scriptures
and he's going there to the synagogue on the Sabbath
because that's when the people are assembled
and he's delivering a message to them in verse number five
and when Silas and Timotheus were come from Macedonia,
Paul was pressed in the spirit
and testified to the Jews that Jesus was Christ.
This is a powerful declaration.
Remember that Paul himself, he's a Jewish man.
He was raised up, he was a Pharisee of the Pharisees.
He was taught at the feet of Gamaliel.
He was just a zealous man,
but he's now preaching that Jesus is Christ,
that Jesus, God incarnate, God in flesh,
that he is the Christ, he is the anointed one,
he is the Messiah, he is the son of God.
This today continues to be a stumbling block for the Jews
to this very day.
It's a stumbling block for the Jews.
We find that he's pressed in the spirit
and he's testifying and he's preaching in verse number six
and when they opposed themselves and blasphemed,
he shook his raiment and said unto them,
your blood be upon your own heads, I am clean,
from henceforth I will go unto the Gentiles.
Now, verse six, in the midst of that verse,
when he talks about your blood be upon your own heads,
I am clean, it's really interesting.
If you were to go back, we don't have time to develop it,
but you go back to the book of Ezekiel
and you look at the son of man, Ezekiel,
as he's called, referred to many times in that book,
that he was set as being a watchman
and he's given this responsibility,
you read it in chapter three and also in chapter 33
and you read in the text of scripture
that he's given the responsibility to sound the alarm
and if you're faithful to do your job,
the response of the people,
that's their accountable for their response.
If they heed the alarm and they flee
and they have safety and rescue, then great.
If they don't, you're not responsible
because you did your job.
But as a watchman, if you fail to do your job,
if you don't sound the alarm and danger comes,
then you're responsible.
That's a big responsibility.
And no doubt in my mind here and also in Acts chapter 20,
when Paul says your blood be upon your own heads,
I am clean, you know, I think what Paul is saying
is that I've done my job as a watchman,
I have given you the truth but you rejected it
and so I am clean, you're responsible.
And then he says this,
from henceforth I will go unto the Gentiles.
Paul never stopped having a burden for the Jewish people.
He desired they be saved.
Romans nine, Romans 10, I mean, you read it,
it is his heart's desire that they would be saved
and by the way, it ought to be all of our heart's desire
that every person trust Christ as their savior
because if not, they're gonna spend eternity
in the lake of fire.
And we find that in verse number seven,
he departed then and entered into a certain man's house
named Justice, one that worshiped God,
whose house joined hard to the synagogue
and Crispus, the chief ruler of the synagogue,
believed on the Lord with all his house
and many of the Corinthians hearing,
believed and were baptized in that wonderful,
praise God, verse number nine,
then spake the Lord to Paul in the night by a vision.
And notice what God tells Paul, be not afraid,
but speak and hold not thy peace for I am with thee
and no man shall set on thee to hurt thee
for I have much people in this city.
That's an encouragement message from God.
In the face of the opposition,
in the face of the difficulty
that God gives the apostle Paul this promise, this truth
and we find that in verse number 11,
the Bible says he continued there a year and six months
teaching the word of God among them.
For 18 months, the apostle Paul
is ministering there in Corinth.
During those 18 months, if I understand not only the culture
but if I understand the approach of the apostle Paul
and I understand the way in which he was ministering
to people and really just investing in people
and desiring the growth, he's spending time with them.
You know, ministry requires time.
I said this before on a Father's Day many years ago
that the way that children spell love is T-I-M-E.
You say, well, that's not how I spell love
but that's how kids spell love.
You spend time with them.
By the way, husbands, your wives like it
when you spend time with them.
Say I love you but you never spend time with them.
You're just kind of running all over the place.
No, they want you, your kids, your spouse
and I believe that ministry requires time.
It's an investment, it's time.
You're building those relationships
and for 18 months as the apostle Paul is there
ministering amongst the people in Corinth,
he's pouring his life into them.
He has relationships and in fact, if you read
many of the times when the apostle Paul
would write a letter and he would write about a church,
he would include all kinds of names
at the end of the letters.
He says to the people in Philippi
that I thank my God upon every remembrance of you.
I don't think it was just the Philippians
that Paul had that kind of love for.
I think it was all the people that he ministered.
or two, we see it in 2 Corinthians 11 when he said,
and that which cometh upon me daily,
the care of all the churches.
The Apostle Paul loved.
And what's the evidence of that love?
Well, as we look at the text of scripture,
we find that in verse 12, back in 2 Corinthians 12,
he mentions about the things that were done there
in the ministry, the work.
That's why we went back to Acts 18 to look at that.
But as we continue in verse 13, it says,
for that is it wherein you were inferior to other churches,
except it be that I myself was not burdensome to you.
Forgive me this wrong.
What he's speaking about in verse number 13,
he's brought up before in the text of scripture
to the believers in Corinth is that he,
as we read in Acts 18, he was a tent maker
and he did not allow them to support him.
It wasn't that it would not be right
for them to support him.
It was not right.
It was not a situation that it would be wrong
for the apostle Paul to have received financial support
from them, but he did not take that support from them.
And he says that that was the one area
in which he really did not allow the church
to flourish in that way.
And it's interesting, I've talked to many people.
In fact, I heard just this week of another church
that lost a pastor and it's happening all over the place.
It's absolutely tragic what's happening,
but I've talked to some young men that are starting churches
with support and they have other churches like ours
and others that will support them in their endeavor.
And I try to encourage these young church planners,
let your church understand their responsibility
to compensate you.
It is their biblical responsibility.
And if you rob them of that responsibility,
you're doing a disservice to God.
And it's absolutely imperative that as we study
the scriptures that we understand that,
but that's what Paul's alluding to there in verse 13.
And so now let's speak about the evidence of Paul's love.
Well, number one, it's evidenced by his actions.
It's evidenced by his actions.
Notice in verse 14, it says,
"'Behold, the third time I am ready to come,'
verse 14, "'Behold, the third time I am ready
"'to come to you and I will not be burdensome to you.'"
Notice what he says here, "'For I seek not yours, but you.'"
Have you ever been in a situation where you felt like
somebody just wanted to get to know you
or be your friend so they could get something from you?
We've encountered that in life, have we not?
And the reality is that the apostle Paul,
through his actions, is making it known
to the church at Corinth that he had no desire
to be burdensome to them.
And he says that, "'I seek not yours, but I seek you.'"
What a perspective.
And through his actions, this would be evidenced
in the things that he did.
And in chapter number, in verse number 15,
notice he says this, "'For I will very gladly spend
"'and be spent for you.'"
It goes hand in hand with what he said in verse 14,
"'That I seek not yours, but you.'"
And then he says, "'I will very gladly spend
"'and be spent for you.'"
That's a heart of a minister,
a heart of a true spiritual leader,
someone that says, I love you,
and it's evidenced by the actions.
It's something where Paul is saying,
listen, I want you to understand
that I will very gladly spend and be spent for you,
not so that I can gain anything in return,
but because I love you as Christ loved.
This is the manner in which we, too,
are to love people, love the brethren.
Notice, if you will, in verse 16,
down through verse number 18,
as we continue to see his love evidenced by his actions,
it says, "'But be it so, I did not burden you.
"'Nevertheless, being crafty, I caught you with guile.'"
Again, that was a reference
to what those Judaizers were saying.
They were really attacking Paul when he sent,
and he talked about that love offering
that we studied a few weeks ago,
and how he sent the men and all that he did for that.
Oh, he's just being crafty,
he's just trying to get some gain.
And the apostles are all saying, no, no, no,
my actions are evidenced of my love for you.
In verse 17, "'Did I make a gain of you
"'by any of them whom I sent unto you?'
And then he begins to list.
"'I desired Titus, and with him I sent a brother.
"'Did Titus make a gain of you?
"'Walked we not in the same spirit?
"'Walked we not in the same steps?''
And so you begin to understand,
as the apostle Paul is writing,
and he's talking about, and we find here,
the evidence of his love, it's evidenced by his actions.
He says at the end of verse number 18,
he uses it twice about his walk.
Walked we not in the same spirit?
Walked we not in the same steps?
You know, your actions speak louder than your words.
Words are important.
We're gonna deal with that one next.
Words are important,
but your actions speak far louder than your words.
We find that not only is Paul's love
for the believers here in Corinth
evidenced by his actions,
it is evidenced by his words.
We find here in verse 15, I read the first portion.
"'I will very gladly spend and be spent for you
"'in the previous thought.'"
But now notice the end of the verse.
He says, "'Though the more abundantly I love you,
"'the less I be loved.'
"'The more abundantly I love you, the less I be loved.'
But Paul wasn't loving them
so that he could be loved by them.
Does that make sense?
He wasn't trying to see what he could get out of the deal.
No, he was seeking to be obedient to Christ.
He was seeking to be obedient to God,
and he was walking in the spirit,
and the love of God is shed abroad in our hearts
by the Holy Ghost, and he's loving them.
And he says, "'Though the more abundantly I love,
"'the less I be loved.'"
But understand, though it's not said,
I believe that what Paul is communicating to the church,
and not only through reading and understanding
all that he does,
what Paul is communicating to the church is,
I'm not gonna stop loving you,
because I've been commanded to love you,
and God's spirit enables me to love you.
And he's not coming to this place of saying,
well, I'm not being loved by you,
so I'm gonna stop loving you.
No.
And it's so important that we understand
that Paul was saying, this is the truth that God gave.
This is the commandment that Jesus gave.
He is the example of this.
He is the one that shows, and demonstrates,
and displays for us his love.
And we are to love in the same way.
We're to love as Christ loved.
We see it here in the context of obviously
the love of the brethren, and the spiritual leader
writing to the members of the church,
but understand that as husbands,
you know, we've been commanded.
Husbands, love your wives, even as Christ loved the church
and gave himself for it.
Wow.
What a truth.
What a responsibility that has been given to husbands
to love our wives, as Christ loved the church
and gave himself for it.
I tell Holly that I love her regularly,
I use my words to express to her that I love her regularly,
but you know, there's gotta be some actions
that show her that I love her as well.
And I think she's happy for the words when she hears
when I tell her that I love her,
but she's also thankful for the actions
that show that I love her.
Amen?
And we find here that as Paul is writing to the church,
that we find that he's saying, I love you, church.
I will very gladly spend and be spent for you.
These are the actions of the Apostle Paul.
Though, the more abundantly I love you,
the less I be loved, it's not gonna stop me from loving you.
It's evidenced by his desire.
As we begin to think about the Apostle Paul,
and we read in Acts 18 and verse number 11,
how he continued there for a year and six months,
teaching the word.
And we read in verse number 19,
where the Apostle Paul says this again,
think ye that we excuse ourselves unto you.
Again, he's saying, we're not making an excuse.
And he says this, we speak before God in Christ.
He's used the same language earlier in the book,
and we've developed this.
And we understand that Paul's saying,
listen, I'm telling you the truth.
And then notice the end of verse number 19.
This was what reveals to us his desire
for these believers in Corinth,
and it's an evidence of his love for them.
He says, we do all things,
and then he calls them dearly beloved.
We do all things dearly beloved for your edifying.
To build you up, to edify you.
Listen, the Judaizers, as we spoke before,
as we look through the passage of scripture,
that these false brethren, that these Judaizers,
that they were using their power to control
and to see what they could get.
And the Apostle Paul understood
that he had been given the responsibility to edify.
He says in chapter number 10 in verse number eight,
for though I should boast somewhat more of our authority,
which the Lord hath given us for edification
and not for your destruction, I should not be ashamed.
Paul understood that he'd been called to be an apostle,
and he'd been given a power, and he'd been given authority,
but that power and authority was given to him
for edification, not for destruction.
I wanna build you up.
I want you to be complete.
in Christ. This is the desire that the Apostle Paul has, and it evidences for us
the love that he has for these believers. See, the Apostle Paul was not a hireling.
The Apostle Paul was not a situation that, let me see what I can get out of
this, and then I'll just move on and whatever, and just... Listen, sometimes you
see that kind of behavior in the world, in our society, where people will
use people to get to the place where they want to get, and then they don't
need them anymore. It happens. But Paul says, no. My desire is your edifying. We
do all things, dearly beloved, for your edifying, to build you up. Look over the
book of Colossians, if you will, and look in Colossians chapter 1, and I use the
example in Colossians. We're gonna go to 1 Thessalonians as well, but I want to
use this example in the book of Colossians first, because it really
reveals to us the heart of the Apostle Paul. In the book of 2 Corinthians,
these are people that Paul's writing to that he ministered to for a year and a
half, 18 months. And as he ministered to them, he had a love for them. He began to
develop that concern for them. We do all things for your edifying. But when we
look at the book of Colossians, the Apostle Paul now is writing to a group
of people that he's never met. He's writing to a group of people that he
never ministered personally to them. In fact, the Apostle Paul simply hears
about their faith. He hears from their faithful minister, who is a paphras,
according to verse number 7 of the text of Scripture. He hears about their faith
in Christ, and not only their faith in Christ, but their love for the saints, and
he hears about that, and God's using him to write back to these believers in
Colossae, those that he never ministered to. But I want you to notice in verse
number 28, notice what Paul says in Colossians 1 and verse 28,
whom we preach, warning every man and teaching every man in all wisdom, that we
may present every man perfect in Christ Jesus. You know, Paul's desire was for
souls to be saved, and for those that were saved to be sanctified, to grow in
grace and knowledge of our Lord and Savior Jesus Christ, so that one day when
they stood before Christ, they could be complete in Christ. That's why he
labored. That's why he did what he did, because he loved people. And he
understood that people, that God gave him the sphere of influence over, whether it
was that personal time, like with the Corinthians, or even in this situation
with the believers in Colossae, where he'd simply write a letter to them that
he knew he loved them because they would stand before God one day. I get to preach
here all the time, and I'm so thankful for it. I love preaching. I really do. I love
opening the Bible, teaching God's Word, preaching God's truth. It's just, there's
nothing for me that's more satisfying. I absolutely love being able to teach the
Bible, and I love being able to do it here amongst those that I've had the
opportunity to minister to for now 14 and almost a half years. And some of you
have been here from the very first, when I first got here. Some of you have been
here for various parts of time with regard to how long I've had, but we've
built a relationship, and there's love. But on Tuesday night, I preached to a
group of people that I never met before. There were a handful of people in that
room that I knew. Last night, I preached at a men's meeting, and when I preached
at that men's meeting, there were a handful of people that I knew, but there
were a whole lot of people that I didn't know. I never met before. But I preach
messages on Tuesday night and on Saturday night to those groups of people
that were assembled because I understand they're going to stand before God one
day, and I wanted to help them with God's Word. Why? Because we love people. We go
and knock on doors because I think they're gonna invite us in and welcome
us and let us sit in their living room and just be so happy that we're there.
No, we love people. We want to see people trust Christ as their Savior. I
believe he's in heaven now, but many of you would remember the man, Chris, that
came here for years and would argue with just about anybody that would talk with
him. One day, he bowed his heart and he bowed his knee, and he trusted Christ as
his Savior. But before that ever happened, he looked at me, and with as much
sincerity as he could possibly have, he said, why do you care? Why do you care so
much? And here's what he told me. I don't care that I'm gonna die and go to hell.
Why do you? He told me that on more than one occasion. He got mad at Holly and said,
don't pray for me anymore. Holly, she said, I'm gonna keep praying for you.
Love people. It's not so that we can get anything in return. It's because Jesus
said that we're to love as he loved. To love as he loved. Notice in the book of 1 Thessalonians,
we'll finish with this. In 1 Thessalonians chapter number 4, Paul is writing to a
church that is a good church. The church in Thessalonica, really we could say it's a model
church. There's no perfect church, and if you think you're gonna find a perfect church,
you'll mess it up because you're not perfect, amen? And none of us are perfect, but we serve
a perfect Savior, and we have a perfect book, and I'm thankful for those truths. But the
church in Thessalonica is a model church, and the apostle Paul is writing, and he's speaking
to them, and he's talking to them about this subject of love, and he says this in verse
number 9. He says, but as touching brotherly love, you need not that I write unto you,
for ye yourselves are taught of God to love one another. It's true. God gave us the commandment
to love one another, and Jesus expanded upon that in John 13, as I have loved. He says in
verse number 10, and indeed, indeed, ye do it toward all the brethren which are in all
Macedonia. Isn't that a wonderful assessment of the love that this church had? You're loving
like Christ loved, and you have this love, this brotherly love, ye do it toward all the
brethren which are in all Macedonia, and then notice the end of verse number 10, but we
beseech you. That word beseech is interesting. It's used in a variety of contexts. Oftentimes,
we refer to it in Romans chapter 12, I beseech you therefore, brethren, by the mercies of
God that you present your bodies a living sacrifice, and we look at that, and we understand
that. He's begging, he's pleading with them, and he says, but we beseech you, brethren,
that ye increase more and more. See, when we look at the passage of Scripture in 2 Corinthians
chapter number 12, we know that the believers in Corinth weren't really helping Paul out
a whole lot. They were criticizing him. They were believing the Judaizers. He says that
I ought to have been commended of you, but instead he's being criticized and critiqued,
and they're calling him to, compelled him to give really his credentials, if you will.
We find that the Apostle Paul says, as he's writing to this church, and he says, the more
abundantly I love you, the less I be loved, but his love is demonstrated for us. The evidence
is here, and he loved them through his actions, through his words, through his desires, and
the Apostle Paul was going to continue to love them because he had been commanded to
do so, and because he was walking in the Spirit, and the first fruit of the Spirit that's mentioned,
or the first element, is love. It's the Holy Ghost that enables you and enables me to love
as Christ loved. And really, as we examine a portion of Scripture like this, we must
ask ourselves this question, how are we doing in the area of love? How are we doing in the
area of love? You know, there are churches that have schisms and divisions and all sorts
of things. The church in Corinth, right, a divided church. It's not what God's plan is,
because God says, by this, by your love one for another shall all men know that you're
my disciples. I'm so thankful on a regular basis I hear people say when they visit our
church, your church is different. It's like you really love each other, and that's encouraging
to me when I hear that. And I believe that it's a good evaluation and assessment of our
church. I do believe that we do love one another. We are a family. But could I use the words
that Paul used in 2 Thessalonians 4 and verse 10? I beseech you to increase more and more.
Don't just get stagnant or comfortable and say, okay, we, no, we just want to love people.
As we see the, and we've had, I've been here for 14 and a half years, the ebbs and flows,
the dynamic of living in Northern Virginia, and people come and people go, and the moving
and all the transient.
and nature of the living here,
and we see times in which there's more people leaving
than there are coming, and so on and so forth,
and we've been through that many cycles already.
I was sharing with someone just recently
that we've had 67 family units join the church
since I've been pastoring,
and of those 67 family units that have joined the church,
53 of them have moved away.
It's crazy.
It's just ministry in Northern Virginia.
When we get new people in, we need to love.
We need to love.
I beseech you that we increase more and more,
because by this, by your love one for another,
shall all men know that you're my disciples,
and anyone that comes into our church,
anyone that has an interaction with someone from our church,
they ought to know they love God, and they love people.
They love people, and Paul,
his love for the Corinthians is evidenced
there in that text of Scripture
in 2 Corinthians chapter 12,
and I'm thankful for the example of the Lord Jesus Christ,
but I'm thankful for the example of those
that have gone before us that are humans,
that are of the same flesh that we are,
that have the same difficulties that we do,
and yet the Apostle Paul,
he said, I'll gladly spend and be spent for you.
I love you, and I'm so thankful for that example.
Let's pray.
Father, we love you this morning.
We thank you for loving us.
I thank you for the brothers and sisters in Christ.
I thank you for those that are gathered today,
and I thank you, God, for the truth of your word,
and I pray that you would help us to love as Christ loved.
We understand that we cannot do it in our own power.
It's absolutely impossible,
but God, we understand that you'll enable us,
just as you enabled the Apostle Paul,
you would enable us to love,
because the Holy Ghost who's been given to us
will shed abroad the love of God in our hearts,
and God, I pray that you would help us
to have that testimony of being a church
that loves God, yes, but also loves people.
I pray, Father, that you would use us.
I pray that if there's one here that's not sure of heaven,
yes, I desire that they would understand that we love them
and we want them to be saved,
but more importantly than that and greater than that,
I pray they'd understand how much you love them.
They'd bow their heart and bow their knee
and trust Christ as their Savior today.
Father, maybe some have had difficulties in this area,
crucifying the flesh and truly loving as Christ loved.
I pray, Lord, that you'd help us in the moment of invitation,
help us, Lord, to be doers of the word and not hearers only.
Well, thank you for the work that you'll do,
for it's in Christ's name we pray.
Would you stand with me?
Heads are bowed, eyes are closed.
If you're not sure of heaven, we'll take a Bible
and show you how you can know for sure
that heaven's your home.
Maybe you wanna come and thank God for his love.
Maybe you wanna come and thank God
for being a part of a church that loves one another.
Maybe you say, God, help me in this area to love
as Christ loved.
As Kimberly plays, the altar is open.