But I want you to start in 1 Timothy, chapter number two, if you will, 1 Timothy, chapter
number two.
And of course, we're preaching through the book of 1 and 2 Timothy this year with regard
to our theme.
And this morning we'll be in the Gospel of Luke as we continue with this subject matter
of prayer.
But let me remind you in 1 Timothy, chapter number two, beginning in verse number one,
notice the Bible says, I exhort therefore, notice that first of all, supplications, prayers,
intercessions, and giving of thanks be made for all men.
You might remember the memory verse from the month of February, verse number eight, I will
therefore that men pray everywhere, lifting up holy hands without wrath and doubting.
And we've dealt with the subject of prayer for a number of weeks now.
We dealt with structure in our prayer lives and how important it is to have that structure,
to have a place and a time.
And we dealt with the fact that we're to pray for leaders.
And I hope that you've been praying for our leaders and they need prayer and we've been
commanded to do so.
And God says that it pleases Him when we do that.
We find that we dealt with the idea of effectual prayer and how can our prayer life, how can
our prayers be effective?
He says that we're to lift up holy hands, the necessity of being clean and how sin will
hinder our prayer lives.
Sin will hinder your prayer life.
The fact that we must be controlled by the spirit of God, the fact that we must understand
that we pray in confidence, that God hears us and that God answers and He is able.
And what a blessing that is.
And we looked last week at a praying church, the church, the first century church, the
church in the book of Acts.
We find that every time as you look through their history and as God was using them in
the first century, you read repeatedly that they prayed, they were praying, they, they
met for prayer and what a blessing to consider the response to many situations that the early
church faced was a response of prayer.
And we mentioned last week specifically there in Acts chapter number 12 dealing with the
church as they were praying for Peter with the instruction that he soon, or the understanding
that he soon would be put to death and how God answered prayer and miraculously delivered.
On Wednesday evening, if you were here, I know we have student ministries, some in other
places of the building, but we dealt with the subject from first Thessalonians five
in verse 17, pray without ceasing.
And what a blessing to understand from that verse of scripture that we have access to
the throne of grace at any time for any reason.
And what a blessing that is, our God is able and it should have an influence on our attitude
towards prayer.
This morning as we continue with the thought of prayer from first Thessalonians chapter
two, we make our way to Luke chapter number 11.
In Luke chapter number 11, God gives us the record of one disciple making a special request.
The Bible tells us in verse number one that this one disciple, because it says one of
his disciples, said unto him this special request.
What was it?
It was this, Lord, teach us to pray.
I often think about those words and I think about the way in which the disciples could
have, any one of the disciples could have asked the Lord Jesus Christ to teach them
a multitude of things.
But we find recorded for us in the pages of scripture is the disciple going to Jesus,
going to God in the flesh and saying, Lord, teach us to pray.
The next few verses of scripture, we find that the Lord Jesus Christ teaches on the
subject matter of prayer.
I would say this, that Jesus provides for us in this text of scripture a model or a
pattern for prayer.
He says, by the way, when you pray, not if you pray, the expectation is that we as God's
people will be engaged in prayer.
And we find that he provides us with this pattern, this framework, if you will, for
prayer.
This is not the Lord's prayer, although it's often referred to as being the Lord's prayer.
It's a model prayer.
The Lord's prayer, I believe you can read in John chapter 17, and what a great prayer
that is.
But we find here this model framework, if you will, the pattern.
By the way, it's not a prayer that we should just repeat.
It's not a repetitive idea that we memorize the pattern that he establishes here and we
just pray that.
No, he's just simply providing us with a pattern.
Notice with me in verse number two, and he, Jesus, said unto them, the disciples are there,
and we find that one, according to verse number one, says, Lord, teach us to pray, as John
also taught his disciples, and he, Jesus, said unto them, when ye pray, say, Our Father
which art in heaven, hallowed be thy name.
By the way, we ought to recognize who we're praying to.
The God of the universe.
But not only the God of the universe, our Father.
See prayer is a privilege for the children of God, the people of God, those that have
been saved by the grace of God, that know that they're going to heaven to be with God
for all of eternity.
And he says, when you pray, say, Our Father which art in heaven, hallowed be thy name.
He's holy.
We must never forget that our God is holy.
Notice the Bible says, Thy kingdom come, thy will be done, as in heaven, so in earth.
Give us day by day our daily bread, and forgive us our sins, for we also forgive everyone
that is indebted to us, and lead us not into temptation, but deliver us from evil.
In verse number two, there are, tucked within the instruction that I've just read in verses
two through four, there are four words that I want to draw our attention to this morning.
These four words, I believe, are critical for us to understand.
In fact, these four words, I believe, will have a major impact on your prayer life and
on my prayer life.
Those four words, if you've already looked at the back of the bulletin, serve as our
title for the message this morning, Thy will be done.
Thy will be done.
Let me ask you this morning, how strong is your will?
How strong is your will?
You know, for some, we have a stronger will than others.
We, if you are a parent, you have had the privilege of raising children.
You know at times that some children have a stronger will than other children.
Maybe you were the child that your parents said you have a strong will.
We understand that terminology.
But I wonder this morning, if you were to evaluate your own life, how strong is your
will?
And as a follow-up to that question, let me ask this question.
How much influence does your will and my will have on our prayer lives?
I think if we're not careful, sometimes our prayer lives can be influenced more by our
wills than by His will.
And this morning as we look at this text of Scripture, and again, we've looked at a variety
of aspects of prayer over the last several weeks, and I very quickly, through introduction
this morning, gave you kind of a summary and overview of each of the last messages that
I preached on the subject of prayer.
But we find this morning that these four words, I mean they're simple words, thy will be done.
But each of us have a will.
Each of us have a will.
We believe this morning that as we understand our will, and you know how strong your will
is, and you know how submissive you are to the will of God, but if we're not careful,
our will influences our prayer lives more than God's will influences our prayer lives.
How can we, how can you, how can I this morning, how can we truly say, not my will, but thine?
But thine be done.
Because we all have a will, we all have a desire, and this morning we find it tucked
within these verses of Scripture, the instruction, thy will be done.
As we examine this truth and these four words this morning, this might be one of the most
critical aspects of prayer that I've dealt with in the last several weeks.
Thy will be done.
How do we determine God's will?
Well, God's will is revealed to us in His Word.
We must be students of the Word.
We're to pray according to His will, according to the truth that we receive in 1 John 5,
14, and 15.
We find that as even looking at the text of Scripture in 1 Timothy 2, verses 1 through
8, tucked, I preached a message on it, God's will for humanity, because tucked within the
instruction of prayer in 1 Timothy 2 is really a parenthetical statement that God gives us
and reveals to us what His will is for mankind.
How is it that I can align my will with God's will?
Because that's really what it boils down to, is how is it that we can align our will with
God's will?
Take your Bible quickly, if you will.
Turn to the book of Psalm, Psalm 37.
I believe in Psalm 37, God gives us some really nuggets of truth, some indicators, if you
will, for how we, as God's people, can align our will.
with His will, because Jesus, in responding to the request of the disciple,
Lord, teach us to pray, gave this framework, this pattern for prayer,
and within the framework, He says,
Thy will be done.
In Psalm chapter 37, the Bible says this in verse number 3.
I'm going to look at verses 3 through 7.
Notice what the Bible says.
Trust in the Lord and do good.
So shalt thou dwell in the land, and verily thou shalt be fed.
Delight thyself also in the Lord, and He shall give thee the desires of thine heart.
How many times have you heard verse 4 taken completely out of context?
God said He'll give us the desires of our heart.
Read the whole verse. Amen?
Verse 5, notice, commit thy way unto the Lord.
Trust also in Him, and He shall bring it to pass.
And He shall bring forth thy righteousness as the light,
and thy judgment as the noonday.
Rest in the Lord, and wait patiently for Him.
Fret not thyself because of Him, who prospereth in His way
because of the man who bringeth wicked devices to pass.
There are four nuggets of truth within these verses of Scripture that God gives us
that I believe will help us, they will aid us
in having our will aligned with God's will.
And notice with me in verses 3 and also in verse number 5,
the Bible says, trust in the Lord.
Trust in the Lord.
It says in verse number 5, trust also in Him.
You know, it's important that we trust Him.
The Bible says, trust in the Lord with all thine heart.
Not part of it, not most of it, but with all of it.
We find that we sing the song, trust and obey,
and there's no other way to be happy in Jesus but to trust and obey.
Trusting Jesus, simply trusting.
I'm so glad I learned to trust Him, the songwriter said.
And indeed, our God is trustworthy.
And He says to His people that we're to trust in the Lord.
Notice verse number 4, the instruction, the nugget of truth given to us,
delight thyself also in the Lord.
On the front of our bulletins for today,
if you looked at it, is Psalm 1611.
And thy presence is fullness of joy.
And what a blessing to enter into the presence of God,
to understand the joy that God gives as we enter into His presence.
But we delight thyself also in the Lord.
And as we delight ourselves in the Lord, notice it says,
and He shall give thee the desires of thine heart.
I believe this morning as we look at this truth,
and we actually see it in Psalm 21 and verse number 2,
thou hast given him his heart's desire,
and hast not withholding the request of his lips.
I believe that as we delight ourselves in the Lord,
that our desires are really God's desires.
So what happens is God's desires become our desires.
I wonder this morning, before you got saved,
were there certain desires or ambitions that you had,
somebody said to you when you were a teenager,
if you were not saved at that point in your life,
they said, hey, what do you want to do with your life?
I mean, what are you going to do?
And we have our desires, our ambitions,
our ideas of what we're going to do.
And then we understand that as we look at the truth of God's word,
that we are His children.
And if we delight ourselves in the Lord,
His desires really become our desires.
The more time you spend with the Lord,
the more that you're in His presence,
the more that you're trusting Him,
the more that His will and His desire
becomes your will and your desire.
It's found in His word,
how much time we must spend in God's word every day of our lives.
Notice with me in verse number 5,
commit thy way unto the Lord.
And then we see again, trust also in Him.
So we are told to trust in the Lord.
We're told to delight thyself also in the Lord.
We're told to commit thy way unto the Lord, trusting Him.
Listen, because we know who He is,
then we can commit our way unto Him.
And then we find in verse number 7,
notice these words, rest in the Lord.
Rest in the Lord.
You know, when we look at the truth that God gives us here in Psalm 37
in verses 3 through 7,
these four nuggets of truth as we seek to answer the question,
how can I align my will with God's will?
We find that it's necessary that we're in His presence,
that we're trusting Him, that we're delighting in Him,
that we're committing our way unto Him,
that we're resting in Him.
This morning as we think about the subject of prayer
and looking at these four words,
thy will be done,
two thoughts for you this morning.
When we pray thy will be done,
number one, we recognize that His will or His way is superior.
When we pray, thy will be done.
Now understand, that's not just a cliche that we add to the end of a prayer.
And when you read James 4,
and the Bible says that we ought to say,
if the Lord is willing,
that's not just a cliche that we say.
Now sometimes we'll say, hey, Lord willing, we'll see you,
and we might use that,
and it can become cliche-ish.
But you understand, it's not to be a cliche.
It is the Lord's will.
We desire to know the Lord's will.
We understand this morning we are gathered here
because it's God's will.
God says not forsaking the assembling of ourselves together
as the manner of some is,
but exhorting one another,
and so much the more as you see the day approaching.
We are gathered together because it's God's will.
I am preaching the word this morning
because it's God's will.
He said preach the word,
be instant in season, out of season,
reprove, rebuke, exhort,
with all longsuffering and doctrine.
He says, yes, the time will come.
I think we're there,
that men will not endorse sound doctrine.
Nevertheless, we are to continue,
and we are to preach the word.
We do this at God's will.
And when we delight ourselves in the Lord,
when we're trusting Him,
and committing our way to Him,
and we're resting in Him,
God's will becomes our will.
I hope no one had to drag you to church this morning.
Honestly.
I know sometimes you might think about that
with little kids or something,
but I hope this morning,
listen, when I wake up on Sunday,
man, I am so excited
about the opportunity that God gives us
to gather as the people of God
on the Lord's day to celebrate the resurrection
because every Sunday that we meet
is because we serve a risen Savior,
and we get to be in church.
And you say, well, you're the pastor.
Listen, after I got saved,
I wanted to be with God's people.
You know how many times I wanted to go to church
before I got saved?
Zero.
Honestly.
I remember my dad coming home from work,
and he said, we're going to go to church on Sunday.
I said, we're doing what?
I was almost 13 years old.
I was a teenager.
I had other things that I did on Sunday.
I'm just being honest.
And dad said, we're going to church.
We're doing what?
And then my dad got saved,
and we're going to church for Sunday school
and Sunday morning and Sunday evening
and Wednesday night and Saturday bus visitation,
and he's all in.
My dad never went to church,
but he got saved by the grace of God.
He's in church.
I remember before I got saved,
I didn't want to be in church,
but some of you can testify.
Mickey was testifying this morning in Sunday school.
You know what happens when you can't be in church?
Man, you miss it.
Why? Because I want to be with the people of God.
With the people of God.
And so we're gathered because it's God's will,
but we understand this morning
that when we pray, thy will be done,
when we pray that way,
we're recognizing that His will,
that His way is superior.
You might think that your will is best.
You might think that your way is best.
I mean, this is the best thing ever,
but I guarantee you this morning
that God's way is best.
God's will, thy will, be done.
He is eternal.
He is sovereign.
He is in control of all things.
He alone has all power.
He alone has all wisdom.
Amen?
Wisdom didn't begin with you.
It doesn't end with you.
Hallelujah.
Our God is the all-wise God.
And we find here that the God
who alone has all power and all wisdom,
that He is our God.
He is our Father.
He is holy.
And when we look at the instruction
that Jesus gives,
He says, thy will be done.
Why does He say that to the disciples?
Why are these four words
tucked within the instruction?
Because it's so important for God's people,
for the children of God to understand
that God's will is best,
to recognize that,
that God's way is best.
And we must pray thy will be done.
God always has a plan.
Always.
Nothing ever surprises God.
You ever been in a situation
where you were surprised by something?
Maybe you said something like this.
I didn't see this coming.
I didn't plan for this.
But I can guarantee you this morning
that that's never happened to God.
The start of human history
when sin entered into the world.
When Satan tempted in the garden Eve
and she partook of the fruit,
also ate likewise."
That was not a surprise to God.
For God tells us in His Word that Jesus is the Lamb of God slain before the foundation
of the world.
Provision had already been made.
He already understood because nothing surprises God.
Thy will be done.
Again, I asked you in the beginning of the message this morning, how strong is your will?
I asked you in the beginning of the message this morning, how much does your will influence
your prayer life?
How much of our will are we praying versus God's will are we praying?
It requires that we do some examination of our prayer lives.
Thy will be done.
Notice with me, God's way is perfect.
Have you ever met anyone that they thought their way was perfect?
I mean, you can't do it any better.
You have to do it their way because it is the only way to do something.
I can tell you this morning that God's way is perfect.
That's what the Bible tells us.
Turn to the book of 2 Samuel, if you will.
And this is important for us to understand as we go through this understanding of this
critical instruction, these four simple words, thy will be done.
In 2 Samuel chapter 22 and verse number 31, we find this is the song of David.
And I want you to see what David says.
Now, David had some great triumphs during his life.
Would you agree this morning?
I mean, David had some great triumphs during his life.
I mean, some amazing things happened during the life of David.
But David also dealt with some great opposition.
I'm not simply talking about the opposition and the difficulty that David endured after
the sin with Bathsheba.
I'm talking about difficulties that he had just as he was seeking to do the will of God.
Just as he was seeking to follow the Lord.
He didn't ask to be anointed to be the next king of Israel.
Amen?
God chose him to be the next king of Israel.
He simply was ministering to Saul and Saul wanted to kill him.
Saul made it his number one agenda.
Most important thing, kill David.
God spared him.
We can read on a number of occasions how David was miraculously spared by God and how David
testified even while he's on the run that there's but a step between me and death.
But yet God preserved his life and God did bring him to the place of being king.
And I want you to see what David says near the end of his life in 2 Samuel 22 and verse
number 31, as for God, his way is perfect.
His way is perfect.
You say, well, what about that his way is perfect?
I didn't see this coming.
I didn't plan for this.
That's not what I...
His way is perfect.
Why?
Because he has a purpose.
He has a plan.
And his way is perfect.
And we find that in his plan and in his purpose and understanding this morning that his way
is perfect, we understand that he has a purpose ultimately, primarily, his purpose is to bring
honor and glory to himself.
Ultimately that's the purpose, the plan.
How is he going to do that?
A variety of ways.
But we find this morning that as we look at David and he gives this testimony, his way
is perfect.
Notice the word of the Lord is tried.
He is a buckler to all them that trust in him, a shield.
Do you remember Psalm 37 twice in those verses of Scripture, trust in the Lord.
And we find here this morning that when we understand thy will be done, we are recognizing
when we pray that way, when our prayer life is influenced and impacted by this phrase,
we are recognizing that his way, his will is best.
It's best.
You say, well, it might not be what I've chosen.
You don't know what God's going to do.
You don't know how God is going to work.
The book of Philippians in the first chapter, Paul says to the believers in Philippi, I
want you to understand something.
What I want you to understand is that the things that have happened to me have happened
for the furtherance of the gospel.
Praise God.
In chapter number four, he speaks about those of Caesar's household that send their greetings.
No doubt they heard the gospel because Paul was imprisoned.
You say, well, I don't want to be in prison.
You can read of many countless that have gone on before us that have suffered.
They faced persecution and difficulty and we find that in so doing, God was glorified.
Souls were saved and lives were changed because of their submission to God's plan and God's
will.
See, God's way is perfect.
You might think that your way is perfect, but you're mistaken.
Our way is not perfect.
God's way is perfect.
I think this morning about some very new situation, really kind of, you know, overwhelming if
you will for the Scholl family, but I think about having communication with Brother Scholl
this week and understanding that his wife has been diagnosed with cancer and they're
in Greenland and they can't get medical treatment.
What do they do?
And they're believing that God can heal her, but they're praying that God's will would
be accomplished.
You know, it's really exciting when I read the correspondence and had the opportunity
to have some conversation via text and email with the family, understanding that they said
this.
They said, you know, there's some people that we've been ministering to for a long time
in Greenland.
You know what they're doing?
They're watching us right now.
You know what they want to know?
They want to know if our God's real.
They want to know that if the God that we tell them they should trust in, if we're going
to trust in Him in our moment of crisis.
Have you ever considered that this morning?
We tell people that God is trustworthy.
I referenced last week on Wednesday evening when we dealt with that subject of prayer
and developing our attitude towards prayer, and we looked at a text of Scripture in Ezra
chapter number 8 where Ezra was ashamed to ask for a group of soldiers to come and to
help them along the way against the enemy.
Why?
Because we've already told the king that our God is great, that our God is able.
So then I'm not going to go to the king and say, by the way, can we have some soldiers
and some army, some folks to help us along the way?
No, we're trusting our God is going to protect us.
And guess what happened in Ezra?
They made it to Jerusalem.
They said there's going to be some people that are going to be watching us.
You know there are people watching you today.
You say, why are we dealing with this, whatever it is, health issue, financial issue, a hardship
with a family situation, whatever it is, God's way.
We must align our will with God's will.
We must seek God's face.
We must know.
And when we pray, we pray, thy will be done.
You know how the Shoals are praying?
They're praying that some of those people they've been trying to reach for years will
be saved.
Some have already said, we're going to be in church.
Now they're not even there right now.
They're going to come to church.
That's exciting.
Is it okay in your life?
Is it okay in my life if we allow God to have His way?
You understand what I mean?
I understand that we don't want hardships.
I'm the last person on the face of the earth that wants a difficulty, honestly.
I like it when things go easy, Brother Armando.
I really do.
But sometimes in the midst of those hardships, God's proving Himself and God's developing
His children and God's allowing for His glory to be known to those that are watching.
If thy strength fail in the day of adversity, if thy faith fail in the day of adversity,
thy strength is small.
See this morning, we understand that His way is perfect.
You can see in Psalm 18, it's the similar passage that we see in 2 Samuel 22, but not
only is His way perfect, but He always does right.
We cannot say of ourselves that we always do the right thing.
In fact, there are many times that we mess things up.
Many of our difficulties are the result of our own doing.
We just mess things up.
But the Bible tells us that God always does what's right.
Notice in Genesis 18 and verse 25, in Genesis 18 and verse 25, the Bible tells us in this
text of Scripture a great truth.
Notice what the Bible says in Genesis 18 and verse 25, that be far from thee to do after
this manner to slay the righteous with the wicked, and that the righteous should be as
the wicked, that be far from thee.
But then notice at the end of the verse, shall not the judge of all the earth do right?
Understand that He is the judge of all the earth, and understand that He is righteous.
His way is perfect.
He always does what is right.
It may not be exactly what you desired or you thought was going to be the situation,
but as we align ourselves, we commit ourselves, we delight ourselves in the Lord,
commit our way unto Him, and we allow our wills to be influenced by His will,
and our will becomes His will, then we find that we can pray this way,
Thy will be done.
Not simply a cliche, but sincerely, why?
Because we're recognizing that His will is superior.
His will is superior. His will is best.
And I hope you believe that this morning.
I hope this morning, listen, the more time you spend with God,
the more you'll understand it to be the case.
The more time you learn about how sovereign our God is and how powerful our God is
and how He moves and how He works, the more you'll be able to say,
Thy will be done.
Notice with me, not only when we pray, Thy will be done,
does it recognize that His will is superior,
but number two, I believe this, it reveals the submission of God's people.
You know, we as the people of God, we are to submit to God.
That's what the Bible says in the book of James, if you will.
And turn over to the book of James, and I want you to see what God tells us.
In James chapter number 4,
when we talk about will, we think about submission.
How strong is your will?
I don't know if you ever had, I remember as a kid having an uncle
that wanted to wrestle around.
You know what he was trying to do? He was trying to make me submit.
And there were times that he would say something like this to him,
Say uncle.
Anyone ever been in that situation?
Any of you struggle to say uncle?
You don't want to surrender. You don't want to submit.
I remember trying with all of my might and all of my strength,
and yet he's several years older than I am, much bigger and stronger than I was at that point as a little child.
And he could do with me whatever he wanted to do.
And he was trying to get me to submit.
Sometimes it's hard to submit.
Because you have a will. And I have a will.
But when we pray thy will be done, not only are we recognizing that God's will is superior,
but it reveals the submission in our lives to God's will.
See, notice in James 4, in verse number 7, notice what the Bible says.
Submit yourselves therefore to God.
Submit yourselves to God.
We see that the Bible continues.
Resist the devil and he will flee from you.
Draw nigh to God and he will draw nigh to you.
Cleanse your hands, ye sinners, and purify your hearts, ye double-minded.
In what great truth, in verse 9, be afflicted and mourn and weep.
Let your laughter be turned to mourning and your joy to heaviness.
Humble yourselves in the sight of the Lord and he shall lift you up.
You know what is required for submission?
Humility.
Without humility, you're never going to submit.
You're just not.
But why should we humble ourselves?
Well, we find that God instructs us to.
He says that we're to humble ourselves.
He says that God resisteth the proud, but he gives grace unto the humble.
He says that we're to humble ourselves and that we're to be clothed with humility.
We can read of that as Peter writes in 1 Peter chapter 5.
And by the way, pride.
We said that it requires humility.
Pride is a major issue in many people's lives.
It's my life.
Have you ever heard anyone say that?
I'm going to do what I want to do.
Well, there's a problem if you're a Christian because 1 Corinthians 6, 19 and 20 says, what?
Know ye not that your body is the temple of the Holy Ghost which is in you, which you have of God?
And you're not your own, for you're bought with a price.
Therefore, glorify God in your body and your soul, which are his.
See, I'm no longer my own.
I've been bought.
You've been bought.
With the precious blood of Christ.
And therefore, it requires that we have humility in our lives
and that that humility leads to submission.
And when we pray, thy will be done,
what's being evidenced, what's being revealed through that prayer
is that we are submitted to God.
We're not in rebellion to God.
You can read of examples in the Scriptures of those that are in rebellion to God.
By the way, it never works out well for them.
Amen?
It never works out well for those that are in rebellion to God.
Why? Because God's will is going to come to pass.
This morning, we recognize, we can speak of the dangers of pride.
We can discuss the importance of humility.
But I wonder this morning as we examine our prayer lives
and think about these four simple words, thy will be done.
Is that submission evidenced in our prayer lives?
I know I've said this before, but I think it's worth repeating.
The reality is that there are times in which we bring our petitions before the throne of grace
just as we're instructed to do so.
And as we're praying, we're going to decide that we're going to help God understand
how he can answer our prayers.
I've said many times, especially when I worked in the corporate world,
I experienced it on a regular basis.
Those of you that are working in the corporate world probably can identify with this.
Many, many times I would find that there's a lot of problem identifiers in the world.
Amen? A lot of problem identifiers.
But there are a few problem solvers.
There are a lot more problem identifiers than there are problem solvers.
And I determined at a young age when I was working in the corporate world
that I would never take a problem to a superior without also bringing a solution.
Now, it might not be the right solution.
It might not be the one that's incorporated, that's going to be used to fix the problem.
But I did not want to just be a problem identifier.
Can I tell you in my Christian walk, that's a little bit of a hindrance.
Why? Because sometimes I want to help God on how he can answer my prayers.
I'm being transparent with you this morning.
And by the way, I think it's important that each of us would be transparent with God.
Because we need to get a grasp of this simple phrase,
Thy will be done.
And how critical it is in seeing your prayers and my prayers answered.
It recognizes that his way, his will is superior, but it reveals submission.
How submitted are we to God?
How much do we resist God's will?
God has a plan for the ages, by the way.
You understand that. Amen?
Right now, God's plan specifically is with the church.
We're in what would often be referred to as the church age.
You tracking?
God has a plan. God has a will.
You know what God's plan and God's will is for the church age?
That the gospel of the Lord Jesus Christ will be preached to the entire earth.
That's God's plan and God's will.
In a summary statement. Amen?
And God tells us in his word that the gospel...
Paul says, I am not ashamed.
We heard the kids last week on Sunday morning do such a wonderful job of quoting the verse in Romans 1.16.
For I am not ashamed of the gospel of Christ.
Why? For it is the power of God unto salvation to everyone that believeth.
To the Jew first and also to the Greek.
See, because why?
Well, because God's plan for the church age is that all people will be saved.
That we proclaim the gospel to all the world.
Why do we support missionaries?
Why do we send an offering so that Brother Cottle and his wife can go to Africa to go on a missions trip this summer?
Because we are given the task in this era to preach the gospel to every creature.
God has a plan.
The church age is going to end one day.
The trumpet of the Lord shall sound.
Aren't you looking forward to that?
The dead in Christ?
Going to be raised.
Then we which are alive and remain, I hope I'm one of those.
So be caught up to meet the Lord in the air.
So shall we ever be with the Lord. Amen?
Hallelujah. The rapture.
There's going to be a tribulation.
You know what God's doing in the tribulation?
He's dealing with Israel again.
He's dealing with Israel.
Because it's God's plan.
It's God's plan.
You're not going to change God's plan.
It doesn't make any sense to resist God's plan.
Because God's plan is going to come to pass.
And so you can resist it.
And you can show your pride.
Or you can submit to it.
Amen?
You can submit to it.
You say God has a plan.
God's going to bring His people.
into the land again. It's God's plan. It's God's plan. And we can go on and on and look
at God's plan. The problem is that we need to be submissive to God's plan. See, we don't
resist God's plan, we submit to God's plan. And when we say, thy will be done, what is
God's plan? What is God's will in this moment, in this life, in this day? Thy will be done.
Use me, Lord, however you see fit to accomplish your will this day. Submission. Humility.
It's on full display. Surrender. We sang this morning, I'll go where you want me to go.
Do what you want me to do. Say what you want me to say. See, that's a song of surrender,
is it not? A song of submission. And this morning when we look at these four simple
words, thy will be done. You know what a lot of problems have been historically? You can
look through the Old Testament, you can look through human history. You know what a lot
of problems have been the cause of? Man resisting the will of God. Man resisting the will of
God. And it leads to great turmoil. Why? Because you have a strong will. You have a strong
will. And so do I. Therefore, Jesus says, when you pray, yes, there's other pieces of
the framework, but four simple words, thy will be done. I wonder this morning, truly,
I'm not asking you to tell me, I'm asking you to be honest with God. Truly this morning,
how much of our will influences our prayer life? If we examine our prayer life, is it
more of, now God, I know that you're sovereign and you can do all things, and so here's my
list of what I want you to do. Because I want you to do what I want you to do. No, that's
not how it works. Thy will be done. And we come to that place of full surrender and submission,
say God use me, help me to submit to your plan, to your will, and use me to bring glory
to your name. I don't know all that that's going to look like, but can I tell you that
it's going to be best? It's going to be perfect. It's going to be right. It's going to accomplish
what it's caused to accomplish. Because we as God's people recognize that His way, His
will is superior and we must submit. It reveals submission. I hope this morning, as we kind
of conclude this little mini-series that was born out of 1 Timothy chapter 2, the importance
of prayer, that we would recognize these four simple words. And as you pray today and tomorrow
and this week, that you would be regularly aware of how you're praying. Am I praying
thy will be done? Not as just a cliche, but truly, truly God your will is far superior
than my will. God you know things I could never even begin to comprehend. God I'm just
going to submit to you. I'm going to trust you. Thy will be done. Let's pray. Father
we love you. We thank you for loving us. We thank you for your word, the truth contained
therein. God I pray this morning that the Holy Spirit of God would take the word of
God and work in the hearts of your people. If there's one that's not sure of heaven,
we would love to have an opportunity to take a Bible and show them how they can know for
sure that heaven is their home. God I pray that each of us that are saved, God we truly
do some examination this morning of our prayer lives. We all acknowledge that we have a will,
some stronger than others. But the real question this morning is how much influence does our
will have in our prayer lives? How much of our prayer is based on my will and not your
will? How is it that we can truly say not my will, but thine? Lord help us to recognize
that your will is superior. Help us Lord to submit to your will for our lives. Well thank
you for the work that you'll do for it's in Christ's name we pray. Would you stand with
me?