your last name publicly,
but it's certainly good to see you this morning.
We're thankful that you could be here.
And then Juliana and Evan are here this morning as well,
and they're doing well.
Juliana's struggling with some morning sickness,
but that's to be expected.
And it's good to have them.
They'll be traveling back this afternoon
and thankful for the visit
that we've been able to have this weekend.
We'll get to Psalm 12, six and seven,
but after they sang that song,
I thought we should start here in 1 Peter 1.
And verse number 23 says this,
"'Being born again, not of corruptible seed,
but of incorruptible,
by the Word of God which liveth
and abideth forever.
For all flesh is as grass
and all the glory of man
is the flower of grass.
The grass withereth
and the flower thereof falleth away,
but the Word of the Lord
endureth forever.'"
And this is the Word,
which by the Gospel is preached unto you.
This morning, we're gonna look at this subject,
Preservation Reveals the Greatness of God.
Our theme for 2023,
Great is the Lord and Greatly to be Praised.
And our God is great,
and I'm so thankful that He's revealed to us
through the pages of Scripture
that He's a great God.
I'm thankful that the psalmist said this,
I know that the Lord is great.
And I hope this morning that each of us,
as we've entered into this worship service,
that we would agree with the psalmist
and we would say, I know that the Lord is great.
But then the psalmist says this,
and there's no contradiction in what he says,
he says this, that His greatness,
God's greatness is unsearchable
because the reality is as great as you think
that God is today, He's greater.
As great as you think He is tomorrow,
as your understanding of God's greatness
will increase as you walk with God,
He's greater.
He's greater still.
And the psalmist comes to this great declaration
and he says this, I will declare thy greatness.
And that's where each of us need to be in our lives,
that we understand that God is great,
but then we declare His greatness.
We look at the fact that creation reveals
the greatness of God.
I'm so thankful that God said, and it was so.
I'm thankful that the Bible reveals to us
and records for us the origin of man,
the origin of the universe.
And God tells us that He is the creator.
He tells us how He did it.
What a blessing to understand the truth of creation
and then to understand that the creator God is my helper.
I will lift up mine eyes into the hills
from whence cometh my help.
My help cometh from the Lord, which made heaven and earth.
And what a joy to know that the creator God is my helper.
He's your helper.
And we can go to Him understanding that He is able
to do exceeding abundantly above all that we ask or think.
Last week, we looked at the truth of inspiration.
Inspiration reveals the greatness of God.
And what a blessing to understand how God gave us His word.
We said this last week,
that the Bible is the greatest of all books.
The Bible is the best-selling book of all time.
It's the most translated book of all time.
And we are so blessed this morning to have the Bible.
We asked this question and we answered it last week,
and we'll reference it again this morning.
What is it about the Bible that sets it apart
from every other book?
What is it about this book that makes it
the greatest book of all time?
What is it that makes it the best-selling
and most translated book?
We understand this, that God, who alone is great,
is the author of this book.
It is God's word.
It is not man's word.
All scripture is given by inspiration of God.
We dealt with that last week.
And I'm so thankful for the truth of inspiration.
But the reality is that inspiration without preservation
is great for the original recipients.
But there's not one of us that are the original recipients.
So I'm thankful this morning for the truth of preservation.
The word preservation means this,
the providential keeping of the original text
from loss or alteration.
And I'm thankful that as you think about
that definition of preservation,
that we have this morning the word of God.
And we can have confidence in what we hold
in our hands this morning that this is God's word,
that God is the one that has promised
to providentially keep His word.
And we understand this morning,
even as we read this text of scripture
in 1 Peter chapter number one,
that we're born again not of corruptible seed
but of incorruptible.
By the word of God which liveth and abideth forever.
How is it that you were aware of the fact
that you were a sinner in need of a Savior?
How was it that you were aware of the fact
that God is gracious and He's merciful
and He loves you and He died for you
and He was buried and He rose again
and He offers eternal life?
You know those truths because of this book.
And it's been preserved for us this morning.
How do we know?
We sing songs, we're singing this morning
and you begin to think about the future
of the child of God, the hope that we have
and the return of the Lord and the truth of eternity.
How is it, what is it that gives us that hope,
that confidence, it's this book
that's been preserved for us this morning.
I believe that preservation reveals the greatness of God.
I'm thankful that He gave it by inspiration.
God breathed, but I'm thankful that He's preserved it.
I've heard people say this over the years.
Nowhere in the Bible does God say
that He would preserve His word.
The problem is that they're using the wrong Bible.
Turn over to Psalm 12, it's where we were going
to begin this morning before they sang that song.
By the way, it was quite interesting.
I referenced Anywhere With Jesus
in Sunday school this morning and then we're singing it.
And I had a couple of people come to me and say,
did you know we were singing that song?
I had no idea actually.
I don't pick the songs, Dean does,
and we just roll with it.
I saw the list, but I didn't even look up
the songs this week.
And Anywhere With Jesus, the songwriter said in verse five,
I can go to sleep.
And we saw Peter sleeping between those soldiers
this morning in Acts chapter number 12.
But look here in Psalm 12 in verses six and seven.
If you're taking notes this morning,
number one, the promise of preservation.
The Bible says this in verse six,
the words of the Lord are pure words.
We mentioned this last week that they're pure words
because they're God's words.
All scripture is given by inspiration of God.
And because they're God's words, they're pure.
They're without error.
They are trustworthy, they are reliable.
And we can go to the Bible and we can have confidence,
even as the wise man says in Proverbs 30,
the word of the Lord, it's pure.
Every word of God is pure.
We find here that the Bible says that they are pure words.
Why?
Because they're God's words.
And notice he says as silver tried in a furnace of earth,
purified seven times.
Many of us have no idea about metalworking
and we've never done it.
We're not experienced in metalworking.
Obviously there's some people during the time
of this writing that would have understood
the reference here to silver being tried
in a furnace of earth, purified seven times.
For most of us, our only understanding of that
is by looking it up and studying something
about metalworking.
But what I understand, I've never done it personally,
but what I understand through study
is that they would say that the purest silver
you could receive is silver that was tried seven times.
That's how pure this book is.
And notice what he says.
We understand the truth of inspiration,
but when we look at the promise of preservation,
notice in verse number seven,
thou shalt keep them, oh Lord.
Thou shalt, what does it say?
Preserve them from this generation forever.
This promise that we find in Psalm 12 in verse number seven
with regard to the truth of preservation
is a precious promise that we hold dear
and we rejoice in this promise.
And we understand that the Lord himself
has made this promise and let me say this,
God is the only one that could fulfill this promise
because he's the only one that's eternal.
He's the only one that can say,
I will preserve this word, my word,
from this generation forever because he's the eternal God.
No church can make that claim,
no individual can make that claim,
but God Almighty, the one who's the creator,
the one that spoke everything into existence,
the one who's my redeemer
that they sang about this morning,
he gave us a promise that he would preserve his word
and he said from this generation and forever.
I'm thankful that we still fall
within the category of this generation forever, amen?
God is alpha and omega.
He's the first and the last.
He's outside of time, he is the eternal God
and he's given us this promise this morning
and we ought to rejoice that God Almighty
has given us a promise
and he alone is able to fulfill that promise.
See, the reality this morning
is that the promise is only as good as the one who makes it.
A promise is only as good as the one who makes it.
You could promise something all day long,
you could promise your kids,
you could promise some other person
and you can make promises,
but the reality is that God Almighty made this promise
and he.
is able to fulfill it.
I would say this morning that he has fulfilled it.
Forever, O Lord, the psalmist said,
thy word is settled in heaven.
Oh, no doubt, and we'll look at some of this next week,
there have been many that have sought to destroy it.
There have been many that have tried to alter it.
But remember that definition of preservation
is the providential keeping of the original text
from loss or alteration.
It's very interesting that this morning
there's much with regard to the alteration of God's word.
And they seek to change it and what have you,
but we find this morning that God's given us this promise.
Turn to the book of, right here in Psalm, Psalm 119.
Look over at what the psalmist says.
We'll look at two verses.
I've already referenced Psalm 119 in verse 89,
where the Bible says, forever, O Lord,
thy word is settled in heaven.
I wanna draw your attention to Psalm 119, 160.
Psalm 119, and look at verse number 160.
Notice what the Bible says.
The psalmist says, thy word is true from the beginning.
Thy word is true from the beginning.
And then notice, and every one of thy righteous judgments
endureth, how long?
Forever.
So does that mean that this morning in 2023,
can we have confidence in our Bible?
Absolutely.
We can have confidence this morning
that God has fulfilled what he said he would fulfill
and that his word is going to endure forever
because he gave the promise.
And that oughta cause us to rejoice.
Listen, when we think about the truth of preservation,
look over to the New Testament.
Notice this, Christ declared the truth of preservation.
The Lord Jesus Christ, he declared this truth.
Look in the book of Matthew, if you will,
in Matthew chapter number four,
we'll look at the several verses of Scripture
through the Gospels and referencing this morning
that the Lord Jesus Christ declared
the truth of preservation.
Here in Matthew chapter number four,
and we know that this is the passage of Scripture,
the Gospel account in Matthew's Gospel
of the temptation of the Lord.
And the Bible says this in verse number four,
but he answered and said, it is written,
man shall not live by bread alone,
but by every word that proceedeth out of the mouth of God.
The Lord Jesus Christ made this statement here
during his earthly ministry, during this time of temptation
and we find that he's quoting Deuteronomy chapter eight
in verse number three.
He's quoting that book that was written
many, many, many, many centuries prior,
but he's quoting it, why?
Because the word of the Lord endureth forever.
God's word, the truth of preservation.
Notice in Matthew 24,
and notice what the Bible says here
is Jesus is giving answers to those
that have asked questions
and he gives us this great truth with regard,
again, to the truth and the teaching of preservation.
In Matthew chapter 24, in verse number 35,
Matthew 24 in verse 35,
the Lord Jesus Christ said,
heaven and earth shall pass away,
but my words, my words shall not pass away.
Heaven and earth shall pass away,
but my words shall not pass away.
In the gospel of Mark,
Mark records for us in Mark chapter number 12
in verse number 24,
this truth again with regard to preservation.
And it's interesting because in this particular passage
in Mark chapter 12,
I'll give you a moment to turn there
and before I read the verses that I wanna deal with,
we find once again that the Lord Jesus Christ
is being confronted by those that are seeking to attack him
and seeking to trip him up with some teachings
and what have you.
And we find that the ones that are coming to him
in this particular account are the Sadducees.
Now, something interesting about the Sadducees
is that they did not believe in the resurrection.
Some Bible scholars have said that's why they're sad,
you see, because they don't believe in the resurrection.
But the reality is that there were several things
they didn't believe in,
but one of them is the resurrection.
It's quite interesting because they come to Jesus.
Now, understand, they don't believe in the resurrection,
but they say in verse number 18,
which say there's no resurrection,
and they asked him saying,
Master, Moses wrote,
and he goes through this whole situation,
and he says in verse 23,
these false teachers, these Sadducees,
they say in the resurrection, therefore,
when they shall rise,
whose wife shall she be of them?
For the seven had heard a wife.
They didn't believe in the resurrection,
but they're trying to catch Jesus in something,
and they're trying to trip him up.
They didn't believe in the resurrection,
but yet they say in the resurrection, therefore,
but notice the answer that Jesus gives.
In verse number 24, Jesus said this,
do ye not therefore err?
Why?
Because you know not the scriptures.
What's he referring to?
He's referring to the Old Testament,
to the writings of Moses in which they're referring to,
and he says you err, why?
Because you do not know the scriptures.
Notice where he says this,
neither the power of God.
I believe this morning
that there's certainly an understanding
with regard to the truth of preservation
and the promise of preservation of God's power.
No, I believe that God has the power.
He has the ability to preserve his word.
I ask this question of people
that don't believe in preservation.
They don't believe that God has preserved
as he said that he would.
You believe that he's gonna take you to heaven one day,
but you don't believe that he can preserve his word.
That's questionable.
God promised to preserve his word.
The Lord Jesus Christ, during his earthly ministry,
he declared, he referenced the truth of preservation.
The apostles, they taught the truth of preservation.
We've read already there in 1 Peter 1,
it's where we started this morning,
and we read where Peter,
he talks about the preservation of scripture.
He says in just a couple of verses,
he talks about how it abideth forever.
He says in verse 25 of 1 Peter 1,
but the word of the Lord endureth forever.
He gives the truth in verse number 24,
for all flesh is as grass,
and all the glory of man is the flower of grass.
The grass withereth, and the flower thereof felleth away.
Listen, we see that in life.
We understand that.
Things come and things go,
but we understand this morning that Peter's saying,
but listen, that's not like the Bible.
That's not like the word of God,
because the word of God endureth forever.
I'm so thankful for that.
We read last week about the truth of inspiration,
and Paul made the claim there
under the inspiration of the Holy Spirit of God
in 2 Timothy 3,
that all scripture is given by inspiration of God
and is profitable,
but before he said that,
he said to Timothy in verse number 15,
that thou, you've learned these things,
and that from a child thou hast known the holy scriptures,
which are able to make thee wise unto salvation.
What are these holy scriptures that he's referring to?
Again, the Old Testament.
So what are they teaching?
They're teaching this truth of preservation,
that God's word has been preserved.
It's interesting to me,
in 2 Timothy chapter four,
turn there, if you will,
in 2 Timothy chapter number four,
Paul is, of course, near the end of his life,
and he's given that great declaration
that he's ready to be offered,
and we're familiar with verses six through eight.
We often reference those,
and Paul coming to the end of his life with no regrets,
understanding that he's finished his course,
he's kept the faith,
and what a joy and what a blessing
to be able to finish in that matter.
But I want you to notice,
as he closes out the text of scripture
in this book to Timothy,
he gives some parting comments
beginning in verse number nine.
I want to draw your attention
specifically to verse number 13
as it's applicable to our message this morning.
He says this,
the cloak that I left at Troas with Carpus,
when thou comest, bring with thee,
end the books,
but then notice what he says,
but especially the parchments.
Do you know what he's referring to
when he says especially the parchments?
He's talking about the Old Testament scriptures,
and he understands the truth of preservation.
He understands the power of the word of God,
and he says, listen,
there's some things that I want you to bring,
and he talks about a cloak,
and he talks about the books
that he references there in verse number 13,
but I love how he uses the phraseology
when he says, but especially the parchments.
Listen, if you forget the cloak,
if you don't have room for the other books,
don't worry,
just make sure you bring the parchments.
I understand that there's a story
about a missionary in Africa
years and years and years ago,
decades ago,
and he was going,
and he's going into the jungle,
into the bush,
and it was a very difficult trail,
and it was a difficult journey,
and all of the obstacles that we're facing,
and he had brought with him
a great load of things
that he was planning to use for ministry,
and along the way,
he realized that it's just not gonna be possible
to take everything that he brought with him.
The load was too large.
So along the way,
he had to choose some things to part with.
The missionary decided,
I don't need these things,
I can do without these,
and as he tried to continually decrease the load,
it just became.
became more and more difficult to make the journey, the trek, with anything.
The one thing that he said he could not part with was this book.
I can leave all the other books.
I can leave the books that I thought would help me in ministry and what have you, but
I can't part with the Bible.
And Paul, he says, listen, especially the parchments, understanding the truth of preservation
and teaching for us the truth of preservation.
On Wednesday evening, Brother Tim came and asked me some questions down in my office.
We had a good time chatting about preparation of messages and various things, and it was
a real good conversation.
And we're standing there in my office, and there's bookshelves with books.
And I said to him, I said, listen, all of those books have their place, but they cannot
take the place of this book.
I've read a number of the books on my bookshelf.
There are some that I've recommended for other people to read.
They've been helpful.
But I told Tim this.
He can vouch for me.
I said, listen, you read a commentary, a commentary is man's words about God's Word.
Is that what I told you?
The best commentary on the Bible is the Bible.
You better dig in the Word of God.
Get into this book.
Why?
Because it's been preserved for us, and we can rejoice this morning in knowing that God
has given us this promise of preservation.
We must hold dear to this promise and understand that He alone who made the promise is the
only one that can fulfill the promise.
Now notice with me number two.
We see the promise of preservation, but let me remind you of the process of preservation,
the process of preservation.
We're not going to get deep into this this morning, but we find that the process of preservation,
again, you find that the definition is the providential keeping of the original text
from loss or alteration.
There are people today that are saying, well, I want to find the originals.
If I could get the originals, then I'd believe it.
But God promised to preserve, and so I don't need the original if my God promised to preserve
it and He has, and that preservation is the providential keeping, remember, of what?
The original.
From loss or alteration.
So if God has promised to preserve His Word, and He has, and God has always fulfilled what
He's promised, I don't need to search for an original.
There's all this conversation that took place and still takes place today about the Dead
Sea Scrolls.
No doubt you've heard about it.
Listen, when God said He was going to preserve His Word, He didn't mean in some cave over
in Israel.
And for 18 centuries of biblical Christianity, they don't have the Bible.
It doesn't even make sense.
God promised to preserve, and He's preserved His Word, and it's a providential, miraculous
work of God.
How did He do it?
Well, He used His people.
He used His people to carry out the work of preservation.
But I want you to understand that God is the one who has providentially preserved.
Though He would use people, it is God who is the one that's superseding.
It's just like when you understand the truth of inspiration, we say, well, who wrote the
book?
How many of you ever had that question?
Maybe some of the teens, they won't ask it now, so I'm trying to get some of the hard
questions out of the way for the book of Genesis.
No, I'm just kidding, I won't take any more.
But the reality is that who wrote the book of Genesis?
Who wrote the book of, right, we hear that, right?
But ultimately, that little boy in Sunday school or in junior church that has the same
answer for every question, God, God, you ever met that person that just, that's their answer
for every question?
Well, the reality is that God did write it.
He's the author of Scripture, but God used man.
God used human penmen to write the Word of God, and God has used man to preserve His
Word.
But understand, it's not in some group of men that have preserved it.
It's God that has preserved it using His people.
Does that make sense this morning?
And we must understand that, and we look at this process of preservation.
Let's go to the book of Romans, if you will, Romans chapter number 3.
In Romans chapter number 3, a question is asked, and we find that there's a great truth
that's revealed to us in answering that question.
In verse number 1, the Bible says this, "'What advantage then hath the Jew, or what profit
is there of circumcision?'
And then notice what he says in verse number 2, "'Much every way, chiefly because that
unto them were committed the oracles of God.'"
That's a reference, another name that God uses for the Word of God, and we find that
God had committed to the Jewish people.
You think about the scribes and what their responsibility was in writing out and giving
the copies of God's Word, and you understand how God would use and how God would work through
that process of preservation.
Many times the originals weren't available.
Why?
Because the originals were used.
And once they got to a point where they weren't able to be read or able to be used any longer,
they would be destroyed, but you would have these copies, and the process of copying
out these scribes, the process that would follow was very, very specific and very detailed
as to what they would do and how they would do.
You ever write something by hand, and you get down to the bottom, and you make an error,
and you just want to kind of cross it out and keep going, right, because you don't want
to have to start over?
They weren't allowed to do that.
To make an error, you've got to throw the whole thing away and start over.
They counted every letter.
I mean, they were meticulous in their process, but it was God who was supernaturally preserving
His Word.
I want you to think about this.
The Bible says this in 1 Timothy 3, in verse number 15, that the church is the pillar and
ground of the truth.
And in a very real sense, we find that God has used the church in preserving His Word,
His people.
Notice over in Matthew chapter 28, a familiar passage of Scripture that each of us would
be familiar with, the Great Commission, in Matthew chapter 28, but we think about the
Great Commission in light of what I just mentioned about 1 Timothy 3 and verse 15, where the
Bible says that the church is the pillar and ground of the truth.
What is the truth?
The Bible.
Thy Word is truth.
Jesus is truth, right?
He said, I am the way, the truth, and the life.
No man cometh unto the Father but by Me.
He then says this in John 17, sanctify them by Thy Word.
Thy Word is truth.
And so we find that the church is the pillar and ground of the truth and that God has committed
to us the Word of God, the Bible, and what a blessing it is to have the Bible.
But notice with me this process of preservation.
How is it that God would use His power?
He's obviously, or His people, He's supernaturally overseeing the providential preservation of
His Word.
But notice in verse 18 of Matthew 28, and Jesus came and spake unto them saying, all
power is given unto Me in heaven and earth.
We mentioned just a little while ago in the Gospel of Mark where He said you do err not
knowing the Scriptures nor the power of God.
He says all power is given unto Me in heaven and earth.
Aren't you thankful that you serve the omnipotent God and that the omnipotent God reigneth?
What a joy and what a blessing to know His power.
Notice the commission in verse 19, go ye therefore and teach all nations.
What are we supposed to teach them?
The Word of God, the Gospel.
Teach all nations, notice what He says, baptizing them in the name of the Father and of the
Son and of the Holy Ghost.
So we understand that we give the Gospel, right?
What has to happen before somebody gets baptized?
Well, they've got to be saved, right?
If somebody comes to me and says, Pastor, I want to be baptized, I say, well, talk to
me about when you got saved.
When did you trust Christ as your personal Savior?
Because if you haven't been saved yet, baptism is not yet for you.
Because we believe the Bible plainly teaches that baptism, it's believer's baptism by
immersion.
And we believe that.
We can go to passages of Scripture.
Remember the Ethiopian eunuch, he says, hey, Philip, there's water.
What doth hinder me to be baptized?
If you believe, you may, right?
So we understand that as I stand in these waters just a couple of weeks ago, had baptism
and I stand here and I say, listen, Ethan, have you trusted the Lord Jesus Christ as
your personal Savior?
Do you have assurance that heaven is your home?
He says, yes, I do.
I say this, Ethan, according to your profession of faith, I now baptize you in the name of
the Father, Son, and the Holy Ghost, right?
And so we understand that salvation, the Gospel has to be preached.
We preach the Gospel.
We give the truth of the death, the peril, and the glorious resurrection of our Savior.
And then we baptize.
but notice what it says in verse 20,
teaching them to observe all things
whatsoever I have commanded you.
Teaching who?
Well, the people that got saved and got baptized, right?
If you look at verse 19,
he says that we're to go into all nations,
we're to teach all nations, baptizing them,
and then we're to teach them.
And so we would look at verse number 20
as being the truth of discipleship.
See, it's not about just seeing people
make professions of faith and just getting them baptized.
We want to see people saved
and we want to see them baptized,
but there's this need for discipleship.
And notice what he says,
teaching them to observe all things
whatsoever I have commanded you.
So if Jesus says to the disciples
that you're to command,
that you're to teach them to obey,
to observe all things that I have commanded you,
then does he, in giving this command,
is there not a reference to preservation?
Because how are we gonna teach all things
if all things are not preserved?
Does that make sense this morning?
And so we find that he says,
and lo, I am with you always,
even under the end of the world.
Bookends, if you will, to this wonderful command
that God has given us.
In verse 18, he's all powerful.
In verse number 20, he's everywhere present.
He says, I've given you all things
and I'm commanding you.
I have all power and I'm commanding you
to teach all these things,
whatsoever things I've commanded you,
to these that have been saved and baptized.
And by the way, he says, I am with you always,
even under the end of the world.
Amen.
The church is the pillar and ground of the truth.
As the church preaches the gospel,
sees people saved and baptized and discipled,
we see how God is continuing the work of preservation.
We can look over the centuries
and we can see how God has supernaturally,
providentially preserved his word
through using his people.
Let me finish up number three,
principles of Bible preservation.
We look at the promise, the process,
but then look at some principles.
I want you to understand this morning
that preservation is linked to the very character of God.
Preservation is linked to the very character of God.
Turn to the book of Psalms again, Psalm 100.
Psalm 100 is a familiar passage of scripture.
In fact, many times we would be able to recite this passage
and what a joy to think about the truth
that God would contain in just five short verses
of scripture.
In Psalm 100,
we look at verse number five.
Notice what the Bible says,
for the Lord is good.
Aren't you thankful that we have a good God?
The psalmist had declared earlier,
taste and see that the Lord is good.
He had experienced the goodness of God
and he desired for others to have that same experience,
to have that same understanding that God is good.
By the way, it's his very nature.
God's goodness is not dependent upon your circumstances.
So many people in life have the idea
that when things are going well,
when everything's kind of squared away, so to speak,
then God is good.
But the reality is that God is good all of the time
because it's his nature.
He's a good God.
God is good.
Notice it says this, his mercy is everlasting.
Aren't you thankful for God's mercy?
Ephesians chapter number two says it this way,
but God who is rich in mercy.
I'm thankful for the mercy of God.
His mercy endureth forever.
And we this morning have been the recipients
of God's mercy.
I'm thankful that God declares that he is a merciful God.
And it says that he's good.
It says that his mercy is everlasting,
but then notice in verse number five,
and his truth endureth to all generations.
Listen, the same verse of scripture
that tells us that God is good and God is merciful
tells us that God preserves his word.
That his truth endureth to all generations.
This morning, I've already asked the question in 2023,
are we still part of every generation?
Absolutely.
Are we part of forever?
Are we part of to all generations?
Absolutely.
And God has preserved his word.
And so we understand that the truth,
the promise of preservation is linked
to the very character of God.
God said he would do it.
Preservation extends to the very words.
This morning, there's groups of people
that have been producing new versions of Bibles
for several decades now.
And there's a school of thought that,
well, God's word is, you know,
the Bible contains God's words, but it's not God's word.
There are people that have the idea
that it's just the thoughts.
No, it's the very words.
All scripture is given by inspiration of God.
And he says that he would preserve the words.
Remember, we looked already there in Matthew 4,
in verse number four, but by every word,
he says in Matthew 24 and verse number 35,
that his words shall not pass away.
Listen, the words matter.
I mean, which ones can we cut out?
And don't take a pen knife and just start cutting out
the ones that you would rather not have
because I don't want to submit to that.
No one seems to want to change John 3 16.
No, no, no, that one's in all of the manuscripts.
But these ones over here, well, you know, no, no, no, no.
Who becomes the authority?
God said he would preserve it, and he has.
And it's the very words.
Notice in Revelation 22, turn over there if you will.
In Revelation 22, and I know we've been
in a number of passages this morning.
Revelation chapter 22.
In Revelation 22, in verse number 18,
notice the Bible says this,
for I testify unto every man that heareth the words
of the prophecy of this book.
If any man shall add unto these things,
God shall add unto him the plagues
that are written in this book.
And if any man shall take away from what?
From the words of the book of this prophecy,
God shall take away his part of the book of life
and out of the holy city,
and from the words of the book of this prophecy,
God shall take away his part of the book of life
and out of the holy city.
And from the things which are written in this book.
So if you look at verse 18 and 19 of Revelation 22,
do you think God's concerned about the words?
Absolutely.
You can look over in the book of Deuteronomy,
and we referenced this last week,
and you can see in Deuteronomy chapter number four,
where the Bible very specifically talks about the words.
And see, God is concerned about the words.
Again, as I mentioned last week,
there's no filler in this Bible.
There's no filler.
God gave us exactly what he wanted us to have.
And when we find that there's verses that are repeated,
when you find that there are phrases that are repeated,
such as you find with, I mentioned already,
the mercy of the Lord, that his mercy endureth forever.
You read Psalm 136, and you see every single verse
in that chapter says the mercy of the Lord,
it endureth forever, it endureth forever.
And why does he keep saying that?
Because he wants us to know.
That his mercy endureth forever.
Sometimes we repeat something
because we just don't know what to say next.
God doesn't do that.
Every word is precious, and every word is important.
And we find that the truth of preservation,
it's not just that God preserved his thoughts,
and some people fill in all the, no, no.
God preserved his words.
And we find that the truth of preservation
is that, no, no, God preserved his words.
By the way, preservation, I believe,
is something that we accept by faith.
Preservation is something we accept by faith.
God said it, and God does it.
You know, there's no promise that God has given
that he's not fulfilled.
I often take great joy in reading the passage
in Matthew with regard to the resurrection
when the disciples arrive and the angel says,
come and see the place where the Lord laid.
He is not here, for he has risen as he said.
God always does what he says he will do.
He's not a man that he should lie, amen?
He's able to do what he's promised to do.
I've used the illustration before.
Juliana's here this morning.
She probably doesn't remember it
because she was just a toddler,
but I made a promise to Juliana when I was,
she was just a little toddler,
and I promised her that on Saturday
of this particular week that we would do
this particular activity.
It was an outdoor activity.
I said, Juliana, I promise you.
She wanted to do it, wanted to do it, wanted to do it,
and I was working and all kinds of stuff going on.
I said, on Saturday, honey,
I promise we're gonna do this on Saturday.
It poured rain.
I mean, just poured.
And we couldn't do what I had promised Ron that we would do.
And as a little two-year-old,
old girl, she looked at me and she said these words, but daddy, you promised.
I can't control the weather.
I couldn't fulfill, and so I never made another promise.
I learned that I can't promise something that I don't have the control of being able to
fulfill.
I intend, I plan.
You just pick different words, amen?
But God has promised, and God does.
Notice in the book of 1 Thessalonians, notice what the Bible says in 1 Thessalonians 2.
We talk about the truth that these principles, if you will, of biblical preservation, the
truth that God has promised to preserve and understanding the process, but notice that
preservation, it's accepted by faith.
Many people will attack the Bible.
It's nothing new, started in Genesis.
Many people will attack the Bible, but we this morning, we accept by faith that God
has done what God said He would do, and I want you to notice what the believers in Thessalonica,
I want you to understand how Paul commends them in verse number 13.
If you study the book of 1 Thessalonians, in fact, you'll find that the believers in
Thessalonica are commended for a number of things, but specifically with regard to the
topic of our message this morning, I want you to notice in 1 Thessalonians 2 and verse
13, the Bible says this, for this cause also thank we God without ceasing.
Now think about just the preface of how Paul is saying this.
This thing that I'm about to say to you has so impacted us as the apostles, as the ones
that have been privileged of God to bring you the gospel message and to bring you the
Word of God, this thing that I'm about to say has caused us to thank God without ceasing.
That's pretty significant.
What is it?
What is it, Paul, that's so important?
What is it, Paul, that's had such a profound impact upon you that you are thanking God
without ceasing because when you received the Word of God, which you heard of us, you
received it not as the Word of men, but as it is in truth, the Word of God, which effectually
worketh also in you that believe.
Paul was saying, listen, I'm rejoicing greatly.
I am thanking God without ceasing.
Why?
Because we came to you.
Notice, we don't have time this morning to look at the beginning of chapter number one
and the beginning of chapter number two and to see how Paul is saying, listen, we came
and we were speaking to you.
We were bold in verse number two in our God to speak unto you the gospel of God with much
contention, he says in verse number four, but as we are allowed of God to be put in
trust with the gospel, even so we speak not as pleasing men, but God, which trieth our
hearts and they received it as it was the Word of God.
They didn't say, oh, this is what Paul says, let's next, who's got something else to tell
us?
No, no.
They heard it and they accepted it in faith that this is the Word of God.
This morning we accept it by faith.
I would finish by saying this this morning, questioning preservation is the starting point
for apostasy.
Questioning preservation is the starting point for apostasy.
Pastor, why do you say that?
Because if this book isn't true, everything falls apart.
If every Word of God isn't pure, if all Scripture isn't given by inspiration of God and preserved
everything starts falling apart.
It's your opinion.
It's their opinion.
It's your scholarly, quote, unquote, ability.
But I'd rather say God, who's eternal, gave me a promise that He's going to preserve His
Word.
See, why is it the starting point of apostasy?
Well, because Satan, as the serpent in Genesis chapter number three, he's more subtle than
any other beast of the field.
He comes to the garden and here's what he says, "'Yea, hath God said,' questioning the
Scripture."
God said it and it's settled.
Why?
Because God said, all Scripture is given by inspiration, but He said, I'll preserve it.
This morning, I mentioned already that inspiration is great for the original recipients.
Inspiration is great for us, but if inspiration without preservation, I'm not an original
recipient.
But inspiration and preservation together are two wonderful Bible truths that cause
us to have great confidence in the book that we hold in our laps this morning, God's Word,
that this book is powerful, it's alive, and this morning it abides forever.
Listen, next week, the week after, we're going to start talking about, okay, so we understand
what the Bible is, but now how do I approach the Bible?
I said this multiple times two weeks ago.
Before we talk about what the Bible says, we must agree on what the Bible is.
If I don't agree with what the Bible is, then talking about what it says is just open for
debate, but when we can agree that this book is God's Word and it's been providentially
preserved for us without any loss or alteration, then we start getting into, okay, what does
it say?
Because we agree that this is God's Word, and therefore, because it's God's Word and
it's been preserved for us, this book is authoritative, this book is essential for my life.
Why do we say, read your Bible?
Because it's God's Word.
If I don't believe that this book is God's Word, why am I going to read it?
If it's just man's word about God?
No, no, no.
When we understand what this book is, then we dig in to see what this book says, and
we need to take heed to what this book says because this book is the Word of God, and
I'm so thankful for the biblical truth of preservation, and we can have great confidence
this morning.
We can sing, hallelujah, I'm saved.
How do you know you're saved?
Because God gave His Bible, and God preserved it, because if you don't believe in preservation
this morning, how do you know the way to Christ?
I know the way of salvation because I believe that God preserved His Word.
Everything falls apart without inspiration and preservation, but our God, who is eternal,
who is able, He said, I will preserve it, I will preserve it from this generation forever.
The Word of the Lord endureth forever, hallelujah.
Let's pray.
Father, how we love You, how we thank You for loving us.
I'm thankful that You gave Your Word by inspiration.
All Scripture is given by inspiration of God.
It's profitable.
I'm thankful this morning that You promised to preserve Your Word.
I believe this morning that we have the perfect preserved Word of God.
I'm so thankful that You fulfill Your promises.
We can speak about the process and various principles, and I pray that You'd help us
this morning to rejoice in understanding the truth, the teaching of preservation.
We pray that, Lord, You would help us to dig into the truth of Your Word, that we'd search
the Scriptures, that we'd study to show ourselves approved unto God.
Why?
Because we understand that this book is the preserved Word of God.
Help us to apply truth in our lives, Lord, help us as we pray so often to be doers of
the Word and not hearers only.
I pray that as we leave here in just a few moments that we'd rejoice greatly in knowing
that we have the Word of God.
Thank You for preserving Your Word for us.
Lord, I pray that if there's one that's not sure of heaven, Lord, I pray that today
would be the day of their salvation.
We talk much about the Bible, but we spoke much about salvation as well.
Lord, if there's one present, one that's tuned in via live stream, that's not sure of heaven,
oh, God, I pray that You would move in their heart this morning.
We'd have the opportunity to take the Bible and show them how they could know for sure
that heaven is their home.
Lord, I pray that You'd help each child of God to be encouraged this morning through
this promise of preservation and to recognize that preservation reveals Your greatness.
I pray that You'd move and work in the few moments of invitation for it's in Christ's
name we pray.
Would You stand with me?
Heads are bowed, eyes are closed, no one's looking around this morning.
If you're not sure of heaven, we'd love to take a Bible and show you how you could know
for sure that heaven's your home.
Remember this morning, you just want to come and thank God for the Bible.
Thank Him for this truth of preservation and His greatness that is revealed there.
And maybe the Lord spoke to your heart through some other way.
to thank Him for salvation. As Kimberly plays, the altar is open.