Leviticus chapter number 25, and the thunder is roaring and the skies have gotten dark.
If you're watching live stream, Joseph asked me a moment ago, what happens if the power
goes out?
It means that you lose your connectivity to our live stream, okay?
And so we are having some thunderstorms.
And so we, those that are here, we get to just continue, amen.
And praise the Lord for that.
But Leviticus chapter number 25 this evening, and I'll be looking at verses 1 through 7,
and then we'll skip down and look at verses 18 through 22.
And let me just remind you, last Wednesday evening, we studied the 16th chapter of the
book of Exodus.
And as we studied Exodus 16, I asked this question, and we used it as the title of the
message.
I asked the question many times throughout the message, would you have passed the test?
And that was a purpose of evaluating our own selves.
And I mentioned often throughout that lesson that we could answer quickly and say, yes,
I would have passed, because that's what we'd like to have said.
And I asked you to really examine.
And we know that there were some that did pass, and I'm so thankful for that.
There were some, of course, that did not pass.
But as we studied that passage of scripture, we were reminded how the Lord miraculously
and graciously provided manna for His people.
They had complained earlier about no water, and God provided for them the water that they
needed.
They had now complained about no food, and God provided for them.
And what a blessing.
The end of the chapter tells us in Exodus 16 and verse number 35 that they ate manna
for 40 years.
And what miraculous provision that God gave to His people.
And it's interesting, and we mentioned this as we studied through the book of Joshua during
the last several months, as we were studying through that book.
In Joshua chapter number 5 and verses 10 through 12, the book of Joshua records for us the
historical account of when the children of Israel observed the Passover in the land.
And then in verse number 12 tells us that the manna ceased.
They no longer had manna, and God had provided them the manna until they would then be sustained
from the fruit of the field and the land in which God would provide them with.
And what a blessing to understand that.
As we considered the lesson last Wednesday evening, we mentioned that with the provision
came instruction.
And as we consider the instruction that God provided the children of Israel with on how
they would gather the manna, and of course we specifically zeroed in on day number 6
and dealing with how they were to do that and whether they would obey the instructions.
And the reality is that we said that God really, as you look at the text of Scripture,
it says that He was going to prove them, test them.
And it was a test of faith, and it was a test of obedience.
Would they obey God?
Would they exercise faith in that which God said?
This evening as we look at Leviticus chapter number 25, I want to examine the instruction
that God gives with regard to the Sabbath year.
And let's read just a couple of verses of Scripture and dig into the passage this evening.
In verse number 1 of Leviticus 25, the Bible says,
And the Lord spake unto Moses in Mount Sinai, saying,
And so we see that this is the word of the Lord.
What a blessing to know that God communicates with His people, amen?
And I am so thankful this evening that we have a Bible.
I'm thankful that God has given me the simple instruction, though it's simple in its instruction.
It's a challenging task, but we're to preach the word.
We're to live and teach the word of God, and I'm thankful that God has given us His word.
This isn't Moses just providing instruction to the people they've been called to lead.
This is God's instruction.
It says,
Speak unto the children of Israel, and say unto them,
When ye come into the land which I give you, then shall the land keep a Sabbath unto the Lord.
We'll read down through verse number 7.
We'll look over, if you will, though, in verse number 21.
I want to give you the title for the message, and I've adopted it here from verse number 21 of Leviticus 25.
The Bible says,
Then I will command My blessing upon you in the sixth year,
and it shall bring forth fruit for three years.
I want to preach a message, share a lesson with you this evening that I've simply entitled,
I will command My blessing upon you.
Now, think about that as being the words of God,
and God saying to His people,
I will command My blessing upon you.
That's precious.
And as we look at the passage of Scripture this evening,
and dig here through what God gives us,
I want you to, first of all, if you're taking notes, consider God's plan for the seventh year.
Really, here in Leviticus 25, verses 1 through 7,
we have the opportunity to look and to understand the plan of God
for His people with regard to the land during this seventh year.
Notice, I've already read verse number 2,
but it is important that we understand and make note of the fact that the Bible says,
When ye come into the land which I give you.
It was not a question on whether they would enter into the land.
It's not an if you enter into the land.
It's a when, because God promised to do that,
and God would bring that to pass.
And we understand scripturally, as we study the Word of God,
that after the wilderness wanderings,
Joshua becomes the human leader of the nation of Israel.
They miraculously cross over the Jordan River.
They enter into, conquer, and possess the land that God had promised
hundreds of years earlier.
And so what a blessing to understand that God is saying to the nation of Israel,
at this particular moment in their history,
When ye come into the land which I give you,
then shall the land keep a Sabbath unto the Lord.
So here in Leviticus 25,
we see that God is reminding them that they will enter into the land,
and here's the plan that I have for you.
Here's my plan. Here's my instruction for you.
By the way, aren't you thankful again that God gives us His plan?
He gives us His instruction.
Notice verse number three.
Six years thou shalt.
So notice, for this period of six years, here's what they're to do.
Number one, sow thy field.
Right? We understand the principle of sowing and reaping.
Many of us probably have never really had a farm,
or lived on a farm, or worked on a farm.
I know my dad, as a young boy, worked on a farm.
But we understand here that the agricultural aspect
of what God is dealing with here
was absolutely essential for their survival.
It says six years, here's what you do.
Thou shalt sow thy field, notice,
and six years thou shalt prune thy vineyard.
That's an important aspect.
Again, if we've not been in the field of agriculture
and doing those things, we may not understand the full significance,
but we understand that God is giving them good counsel and good direction.
He's providing them with this plan for what they do.
And then you notice at the end of verse number three,
and gather in the fruit thereof.
The reaping.
So for six years, you sow, you prune, and you gather the fruit.
But you notice as you come to verse number four
that it begins with this but.
This conjunction.
A different plan for that seventh year.
But in the seventh year shall be a Sabbath of rest
unto the land.
A Sabbath for the Lord.
Now we understand that the people of God
had already been instructed with regard to the Sabbath day.
And we understand that God had set forth that pattern
even in creation where He rested on the seventh day.
He created all that He created in six days
and then He rested on the seventh day.
Thus providing a model for the children of Israel
in Exodus during the giving of the Ten Commandments.
We find that it's referenced to them
with regard to the Sabbath and their responsibility.
And now we find that God is dealing with
this Sabbath year, this seventh year.
It says at the end of verse number four,
Thou shalt neither sow thy field
nor prune thy vineyard.
So in the seventh year,
you're not going to do what you did
in year one, two, three, four, five, and six.
You're not going to sow.
You're not going to prune.
Verse five, that which groweth of its own accord
of thy harvest thou shalt not reap.
Neither gather the grapes of thy vine undressed
for it is a year of rest unto the Lord.
Excuse me, unto the land.
Notice verse six.
And the Sabbath of the land shall be meet for you,
for thee and for thy servant,
for thy maid and for thy hired servant
and for thy stranger that sojourneth with thee.
And for thy cattle and for the beasts
that are in thy land,
shall all the increase thereof be meet.
I find just as it was noted in our last lesson
last Wednesday evening in Exodus 16,
that God gave pretty specific instruction.
Amen?
Do you feel like as we've read these first seven verses
that there's anything overly complicated
about the instruction, the plan
that God has communicated to His people?
It's not a complicated plan.
It's a plan that God communicates to His people
just as the case was for gathering the manna.
You go out and you gather so much on day one.
two, three, four, right? This is what you do. If you store up too much, it's
gonna spoil, it stinks, and it breeds worms, and therefore you just gather this
much. But on day number six, you gather a double portion, right? Days one through
five, a single portion. This was God's plan. Again, not complicated, not difficult,
but it was God's plan. And here, with regard to the seventh year, the Sabbath
year, God is giving a plan. He reveals His plan to His people, and He tells them
that this is what you're to do when you enter into the land which I give you. So
this was not a plan to be implemented during the wilderness wanderings, right?
This was a plan that they were to incorporate, implement, when they entered
into and possessed the land. Now, I would submit to you that as we go through the
passage of Scripture this evening and we consider the plan of God, I would also
say this, that I would look at, and if you're taking notes, number two, I would
consider the preparation of God's people. It's interesting to me that as we look
at the passage of Scripture and we see what God is giving them to do as far as
a plan, we would find that through what we studied last Wednesday evening with
regard to the manna that had miraculously and graciously provided
for His people for 40 years, that was a process of preparing the people of God.
See, God prepares His people. God, I think often as we would consider how God would
call us to do certain things and He would lead us in our lives, and we
understand the Bible says, so then faith cometh by hearing, and hearing by the
Word of the Lord, by the Word of God, and we understand that as we go through life
that we're to exercise and live by faith, and we mentioned last week that it was a
test not simply of obedience, it was a test of obedience, but also was a test of
faith. Well, this was going to be a test of faith as well. This wasn't just a
single day, this was an entire year. But God had prepared His people. I think
about Gideon. You think about when God first arrives to the angel of the Lord
comes to Gideon and he introduces himself and he calls him a mighty man of
valor, right? And Gideon kind of has this perspective of like, you got the wrong
guy, right? I'm the least of my father's house, and you understand that these
things are going on, and it's interesting if we don't have time this evening to go
through all of it, but if you look in Judges 6 and even into chapter number
7, and you begin to find how that God develops Gideon for the task that He had
for him. See, Gideon wasn't ready on that first day when God came to him. Gideon
had to have his faith increased. He had to be prepared for that which God had
for him, and we find that the angel of the Lord departed out of his sight in
verse number 21 of Judges chapter number 6, and we really believe that as you
look there in that text of Scripture, in that section, that God is giving
faith builder number one to Gideon. But then Gideon's still not ready, and you'll
remember that Gideon, his faith was still small, and he says to God in Judges 6
in verse 36 and 37, he says this, he says, if thou wilt save Israel by mine hand as
thou hast said, behold I will put a fleece of wool in the floor, and if the
dew on the fleece only, be on the fleece only, and if it be dry upon all the
earth beside, then shall I know that thou wilt save Israel by mine hand as
thou hast said. What did God do? God increased his faith. It tells us in verse
38 of Judges 6, and it was so. For he, Gideon, rose up early on the morrow, and
thrust the fleece together, and wringed the dew out of the fleece, a bowl full of
water. God increased his faith. God was building his faith. He was preparing his
servant. See, Gideon had said to God, he said, God, if thou wilt save Israel by
mine hand as thou hast said, then do this thing, and if you do this thing, then I
will know that thou wilt save Israel. And God did it. You know what Gideon said?
Let's try again. Right? In Judges 6, in verse 39, Gideon said unto God, let not
thine anger be hot against me. I probably would want to introduce my request in
a like manner, amen? Because I'd already said, if you do this, I'm gonna believe
you. I'm gonna know that this is what you have for me. He says, let me prove, I pray
thee, but this once with the fleece, and let it now be dry only upon the fleece,
and upon all the ground, let there be dew. So he reverses what he had the night
before. What does God do? Verse 40, and God did so that night. For it was dry upon
the fleece only, and there was dew on all the ground. But do you know that Gideon
still wasn't ready? He wasn't. You read Judges chapter number 7, and he's still
reluctant, he's still unsure as to what's really gonna happen. And we find that God
comes to him, and he says, in verse number 9 of Judges 7, it says, and it came to
pass the same night that the Lord said unto him, arise, get thee down into the
host, for I have delivered unto thine hand. But if thou fear to go down, go thou
with pure thy servant down to the host, and thou shalt hear what they say, and
afterward shall thine hands be strengthened to go down unto the host.
You know what he goes and he hears? He hears this dream being told, and they
hear the interpretation when they say, this is none other, in verse number 14,
and his fellow answered and said, this is nothing else save the sword of Gideon,
the son of Joash, a man of Israel, for into his hand hath God delivered Midian
and all the host. What's God doing? He's preparing Gideon. You know God's
preparing you. God's preparing me, right? He is. He's preparing us for what's to
come down the road. He's preparing us that we would have faith when we are to
have faith, that we'd exercise that faith, and I believe that for the children of
Israel during those 25 years of, excuse me, those 40 years of wilderness
wanderings, that when we come to Leviticus 25 and we see the instruction
for when you come into the land, this is what you're supposed to do, this is how
you're supposed to deal with the land with regard to sowing and pruning, and
this is my plan for you, but God had been preparing them. Not only had he prepared
them through the miraculous supply and provision of manna, but we find that
he had worked miraculously through many other areas during that period of
wilderness wanderings. God's preparing his people. God's, I believe that he's
regularly preparing his people if we would allow God to work in our lives that
as we, see that's why it's so important to have a daily walk with him. That's why
it's so vital that every day we're in the Bible and we're, because when the
crisis comes and we've been neglecting this book and we've been neglecting the
house of God and we've been neglecting all of those things, our walk with God,
we've become anemic spiritually and that crisis comes, we're not ready for it. And
then all of a sudden it's like, oh I better go get alone with God, I better go
find out what he has for me, and you start looking at the Bible like this and
you start flipping here and flipping there and you're going because you're
trying to find a verse that's going to help you with that particular situation.
But if we had that daily consistent walk with God and he's building us up and
he's preparing us for that which will come at some point in our lives, he's
preparing us. So then faith cometh by hearing and hearing by the Word of the
Lord or the Word of God and we find it as we get into the Word of God that when
that moment of trial comes, that moment of difficulty comes, that moment of
temptation comes, that we have already spent that time in the Word of God and
we have some level of preparation, oh it does not mean that we are sufficient in
of ourselves, I'm not seeking to suggest that in any way, but I'm simply saying
that God prepares us. And I can't help as I look at Leviticus 25 to consider how
that the people of God had been adequately prepared during the
wilderness wanderings to really be obedient in this area of instruction
that God gives in Leviticus 25 verses 1 through 7. I want you to consider with
me that the very next contextually in Leviticus 25 begins to deal with the
the year of Jubilee, the 50th year and all of the things that would happen and
all of that and that's not really part of the message this evening so I'm going
to skip down to verse number 18 as we consider and keep in thought with the
subject matter before us with regard to the seventh year. We see the plan of God,
we see the preparation of God and we find in verse number 18 the Bible says
this, wherefore ye shall do my statutes and keep my judgments and do them and
ye shall dwell in the land in safety and the land shall yield her fruit and ye
shall eat your fill and dwell therein in safety. And notice this in verse number
20, and if you shall say, what shall we eat the seventh year? Behold, we shall not
sow nor gather in our increase. Now honestly I believe that as you look at
verse number 20 God is preemptively answering a question
that they'd not even asked yet.
Because God knows everything.
But I can't help but understand this evening
that it would be a natural question
that would arise.
Right?
You're not going to sow. You're not going to prune.
So what am I going to eat?
Right?
And we find that as we look at these verses
in Leviticus 25, verses 18-22,
if you're taking notes,
number 3, embrace the promise of God.
Embrace the promise of God.
What shall we eat the seventh year?
Let me ask you this as we consider
the teachings of Jesus in Matthew 6.
Is it not adequately revealed to us
that God knows what our needs are?
He's the One that designed us.
He's the One that created us.
He knows that we need food
and water, raiment, shelter.
But what does He finish there
in Matthew 6?
Seek ye first the Kingdom of God.
And all these things shall be added unto thee.
Right?
And so we understand here
that there's a question from a human perspective
even as we've understood in our lesson
from last week in Exodus 16,
we have no food.
God knew that they needed food.
He created them.
He made us that way.
So we find here
where we looked at and gave our title
for our message this evening in v. 21.
Embrace the promise of God.
Notice v. 21.
Then I will command
My blessing upon you in the sixth year.
I want God's blessing.
Don't you?
He tells them in v. 18 and 19
that if you do these things,
if you do My statutes,
keep My judgments,
if you do them,
you shall dwell in the land in safety.
The land will yield her fruit.
You shall eat your fill
and dwell therein in safety.
And God then says in v. 21,
then I will command My blessing upon you.
I just love the imagery that I see in my mind
as my sanctified imagination
as God Almighty,
the Creator of the universe,
saying to His people,
I am going to command My blessing upon you.
That's pretty awesome.
Notice what He says.
He's going to command it in the sixth year.
And it, the land, shall.
I like the word shall.
Bring forth fruit for how long?
For three years.
It's not going to be because of your creative
agricultural abilities.
No, no, I'm going to command My blessing upon you.
If you do what I'm telling you to do,
if you follow the plan
that I'm giving you to follow,
again, we've already settled the fact
that it's not a complicated plan.
But it is a plan that requires faith.
Right?
Just like on day number six with the manna,
it required faith that it wasn't going to stink
when you got that double portion in breed worms.
Just like on day number three,
or if you just say day number one,
you see all this manna,
you didn't have any food.
You were complaining about food.
And you understand that Moses said,
hey, only take a single portion.
Don't take more than what you need.
And you're like, I don't know if this stuff's
going to come back tomorrow,
so I go ahead and gather as much as I can
to fit in my basket.
You know what I mean?
And then all of a sudden,
it stinks and it's bred worms.
It requires faith.
This plan that God gives with regard
to the seventh year, it requires faith.
That God is going to do what He said
He was going to do.
By the way, when you really consider
the introduction to this instruction,
when God says when
you come into the land which I give you,
again, it was God that brought them there.
And this is the plan that you're supposed to follow.
And here's what I'm going to do.
I'm going to command my blessing upon you,
and in that sixth year, the land,
it shall bring forth fruit for three years.
Notice, it says in verse number 22,
and ye shall sow the eighth year.
You're not sowing the seventh year, remember?
That's the plan.
In verse number four and five,
we understood that God said this is what
you're going to do in this seventh year.
Thou shalt neither sow thy field
nor prune thy vineyard.
So here we find in verse 22,
and ye shall sow the eighth year
and eat yet of old fruit until the ninth year.
Until her fruits come in,
ye shall eat of the old store.
So when you sow in that eighth year,
you will take that harvest
and eat in that ninth year,
but because I'm going to bless in that sixth year,
because I'm going to command
that my blessing will be upon you
and that the land shall bring forth fruit for three years,
then in year six, seven, and eight,
you're going to have enough.
Because I'm going to command my blessing upon you.
Here's the question.
What would they do?
Would they believe God?
Would they exercise faith?
Unfortunately, the answer is no.
There's absolutely no record
in the Old Testament account
that they ever did what God told them to do
with regard to this Sabbath year.
However, 2 Chronicles 36,
if you want to turn there quickly.
And just before,
or just at the end of the text of Scripture
that records for us the Babylonian captivity of Judah,
of course, we understand that Jeremiah
had been prophesying.
You remember much of Jeremiah's prophecy
with regard to the Babylonian captivity
and that a remnant would return after 70 years.
There's significance to that number
with regard to their violation
of this instruction that we're studying this evening.
And you read in verse 21,
the Bible says,
"...to fulfill the word of the Lord by the mouth of Jeremiah
until the land had enjoyed her Sabbaths.
For as long as she lay desolate,
she kept Sabbath to fulfill
threescore and ten years."
So for 490 years, if you do the math,
there'd have been one year of Sabbath each seven.
They didn't do it.
They didn't follow the plan.
Was it a lack of faith?
Was it just flat-out disobedience?
I think it's a couple of both.
Amen?
It's a combination.
Not a couple of both,
it's a combination of both.
And this evening, when we think about this
and we think about this simple instruction,
I understand, listen,
I am in absolutely no way trying to tell you
that the text of Leviticus 25
is to be applied in our lives today
from a perspective of agriculture.
I'm showing you a principle that God gives.
If you just follow His plan,
He'll bless.
And He'll always do what He says He will do.
And the reality is that
the subject matter in which we studied
last Wednesday evening,
that as they would weekly, daily,
as they would collect that manna
every day that they would go out,
I understand they didn't stand in awe of it.
I understand every day,
they didn't come out of their tents
and say, oh, there's manna again.
Honey, it's here again.
God did it.
No, they said we hate this bread.
Is that not what they said?
But can you imagine if they had that perspective?
Can you imagine if every day
they understood God did it again?
He rained bread from heaven.
He gave us this manna.
He's providing for us.
We collected a double portion again this week
on day number six,
and it didn't spoil.
God was preparing it.
God prepares us.
And we see that here in Leviticus 25,
this truth is given.
And there's just a lack of faith and obedience
on the part of the nation of Israel
with regard to these things.
But can I tell you that God wants to prove Himself
real in our lives?
I believe Ephesians 3.20.
I believe that He is able to do exceeding abundantly
above all that we ask or think.
Do you believe that this evening?
He is.
You know, you think about the truth
of Philippians chapter number four
when Paul is commending the believers in Philippi
for their regular communication with Him.
And if you understand contextually
what he's dealing with,
how that they gave to help him financially
in that ministry in which he was engaged in.
And he says to them with regard
to his commendation of them,
he says that he had received these things
and that it was an odor of a sweet smell,
a sacrifice acceptable and well-pleasing to God.
And he then tells them,
he gives them this wonderful promise
in verse number 19.
He says, but my God shall supply all your need
according to His riches and glory
by Christ Jesus.
Is he still able to do that today?
Absolutely.
He's God.
He's on His throne.
He's able.
I read it recently.
It took place many generations ago.
So it's not a current event story
from a missionary.
It's a historical record
And it was such an encouraging
little truth that I thought it would be appropriate
to share it with you this evening
with regard to the subject matter
which we're dealing with
of trusting God and believing God.
That God said, I will command My blessing upon you.
You do what I'm telling you to do.
You follow My plan and I'll bless.
In any case, this missionary is teaching
and he'd been laboring in the field
and he'd been teaching the people.
And he began to teach them
about the importance of giving.
And we understand that's a biblical truth.
We understand the Bible truth
with regard to giving.
God loveth a cheerful giver. Amen?
And we understand those principles
and those truths that God has given.
I'm not going to teach a message on that this evening,
but we understand that.
To participate in the contribution
for the work of the Lord.
And he had been teaching this truth
to the people that he'd been reaching
as they'd established a church there
on that mission field
and teaching them how they need
to participate in giving.
Now, one particular day,
he was just going around his business
and he was at his home
and a little boy from the church
came to his house.
A little boy came to the house
and he said, Pastor,
I'm bringing my tithe.
Because of the particulars
and the area in which they were,
it wasn't that he was bringing a monetary tithe.
He was bringing a fish.
There's some mission fields
that still have those types of things
where they'll bring of the grain offering
and they'll bring those things.
That's what they have as their tithe.
I mean, that's what they bring.
And this young boy brings a fish.
And he says, Pastor,
you've been teaching us
about tithing and about giving
and about trusting God.
And here's my offering.
The pastor was excited.
He was encouraged.
This little boy's getting it.
And he says to the little boy,
and he's not from America,
so his name wasn't Johnny,
but he says to the little boy,
he says, so where are the other nine?
Because if you brought me one fish
and it's a tithe,
then that means you caught ten.
You understand how that math works.
He said, oh, Pastor,
they're still in the river.
I'm going to catch them.
That's pretty awesome.
That missionary pastor sat back and thought,
he understands a principle
of believing God.
And that little boy had full confidence
that he's going to go back to the river
and he's going to catch himself nine more fish.
Because he just believed God.
And sometimes in our lives,
we just need to get back to the simple truth
of just believing God.
Sometimes we try to get too analytical.
I'm guilty, right?
I'm an analytical kind of person.
We try to make everything make sense.
But God is God.
He didn't tell him He was going to make
the land produced for three years
bring forth a fruit in the second year.
He told him in the sixth year.
And it would last for that time
because I will command My blessing upon you.
Then I will command My blessing upon you
in the sixth year,
and it shall bring forth fruit
for three years.
This evening,
as we think about the nation of Israel
and we think about these two lessons,
and I did not initially intend
to teach these two lessons
these past two Wednesday nights,
but the reality is that
God was teaching His people
a very important lesson.
And as we can study the history of it
and the account that is given,
we can gain profitable principles
about how God works
and how God expects us still today,
the just shall live by faith, right?
We're to live by faith.
We understand Hebrews 11, six,
without faith, it's impossible to please Him.
So this evening,
I want God's blessing.
God's given us a plan.
I believe that He's prepared us.
He's given us all things
that pertain unto life and godliness
is what the Word of God says.
And so He's prepared us adequately,
and we just need to believe Him
to test of faith and obedience.
This evening, God said to His people,
I will command My blessing upon you.
That's encouraging.
Let's pray together.
We love You.
We thank You so much for loving us.
We thank You for Your Word,
the truth contained therein.
We thank You for the opportunity to study it.
Lord, we are saddened by the disobedience
of the nation of Israel,
historically as it's been recorded.
God, I pray that You'd help us
to be obedient to the plan
that You have for our lives.
Help us to understand that the Gospel still works.
It never stopped working.
You said in Your Word that the Gospel
is the power of God unto salvation.
You said in Your Word that we're to go
and preach the Gospel to every creature.
Help us to just have faith.
Help us to simply obey
the instruction that You've given.
That we would see souls saved,
lives changed,
folks discipled.
Ultimately, that You would be glorified.
Lord, we pray that You'd bless our time of prayer.
We thank You for the privilege.
We thank You for the power and prayer,
the invitation that You've given us.
We pray that You'd work mightily.
And we'll thank You for all that You'll do.
For it's in Christ's name we pray, amen.