I'm gonna preach our behavior in the workplace,
Colossians 3.
I'll preach it next week or the following, we'll see.
We have a baby dedication next week,
so we'll probably be preaching something different next week.
But I'm so thankful, as I was praying this morning
and even thinking about that song
as I heard them practicing.
Our Savior is coming again, amen.
We live in the midst of chaos and confusion and turmoil
and people are living in fear
and all sorts of things are going on.
But man, we are singing this morning
those songs that we sang about Jesus coming,
my cup's over run, right?
Oh, say, but I'm glad, why?
Because my sins are forgiven.
But you know, the reality is that the story
of the Lord Jesus Christ, the truth of God's word,
as I mentioned, William Scroggie saying
that the Bible is the unfolding drama of redemption.
You look in the Old Testament
and you find how the Lord, through the Old Testament,
is giving us types and pictures and prophecies
with regard to the coming of Messiah.
But you understand that the prophecies
that are contained within the Old Testament
are not strictly just isolated to His first coming.
In fact, there are many prophecies
with regard to His second coming.
And we find that when the fullness of time was come,
that God sent forth His Son, born of a virgin.
Why?
For the purpose of dying on the cross of Calvary.
He was the Lamb that was slain
before the foundation of the world.
Why was it necessary?
Because if He didn't, we'd be lost forever.
We'd have to pay for our own sin.
Sin carries, listen, we're all sinners.
All have sin and come short of the glory of God.
And sin carries with it a penalty.
A payment must be made.
I'm thankful that Jesus came the first time.
I'm thankful that when He came the first time,
He fulfilled that which He was to do.
I'm thankful that He declared on the cross of Calvary,
it is finished.
Amen?
And He was buried in a borrowed tomb,
and then He rose triumphantly,
conquering sin, death, and the grave.
But I want you to understand that in John 14,
before we ever get to the death,
the crucifixion of the Lord Jesus Christ,
that Jesus, in this portion of Scripture,
is encouraging His followers, His disciples.
We find that it's in the 13th chapter of the book of John
that Jesus demonstrated and displayed for them
service and ministry and being a servant.
And of course, through washing the feet of the disciples,
He showed them, demonstrated for them,
the importance of being a servant.
We find that near the end of the 13th chapter
of the book of John, that Jesus is continuing
to reveal to them that soon He would go to the cross
and that He would die on that cross.
We understand that these men, as they walked with Him,
that as He began to reveal these things
and give them further insight as to all that was going on,
notice in chapter 13 and verse number 31 that Jesus,
He says, now is the Son of Man glorified
and God is glorified in Him.
How is this going to happen?
Well, if you read chapter 17,
you understand it was through going to the cross.
We find, no doubt, that the message
that had been received by these disciples
at the end of chapter 13 was a message
that brought them troubled hearts.
How do we know that?
Well, because Jesus begins John 14 and verse number one
by saying this, let not your heart be troubled.
Let not your heart be troubled.
You believe in God, believe also in Me.
And then He says this, in My Father's house
are many mansions.
If it were not so, I would have told you.
And then notice where He says,
I go to prepare a place for you.
Now, I'm thankful that there are many things
that Jesus, after His ascension, is doing.
One of those things that He's doing
is He's making intercession for us, amen?
is He's our advocate, according to 1 John chapter number two,
and I'm thankful that He's our great high priest
and He is fulfilling those ministries.
But we find here in this passage of Scripture
that He says, I go to prepare a place for you.
And as I think about this preparation,
we find that the text does not end there.
He says in verse number three, and if I go.
Now, He just told him He was going, right?
And then He says, if I go, He says,
and prepare a place for you.
Notice these words, I will come again.
I will come again and receive you unto Myself,
that where I am, there ye may be also.
Isn't that a precious promise of the Word of God?
If you're taking notes,
I just titled the message this morning,
I will come again.
We understand the interactions
that we have humanly speaking in our relationships
and times in which we'll depart,
we'll go maybe just to the store,
maybe to the office, maybe we go on a business trip,
whatever it may be, and we'll say,
we'll see you when we get back.
The idea of that statement is that you're planning
to return, now we know and we understand,
we can read accounts and stories of those that never returned.
They did not ever complete that which was to be completed.
They never returned, why?
Because death knocked upon their door
and they never were able to return.
But I want you to understand something
about the promise of the Lord Jesus Christ
when He says to His disciples, I will come again,
the reality, if you're taking notes,
just think about this, the simplicity of the promise.
This is a simple promise.
There's nothing that's complex about the promise
that we find here in John chapter number 14,
but man, this is a wonderful promise.
And we think about the way in which God gives us
in His word these wonderful promises
and Peter will refer to them as exceeding great
and precious promises.
We consider the simplicity of this promise
and he says, I will come again.
And we understand that throughout the word of God,
you will be sure of this one thing
that God always does what He says He will do.
Always.
He says, I will come again,
you can guarantee that He's going to return.
There are many people in our land,
there are many people throughout history
that have sought to make commitments
and to give some sort of a word to someone
and make some type of promise
that they were not in of themselves able to fulfill.
But I want you to understand that God Almighty
is able to fulfill everything that He's ever said.
And when He says, I will come again,
that ought to bring great hope and great joy
to the heart of every child of God.
The reality is that Paul, as he's speaking
and ministering to Titus,
he says that we're looking for that blessed hope
and glorious appearing of our great God and Savior,
the Lord Jesus Christ.
We understand something about that word hope.
It's not the context in which oftentimes today
we use the word hope.
Today we use the word hope as just a wishful type of thing
I hope this is going to happen.
I hope that's going to happen.
No, no, biblical hope is something that is based upon,
founded upon, secured on what God says.
It is an expectation.
I believe that the simplicity of this promise
will bring confidence to every child of God.
You think about the confidence that we have
that one day, even as they sang that song this morning,
listen, Jesus is coming again and we don't know the hour,
we don't know the day,
but we're to live with a level of confidence,
understanding that our God rules and reigns
and He is in control.
He is the Lord God omnipotent.
And oh, when He comes,
what a glorious day that'll be.
Many over the years,
I know Brother Mershon uses the phraseology often,
I'm not looking for the undertaker,
I'm looking for the upper taker.
I'm looking for, listening for that trumpet, amen?
The song, I think it was that second verse
as they sang this morning that special about,
I can almost hear the father say,
son, go get your children, right?
Listening for that trumpet,
I don't know who it was that wrote the song,
listen for the trumpet.
I know the first time I ever heard it, Ron Hamilton,
I'm not sure if he wrote that song,
but I heard him sing that song.
And oh, how we're to listen for the trumpet
because it will sound and the dead in Christ
shall be raised, will be changed, amen?
And you think about the confidence that we have
as we live life and we understand
that our Savior is coming again.
Think about these disciples
that had hearts that were troubled, troubled hearts.
What do we need in the midst of turmoil and trouble?
We need a word that will bring confidence,
a word that will bring calm,
a word that will bring assurance.
And we find that Jesus gave just that word.
He said, listen, I understand that your hearts are troubled
but let not your heart be troubled.
And He then gives them this wonderful promise
about His departure.
Of course, later He would give them other insights
with regard to His need to go to the cross of Calvary.
He said that it's expedient for you that I go.
It was necessary, it was advantageous
that He go to the cross of Calvary for human beings.
And we understand all that was accomplished.
But when He made that statement, I will come again.
I want you to consider the impact
that those words would have upon the disciples
and the impact that those words ought to have
upon you and upon me.
We think about the simplicity of the promise
that brings confidence,
but it brings a measure of expectation.
It brings a measure of expectation.
I wonder this morning,
I wonder as we go through life,
I wonder how often we are...
I'm mindful of the fact that Jesus may come back today.
I preached a message two Sunday mornings ago
about being ready for revival,
and I spoke about the statement
that often the question that will be asked,
are you ready?
And I said this in that message by way of introduction,
that the question requires context.
Am I ready for what?
Well, this morning, I asked the question
within the context of the Lord's return.
Are you ready?
It would be wonderful if He came
before I got done preaching this morning.
I mean, seriously.
Those guys up there in Pennsylvania
that are expecting me to come and preach,
I don't think they'd be upset for one second.
Why? Because we'd be with the Lord.
It'd be awesome, amen?
Listen, He could come at any moment,
and the question that we must ask ourselves this morning
is are we ready?
The expectation that this promise gives.
I mean, think about the disciples
when they're hearing this message,
and they're receiving this simple promise
that Jesus says, I will come again.
Well, when?
We understand that in Acts,
they begin to inquire,
and they want to know when He's going to set up His kingdom.
Turn over, in fact, to Acts 1,
and I want you to notice what is said
in this passage of Scripture,
and this is after the death and burial
and resurrection of the Lord Jesus Christ.
It's after He made Himself known to those,
and it made many appearances
by many infallible proofs, the Bible tells us.
We find that we come to Acts 1.
It's recorded for us also at the end of the book of Luke,
and the record that's given to us here
is really the ascension of our Lord and Savior Jesus Christ.
When He ascends and goes back to heaven,
and I want you to think about the words
that Jesus speaks to His disciples here.
He tells them in verse number seven, in verse six,
it says, when they therefore were come together,
they asked of Him, saying,
Lord, wilt Thou at this time
restore again the kingdom to Israel?
And He said unto them,
it is not for you to know the times or the seasons
which the Father hath put in His own power,
but ye shall receive power
after the Holy Ghost has come upon you.
And ye shall be witnesses unto Me,
both in Jerusalem and in all Judea and in Samaria
and unto the uttermost part of the earth.
And then the Bible says this in verse number nine,
and when He had spoken these things,
while they beheld, He was taken up.
Can you imagine?
I mean, Jesus is there having conversation
with His disciples.
They're speaking and they're asking Him
about the restoration of the kingdom.
Will you at this time restore again the kingdom to Israel?
And Jesus speaks to them and says,
listen, it's not for you to know the times or the seasons.
He tells them, here's your duty,
here's your responsibility.
You shall receive power
after that the Holy Ghost has come upon you.
And you're going to be witnesses.
We're commissioned to go and preach the gospel
to every creature.
And we find that here He listed as being Jerusalem
and Judea and Samaria and the uttermost part of the earth.
And while He's speaking those very words
and while the disciples are listening to Him speak,
the Bible says that they beheld
and it says that He was taken up.
Can you imagine?
I mean, honestly, can you put yourself there
and see as Jesus had just given
these last words of instruction
and now He's ascending up out of their sight.
He's taken up, the Bible continues and says this,
and a cloud received Him out of their sight.
Wow.
He was there speaking to them.
And then He rose, He was ascended up
and then the cloud received Him
and no longer could they see.
And the Bible tells us,
and you and I would probably do the very same thing
in verse number 10.
The disciples, notice what it says.
And while they looked steadfastly toward heaven
as He went up.
You and I'd probably do the same thing, wouldn't we?
I mean, it'd be an awesome sight, right?
I mean, man, He was just talking to us
and now He's ascending up out of our sight
and we stand there gazing up into heaven
and watching this scene that has just transpired
before our very eyes.
And the Bible tells us here in this portion of Scripture
that these angels, these two men stood by them
in white apparel and notice what they say.
Ye men of Galilee,
why stand ye gazing up into heaven?
And then notice this confirmation of the promise
that Jesus gave in John 14.
This same Jesus,
which has taken up from you into heaven,
notice, shall so come in like manner
as ye have seen Him go into heaven.
He said in John 14, I will come again.
And now these very disciples that were there
and heard the Word in John 14
are now watching as Jesus has ascended to heaven
and the cloud receives Him out of their sight
and the angels come and speak to them
and the angels said, hey, why are you standing here?
Why are you gazing up into heaven?
Don't you know that the same Jesus,
not another Jesus, the same Jesus in bodily form,
just as He rose from the dead,
just as He ascended to heaven,
this same Jesus, which has taken up from you into heaven,
shall so come in like manner.
Do you think for a moment
that perhaps these disciples
had a bell kind of ring off in their head?
You ever hear something
and maybe you kind of had forgotten about that,
whatever that is?
I mean, think about what has transpired
over the last, let's say, what, six weeks,
seven weeks in the lives of the disciples
because He showed Himself alive for 40 days.
And you think about all of these events
that had transpired from John 14 until Acts 1.
And over these weeks of time,
all of these things that had transpired,
perhaps that promise that had been given in John 14,
now as it's repeated, it's confirmed here in Acts 1,
that light bulb kind of goes off, right?
Man, He's coming again.
This is what He mentioned in John 14.
Remember that when the disciples,
remember, they had forgotten
that He said He was gonna rise again.
If you look at John 2, He says,
if you destroy this temple, I'll rebuild it in three days.
And He spoke of His own resurrection.
They had forgotten that until when?
Until resurrection morning.
And then all of a sudden they remember,
oh yeah, Jesus told us He was gonna rise again.
Well, Jesus told them He's gonna come again.
And now as He's ascended out of their sight,
these angels repeat, confirm,
this promise that He's coming again.
Do you think that it gave the disciples
a level of not only confidence,
but a measure of expectation?
I mean, if you read the book of Acts,
I believe that you're reading as the Holy Spirit of God,
as God worked through His people,
you're reading about a people
that were expecting the return of the Lord.
They were living in expectancy.
They were living that Jesus could,
we don't know when He's coming back.
He didn't give us the date or the time.
And so He just said He's coming again.
And so therefore, I'm living in that state of expectancy.
I'm expecting that He could return at any time.
And if we're expecting that He could return at any time,
the question that must be answered is, are you ready?
Are you ready for His return?
Are you ready?
Look over at 2 Peter, if you will.
It's a verse of scripture that we're familiar with,
but I wanna focus on this verse
just for a moment here this morning.
And I want you to just allow it to sink in.
Remember here in 2 Peter 3,
actually begin reading in verse number one.
We'll take a little time here
and look through these first several verses
in 2 Peter 3, but notice the Bible says this,
"'This second epistle, beloved, I now write unto you,
"'in both which I stir up your pure minds
"'by way of remembrance.'"
Listen, it's good for us to be reminded of some things.
Amen?
Peter's basically saying this to the disciple
or to those that he's writing to.
He's saying, listen, I'm not writing anything new to you.
I'm reminding you of some things.
I'm reminding you.
In fact, he mentions that even as he writes
the book of 1 Peter, that he was stirring up their minds
and he was trying to help them remember some things.
And we find here, it says this in verse number two,
"'That ye may be mindful of the words
"'which were spoken before by the holy prophets
"'and of the commandment of us, the apostles,
"'of the Lord and Savior, knowing this first,
"'that there shall come in the last days scoffers
"'walking after their own lust.'"
And notice what they're going to say
according to verse number four,
where is the promise of His coming?
Isn't it interesting to you that the scoffers
are aware of the promise that God has made?
The scoffers are aware of it,
but because of the length of time
between the promise given and the promise fulfilled,
there will be scoffers, mockers, that will say,
where is the promise of His coming?
For since the fathers fell asleep,
all things continue as they were
from the beginning of the creation.
And then notice this statement in verse number five.
The Bible says, for this,
they willingly are ignorant of.
You know, it's sad that we've come into contact
with individuals that are willingly ignorant.
They just don't want to know the truth.
It's not that the truth isn't available.
It's not even perhaps that you haven't tried
to present the truth,
but they just don't want the truth.
Of this, they are willingly ignorant.
It's not that the Scriptures don't declare
what Peter is getting ready to say.
Remember, he says I'm going to remind you
of some things.
This is not something new.
Notice what he says in verse 5,
that by the word of God,
the heavens were of old
and the earth standing out of the water
and in the water,
whereby the world that then was
being overflowed with water perished.
What's he speaking of?
The flood.
He's speaking of the flood.
You go back to Genesis 6-8
and you read about the flood
that God of course is judging.
Why?
Because of the wickedness,
the sinfulness,
their thoughts and imaginations
are evil continually
and God as a righteous, holy, just God
says they're going to be judged.
Now because He's gracious and merciful,
He has Noah, a preacher of righteousness,
preach for 120 years.
There was safety in one place.
That was in the ark.
It's interesting to note that the ark
had but one door.
There's only one way to enter into the ark.
There was only safety in one place
and that's in the ark.
And when the floods came,
when the rains came,
when the deep was opened up,
no doubt in my mind,
there were individuals
that had wished they had listened
and they had gotten in the ark.
The Bible doesn't tell us this,
but I do not believe that it's a far stretch
to have the idea that perhaps
when those rains came,
that there were people that sought
to get into the ark.
But you know what the Bible tells us?
That God shut the door.
God shut the door.
You know, those people didn't know
when the rain was going to come.
They didn't even know what rain was.
Right?
You study it, you understand it.
Noah says it's going to rain.
You're crazy, Noah.
They don't even know what rain is.
But the rain came.
And Peter says here,
they're willingly ignorant of this.
Listen, judgment came, the flood.
Jesus is coming.
They said, where is the promise of his coming?
Notice verse seven,
but the heavens and the earth,
which are now by the same word
are kept in store,
reserved under fire against the day of judgment
and perdition of ungodly men.
There will be a judgment again.
And we see that detailed in more
in verse number 11.
But I want you to notice in verse number eight,
the Bible says, but beloved,
be not ignorant of this one thing,
that one day is with the Lord as a thousand years.
And a thousand years as one day.
Now, why is that the case?
It's because our God transcends time.
He's outside of time.
Now, we are controlled by time, are we not?
We have appointments and we have calendars
and we have clocks and we have watches,
and we're controlled by time,
some of us more than others,
but we understand the way that time operates
in our society.
And the reality is that God is outside of time.
He says, listen,
I don't want you to be ignorant of this one thing.
I want you to be informed.
I want you to understand this
because they're saying,
where is the promise of his coming?
And though it's been over nearly now 2000 years
since Jesus ascended into heaven,
it does not mean that there's any less
of the promise, any less confidence,
any less expectation that we have.
In fact, our expectation increases even more
with each passing day
because we're a day closer, amen?
And here we find that he says,
I don't want you to be ignorant of this thing.
I want you to understand that our God is outside of time,
that one day is as a thousand years
and a thousand years as a day.
And so for us this morning in 2021,
it's been nearly 2000 years
since Jesus Christ went to that old rugged cross
and he bled and died and he was buried and he rose again.
And then after he'd made himself known and appeared,
he ascended to heaven giving that promise.
And here we are nearly 2000 years later,
but on God's timetable,
according to what we see here,
it's just a couple of days, right?
Because God is outside of time.
I want you to understand the significance
of verse number nine.
The Bible says this,
the Lord is not slack concerning his promise
as some men count slackness.
Aren't you thankful that our God
is not slack concerning his promise?
Listen, there will be scoffers,
there will be individuals that say,
hey, where is the promise of his coming?
I mean, you guys are preaching about
and you're singing about
and you're living with this expectation
that there'll be scoffers and mockers
that say, where is the promise of his coming?
And we just reassure and comfort ourselves
and have that confidence that our God,
the Lord is not slack concerning his promise
as some men count slackness.
No doubt in your life and in my life,
there have been times that we've made a promise,
a commitment to someone that we just flat out
were not able to fulfill.
It's not the case with God.
It's not the case.
Notice the conclusion of verse number nine,
but is long suffering to us word.
Aren't you thankful that he's long suffering?
And then it says this,
not willing that any should perish,
but that all should come to repentance.
There's some lost people that need to be saved.
I want you to just for a moment, think about this.
Think about the day that you got saved.
How many of you know the day that you got saved?
You remember, I mean, maybe not the exact day,
but you remember the time period in which you got saved.
I remember I got saved on August 31st, 1997.
I was 17 years old when I got saved,
senior in high school.
Each of you, you have a day
in which you trust that Christ is your savior.
Let me ask you this question.
When you think about that day
that Jesus saved your soul,
aren't you thankful he didn't come the day before?
You ever think about that?
What if he came back on August 15th, 1997
as before I got saved?
I'd heard the gospel, but I'd rejected the gospel.
I'd heard it for a couple of years at that point,
but I never accepted it.
I never trusted Christ as my savior.
And we can go around the room and say,
when did you get saved, when did you get saved,
and you know that date, that time frame, the year maybe.
Say, man, aren't you thankful
that God didn't come back before then?
See, because he's not slack concerning his promise
that some men cannot slackness,
but he's long-suffering to us-ward,
not willing that any should perish,
but that all should come to repentance.
There's going to come a day that he's going to return.
I don't know what day that is,
but I'll say this, for those that have heard the gospel,
they've heard that Jesus loved them,
that they're a sinner,
and they heard that Jesus, the sinless Lamb of God,
went to the cross of Calvary,
he shed his blood, he was crucified on that cruel cross,
and he was buried in a borrowed tomb,
and he rose in victory, conquering sin, death, and the grave.
He wants you to be saved.
Paul said this, today is the day of salvation, amen?
And you think about the significance of this promise
that he's long-suffering to us-ward.
I'm not sure when that last person
before the tribulation hour
is going to place their faith and trust in Christ.
I'm not sure when that's going to happen,
but I can be confident and I can have great joy
in knowing that our God is not willing
that any should perish,
but that all should come to repentance.
For God so loved the world
that he gave his only begotten Son,
that whosoever believeth in him should not perish,
but have everlasting life.
Why is it that we work on putting Bibles together
during our scripture assembly?
Why is it that we send money
to have Bibles printed in Samoa?
Because we want them to hear the wonderful message
that God so loved the world.
We want them to understand those that are in darkness,
those in whom the God of this world
hath blinded their minds,
lest the light of the glorious Gospel
should shine in unto them.
We want them to know Jesus saves.
Amen?
Why?
Because there's a real hell.
There's a lake of fire.
And the Bible tells us in Revelation 20
that the books are open.
And whosoever is not found written in the book of life
was cast into the lake of fire.
This is the second death.
Oh man, that's sobering.
Is it not?
Speaking of the simplicity of the promise,
getting back to the truth
that our God is not slack concerning His promise,
it brings confidence, it brings expectation.
I spent much time dealing with the simplicity
of the promise, but I want you to understand
the significance of the promise.
and the significance of the promise.
Why is it that we call it the blessed hope?
Why is it that we sing and rejoice?
Why is it that when we sing,
coming again,
and Dean is up here leading
and getting excited,
why is it that when Holly and Joseph
sang that song this morning,
when they practiced, I said,
hey, listen, don't get bothered if I join you.
I know the song.
It doesn't mean I'm going to sing it on tune,
but I know the song.
And I said, don't get nervous
if I start singing behind you.
Why does it cause us to be excited?
Why does it bring joy?
Because there's some significance
about this promise.
Turn to 1 Thessalonians 4 if you will.
I want you to first think about
the significance for us
as the people of God.
In 1 Thessalonians 4,
in fact, much of that special
that Holly and Joseph sang this morning,
you could look at 1 Thessalonians 4
verses 13-18 and you could see
how this particular portion of Scripture
had great influence upon the songwriter
who wrote that song.
And we notice in this portion of Scripture,
the Bible says this in verse number 13,
but I would not have you
to be ignorant, brethren.
We saw that in the book
of 2 Peter 3.
Listen, God doesn't want people to be ignorant.
He wants us to be informed.
He's given us a precious book
so that we could know.
He says, I would not that you be ignorant, brethren,
concerning them which are asleep.
Notice what he says,
that you sorrow not even as others
which have no hope.
You know that we're living in the midst
of a people that are hopeless.
They have no hope.
The fear of death has gripped,
literally gripped the lives of billions.
We see it all around us today.
Do we not?
In these last 18 months,
people that never gave really two thoughts
about dying have been absolutely controlled
by the fear of dying.
Why? Because they're hopeless.
They don't know what's going to happen
when they die.
I don't fear death.
According to Hebrews chapter 2,
one of the things that the Lord accomplished
on the cross of Calvary
is He delivered those that had the fear of death
from the fear of death.
Amen?
And notice He says this,
I'm thankful that we have hope.
Notice when He says,
but if we believe that Jesus died and rose again,
we believe that.
Even so, them also which sleep are dead,
that's the word, it's what it means,
in Jesus will God bring with Him.
Remember when Jesus tells the disciples
in John 11 that Lazarus was asleep.
And they said, man, if he's asleep,
let him sleep because he'd been sick.
And Jesus had to speak plainly to them
and said, Lazarus is dead.
That's a common vernacular that they would use.
And here He's speaking of those that died in Christ.
It says this in v. 15,
for this we say unto you,
notice what He says,
by the word of the Lord.
It's important for us to understand
that significant statement.
This is not just Paul's opinion.
We're not just sitting around a round table
saying, okay, what's your thought?
What's your opinion on this?
And how about you?
No, no, no, we're not looking for opinions.
We're looking for what thus saith the Lord.
Amen?
You can find many opinions around our world today.
You can find opinions,
you go and have surveys,
and you can ask people what they need to do
to go to heaven.
You can ask people all sorts of questions
about religion and so on and so forth.
And there's a plurality of ideas that exist.
The devil is not short on deception.
But what does God say?
Paul says, I am telling you this,
this we say unto you,
by the word of the Lord.
He actually says that we,
which are alive and remain unto the coming of the Lord,
shall not prevent them which are asleep.
You notice that in verse number 15,
it's a level of confidence and certainty
that are alive and remain unto the coming Lord.
He's going to come.
And there's going to be a group,
a generation of believers that are alive and remain
at the coming of the Lord.
Wouldn't it be great if we're that generation?
Amen?
It'd be wonderful.
And he says that we shall not prevent
or go before those that have died in Christ.
Notice in verse 16,
for the Lord himself,
isn't that what the angel said in Acts 1?
This same Jesus,
which you've seen go into heaven,
shall so come in like manner.
He says this,
for the Lord himself,
it's a personal return,
shall descend from heaven with a shout.
The voice of the archangel with the trump of God.
He says this,
the dead in Christ shall rise first.
I'm thankful that Jesus himself is coming to receive us.
He could send an angel,
but he's coming himself.
Isn't that wonderful?
It's sweet.
It's precious.
We see those that have died in Christ,
the reality is that we may not be the generation
that are alive and remain unto the coming of the Lord.
Why?
Because the reality is just as David said,
remember when David was being hunted by Saul,
and he says this,
there's but a step between me and death.
You know the reality is that for you and for me,
there's but a step between us and death.
Boast not thyself of tomorrow, Solomon says,
for thou knowest not what a day may bring forth.
We have plans for tomorrow,
but we don't know if we're gonna live tomorrow.
What is your life?
It's but a vapor that appears for a little time
and then vanisheth away.
That's what we find in the book of James
in the fourth chapter.
And so we find here that as the truth is,
we may die in Christ,
we may die before the coming of the Lord.
And if we do, we have this promise
that we're going to be raised first.
Because those that are alive and remain
shall not prevent them,
shall not go before them that are dead in Christ.
The dead in Christ shall rise first.
Notice verse 17, then.
And this is speaking to the generation that's still alive.
And I hope it's my generation, I really do.
Then we which are alive and remain
shall be caught up together with them in the clouds
to meet the Lord in the air.
And so shall we ever be with the Lord.
Isn't that wonderful?
He finishes the passage by saying this,
wherefore, comfort one another with these words.
Now think about the significance of that
where we started in John chapter number 14.
Let not your heart be troubled, right?
And so God, the Lord Jesus Christ,
He gave a word to those disciples
that had troubled hearts
that would cause them to have some confidence,
but also cause them to have some comfort
for their troubled hearts.
And here we find that Paul says,
wherefore, comfort one another with these words.
And we find here this morning,
that in fact, we could be that generation
that are alive and remain until the coming of the Lord.
And the Bible tells us
that we will be caught up together with them.
There's gonna be this great,
I mean, it's amazing what's going to happen.
The dead in Christ are gonna rise first.
By the way, this all happens in a moment
in the twinkling of an eye,
according to 1 Corinthians 15.
I mean, just bam, that fast.
According to 1 Thessalonians chapter number five,
right here, the next passage,
it says that he's gonna come like a thief in the night.
Okay, so it's just bam, it just takes place.
But the dead in Christ are gonna rise first.
Then we which are alive and remain
are gonna be caught up together.
And the Bible says together with them in the clouds
to meet the Lord in the air.
Then it says this,
and so shall we ever be with the Lord.
Man, that's wonderful.
That gives us a level of confidence.
I mean, listen, this is a significant promise.
It's a simple promise.
But when you begin to study the whole of Scripture,
you begin to dig into the Word of God,
you say, listen, this promise is significant to me.
This promise brings me joy and comfort
and confidence and expectation.
This promise is going to influence and impact
the way that I live my life.
Why?
Because He might come today.
What a joy.
We get to meet the Lord in the air.
He said, I go to prepare a place for you.
He says, if I go, I will come again
and receive you unto Myself,
that where I am, there ye may be also.
We have great confidence as the people of God.
Gives us great joy.
Listen, we've mentioned in the book of Hebrews
in the 11th chapter
that we're just pilgrims and strangers.
We sing the song, this world is not my home,
I'm just a passing through.
Amen?
My treasures are laid up somewhere beyond the blue.
I'm going home one day.
Listen, my citizenship is in heaven.
I'm an American citizen
and I'm thankful for the opportunity to be in this country
and to be a citizen of this country.
But most importantly is that I'm a citizen of heaven.
I'm a child of God.
And as a child of God, I have this great promise.
Listen, you understand that this promise,
the significance of this promise
as we're looking here in this portion of Scripture
is that it's significant to me as a believer.
But I want you to think about it for the unbeliever.
I want you to think about it for the truth that listen,
God is not slack concerning His promise.
He's not willing that any should perish,
but that all should come to repentance.
But we understand and we know this morning
that not all people are saved.
There are two groups of people in the world.
There are people that have been saved
that have been born again,
and there are people that are lost.
And by the way, all of the people that are saved
and born again were lost at one point.
Amen?
We were lost.
We were dead in our sins and our transgressions.
trespasses. We too had no hope. But God, you read Ephesians 2, it'll cause you to rejoice
greatly in your salvation. But God, we understand there will be people that have rejected this
message and they will enter into the tribulation. Specifically, I'm speaking of those that have,
I believe, received, they've heard the message, but they've rejected the message. And the
Bible tells us, I don't have time to read all of it, but in 2 Thessalonians chapter
number 2, really verses 3-12, if I had the time I'd read the entirety of the portion
of Scripture that is before us. But he's speaking about the return of the Lord and the midpoint
of the tribulation is in full view in verse number 3. And he speaks about the fact that
the mystery of iniquity doth already work. Listen, we see that, it's in verse number
7, we see that in our society today. The mystery of iniquity doth already work. Some people
are looking at what's taking place in our world today, in our country today, and they're
saying, things are falling apart! No, no, things are falling in place. You know why
things aren't falling apart? Because we serve the Lord God omnipotent. And he's in charge.
The heathen rage, right? I mean, they set up their plans on how they're going to the
kings of the earth, how they're going to overthrow, and God shall have them in derision. He laughs
at them. Psalm 2, right? You just go over there and read it. Our God reigns and He rules.
There's no way that things are falling apart. It's that they're falling in place and God's
plan and God's purpose will be fulfilled. We find that it says this in verse number
10 of 2 Thessalonians 2, and with all deceivableness of unrighteousness in them that perish because
they receive not the love of the truth, that they might be saved. Speaking of those that
had heard and rejected, it says in verse number 11, and for this cause God shall send
them strong delusion that they should believe a lie, that they all might be damned who believe
not the truth but had pleasure in unrighteousness. Those are sad verses of Scripture, to be honest
with you. There are some people that think that they can play a game with God. They feel
like that they can play with eternity. You know, I'm not really interested in trusting
Christ as my Savior now, but if all these things really come to pass that you say are
going to come to pass then, I'll go ahead and trust Christ then. It's not going to happen.
On the authority of the Word of God, it's not going to happen because God is going to
send strong delusion and they're going to believe a lie. I don't know how it all works,
but somehow they're going to believe that lie, the lie of the Antichrist, the lie of
the enemy. And so that's why it's so imperative that we understand that today is the day
of salvation. That's why it's so imperative when we think about this promise of His return.
Listen, the promise of His return is so significant for me. This simple promise is so significant
for me as a child of God and I rejoice greatly, but you know at the same time it causes my
heart to be burdened for lost people. It causes my heart to be burdened for lost people.
One of the nights of the revival meeting, the conclusion of the message from Brother
Edwards was that God would put a name on your heart, on my heart, and perhaps there's someone
that God has placed on your heart even then or maybe as you've continued to pray about
it, but the reality is this, we know lost people. There's someone that you work with.
There's maybe a relative. There's somebody that you know that's not saved. We don't look
down upon them. We don't judge them. No, no, rather we pray for them and we desire to share
with them the truth that they might be saved because we don't want them to come to the
place of the rapture and when we're taken out of here and we're forever with the Lord
that they are damned to believe a lie. And if you read about the tribulation, we understand
the significance. I won't have time this morning to get into it of how that really
is dealing with Israel again as a nation and all that's taken place with Jacob's trouble
and so on and so forth, but the reality is that you read about the tribulation in the
book of Revelation, it is an awful period of time. You read about the judgments that
are being poured out. You read about the death. Listen, they think we have a lot of death
now with this pandemic. It is nothing in comparison to what's going to happen during the tribulation.
They are going to collectively lose their minds. Honestly. You're going to go insane.
Destruction. We don't glory in that. Knowing the terror of the Lord, what is it, 2 Corinthians
chapter number 5? Turn over there if you will and I want you to think about what Paul says
here in this portion of scripture because the reality this morning is that when we think
about the significance of this promise that Jesus said, I will come again and those of
us that have been born again, we rejoice greatly, but at the same time, we ought to be mindful
of those that have not yet been saved. It ought to motivate us. It ought to cause us
to have a passion for souls. The Bible, excuse me, the hymn writer said, give me a passion
for souls, dear Lord, a passion to save the lost. Why? Because I understand their destination.
I understand, listen, I'm thankful that my eternal destination is secure. I am kept
by the power of God and if you've been saved, so are you. But what about the lost man? Verse
10 of 2 Corinthians 5, for we must all appear before the judgment seat of Christ that everyone
may receive the things done in his body according to that he hath done, whether it be good or
bad. Notice this, knowing therefore the terror of the Lord, we persuade men. But we are made
manifest unto God and I trust also are made manifest in your consciences. We don't have
time again to read through all of this, but notice what he says in verse number 14. We
hear a great message from Brother Savalle on this verse of scripture, for the love of
Christ constraineth us because we thus judge that if one died for all, then we're all dead.
Notice verse 15, and that he died for all, that they which live should not henceforth
live unto themselves, but unto him which died for them and rose again. Notice verse number
20, now then we are ambassadors for Christ. Who is the we? It's those that have been born
again. We see that in verse number 17, therefore if any man be in Christ, he is a new creature.
Old things are passed away, behold all things are become new. And so those saved people
that are being written to, we are the ambassadors of Christ. And we notice the significance
of verse number 21, for he hath made him, Jesus Christ, to be sin for us, who knew
no sin, that we might be made the righteousness of God in him. How many of you know the song
The Old Account Was Settled? It's a good one. I don't think it's in our hymnal, but man,
The Old Account Was Settled long ago. And if you get a good bass that sings that song,
man, they can get into that long ago, I settled it all, and so on and so forth. Man, it's
a great song. The Old Account Was Settled long ago. You know the significance of that
transaction, what took place? On the day that you got saved, on the day that I got saved,
if there's somebody under the sound of my voice today, whether they're here locally
or they're watching via live stream, that transaction could take place today. I have
nothing to offer. All of my good works are as filthy rags, according to Isaiah. For by
grace are you saved through faith, and that not of yourselves. It's the gift of God, not
of works, lest any man should boast. I understand that I have nothing to offer. I'm just a sinner
in need of the Savior. I'm just a sinner, and my sin condemns me. The Bible tells us
that he that believeth not is condemned already in John chapter number 3. Condemned. For the
wages of sin is death. But there's a God in heaven who loves His creation. And all the
way back in the garden, the picture that was first given of the sacrifice of an animal
for blood to be shed so that Adam and Eve could be properly covered, thus giving us
for all of that Old Testament history, the picture after picture, the Passover would
come on the scene in the book of Exodus, and all that would take place, the significance
that Christ, our Passover, would come. And He would die in our place. When we have nothing
to offer, God commendeth His love toward us in that while we're yet sinners, Christ
died for us. I don't deserve it. That's why it's called mercy. That's why it's called
grace. If we deserved it, it wouldn't be grace or mercy, right? It'd be what we deserve.
But honestly, what we deserve is hell. Because we're guilty. We're guilty. But God who is
rich in mercy. Ephesians 2, I think it's verse 4, maybe verse 5. God who is rich in
mercy. What a joy. And I have nothing to offer, but because of His death, burial, and glorious
resurrection, He who knew no sin, He was made sin for us. The innocent died for the guilty.
The payment was made. And it was accepted. And Jesus offers
us His righteousness, because all of my righteousness is filthy rags, not acceptable. But God says,
I love you so much, I died for you, and now I offer you my righteousness, that we, that
we are now able to have the righteousness of God. We call it the imputed righteousness
as placed upon our account. When God looks at me, when He looks at you, if you've been
saved this morning, He sees the righteousness of His Son, that we're washed in the blood.
We sing the song, Are You Washed? in the blood, the soul-cleansing blood of the Lamb. Isaiah
says, Hey, come, let us reason together, though your sins be as scarlet, they shall be white
as snow. Listen, this morning I'm thankful for the wonderful promise, I will come again.
I will come again. It's a simple promise, it's a significant promise, and we can rejoice
greatly and we can know this morning, listen, I don't know all that's going to happen between
now and then, but I know that one day I'm going to go be with my Lord. There's a whole
lot of people that we meet along the way that have not yet placed their faith and trust
in the finished work of Christ at Calvary. Oh, that God would motivate us to be bold
in preaching the gospel, that we would be His ambassadors, as it says in verse number
20 of this passage of Scripture, that we would understand the terror of the Lord and therefore
persuade men. God would work in the heart and life of the one that may be under the
sound of my voice that does not know Christ as their Savior. If they were to die today,
they have no idea where they'd go. Oh, that today would be the day of their salvation.
The Holy Spirit of God takes the Word of God and works, convinces of sin, of Christ's righteousness
and of judgment to come. So I place my faith and trust in the Lord Jesus Christ. The Bible
says, for whosoever shall call upon the name of the Lord shall be saved. Listen, Jesus
is coming again. But He said, listen, I'm coming again, but you have a job, you have
a responsibility. Work, amen, for the night is coming, the songwriter said, when no man
shall work. So we have an opportunity. You know something that's interesting? When I
go to heaven, when you go to heaven, whether that's through the rapture or through death,
I will never have another opportunity to share the gospel with someone. Only now do I have
that opportunity. Let's pray. Father, we love you. We thank you for loving us. Thank
you for the Word of God. Thank you for the truth of your return. I will come again. I
thank you for that promise. It's a simple promise, but oh, how impactful, how significant
this promise is. Perhaps this morning, there's one that does not have that same level of
joy and excitement about this promise because they've never trusted Christ as their Savior.
Oh God, I pray that you'd work in their heart and life. Help them to understand their need
for the Savior. I pray that before it's eternally too late, that they'd get saved. I pray for
those of us that have been born again, Lord, I pray that you'd help us this morning to
live with that expectation. As we observe the Lord's Supper, we're mindful of 1 Corinthians
11, you do show the Lord's death till he come. Help us to live that life of expectancy every
day, to be mindful that today could be the day. And Lord, I pray that you'd help us to
live in such a way that we would, knowing the terror of the Lord, persuade men, that
we would be your ambassadors, your representatives, that we would be faithful proclaimers of the
gospel, conveyors of the love of Christ. Use us, God, for your honor and glory. I pray
that you'd work in the time of invitation. You know the need of each one that's here.
I pray that you'd graciously work and move, and God, you'd be glorified. For it's in Christ's
name we pray. Would you stand with me? Heads are bowed, eyes are closed. No one's looking
around. Kimberly will play quietly on the piano. It's our custom at the end of our services
to have an invitation where we invite you to respond. The Lord, I've spoken to your
heart this morning. Maybe you're not sure of heaven. We'd love to take a Bible and show
you I can know for sure that heaven's your home. Maybe this morning you just want to
come and thank God for the wonderful promise that He's coming again. Maybe you want to
ask Him to help you to be found faithful, to live with that expectancy of His soon return.
As Kimberly plays, the altar is open.