this morning, Psalm 119 this morning, as we continue with our series here on Sunday mornings,
Great is the Lord.
And I'm thankful for God's greatness.
I'm thankful that we could stand and say, I know that the Lord is great.
And at the very same time, we can say that his greatness is unsearchable because every
day that we walk with the Lord, we just find out how much greater he is than we thought
the day before.
He is great.
And I've said this often over the years, but today in your mind, you have God at a certain
place, elevate it high, holy and lifted up.
And you say God is great, but he's greater than what you can even imagine.
And it is such a wonderful thing to understand the greatness of God.
We understand as we come to this portion of scripture over the last couple of weeks, we
have noted that God's greatness is revealed to us through the inspiration of his word
and the preservation of his word.
And as we've studied those passages that led us last week to deal with the fact that because
all scripture is given by inspiration of God, and because God who is eternal promised to
preserve his word from just this generation and forever, that God's word is sufficient
and it is superior.
And I am so thankful for those Bible truths.
And this morning, as we look at this declaration of the psalmist, we find that the psalmist
then is going to declare in Psalm 119, a familiar verse of scripture in verse number 97,
O how love I thy law!
It thy law is my meditation all the day.
Over the next two weeks, today and next week, you see that it's a part one message.
Next week will be part two.
We're going to discuss this portion of scripture, Psalm 119, looking at a variety of verses
of scripture.
But what I want to know is how the psalmist expresses his love for God's word.
But then next week, that's what we're going to deal with this morning.
Next week we're going to examine the evidence of this claim.
You know, we can claim anything.
But does the evidence support the claim?
I'll preach the message next week, but I will say this morning that absolutely the evidence
and the life of the psalmist supports the claim that he makes here in verse number 97,
O how love I thy law!
I want you to understand that we recognize this morning that we love God and we understand
that the book of Deuteronomy tells us that thou shalt love the Lord thy God with all
thine heart, with all thy soul, and with all thy might.
In fact, the psalmist declares in Psalm 31 and verse number 23, speaking of the saints
of God, it says this, O love the Lord, all ye his saints.
And then in Psalm 116 and verse number 1, the psalmist says this, I love the Lord because
he hath heard my voice and my supplications.
Of course, we're familiar with what John said in 1 John chapter number 4 and verse number
19 when he says that I love him, but we know that we love him, why?
Because he first loved us.
And I'm so thankful this morning that we love God and we should love God, and by the way,
there should be evidence of that claim as well.
We dealt with that last year as we studied through the book of 1 John.
Anyone can stand up and say I love Jesus.
But does the evidence support that you love Jesus?
Because he said if you love me, keep my commandments.
His commandments are not grievous is what he says, and that's true if we love him.
But this morning I want you to understand that because we love God, we find that we
should have a love for this book because it's this book that reveals God to me.
We sang the song this morning, holy, holy, holy.
How do you know that God is holy?
Because he tells us in his word.
Without his word, we wouldn't know that God is holy.
Wash me now, the song that Ms. Lorene sang, I mean really a prayer, and we looked at it
from Psalm 51 before she sang the prayer of the psalmist.
But I want you to consider this morning when we sing that song, wash me now.
What gives us the hope to even sing that song is but understanding that in his word, he
has told us that he is a God that is ready to pardon, a God that is ready to forgive,
a God that with him is forgiveness.
What a blessing to understand this morning, and I believe that the psalmist as he makes
this claim this morning, oh how love I thy law.
Why does he love the word of God?
He loves the word of God because the word of God reveals God.
I know God through his word.
Someone said this years ago, to know God is to know his word.
There are people that know about God, there are people that try to define who God is.
We live in a culture and a society today in which there are many people that are trying
to define who God is and try to explain, whether they be politicians or some level of athletes
or maybe some actors and what have you, and they try to define who God is.
I'm sorry, but God's already defined who he is in his word, and unless you're reading
his word and giving his word with regard to who he is, your opinion doesn't matter, amen?
Because God has told us who he is, and he's told us how we approach him.
He's a holy God, holy, holy, holy.
Think about Isaiah, in Isaiah chapter 6, when he sees God in all of his holiness, it is
broken, it is broken.
This morning, as we look at this 119th psalm, and we'll look at a number of verses, if you're
taking notes, I want you to notice with me number one this morning, and really there's
only one number one, there's no other points this morning, there's a bunch of sub-points.
Because part two will be next week.
But number one this morning, the psalmist expresses his love for God's word.
We see it in verse number 97, I believe, and it ends with an exclamation mark there, that
first statement in verse number 97, I believe that the psalmist, as he expresses his love
for God's word, he's declaring this with loud voice, with excitement, oh, how love I thy
law.
Begin to think about this declaration here, and the psalmist expressing his love for God's
word.
I want you to see that it's not just in verse number 97.
Notice with me in verse number 127, we're going to notice a few verses here where the
psalmist makes this comment or this expression of his love for God's word.
In verse 127, the Bible says this, therefore, I love thy commandments above gold, yea, above
fine gold.
Now that's a great verse of Scripture.
There are a lot of people today that love gold.
A lot of people that love fine gold, right?
The Bible tells us that the love of money is the root of all evil, and I think I mentioned
this before.
I was over at a pizza shop several years ago, and they had a tip jar.
By the way, you recognize today that everyone's looking for tips?
It's kind of interesting.
It never used to be that way, but all of this technology now, before you can sign for something,
it wants you to pick a tip, you know?
And it makes you feel bad if you don't pick what's there.
They just automatically populate it for you.
That's just a side note.
But in any case, they had a tip jar.
And on the tip jar, it said this, money is the root of all evil, therefore, leave us
a tip.
I promise you, that's what it said.
And I stood there, and my pizza wasn't ready yet, and I stood there, and I just pondered
that thing.
And I thought, what in the world am I going to say about this?
Because this is just, I've got to say something.
They gave me my pizza, and I said, hey, just so you know, the Bible actually says the love
of money is the root of all evil.
It doesn't say that money is the root of all evil, it says the love of money.
But I want you to notice what the psalmist says here.
He says, I love, therefore, I love thy commandments above gold, yea, above fine gold.
There are people today that put great value and great treasure in gold, in things, in
possessions, but we find that the psalmist, understanding the value of God's Word, he
says that I love thy commandments above gold.
Take my gold, but give me my Bible, amen?
Notice what he says in verse 162.
Connect it here with understanding the value, why as the psalmist is expressing his love,
he's understanding the value of God's Word, thus he's saying I love it.
Notice, I just absolutely love the imagery that God gives us in verse 162 of the psalmist
and his love.
I rejoice at thy word as one that findeth great spoil.
You think about somebody that finds great treasure.
Man, they rejoice, I mean, they're excited about that treasure that they found, that
great spoil that they found, that they had the opportunity to come and good fortunes
and so on and so forth, and here we find that the psalmist says that's how I rejoice at
thy word.
I wonder this morning, as you read your Bible this morning, as you read your Bible this
week, do you approach it that way?
That you're rejoicing in the same manner in which someone that would find great spoil
would rejoice?
Oh, when I read God's Word, I thank Him each day, thank you for giving me thy word.
Thank you for allowing me to have a copy of your Word
so that I can learn from it.
This is a valued possession.
My children knew as they were younger.
In fact, I still don't really let them carry my Bible.
When they were little kids, man,
they were not carrying my Bible.
You say, pastor, that's just silly.
There was just something about my Bible.
I didn't want them to drop it in a mud puddle or something.
It's my Bible.
I remember a preacher, a missionary,
he was actually here, and he was here a week after.
He was at another meeting.
I think, Brother Mark,
you and I were talking to him about this.
I don't know if you might remember this,
but he stuck his Bible on top of his car
before he left that church.
And he drove off without remembering
that he had set his Bible on the top of his car.
He was disappointed.
He went back, and he looked, and he looked,
and he looked, and he looked,
and he never could find his Bible.
And I just, I mean, you're supposed to rejoice.
This is the day the Lord hath made.
We will rejoice and be glad in it,
but man, it'd be hard for me.
I'm being honest.
He said, well, can't you just get another Bible?
Can, but man, if you read the Bible,
that's why I don't like reading the Bible on a screen.
If you read a Bible on a phone, on an iPad,
that's between you and the Lord.
I'm not saying that it's wrong.
I'm not saying that.
But there's something about holding the Bible,
something about being able to write in the Bible,
underline something, circle something.
Man, it's precious.
Here's what Job said.
He said this in Job 23, in verse number 12.
Neither have I gone back from the commandment of his lips.
I have esteemed the words of his mouth
more than my necessary food.
That word esteem means to treasure.
It means to set a high value on.
And you notice the value that he placed on it
because he says I have esteemed the words of his mouth
more than my necessary food.
In just a little while, most of us anyway
are gonna go eat something.
In a little while, somebody's stomach's gonna be reminding
you that you're ready for lunch.
And we find here that Job says I have esteemed thy words
more than my necessary food.
He's put this value on it.
Notice back in Psalm 119, notice in verse number 140.
He says this, and we dealt with this a few weeks ago
about the fact that God's word is pure.
Notice he says in Psalm 119, in verse 140,
thy word is very pure, therefore thy servant loveth it.
He's expressing his love for God's word.
In Psalm 119, verse 167, notice what he says.
My soul hath kept thy testimonies, and I love them how?
I love them exceedingly, exceedingly.
When you know the psalmist expressing his love
for God's word, I would ask a series of questions
this morning.
Number one, I would ask this, why did the psalmist
have such love for the word of God?
What was it, what is it that would cause you and I,
would cause the psalmist to say, oh, how love I thy law.
What is it about the Bible that should cause us,
we ask why did the psalmist have such love
for the word of God, but I would ask us this morning,
what is it about this book, the Bible, that should cause us
to echo the words of the psalmist?
Should we?
Absolutely.
We should say, oh, how love I thy law,
it is my meditation all the day, and we should echo
the words of the psalmist, but I would then ask
this question, it seems to me, and I'm not speaking
within just the group that's gathered this morning,
I'm talking about broadly speaking within Christendom
this morning, I wonder why it's such a rare thing today
to hear people say, to express their love for God's word.
You say, is it really that rare?
Well, as you drive around, even in our community,
and you see, you don't even have to go in
and talk to anyone, you can just see the evidence
that points to the fact that they do not love God's word.
What do you mean by that?
Just read some signs.
They're sending a message, and the message
that they're sending is a message that they have
no regard for this book, because the behavior
that they're following is a behavior that's not consistent
with the teaching of this book.
I was in the store the other day, I don't know
if any of you have these, you know, they want you
to give your phone number to, you know,
you're a valued customer at whatever place,
blah, blah, blah, they're gonna give you a discount.
I use Holly's number for all that stuff.
Glory, hallelujah.
And so, I gave, I was at some place,
and they said, do you have a number for the whatever,
and I gave them Holly's number, and they said, Holly?
I said, it's my wife.
And they said this, they said, well, you know,
these days, you just can't tell anymore.
I was like, let me set this record straight right now.
Holly is my wife, amen, and there is truth.
That's what I told them, there's truth.
We live in a world today where they seem like they,
well, you know, I gotta be careful.
If I say something, I could lose my job.
That's the pressure that people are feeling today.
And we find that there are churches,
within, broadly speaking, Christendom,
that obviously do not have a love for God's word,
because if they had a love for God's word,
they would obey it, they would preach it,
they would live it, correct?
Amen.
If we love the Bible, like the psalmist,
there will be evidence in our lives,
just like there's evidence within Psalm 119.
Next week, we're gonna look at 10 evidences from Psalm 119,
and there's more than that, but we're gonna look at 10,
as to how, so you get one point today, 10 next week, amen,
and we'll make up for it.
But the reality is that there are 10 evidences,
at least 10 evidences in Psalm 119,
that give us the support necessary to say
that the psalmist absolutely, as he made this claim,
it's not unfounded, no, it's very much sure.
What led to this expression?
He said, oh, how love I thy law.
Notice with me, again, a number of verses
within this great chapter of God's word.
I would say what led to this expression,
number one, the Bible gives wisdom and understanding.
The Bible gives wisdom and understanding.
Notice in verse number 98 of this psalm,
the Bible says this, right after, he says,
oh, how love I thy law, it is my meditation all the day.
Thou, through thy commandments, has made me wiser
than mine enemies, for they are ever with me.
I have more understanding than all my teachers,
for thy testimonies are my meditation.
That's now every young person's life verse.
Verse 100, I understand more than the ancients,
because I keep thy precepts.
You know, God's word gives wisdom and understanding.
Verse 104, through thy precepts, I get understanding,
therefore, I hate every false way.
Verse number 130, the Bible says,
the entrance of thy words giveth light,
giveth understanding unto the simple.
And in verse 169, the psalmist says,
let my cry come near before thee, O Lord.
Give me understanding according to thy word.
Listen, this morning, we need wisdom.
We need understanding.
We find that God's word, the Bible,
gives us wisdom and gives us understanding.
And I'm so thankful for that.
The Bible not only gives wisdom and understanding,
the Bible gives direction.
How many times in our lives we are praying for direction,
we're seeking that God would provide us with clarity,
with direction regarding our path, regarding our lives,
what are the next steps, and so on and so forth.
And we find that God will lead us.
Many times we look at the Old Testament,
we're aware of the truth that God led the children of Israel
a pillar of cloud by day and a pillar of fire by night,
and we think about the way in which God led his people,
and as you study through the Exodus
and look at God's leadership for his people,
and you see how specific God was in leading them
to the place where he led them
for the purpose that he had for them,
and God still leads us today.
I don't have a pillar of cloud or a pillar of fire,
but I have the Holy Spirit of God that lives within me
that will guide me into all truth,
and I have the whole canon of Scripture.
You know, in the book of Exodus,
they didn't have the whole Bible.
They needed that pillar of cloud by day
and that pillar of fire by night,
but now today we have the whole Bible,
and the psalmist says this in verse 105,
thy word is a lamp unto my feet and a light unto my path.
It's a familiar verse of Scripture,
but oh, how we understand that as the psalmist
would make this expression,
and we asked the question this morning,
what led to this expression?
Why did the psalmist say, oh, how love I thy law?
Well, it gives wisdom and understanding.
It gives direction.
I would say this.
The Bible defines right and wrong.
Thy word.
Word is truth.
We live in a society in which they want to remove morals.
They desire to legislate wickedness.
Not desire, they are.
It's no longer just a desire.
It's what they do.
They find that God's Word defines right and wrong.
And listen, it's not for you, it's not for me, it's not for us to have some level of
subjectivity with regard to right and wrong, evil and good.
No, God's Word is the authority.
And I love God's Word because God's Word tells me what's right and what's wrong.
When you live in a culture that's ever-changing, when you live in a people that are departing
from any level of morality, we go back to the standard and we say, no, God's Word defines
what's right and wrong.
And I'm thankful for that.
And it causes me to love God's Word.
Listen, God never changes.
People change.
But as I tether myself and my morals to God's Word that is unchanging forever, O Lord, thy
Word is settled in heaven, then I can define morals, I can define right and wrong regardless
of the year.
Regardless of how many calendar flips there are, we can define right and wrong.
Notice what the psalmist says in Psalm 119.
We read already verse 104, but the end of that verse says this, it says, through thy
precepts I get understanding, therefore I hate every false way.
The Bible exposes those false ways.
Verse 113, he says this, I hate vain thoughts, but thy law do I love.
In verse 128, therefore I esteem all thy precepts concerning all things to be right, and I hate
every false way.
Hey, what's right here?
What's wrong here?
Let's see what God's Word says, because God is the author.
I said this as we studied through Psalm 37, the Bible says in Psalm 37, as the instruction
is given to the believers, trust in the Lord, in verse number 3, and do good.
We ask this question, what does it mean to do good?
Good master?
Not one thing.
Why callest thou me good?
Who's good?
God is good.
That's what he tells them.
And so the good God that we serve is the God who defines what is good.
He defines what is good.
And this morning when we begin to understand this portion of Scripture of Psalm 119, and
understanding this expression that the psalmist gives, we've looked at for these last several
weeks now the inspiration of God's Word, the preservation of God's Word, the sufficiency
in the fact that God's Word is superior, and we look at those things and now we come to
the place that say, I love God's Word because I understand what it is, and I understand
what it does.
It gives understanding, it gives wisdom, it gives direction.
It defines what's right and what's wrong.
It reveals to me who God is.
To know God is to know His Word.
I said that by way of introduction.
But apart from this book, you can think of the most anti-God society or culture or whatever
this morning, and you can think of a people that are idol worshipers and so on and so
forth, and you can say, listen, we'd be in the same place if we didn't have a Bible that
revealed to us who God is.
The story of a missionary that went to a remote area in Asia many, many years ago, decades
ago, and he found as he arrived to that place that the people welcomed him.
There was some opposition leading up to the journey of all that would take place because
of the testimony, if you will, the reputation of that particular people group.
The missionary arrives and finds out that they're welcoming, and there's different reception
than what he anticipated, and he soon finds as he interacts with those of that particular
people group that there'd been someone that had come there and brought a Bible before
that person had arrived.
They trusted Christ as their Savior, and he found that there are many believers within
the village.
It was exciting because the chief of that particular place, as he spoke with that missionary,
he said, you know, it's a really good thing that this happened, that we received the Bible,
because had we not, we would have killed you and eaten you, because that's what we did.
The Bible made the difference.
God's Word changed their lives.
See, this morning, God reveals Himself to us through His Word.
I want you to consider very quickly this morning as we conclude, I want you to consider how
the Holy Spirit will use His Word.
How does He use the Bible in our lives today?
We see the expression of the psalmist, and we know how the psalmist expresses his love
for God's Word, and some reasons within Psalm 119 as to why he would make that declaration.
But this morning, I want you to consider just a few thoughts with regard to how God will
use His Word in your life and in my life today.
Number one, the Bible will convict you.
The Bible will convict you.
By the way, conviction's a good thing.
It's a good thing to be convicted.
Turn to the book of Acts, if you will, in Acts chapter number 24.
In Acts chapter number 24, Paul is giving his testimony here, his defense before Felix.
Sometimes people have the wrong idea.
They think that conviction is a bad thing.
I'm thankful that God, the Holy Spirit, will use His Word to convict us.
You know, there are times in which we need our toes stepped on.
Amen?
By the way, it's a gracious thing that God would convict us.
It's gracious of God.
As Paul was giving his defense before Felix, the Bible says in verse 24, and after certain
days when Felix came with his wife Drusilla, which was a Jewess, he sent for Paul and heard
him concerning the faith in Christ.
And as he reasoned of righteousness, temperance, and judgment to come.
Now, that's pretty interesting that the Bible speaks of that right there in verse 25 as
to what Paul's message was, because in John, the Bible says that when the Holy Spirit
comes, He's going to reprove the world of what?
Of sin, righteousness, and judgment to come.
And here the Bible says that Paul was preaching his reasoning of righteousness, temperance,
and judgment to come.
Notice what the Bible says, Felix trembled.
He trembled.
Why?
Because God's Word will convict you.
He trembled and answered, go thy way for this time.
When I have a convenient season, I will call for thee.
You know, we have conviction in our life.
There's really two responses.
One is what Felix does.
I'm done with this.
Get out of here.
I don't want to hear any more because I don't like the conviction.
Or we can surrender.
God convicts me and I change.
I respond.
There are people that have given testimonies.
My dad would share the testimony, a missionary, I think Brother Haley was here and shared
the testimony of someone grabbing the back of a pew, actually it was Brother Dan Hummel
on Sunday night a couple of weeks ago, and their knuckles turning white under so much
conviction and just refusing to go forward and submit to the conviction.
There are times in which people will leave, as Felix does, just they don't want to hear
it.
But I'm thankful that the Bible will convict us.
Listen, by the way, as God's people, we need conviction in our life.
There are times in which God needs to use His Word.
Listen, as I pray, as I read God's Word, God, would you show me, expose to me areas
in my life where I need to change, where it convicts me?
It's a good thing.
The Bible will convert you.
Notice what the Bible says in 1 Peter, we looked at this verse a few weeks ago.
In 1 Peter chapter number 1, I read this verse of scripture after the song was sang, the
special music, and we started here.
We were going to be in Psalm 12 to begin, but we started here in 1 Peter 1 on that particular
Sunday morning, and verse number 23 says, being born again, aren't you thankful to be
saved?
What does it mean to be born again?
They use the term today, again, I've mentioned this before, that there are many false teachers,
and here's what false teachers do, they'll use our terms, but they use a different definition.
I've been born again.
What does it mean to be born again?
Well, I was baptized.
That's not what it means to be born again.
Nope.
Is that right?
Biblically speaking, baptism does not equal being born again.
Now, if you're born again, you ought to be baptized.
First step of obedience, amen?
If you're born again, you ought to be scripturally baptized.
But being baptized does not mean that you're born again.
Remember what Jesus said to Nicodemus, marvel not that I said unto thee that ye must be
born again.
Praise the Lord.
The second birth, glory, hallelujah, when you trust the Lord Jesus Christ, your personal
Savior, understanding that you're a sinner and that He's the only one that can save you.
only Savior, and you can't get to heaven on your own. I talked to a man just on Friday,
the same guy that I gave Holly's number to, and I said this, I said, listen, do you go
to church anywhere? He said, man, and he kind of gave me an answer, and I said, let me ask
you this, are you 100% sure if you were to die today you'd go to heaven? Right at the
checkout line, no one else was in line, so I was able to ask him. He said, you know,
I can't say I'm 100% sure, but I'm okay with whatever because I know I've sinned. That's
what he said. That's what he said to me. And I said this, I said, you know, I just
use my credit card to pay for that transaction. I said, the reality is that no one at the
credit card company really cares who pays the credit card bill. I made the transaction,
so I'm responsible for it, but if my dad wants to pay for it, he can. Right? The credit card
company doesn't care, as long as it gets paid. Here's what I said, you've done some
things wrong. You just admitted that, that you're a sinner, but Jesus paid for it. Jesus
paid for it, and that satisfies the Father, and that's a glorious truth of God's Word,
the substitutionary atonement. And listen, God's Word, he says, being born again, not
of corruptible seed, but of incorruptible by the Word of God, which liveth and abideth
forever. Hallelujah for salvation. Listen, the Bible will convict you, it'll convert
you. Number three, the Bible will correct you. You ever have a time that you're wrong
in your thinking? Sure there are. Times that we're wrong in our thinking, and we need our
thinking to be corrected. We have a wrong perspective, a wrong view, and we find that
God's Word will correct us. In 2 Timothy 3, we've read this verse, all Scripture, in verse
16, all Scripture is given by inspiration of God and is profitable for doctrine, for
reproof, for correction, for instruction in righteousness, that the man of God might be
perfect, throughly furnished unto all good works. This morning, there are times in which
we need correction. Don't worry about somebody else that needs correction. Recognize that
there are times in your life that you need correction. You know what happens sometimes?
You don't like being corrected. Most people don't like being corrected. You know why?
Pride. Pride. Because in order to be corrected means I have to acknowledge I was wrong. Most
people don't like to acknowledge when they're wrong. Yeah, that was my dad, real loud. Have
you been wrong yet this year? Yeah, probably not. It's only March. Lying in church. You
better move, Mom. Pierre, you might want to back up too, amen? But understand that we
need correction. We need correction. God's Word corrects. Let me say this. This is precious.
God's Word comforts. I want you to think about this. This book, it's a living book.
And this book, all in the same session of reading it, if you want to call it that, and
time with the Lord, hearing preaching of God's Word, whatever it might be, that this book
can convict you and comfort you at the same time. It's amazing. Notice what the Bible
says in 1 Thessalonians. Look at what the Bible says. In 1 Thessalonians, these believers
of Thessalonica, there's confusion with regard to some things with regard to the coming of
the Lord and so on and so forth, and we find there's even more confusion as you look at
the second letter that's written, and Paul is giving them instruction, and we find that
it's a precious passage of Scripture in 1 Thessalonians 4, beginning in verse 13, and
going through the end of the passage, and we find that Paul says, I would, notice how
he begins in verse 13, but I would not have you to be ignorant, brethren, concerning them
which are asleep, that ye sorrow not even as others which have no hope. And we find
that Paul is desiring that these believers in Thessalonica, and of course it's been preserved
for us this morning, that we would have, that we would be informed with regard to these
things, and we find that he's speaking the Word of the Lord. He says that in verse number
15, for this we say unto you, by the Word of the Lord. It's not Paul just giving a pep
talk in his idea, his thoughts. No, he's giving the Scripture, and he's giving the Word of
the Lord, and he ends the passage of Scripture. I don't know how many times I've read this
portion of Scripture, and I've been encouraged with 1 Thessalonians 4 and verse 18, where
the Bible says, wherefore, comfort one another with what? With these words, these words.
See, God is the God of all comfort. You read 2 Corinthians chapter number 1, and you find
that to be declared for us. He is the God of all comfort, who comforteth us in all of
our infirmities. Every problem we have, God is the Comforter. Listen, the Holy Spirit
of God, one of His divine names that's described to Him is the Comforter. But you know God
uses His Word to comfort us. How many times we've had troubled hearts? Maybe as the disciples
had troubled hearts in John 14, after they heard all that Jesus had shared with them
in chapter 13 about the cross, and Jesus says, let not your heart be troubled. Why does He
make that statement? Because He knows that their heart's troubled, and He's going to
comfort them. Let not your heart be troubled. You believe in God, believe also in Me. And
then He gives them that wonderful promise that I will come again and receive you unto
Myself. You look at that passage in John 14, verses 1 through 3, how powerful that is.
In a group of men, these disciples that had hearts that were troubled are now able to
be comforted through the words of Jesus. You ever been in a situation where someone has
said to you, thank you for those words, they were a comfort. No doubt somebody said that
to you at some point in your life. Have you ever been in a place where you've been interacting
with somebody that's having a difficulty and you feel like you don't know what to say?
You ever been in that position? I just don't know what to say here. A loss of a loved one
or some other tragic situation, and we might be in that place where we feel like, listen,
speak God's Word, because God's Word gives comfort. Almost every funeral I've ever preached,
at some point I'm visiting 1 Thessalonians 4. Why? Because we sorrow not as others which
have no hope. And he says, wherefore comfort one another with these words. It's amazing
how God's Word comforts the heart of His people. The Bible will convict you, convert you, comfort
or correct you, comfort you. Finally, this morning, the Bible should change you. The
Bible should change you. The Bible tells us in James 1 and verse 22 that we're to be doers
of the Word and not hearers only. Of course, we're familiar with the song that we sing
with the children that's a result of the teaching of Christ about the wise man and the foolish
man. And we speak about that, or we sing that song and we speak about that portion of Scripture.
We find that in both situations they heard the teaching of Jesus, but one was obedient
and one was disobedient. One did and one did not. And this morning we think about the
Bible changing us. I wonder this morning, if you look at your life, if you look at your
Christian life, how much has God's Word changed you? How much has God's Word changed you?
You remember the maniac at Gadara? Jesus came, the living Word, and He spoke the Word of
God to him. And that maniac at Gadara was transformed. Why? Well, because the Bible
convicts, converts. No doubt it corrected. There was some comfort, understanding that
Jesus is the Savior. There was a change. Those people came back and they found that this
man who was demon-possessed is now clothed in his right mind and he's sitting at the
feet of Jesus. There was a change in that man's life. What do you think about Paul?
His name was Saul before he was converted. In Acts 9, he's traveling the road to Damascus.
He's traveling not alone, there's other people with him, but he sees this light and he hears
the Lord. Who art thou, Lord? I am Jesus. Can you imagine? Saul says, what wilt thou
have me to do? If you read Acts chapter 9 and you skip the middle portion of that passage
of Scripture, you will be confused beyond confused. Because Acts 9 begins with him
going to slaughter, going to arrest. And then you get to Acts 9 and verse 20 and the Bible
says in a straight way, he preached Christ in the synagogues, that he is the Son of God.
Saul, what happened? Jesus stepped in, changed his life. Would you acknowledge this morning
that Saul was never the same after this experience in Acts chapter 9? And I wonder this morning,
has God's Word changed you? Can you look in your life and can you see how God's Word has
changed you? I hope you can. And I hope that it continues.
continues to change us because we are to be conformed to the image of His dear Son, to
be like Christ.
And every day of our lives, we need to have this book a part of our lives.
Why?
Because it will convict.
I hope that you've been converted.
It'll correct, comfort, and change us, oh, that we would be more like Christ.
This morning, the psalmist declares, oh, how love I thy law.
What made him say that?
Well, he understood that the Bible gives wisdom and understanding.
He understood that the Bible gives direction.
He understands that the Bible defines right and wrong.
He understood that the Bible reveals who God is, thus declaring, expressing His love for
this book.
He didn't even have all that we have.
Oh, this morning, I believe that we ought to echo the words of the psalmist.
As we'll mention, as I've already mentioned and we'll look at next week, if we echo those
words, is there evidence that will support our claim?
Is there evidence in your life, is there evidence in my life that would support the claim that
I love this book?
Look at 10 things next week from Psalm 119 that reveal to us overwhelming evidence that
supports the claim of the psalmist, oh, how love I thy law.
This morning, I hope you'll just thank God for His Word.
Let's pray.
Father, we love You.
We thank You for loving us.
We thank You for the Bible.
We could not, we would not be here this morning if it wasn't for Your Word.
We could not sing the songs that we sang.
We could not rejoice in the things that we rejoiced in had we not had Your Word.
But I thank You for the expression of the psalmist, expresses his love for Your Word.
As we've sought to walk through the 119th Psalm to analyze why he would make that declaration,
I trust that this morning, each of us would echo the words of the psalmist, say, oh, how
love I thy law.
God, I pray that You'd help us.
Thank You as we should for this book.
Help us to never neglect it, set it aside.
Lord, I pray that You'd help us daily to get into Your Word so that Your Word would get
into our lives and change us.
Help us to be submitted to Thy Word.
I pray, Father, that as we rejoice and thank You for giving us Your Word that we'd be careful
to share the truth of Your Word with those that we come into contact with, knowing that
just as it's benefited us, it'll benefit them.
Just as it's changed us, it'll change them.
I pray that You'd help us to be faithful.
Lord, if there's one that's not sure of heaven, I pray that this morning, You would convict
them of their sin, of Christ's righteousness, of judgment to come.
Before they leave this place or log off of livestream, they would trust Christ as their
personal Savior.
Help us, Lord, now to respond as we should, and we'll thank You for it.
Would you stand with me?