I am thankful for God's Word and thankful for the truth that God has given us in His
Word and the guidance that He certainly provides us with, Joshua chapter 24.
And let me say this as we get into the message this morning, the purpose of preaching goes
beyond simply dispensing information.
And if we look at the idea, if we have the idea of preaching that it's just simply dispensing
information, we are wrong.
We have missed it.
Now obviously, as God's Word is preached and taught, we ought to be giving truth and dispensing
information.
But ultimately, the preaching of God's Word should bring God's people to a place of decision.
And that is the purpose of it.
It's not just so that we can have our minds filled with information and facts, if you
will, so that we might be able to win some Bible quiz or so that we might be able to
do well at some Bible trivia game.
That's not the idea.
The idea ultimately is that we as God's people would align our lives with the truth of God's
Word.
Let me say this.
It's not enough to simply respond to preaching by saying something like this, that was a
good message.
And it needs to go far beyond just being able to acknowledge from an intellectual perspective
that perhaps there was a good message that was given.
The goal, as I mentioned a moment ago, is that we would apply the truth in our lives.
So as we look at the truth of preaching and we think about the preaching that we've heard
in the last week, if you were here for all of the services of the Revival Meeting, you
heard six messages.
And I wonder, as we think about the Revival Meeting, as we think about every week that
we come to church, that we ask ourselves this question, how did I respond to what I heard?
What was it that God spoke to me about?
That's why we have prayer time before our service.
One of the reasons is because of the desire that we would say, God, I want you to work
in my life today, I want you to teach me something, to show me something, to reveal something in
my life that I need to stop doing or something I need to begin to do, and we have that time.
Of course, we understand that the Lord Jesus Christ, that His house should be a house of
prayer, and a couple of years ago I was deeply convicted over the fact that so often in our
services we would use prayer basically as bookends.
We open a service in prayer and ask God to bless, and we close a service in prayer and
thank God for blessing, and we needed to have some time that was designated to prayer and
asking God to work in our hearts personally.
And so as we have that time, it's God in these next moments as we sing, prepare my heart,
but as we open your word, speak to me and help me to understand what it is that you
have for me personally.
I could say this, not only is how should we respond, but what choices did I make?
Did I make any choices when I heard the preaching of God's word?
Was I brought to a place of decision?
As we look at the final three chapters of the book of Joshua, we find that God records
for us three messages that Joshua delivers.
In Joshua chapter number 22 specifically, we find that that message in Joshua 22 is
delivered to the two and a half tribes.
You'll recall from your Bible study and reading that those two and a half tribes, they spoke
to Moses and asked if they could have the inheritance on the eastern side of the Jordan
River, and as they sought the face of God, as Moses prayed about and sought God's counsel,
we find that those two and a half tribes, they were given that as their inheritance,
but they had the responsibility to go with their brethren to enter into the land of Canaan
to fight with them as they would conquer the land, and we find that they did.
They fulfilled their responsibility, and in Joshua 22, they're going to return back to
the land of their inheritance, and we find that Joshua addresses them specifically.
In Joshua chapter 23, we find another message that is delivered from Joshua specifically
in that portion of scripture.
It's to the leaders of the tribes of Israel, and we find that in Joshua 23, that's who
he's specifically addressing, but we come to the 24th chapter, the chapter in which
we'll be looking at this morning as we seek to look at this really a well-known passage
of scripture, but we find that in Joshua 24 that Joshua is addressing the people of God,
the people of Israel.
Notice in verse number one, and Joshua gathered all the tribes of Israel to Shechem and called
for the elders of Israel and for their heads and for their judges and for their officers,
and they presented themselves before God, and Joshua said unto all the people, notice
what he says, thus saith the Lord God of Israel, so this is not Joshua just delivering a message
of opinion of that which he thought that they needed.
He's giving them what God had for them.
He says, your fathers dwelt on the other side of the flood in old time, even Terah, the
father of Abraham and the father of Nacor, and they served other gods, and we find that
as he continues down, we're going to skip down through and look at this message that
he, Joshua, would deliver to these people, and notice in verse 14, he says, now therefore,
after he's presented the truth in verses two through 13, he says, now therefore, fear the
Lord and serve him in sincerity and in truth, and put away the gods which your fathers served
on the other side of the flood and in Egypt, and serve ye the Lord.
Verse 15, a very, very well-known verse of scripture, at least a portion of it, the Bible
says in it, if it seem evil unto you to serve the Lord, notice, choose you this day whom
you will serve, whether the gods which your fathers served that were on the other side
of the flood or the gods of the Amorites in whose land you dwell, but as for me and my
house, we will serve the Lord.
The people answered and said, God forbid that we should forsake the Lord to serve other
gods, we'll look further into the chapter as we get through the message this morning,
but we find that really, that latter part of verse number 15 is a very well-known phrase
of scripture, in fact, many of you probably have something within your house that may
have this portion of scripture on it, but as for me and my house, we will serve the
Lord.
As we look at this portion of scripture this morning, and really, as we leave the revival
meeting that we just had, and all of those truths just really fresh on our minds, I've
titled the message this morning, The Choice is Yours.
The Choice is Yours.
Again, as we understand the true purpose of preaching is not simply to dispense information
or facts, but it's to bring God's people to a place of decision.
And as we go through God's word daily in our lives, as we seek and read the Bible, as we're
seeking the face of God, every day of our lives, we ought to ask ourselves the question,
what does God have for me?
What is God showing me?
How do I respond this morning or this evening, whenever it is that you might read the Bible
personally, to what God is showing me?
As we gather in the house of God for the purpose of worship, we say, God, we want you to speak
to us as individuals, and then we have a choice, we have a choice.
Why do we have an invitation at the end of our service?
We have an invitation to give you an opportunity to respond.
You don't have to come to an old-fashioned altar to respond to the preaching of God's
word, but we do not want to just have a final amen and then everything's just gone and we
run out and everything.
No, we want to reflect upon what we've heard and respond to what God's done in our lives.
We want to make decisions, make choices.
As we look here in this portion of Scripture, if you're taking notes, number one, I want
you to notice what Joshua recognized.
Notice what Joshua recognized.
He says, now therefore fear the Lord, in verse number 14, and serve Him, the Lord, in sincerity
and in truth.
Put away the gods which your father served on the other side of the flood and in Egypt,
and serve ye the Lord.
He says in verse 15, and if it seem evil unto you to serve the Lord, choose you this day
whom ye will serve.
I believe that Joshua recognized some important truth with regard to the choices that people
make.
Number one, he understood the individual nature of choice.
He understood that every individual had a responsibility to respond to this message
that he was delivering.
He's the servant of the Lord.
He's the messenger of God.
He's giving them the word of the Lord, and he understands that he's going to bring them
to a place of decision, but there's an individual nature of choice.
Every single person has a responsibility to respond, to make a choice with regard to what
they hear.
We do not believe.
We just had in our Sunday school hour, we just spoke about individual soul liberty as
one of the points that we dealt with this morning, and I said this, that with the individual
soul liberty comes individual responsibility, and this morning when we see the individual
nature of choice, and Joshua recognizing this, he says, choose you this day whom you will
serve.
He's speaking to this whole congregation, and he's saying to them they have a choice
to make.
I would say this.
I believe that Joshua also recognized the importance of making the right choice.
You know, the reality this morning is that the man Joshua, the servant of the Lord here,
he understood the importance of making the right choice, but you know what he could not
do is he couldn't make the right choice.
the right choice for every individual.
Why?
Because there's the individual nature of choice
and just because I know, just because Joshua,
just because you may know the right choice to be made,
it doesn't mean that you can make it for the person.
Amen?
Everyone has their own choice to be made
and we find that Joshua understood the importance
of making the right choice.
He brings them to that place of decision.
He lays the groundwork, the framework.
He lays the foundation, he gives them the truth
and he understands the importance
of making the right choice.
Have you ever wanted to make a choice for someone else?
Make a decision for someone else?
You see someone that's going down a path,
maybe a child or maybe someone else,
you see them going down a path
and they're making wrong decisions, wrong choices.
You say, man, I wish I could make the choice for them,
make the decision for them.
But you know what you learn?
You can't.
But Joshua as the leader,
he recognizes the importance of making the right choice.
I believe he also understood and he recognized
the impact that our choices will have on others.
You know, you think about the impact of our decisions,
the impact of our choices.
They not only will affect us,
but they'll in fact affect, excuse me,
impact future generations.
They will impact, they will affect our brothers
and sisters in Christ.
And we find that decisions, choices have consequences,
but there's also great impact.
I want you to think about the book of Joshua this morning
and as you would think back to the battle at Ai
and you would consider what takes place.
And there were 36 men that lost their lives
in that battle of Ai the first time around.
And it was because the Bible tells us
that there was sin in the camp.
It's very interesting if you were to take the time,
we don't have the time this morning,
but if you were to study through Joshua chapter number seven
and you would find that that sin in the camp,
it was Achan, the troubler of Israel
as he's referred to in the book of First Chronicles.
And we find that he was the one
that took of the accursed thing.
The instruction at Jericho was clear,
the instruction was given,
but he, Achan, as an individual made a choice
to take of the accursed thing.
And I would say to you this morning
that that choice affected the entire congregation.
The entire nation of Israel,
there was sin in the camp and it impacted them,
it affected them, 36 men lost their lives.
If you study through the book of Joshua,
it's the only record that we have of anyone dying
in the time in which they went into the land of Canaan
to conquer and to divide the land.
You think about those 36 men,
you think there were families that were impacted?
Those 36 men, husbands, fathers, brothers, sons, right?
People are impacted, people are affected.
And so I believe that Joshua is bringing the people,
the congregation together here in Joshua 24.
He's saying, listen, he's recognizing
the individual nature of choice,
he understands the importance of making the right choice,
the correct choice, he understands the impact
that our choices are going to have on other people.
I believe as you look here in the text of scripture,
he also understands the influence of idolatry.
It's interesting how that in verse number two,
he talks about the gods that their fathers served.
He mentions it again in verse number 14.
He mentions it in verse number 15.
He's dealing with this subject of idolatry
and dealing with the influence of idolatry.
And I wanna draw your attention
to what he says in verse 23.
Notice what the Bible says in Joshua 24 in verse 23.
After they respond, and we'll look at that
in just a moment in greater detail,
but I want you to see what Joshua says in verse 23.
He says, now therefore put away, said he,
the strange gods which are among you.
And incline your heart unto the Lord God of Israel.
Now it's interesting because Joshua here,
he says to put away the strange gods.
Notice where he says which are among you.
There was some truth that Joshua was aware of
that there was already some that had some idols
that had them within their things, within their stuff.
And he says, put away those strange gods
which are among you.
By the way, if you were to go back
and you look at Rachel, remember she took the images
of her father and she hid them amongst the stuff
so much so that Jacob, he's talking to Laban
and he says, search and whoever they're found with,
they can die.
And Jacob didn't even know that Rachel had them,
but she did.
Now she lied to her father and she made up a story
and Laban didn't find them and then Laban and Jacob
are arguing about it, what have you,
but God knew and here Joshua says,
we think about this influence of idols and idolatry
and we know with the nation of Israel,
they're constantly dealing with idolatry.
As you study through the history of Israel
and you see over and over the idol worship
and the detriment that comes as a result of their idolatry
and he deals with and he explains to them
the fact that they must put away those strange gods
that were among them.
John says this, my little children, keep yourself from idols.
Keep yourself from idols.
We live in a time in which I believe some have the idea
that well, we don't have idols like they had idols
and we don't have the danger of idolatry
like the children of Israel had the danger of idolatry,
but we see that he says, keep yourself from idols.
We find that Colossians 1 tells us that in all things,
Christ must have the preeminence and truly this morning,
an idol is anything that takes first place,
anything that takes place of God.
There should be nothing in your life or in my life
that would take that place of primacy
that belongs only to the Lord Jesus Christ
that in all things, he might have the preeminence.
We may not have idols like they had idols.
We may not have figures that are crafted by individuals
that we set into some little cabinet somewhere.
We may not have that type of idol.
We know of places around the globe where they still have
that type of idolatry that takes place,
but for many today, an idol in an American's life
might be a job, a position, a paycheck,
sports, sports, sports.
Amen?
Honestly, it becomes an idol.
Things.
We find this morning that as we look at the text
of scripture, we find that Joshua recognized
some important truth with regard to choices,
with regard to making decisions.
He's bringing the people together and he's encouraging them
to make the right choice and he understands,
he recognizes these principles that we look to,
but we find that as we continue to look
through this portion of scripture,
number one, we said that we notice what Joshua recognized.
Number two, consider the resolve of Joshua.
I love this portion of scripture
and I love the resolve of Joshua.
We know, as I mentioned already,
that the latter part of verse number 15
is a very familiar verse of scripture
that many people would have on some type of material,
wood or something in their home that would declare,
ask for me in my house, we will serve the Lord,
but I notice the resolve of Joshua
as he's bringing the people to a place of decision,
as he's telling them, choose you this day
whom you will serve.
Notice whether the gods which your father served
that were on the other side of the flood,
he mentioned that in verse two,
or the gods of the Amorites in whose land you dwell,
remember they would be faced
with a bunch of idols in the land.
He says this, but as for me and my house,
we will serve the Lord.
I love the resolve of Joshua as it's given to us here
in this single statement of scripture.
And I see this resolve.
I see a man that understood the importance
of him making the decision,
even that he's bringing others to make.
See, he's encouraging others to serve the Lord,
but he himself is saying, I've made the choice to serve God.
I've responded to the same truth,
the same message that I'm delivering to you.
I have responded to this.
And by the way, that's good leadership, amen.
That's good leadership on the part of Joshua
to explain that, listen, I'm not just trying to get you
to as an individual within the congregation of Israel,
the nation of Israel to make a decision.
I've made a decision and I've chosen
that I'm going to serve the Lord.
Me and my house, we will serve the Lord.
Notice, I want you to see as we note this truth
in verse 15, it's interesting.
He made his choice known as a public choice.
He didn't just keep it to himself.
You know, there's accountability in that, amen.
There's accountability.
But as for me and my house, we will serve the Lord.
All of a sudden he stands down.
Notice where he's standing.
He's called all the people together and check him.
We see it in verse one.
In verse two, he addresses the people.
There's a huge group of people that are here
that he's addressing and he says to these people,
but as for me and my house, we will serve the Lord.
That's resolve.
But I want you to know that as he's made his decision
known publicly, that there's an aspect of accountability.
There are some times in which a decision that is made,
a choice that is made by an individual believer,
should be a personal, it should be a personal decision,
a personal choice, but I want you to understand
that at times when we make choices in responding
to what God tells us in his word,
that at times there's a huge benefit
in making that choice known publicly,
because there's accountability.
There's accountability.
Listen, by the way, accountability is a good thing.
It's good to be held accountable.
I remember as I was in Bible college,
I remember a fella that said to me,
he went to our church, he didn't go to the college,
he went to church, and he said,
he came to me after a special meeting that we had,
he said, I wanna know if you'd be
an accountability partner for me.
That was a great idea, a great opportunity,
and we would keep each other accountable,
and all of a sudden I realized real quick
that he really didn't wanna be accountable,
because all of a sudden I would try to give him
phone calls and text messages and just ask,
how are things going, and I wasn't trying to be a pest,
I was just trying to keep him accountable
and help him in his walk with God,
and he said to me, he said,
I wanna read my Bible every day.
I've been struggling with reading my Bible.
I wanna pray every day.
I haven't prayed like I should,
and I wanna do these things,
and so I'm trying to help him to stay accountable,
and then he'd just stop answering my phone calls.
He'd stop responding to text messages.
Unfortunately, that young man today
is actually older than I am,
is nowhere near a church this morning.
It's very sad.
Breaks your heart.
It's a good thing to have an accountability
to brothers and sisters in Christ.
Maybe your spouse is probably one of the best people
to have accountability to,
and you know what happens sometimes?
We get angry when we get asked questions
about being accountable.
It sounds good to be accountable,
but then all of a sudden we gotta answer a question.
I've said this for years.
Counsel is getting answers to your questions.
Accountability is answering the questions
that are asked of you, and there's a difference,
and this morning we find that Joshua,
the resolve of Joshua, but he makes his choice known,
and there's a measure of accountability in that.
Yes, there's an aspect of good leadership in that,
and letting the people know that he's made his choice.
I want you to note with me
that not only did he make his choice known,
but he did not wait for the people to respond
before he made his choice.
Listen, don't wait for someone else
to make a decision to follow Christ.
You decide I'm gonna follow Christ.
Don't wait for someone else to move in an invitation
when God speaks to your heart,
when God moves in your life about something specifically.
You don't have to wait for somebody else to respond
and then say, oh yeah, I think I'll respond as well.
No, I'm responding to God.
I'm not responding because somebody else responded.
I'm not making the choice
because someone else made the choice.
No, I'm gonna make the determination.
The Bible says I have decided to follow Jesus.
The song says I have decided to follow Jesus.
You think about the decision with that songwriter.
He says, though none go with me,
still I will follow.
Though none go with me, still I will follow.
See, this morning as we think about the work of God
and the way in which he works
in the hearts and lives of his people,
our God is an individual God.
I love that.
When we talked and we dealt with earlier in the year
about God's love and we spoke about defining
and describing the love of God,
we said that God's love is universal
for God so loved the world.
And I'm thankful for that,
but God's love is individual
in the fact that he loves me as an individual.
And as our God being an individual God,
you know what he does?
He works and speaks in your heart
and he works and speaks in your heart
and he works and speaks.
And God is able to take a message from his word
and minister to every individual
that's gathered together in a specific personal way.
It's amazing what God is able to do.
There's no way that a speaker,
someone that's just going to get up
and try to speak and give some kind of a message,
they can't meet, I don't know everyone's need.
But as I seek to follow the Lord
and seek to hear the voice of God
with regard to the message that's to be delivered,
then the Holy Spirit of God can use his word
and he can minister to each individual
that's gathered together.
It's amazing what God can do.
Joshua's speaking as he says,
here's what God says, he's giving God's word,
he's challenging the people.
There are times in which I've heard,
I've experienced in the 12 years of pastoring here
where someone would say,
man, this really helped me in the message today,
I made this choice and I'm like,
I didn't even know I said that this morning.
God was working, God's at work.
And so when we understand that God works individually,
that he's an individual God,
then God's working in your life
with regard to decisions and choices
that you need to make and we can go around
and we can say that about every single individual
and so we understand this morning
that Joshua, there's resolve,
he says, ask for me in my house,
we will serve the Lord.
He makes that known, it's public,
he tells everyone but he also makes the decision
before the people respond.
He says, I want you to know that your response
to this message has no bearing on my choice
because we're gonna serve God.
If all of you walk out, if all of you say,
no, we're gonna go ahead and serve
the gods of the Amorites,
no, we're gonna go ahead and serve the,
I'm serving God, amen?
And that's the way it should be.
We're not waiting for, listen,
I understand that it's nice when other people
are going in the same direction that you're going, amen?
It's nice when other people are going
in the same direction and they're making
the same choice and the same decisions
and they're responding but God's an individual God
and he's working in our hearts individually
and we see that Joshua makes that known.
Notice with me, not only do we find
that he's made it known publicly
that he made the choice even before the people responded
but I would say this, his choice was the right choice.
Would you agree?
He made the right choice.
We're gonna serve God.
We're gonna serve the Lord.
What a great choice.
You know, you're never gonna regret serving God.
You never will regret serving God.
You're never going to regret following
the leadership of the Holy Spirit of God in your life.
You're never gonna regret responding
to what thus saith the Lord.
We may regret not responding properly.
We may regret not doing what God called us to do,
what God prompted us to do
but you're never gonna regret following the Lord.
I believe that with all my heart this morning.
You're not gonna ever regret following the Lord.
We find this morning that this choice of Joshua,
this was the right choice.
We need to be careful that in our lives
that we're diligent to make the right choice,
to make the choice that's aligned
with what the Bible teaches,
that we would not be concerned with the crowd,
with the popularity.
We don't take a straw poll to see what the majority
of the people wanna do.
No, we say we're gonna follow the Lord.
If God before us, who can be against us?
And we understand this morning that Joshua,
he makes this choice and what a blessing
to consider this morning, the resolve of Joshua.
As we continue through the passage of scripture,
number three this morning,
we noticed the response of the people.
They made a choice.
They had a choice to make and they made a choice.
The Bible says in verse 16
and we'll read down through verse number 24.
Notice the Bible says,
and the people answered and said,
God forbid that we should forsake the Lord
to serve other gods.
That's a good answer.
It says in verse 17, for the Lord, our God,
he it is that brought us up and our fathers
out of the land of Egypt from the house of bondage
and which did those great signs in our sight
and preserved us in all the way wherein we went
and among all the people through whom we passed.
Are they correct in what they're saying?
Absolutely.
They're saying it's God that brought us out
from the land of Egypt.
And we can think about all of the signs and wonders
that God did in bringing them out of Egypt.
He said, they say that did those great signs.
Notice in verse 17, in our sight, they saw what God did.
They saw his greatness.
They observed his power.
And it says that he not only did those great works
to be able to bring us out of bondage,
but it says in preserved us
in all the way wherein we went.
You think about their journey from Egypt
to where they stand today in Joshua 24
as Joshua is addressing these people.
And you think about the wilderness wanderings
and you think about the entrance into
and the conquering of the land of Canaan,
the division of the land of Canaan.
And they stand there and they say, God has preserved us.
They're right.
It says in verse 18,
and the Lord drave out from before us all the people,
even the Amorites, which dwelt in the land.
Therefore, will we also serve the Lord for he is our God.
Did God do that?
Yes, he promised to do it and he did.
And we find that in verses 17 and 18,
they're responding appropriately to this message
that Joshua has delivered.
And they're saying, we will serve the Lord
for he is our God.
And Joshua said to the people in verse 19,
you cannot serve the Lord for he is an holy God.
He's a jealous God.
He will not forgive your transgressions nor your sins.
If you forsake the Lord and serve strange gods,
then he will turn and do you hurt and consume you.
After that, he hath done you good.
And that's interesting as you read that verse of scripture.
those verses of scripture there in verse 19 and 20 as Joshua is responding to the people
and he's helping them to understand, you know, the Bible tells us in Exodus 20 that our God's
a jealous God. He alone is worthy of our worship. Listen, God will not share His glory with
any other. Amen? He will not share His glory with any other. He alone is holy. He alone
is worthy. And we find that Joshua is trying to help these people understand the seriousness
of the decision that is before them and understanding the seriousness of the consequences of following
strange gods and getting wrapped up in idolatry. If you were to read through, and we don't
have time this morning, but to consider the book of Judges, there was a generation that
died Joshua and that generation they died and you begin to read through the book of
Judges and you begin to see how they served idols. And what happened? Well, God raised
up some people groups that brought His people under oppression. He brought judgment. Notice
it says in verse 20, if you forsake the Lord and serve strange gods then He will turn and
do you hurt and consume you after that He hath done you good. He's the one that brought
them into the land. He's the one that's provided for them as He promised to do so. But if you
read in the book of Judges you find that God was the one that would raise up these people
groups that would oppress the nation of Israel. Yes, God was faithful and He was merciful
and He was gracious to raise up a judge when His people would turn to Him. I'm thankful
that our God is long-suffering. He's ready to pardon and ready to forgive. I think about
Jeremiah. As Jeremiah is brought in and of course he was faithfully preaching about the
Babylonian captivity and we find that he's telling them, listen, this is the result of
your sin. This is the consequence for the choices that you have made. You're following
idols. You're serving strange gods. You're forgetting and forsaking the Lord your God
and all these things that they're guilty of. The nation of Judah and Jeremiah is preaching
and yet we find that on more than one occasion Jeremiah would be challenged with regard to
the message that he's delivering. The king comes to him and says, hey, do you have a
word from God? As if there's something different that Jeremiah is going to tell him. No, you're
going to be conquered. You're going to be destroyed. You're going to be taken captive.
Why? Because of your sin. At one point the people come to Jeremiah and they say, is God
going to fight for us? No. Jeremiah says, God's going to fight against you. That's heavy.
That's heavy. Why was God going to fight against them? Because of their idolatry? Because of
their sin? Let me say it this way, because of the choices that they made. And this morning
when we look here at this book of Joshua and this challenge, he's telling the people, listen,
the gravity of this decision, this choice that is before them, and we find that the
people then respond to Joshua in verse 21 and they say, nay, but we will serve the Lord.
We see a measure of resolve there in verse 21, even amongst the people that Joshua is
speaking to. And he says in verse 22, ye are witnesses against yourselves that ye have
chosen you, the Lord, to serve him. And they said, we are witnesses. Now therefore, we
referenced verse 23 a moment ago, he says, now therefore, put away, said he, the strange
gods which are among you, and incline your heart unto the Lord God of Israel. It's interesting
that even as they were saying that we're going to serve the Lord, that it seems as you look
at the passage here that there were some that even had idols within their stuff. Because
he says, put away the strange gods which are among you. Verse 24, and the people said unto
Joshua, the Lord our God, will we serve in his voice? Will we obey? I want you to notice
that in verse number 24. That's a good statement. As much as we appreciate the statement of
Joshua in verse 25, but as for me and my house, we will serve the Lord, we notice at the end
of verse number 24 that the people say to Joshua, the Lord our God, will we serve in
his voice? Will we obey? That's a good statement. That's a good proclamation. That's the right
choice. This morning as we begin to think about the choice is yours and begin to think
about the text here in Joshua 24, but then also bringing to mind that which we have heard
in the last week with various messages during the revival meeting. Again, if you were here
for the duration of the revival meeting hearing six messages with the preaching, again, not
just to give out information, to dispense information, but to bring God's people to
a place of decision. Perhaps in that moment of invitation during one of those services
that there were choices that were made, there were decisions that were made, there were
people that responded, but at times the Holy Spirit of God, listen, I'm thankful that the
Holy Spirit will continue to work in our hearts and lives even after we've heard the
message. Maybe we didn't respond right away. Maybe there was a measure of delay and the
Holy Spirit just keeps bringing something back to our mind and he keeps reminding us
of the truth and what we need to do and how we need to respond. Moses says this in Exodus
chapter 32 and verse number 26, who is on the Lord's side? Who's on the Lord's side?
We sing that song, who is on the Lord's side, and we understand that as we sing it and we
enjoy the opportunity to sing it, but we find that Moses made that question known in Exodus
32 after the people, you know what they did? They had just received the Ten Commandments,
the law, they got all this instruction with regard to the tabernacle and they made this
covenant with God and in Exodus chapter 32 they break the covenant. They disobey God.
They're serving a calf, an idol, right? That's what they're doing in Exodus 32. And as Moses
and Joshua are coming down, remember God tells them get down there into the camp and they're
coming and Joshua says it's like a sound of war and Moses is going in response and they
come and the people, they have defiled themselves. Moses says, who is on the Lord's side? Who
is on the Lord's side? I think about Elijah in 1 Kings chapter 18 and verse number 21.
We're familiar with the text of scripture when Elijah has that opportunity at Mount
Carmel to have that fire come from heaven, but before the fire ever comes from heaven
and consumes the offering, he stands before the people that are gathered together and
he says, how long halt ye between two opinions? If God be God, follow him, but if Baal, then
follow him. You know what the Bible says in that portion of scripture, they answered him
not a word. Can I tell you that that's a choice? No choice is a choice. You say, well that
doesn't make sense. No, it is. You're making a choice that you're not going to respond.
You're making a choice that you're going to put off, to delay. I want you to turn to
the book of Deuteronomy if you will very quickly. We're going to look at two passages of scripture
as we close this morning in Deuteronomy chapter number 11 and then we'll go over to Deuteronomy
chapter number 30. Look in Deuteronomy chapter number 11 if you will. You go back in history
as you come back to the book of Deuteronomy as Moses is giving the instruction to the
children of Israel before they would enter into the land. Of course Joshua, as we're
looking at Joshua 24, he would become the human leader of the nation of Israel. Of course
God was their leader but humanly speaking he would lead the nation of Israel. Moses
was not permitted to enter into the land of promise. He was told to speak to the rock
but he smote it and God would not allow him to enter into the land of promise and he died.
We read that in the book of Deuteronomy as far as his death is concerned. But we find
that as he's preparing the people for entrance into the land that God had promised them,
we find that on two occasions, and we'll look at both of these this morning very quickly,
but he brings the people again to the same place that Joshua was bringing the people
and speaking of this idea the choice is yours. Notice in verse 26, the Bible says this in
Deuteronomy 11 and verse 26. Behold I set before you this day a blessing and a curse.
A blessing if you obey the commandments of the Lord your God which I command you this
day and a curse if you will not obey the commandments of the Lord your God but turn
aside out of the way which I command you this day to go after other gods which you have
not known. As we look at these two, three verses of scripture, verse 26 to verse 28,
we see that Moses is saying to the people I'm setting before you, listen, a blessing
and a curse. But in verse 27 and again in verse 28 he gives the instruction with regard
to here's the choice that will lead to blessing and here's the choice that will lead to a
curse. Now it seems pretty obvious doesn't it? And I was going to use an object lesson
this morning but I chose not to and I was going to use an object lesson and sometimes
when you have a choice you don't know what the consequence of your choice is going to
be. So he says hey choose and I was going to have up here this table with all these
solo cups, you know the cups that we drink drinks out of and I was going to put some
money under one of them so that somebody could pick a cup and they'd get some money. But
here's the object lesson if you think about it. If I have 50 cups up here and I tell Tim
you pick a cup under one of them there's a $20 bill if you pick it you can have it. His
odds are pretty low. Right? One of 50. Pretty low odds. Now he may or may not and if I pick
put them all up here and he picked the right cup it would just destroy my object lesson
and so that's why I didn't do it this morning. But if he picked, likely he would pick the
wrong cup, it'd be empty. But here's what God does. If I could use that same object
lesson this morning and in your mind you can see it this morning, what God does is we see
here in Moses addressing the people of Israel, he says, I set before you this day a blessing
and a curse. A blessing if you obey. A curse is the result of disobedience. So if we were
to use that object lesson this morning, I'd say to Tim, Tim, there are 50 cups up here
and one of them has a $20 bill under it. If you pick that one you can keep the $20 bill.
Now Tim, before you choose, let me show you, this is the cup that has $20 underneath of
it, okay. So Tim, you're going to pick whatever one you want out of these 50 cups but this
is the one I'm showing you. Can you see the $20 bill? This is the one that has the $20
bill and I put the cup back down and I say, now you choose. Now if he picked one of the
other 49 cups, what would you think about Tim? She said he's stupid. Oh man. But you
would think, what is he thinking? You just showed him. Is that what you would think?
So what would you expect Tim to do if we went through that same process that I just
revealed and I said, Tim, now remember Tim, it's this cup right here. I showed you already,
now it's this one. What would you expect Tim to do? He would pick that cup up, he'd get
$20 and he'd go have lunch somewhere. God says, I set before you this day a blessing
and a curse. A blessing if you obey. But obey what? Well obey my commandments and by the
way I've given them all to you. I've preserved them for you. A curse if you disobey. Disobey
what? My commandments and by the way I've preserved them for you. And so God has done
his part to really make it simple for us. He says, I've given you all the commandments.
If you obey them, there's a blessing. If you disobey them, there's a curse. But the
choice is yours. The choice is yours. As much as I could try to help Tim to make the right
choice in picking the right cup, as much as some in the audience might say, no, no, no,
not that one, not that one, pick that, he already showed you, right? If you brought
a real little kid up here, maybe there was a cup that was pink and they just like pink
and they're going to pick the pink cup because that's the one that they like the most and
you're saying, no, no, no, no, no, no. You can't make the choice for them. And I feel
like at times that God's saying, my child, my child, I've given you, I've provided you
with the commandments, the truth of my word. Why are you making those choices? Why are
you choosing to disobey? Choose to obey, choose to follow, choose to submit. God says
this in his word that in keeping of them, in Psalm 19, a familiar passage of scripture,
the law of the Lord is perfect and we're familiar with the portion of scripture and we rejoice.
And it says that, moreover, by them as thy servant warned and in keeping of them there
is great reward. I want the blessing. I want the great reward. I want God's favor. But
it comes through obedience. Notice in Deuteronomy chapter 30, we'll close here with Deuteronomy
chapter number 30. I love what God says here through Moses. He's speaking to the people
beginning in verse number 11. I really want to get to verse 19. I may not read all of
the portion, but we'll read starting in verse number 11 and we'll eventually get to verse
19. It says, for this commandment which I command thee this day, notice what it says,
it is not hidden from thee, neither is it far off. You ought to thank God for that.
Verse number 11, you ought to thank God that His commandments are not hidden from us, that
they're not far off. Could you imagine if you were held accountable for something that
you did not know? Could you imagine if you were held accountable for something that was
not communicated to you? That would be tough. But God has been faithful. He said all scripture
is given by inspiration of God, but then He said He would preserve it for every generation.
I'm so thankful for God's Word. And Moses says here to the children of Israel, for this
commandment which I command thee this day is not hidden from thee, neither is it far
off. God has been faithful to give it. Moses has been a faithful servant to deliver it.
Notice in verse 12, it is not in heaven that thou shouldst say, who shall go up for us
to heaven and bring it unto us that we may hear it and do it? Neither is it beyond the
sea that thou shouldst say, who shall go over the sea for us and bring it unto us that we
may hear it and do it? But the Word is very nigh unto thee in thy mouth and in thine heart
that thou mayest do it. Wow. Praise the Lord. Verse 15, see I have set before thee this
day life and good and death and evil, that I command thee this day to love the Lord thy
God, to walk in His ways and to keep His commandments and His statutes and His judgments that thou
mayest live and multiply. And the Lord thy God shall bless thee in the land whither thou
goest to possess it. Look at verse 19, I call heaven and earth to record this day against
you that I have set before you life and death, blessing and curse. Therefore, choose life
that both thou and thy seed may live. Remember we mentioned about what Joshua recognized
with regard to the choice, the individual nature of choice. But we also spoke about
the importance of making the right choice. Notice Moses saying, I call heaven and earth
to record this day against you that I have set before you life and death, blessing and
curse. Therefore, choose life. That's the right choice. He says that both thou and thy
seed may live. The impact of our choice. We find this morning that Moses is bringing the
people here and then Joshua in Joshua 24, bringing the people to a place of decision.
You have to make a choice. In Luke chapter 12, the Bible gives us the principle that
we often refer to as to whom much is given, much is required. I'm thankful that God's
given us His Word. I'm thankful that we have the opportunity to read daily His Word. I'm
thankful, yes, as the pastor I know, to be able to have the privilege of preaching God's
Word regularly. But I'm also thankful for the opportunity to be able to hear the preaching
of God's Word and to be challenged by what God teaches us in His Word. And God brings
us to a place of decision. The choice is yours. This morning, maybe there's some choices,
some decisions that you need to make. Maybe through the revival meeting God was just working
and moving. But maybe you've just not made a choice. Maybe this morning through something
that was said, the Holy Spirit of God just kind of touched a spot in your life, in your
heart. And the question is not that we just dispense information. It's not that we just
say, oh, that was a nice message. No, what does God have for me? What is God doing in
my life? Because He's an individual God that wants to work in each of our lives and bring
us to a place of decision. We will serve the Lord. What a great decision, what a great
choice. But the choice is yours. I can't make it for you. No one else can make it for
you. God's given you the individual responsibility to make that choice. So this morning the choice
is yours. Let's pray. Father, we love you. We thank you for loving us. Thank you for
your Word. Thank you for the truth of your Word. God, I'm not sure how you might be working
in the hearts of your people. God, I trust that you're at work. I trust the Holy Spirit
is moving and working. And I pray that in these moments of invitation that just as we've
been ready to receive your Word that we'd be ready to respond. God, help us to determine
to obey you, to follow you. Lord, help us to dig into your Word daily so that we could
know your commandments and your statutes and your judgments so that we might apply and
keep them and do them. I pray, Lord, that if there's one that needs to make the choice
of trusting Christ as their Savior, they've never been born again, I pray that this morning
they would make that choice to trust Christ. Maybe you've been calling someone to the ministry.
Maybe you've been working through some other means in someone's life with regard to choices,
decisions, and how they're serving you. Lord, I pray that you'd just move and work. I pray
that we'd respond in obedience. We'll commit this time to you and we'll thank you for what
you'll do. For it's in Christ's name we pray. Would you stand with me? Heads are bowed,
eyes are closed. Kimberly's going to play quietly on the piano. We'll have a time of
invitation where you have an opportunity to respond. As Kimberly plays, the altar is open.