principles from God's Word. Amen. And praise the Lord for that. If you have your Bible
with you this morning, the book of James, James chapter number one. And last year we
studied through the book of 2 Corinthians and we finished up with a final message just
last Sunday morning and thankful for all that God taught us through that study and looking
forward to studying now through the book of James. And I've never preached through this
entire book. And so we're excited for the opportunity to do so. And I'll just read verse
number one this morning as we kind of get into the book. The Bible says this, James,
a servant of God and of the Lord Jesus Christ, to the 12 tribes which are scattered abroad,
greeting. I've titled the message as you've perhaps looked at the back of the bulletin
this morning, simply this, James, a servant. James, a servant. It is a joy to know the
Lord Jesus Christ as your personal savior. Amen. If you're here this morning and you
know for sure that heaven is your home, you have trusted Christ as your personal savior.
What joy that is. Can I tell you this? If you do not know the Lord Jesus Christ as your
personal savior, you've never been born again. You say, I don't even know what it means to
be born again. Can I tell you that today is the day of salvation? At the end of our service
we'll have opportunity for a time of folks being able to come and we'll be able to share
a Bible and show you how you could know for sure that heaven is your home. And I'd not
like for you to leave here without knowing that you have 100% confidence that heaven
is your home. For those of us that are saved by the grace of God, one glorious day we will
see our savior face to face. Isn't that an encouraging Bible truth? It's not just some
kind of hope and, you know, pie in the sky kind of a perspective. No, it is a confident
expectation that we have as the people of God that I've been born again, I've been saved
and one day I'm going to see my savior face to face and what a wonderful, glorious day
that will be. Until then, however, we are to live our lives daily to bring honor and
glory to the Lord Jesus Christ. I've said this last year many times as we study through
the book of 2 Corinthians, if you're saved, you will live with him forever. The question
is will you live for him today? And that really helps us with a perspective. In fact, I read
something just recently that I thought was such a great perspective on life and it said
so often as believers we do this. We say, I have to go to the grocery store to pick
up some things. I have to go over here to do this. I have to go to the bank to make
a transaction. I have to go to get some gas and so on and so forth. They said, as believers
why don't we change our perspective? And here's what they said. It was good. I liked
it. I need to go to the grocery store so that I can give somebody a gospel tract and while
I'm there I'm going to buy some groceries. I thought that's pretty good. And it's just
a different thought, right? Because why? I'm going with the purpose that I'm going to tell
somebody about Jesus because I'm going to encounter people. I'm going to the bank but
there's going to be somebody that I'm going to talk to and I want to share truth with
them. Oh, I have to make a transaction while I'm there but while I'm there I'm going to
be a witness. Amen? And I thought, man, that's a great perspective and something that would
help each of us. By God's grace and with God's help we're going to study through the book
of James in 2026 on Sunday morning. Someone said, Pastor, you know that there's only five
chapters. I do, but if you've ever read the book of James you know that the content is
so great and there's so much that we will be pressed to get through the entire thing
in one calendar year. And I'm looking forward to it. I'm excited about it. James is near
the end of the New Testament but actually the book of James is one of the first letters
written as far as the New Testament is concerned. So it's one of the oldest of the New Testament
writings and some of you might be doing a chronological Bible reading schedule this
year and you'll understand some things that the Bible is not laid out chronologically,
particularly when you look at the Old Testament. There's a lot of that that is there. But the
New Testament as well, and so when you think about the book of James, though it's at the
near the end of the New Testament in its placement within the canon, it's one of the earliest
writings of the New Testament. Why is it placed where it is? Well, it logically makes sense
to be with Hebrews and with 1st and 2nd Peter because those books coupled with the book
of James are not written to specific individuals or to specific churches that are more general
in their audience. We often refer to them as being general epistles and we find that
James is not written to a specific church. In fact, as we find here in verse number one
it says to the twelve tribes which are scattered abroad. We'll touch on that in just a moment.
James is a very common name. In fact, there are several people in the New Testament with
the name James and many people have tried to figure out who's the human penman. We know
that all scripture is given by inspiration of God, but God used men, holy men of God's
spake as they were moved by the Holy Ghost. And so who is this James that is the human
penman of the book of James? It is commonly agreed that this James is the half-brother
of the Lord Jesus Christ. And when you begin to think about that you understand I say half-brother
because of the, we just celebrated Christmas, the virgin birth and we understand that Joseph
is not the human father of Jesus and the miracle of the virgin birth. But the Bible tells us
within the Gospels some things about James with regard to the information that we'd find
as we move into studying the book of James, but I want to take you there and begin to
look at some things. Look first at Matthew chapter 13 if you will. And Matthew chapter
number 13 sets for us the truth that there's some siblings if you will, and again half-siblings
understanding that the virgin birth of the Lord Jesus Christ. But we find that he had
a family, Joseph and Mary. They would have more children and the children that Joseph
and Mary have are not in the same category as Jesus, amen, the virgin birth, the miracle
of the virgin birth. And so we find that as we come to Matthew chapter number 13 notice
what is said in verse number 53 it says, and it came to pass that when Jesus had finished
these parables he departed fence. And when he was come into his own country he taught
them in their synagogues insomuch that they were astonished and said, whence hath this
man this wisdom and these mighty works? So obviously in verse 54 the Bible says that
he came into his own country and so they would be familiar with him, with his family, they
would understand the dynamics there. And they say in verse 55, is not this the carpenter
son, who they're referring to Joseph the husband of Mary, is not his mother called Mary, no
notice, and his brethren James and Joseph and Simon and Judas and his sisters, are they
not all with us? When then hath this man all these things? And they were offended in him,
but Jesus said unto them, a prophet is not without honor, save in his own country, in
his own house, and he did not many mighty works there because of their unbelief. And
so we find the principle, the foundational truth in verse 55 and 56 of the existence
of these brethren. Okay, so we're trying to lay the groundwork here and understand as
we move into studying through the book of James that James is listed specifically in
Matthew 13 verse 55 as being a son of Mary and Joseph, thus a half-brother to Jesus.
Notice if you will over in the book of John in chapter number 7, and I'm going somewhere
with this and I hope that it would help us this morning because it's important when we
study through the book of James to have a grasp and understanding of who is writing,
who is he writing to, all of those things are important as we're going to seek to understand
the content of the book. In John chapter number 7, the Bible tells us about an event that
takes place, and I want to look specifically in verse number, we'll start in verse 1, it
says, after these things Jesus walked in Galilee, for he would not walk in Jewry because
the Jews sought to kill him. Now the Jews' feast of tabernacles was at hand. His brethren
therefore said unto him, so these are the same group of people that we just looked at
in Matthew, they said unto him, depart hence and go into Judea that thy disciples also
may see the works that thou doest. In verse 4, for there is no man that doeth anything
in secret and he himself seeketh to be known openly, if thou do these things, show thyself
to the world. But then notice verse 5 specifically, for neither did his brethren believe in him.
So what do we learn? The very people, the brethren that lived with Jesus, God in flesh,
they didn't believe him. How many of you ever heard somebody say, if I just saw Jesus with
my own eyes then I'd believe him? I'd say that you wouldn't. If somebody would come
back from the dead, well we read about that over in the book of Luke, amen, they have
Moses and the prophets, and so we find that
Those that grew up that were in the household
that experienced, the Bible says
that they didn't believe on him.
So when we begin to understand that,
we begin to see that here even at the Feast of Tabernacles
in John chapter number seven,
his brethren go and then Jesus would then go.
He tells them that he goes not up yet
and he eventually goes.
And so his brethren, they didn't believe him,
but they observed him.
Is that fair?
Do we understand?
We're kind of tracking.
And so we find that in the next several events
that take place in the life of the Lord Jesus Christ,
he's nearing when he's gonna go to Calvary, all right?
He's gonna go to Calvary, he's gonna bleed,
he's gonna die, he's gonna suffer,
he's going to pay for the sins of humanity.
And we understand that the Bible says
that he hath made him to be sin for us who knew no sin,
that we might be made the righteousness of God in him.
And can I tell you that we often say
that he died for the sins of the entire world
and that's so true and I'm so thankful
for that biblical truth.
And there we also understand
he died for the sins of his brethren, amen?
He died for the sins of Mary,
he died for the sins of Joseph,
he died for the sins of James and Joseph
and all of his siblings, he died for their sins.
Because he died for the sins of the world.
He was buried in a borrowed tomb
and aren't you thankful that three days later,
we sing it at Easter time,
we should sing it more frequently,
up from the grave he arose, hallelujah.
The tomb, it could not keep him, amen?
And he tore those bars away and we serve a risen savior
and 1 Corinthians chapter 15 is probably
one of the largest chapters dealing
with the teaching of the resurrection,
about the resurrection of the Lord Jesus Christ
and then how it affects us as believers, why?
Because he's the first fruits of all them
that slept or that have died
and so we understand that Christ is risen from the dead
but after he rose from the dead,
there was a number of individuals
and groups of people that he appeared to.
The Bible tells us in 1 Corinthians 15,
moreover, beginning in verse number one,
brethren, I declare unto you the gospel
which I preached unto you,
which also you have received and wherein ye stand,
by which also ye are saved,
if ye keep in memory what I preached unto you
unless ye have believed in vain.
For I delivered unto you first of all
that which I also received,
he's gonna give him the gospel,
how that Christ died for our sins
according to the scriptures
and that he was buried and that he rose again
the third day according to the scriptures
and that he was seen of Cephas, then of the 12,
after that he was seen of above 500 brethren at once
of whom the greater part remain unto this present
but some are fallen asleep.
After that, verse seven, notice specifically,
he was seen of, what's the Bible say?
James, you know who that James is?
It's the brother of Jesus, the half brother of Jesus.
Well, how do we know that?
Well, you see that he says that he appeared to Cephas,
then of the 12 and the distinction there
and so he appeared to him and it says then,
again in verse number seven, of all the apostles
and last of all, he was seen of me also
as of one born out of due time.
So what happens is we begin to look at this man James
and begin to understand the man that God would use
to write this epistle that we're gonna study this year.
We find that as you look here at the timeline
of the Lord Jesus Christ and you see
that during his earthly ministry,
though they lived with him, James did not believe in him.
He did not trust him as his own personal savior.
He saw him, he knew him, he knew what he did
but he didn't believe him, he didn't accept him
as his personal savior.
He would watch Jesus Christ go to the cross,
he would understand that he was buried
in that borrowed tomb and then Jesus appeared to him
and we go back to Acts chapter number one
and after those 40 days, after the resurrection
and before the ascension, Acts one records for us
the ascension, we find that God gave instruction
to his followers and he gave them instructions
about receiving the power of the Holy Ghost
and he gave them all of this instruction
as we begin Acts chapter number one
but I wanna draw your attention in the book of Acts
to chapter one in verse number 14
because the Bible says this,
these all continued with one accord.
Where are they?
Well according to verse 13, they're in the upper room
and the Bible says these all continued with one accord
in prayer and supplication with the women
and Mary the mother of Jesus and with,
what does the Bible say?
His brethren.
Presumably James is there in the upper room.
Something happened in the life of James.
Something happened that he observed the life
of Jesus Christ but he didn't believe in him
and he observed as Jesus went to the cross
and he observed and he heard and he was a witness
of those things and then Jesus appeared to him
and he's now in the upper room and something happened.
His life was changed.
He believed in Jesus.
What does it mean to believe in Jesus?
Not just to have a mental acknowledgement of who he is.
He lived with them.
He knew that he was a person
but to believe in him is to receive him
as his own personal savior.
His own personal Lord and savior.
James was in fact Galatians two in verse nine
as Paul is writing, refers to James as being a pillar
in the early church.
It's very interesting to see as you study
through the book of Acts, you begin to see
the prominent role that James had.
If you were to read and we won't take time
to do it this morning but in Acts 15,
the council that takes place at Jerusalem,
you find that there's a number of people that speak
but then James stands up and he's a pillar
in the early church, the church there at Jerusalem
and we find that God is using this man.
Of course, as we look quickly at these things,
we see the man that God would use to write
the book of James but then we find that the Bible says,
as we'd understand that the book is written
to Christian Jews that had been scattered.
Now the scattering of these particular recipients
that James is writing to in the book of James
is different than the scattering that we read of
in the book of 1 Peter.
See, Peter is writing to those that have been scattered
as well but when you understand the writing of Peter
and you find that he's talking about to the stranger
scattered throughout Pontus, Galatia, Cappadocia,
Asia and Bithynia, the timing of Peter's writing
aligns with the scattering that took place
because of the wicked Roman emperor Nero.
But the scattering that James is speaking about
is something different.
How do we know that?
Well, because that took place years earlier.
James was already, as far as we understand historically,
had already gone to be with the Lord before Nero
and all of that took place and so James is writing
and we have indication in the book of Acts,
look in Acts chapter number eight,
he's writing to these Christian Jews
that had been scattered.
Why were they scattered?
Well, there are some interesting things that happened
in the early church after the ascension
of the Lord Jesus Christ, the day of Pentecost
and thousands of people are getting saved.
I mean, it's a transitional period.
The book of Acts is such an interesting book
and you can correlate some things with the book of James
and the book of Hebrews as well from the book of Acts
and you find that that transitional period,
I've often said to people, there's only one generation
of people that ever lived through that kind of transition.
Let me explain it this way.
Before Jesus died, it was appropriate to go to the temple
and to provide sacrifice.
After Jesus died, it was no longer required.
When you're living in that single generation
that lived in that transitional period,
oh, the challenges that were presented.
And listen, the law is a shadow of good things to come.
Jesus came, hallelujah, praise the Lord,
we're no longer under that, but they were still living
kind of in that shadow, if you will.
And so we find that as we come to Acts chapter number eight,
thousands and thousands of people have been saved.
The persecution against the church is,
I mean, it is at reaching its pinnacle.
I mean, the Jews that killed Jesus are not happy
with all that's going on.
They've imprisoned, they've beaten,
they've threatened the disciples,
but people still get saved.
The gospel is still going forward.
The church is still growing.
And so they intensify the persecution.
Stephen is martyred in Acts seven.
And in Acts eight, the Bible says,
and Saul was consenting unto his death, speaking of Stephen.
And at that time, there was a,
notice what the Bible says,
a great persecution against the church,
which was at Jerusalem, and James is the leader.
The Bible says, and they were all scattered abroad
throughout the regions of Judea and Samaria,
except the apostles.
Devout men carried Stephen to his burial
and made great lamentation over him.
As for Saul, he made havoc of the church,
entering into every house and hailing men
and women committed them to prison.
Therefore, they that were scattered abroad went.
everywhere preaching the word.
So these people were scattered because of persecution.
It's a different scattering than what we speak of
as Peter deals with there in 1 Peter,
but we note here that these, the recipients,
the original recipients to this book of James
were Christian Jews, born again believers.
These Jewish people that had trusted Christ
as their savior, we understand that.
In James one, he talks about, he notes,
there's an emphasis on the importance of being born again.
He's not just writing to Jews generally,
he's writing to those that have been saved
by the grace of God.
By the way, there's only one way to be saved.
James talks about that in Acts chapter 15.
The Jew, the Gentile, they're saved the same way,
for by grace are you saved through faith, amen?
It's Christ alone and accepting him as your personal savior
and so he regularly refers to the recipients
of this book of James as brethren.
Now, it's not just brethren as in they're Jewish,
but it's brethren as in they've trusted Christ
as their savior, the way that we would use the term today
of being brothers and sisters in Christ, we're brethren.
And so we find that these brethren
that were scattered abroad, the Bible tells us
that they went everywhere, verse number four of Acts 8,
preaching the word.
But as they went out preaching the word,
they were met with opposition.
They were met with difficulty.
By the way, it's still the same today.
You go out and preach the gospel,
you're met with opposition, you're met with adversity.
Why?
Because the devil doesn't like it, amen?
The Bible tells us that the little G God of this world
hath blinded the minds of them that believe not,
lest the light of the glorious gospel
should shine unto them.
And we find this morning that there's opposition
when we seek to preach the gospel,
but there is power in the gospel.
I'm not ashamed of the gospel of Christ.
It is the power of God unto salvation
to everyone that believeth, to the Jew first
and also to the Gentile.
And we find here that as we look at the text of scripture
here in Acts chapter eight,
they go out and they're preaching the word.
Praise God that the word is going forth.
But I want you to understand
according to Acts chapter 11,
the Bible tells us something that's important
for us to understand with regard to the preaching
and who they were preaching to.
And in Acts 11 and verse number 19, it says this.
By the way, the Bible is an awesome book.
It really is.
And praise the Lord that God has divinely preserved his word
and we can understand the things
that God wants us to understand.
In Acts 11 and verse 19,
now they, which were scattered abroad,
notice under the persecution that arose about Stephen.
So we know that that's directly related
to the group of people that we just read about
in Acts chapter number eight.
And so these individuals,
these Jewish people that were persecuted,
that were facing that opposition,
that were in Jerusalem, they were scattered abroad.
And the Bible says that they traveled as far as Phineas
and Cyprus and Antioch,
but then notice the end of the verse,
preaching the word to none, but unto the Jews only.
All right?
Now, is the gospel just for the Jews?
No.
Is the gospel just for the Gentiles?
The gospel is for every human being.
Amen.
I just quoted from Romans chapter one in verse number 16.
And the reality is that the gospel
is the power of God unto salvation
to every single person upon the face of the earth.
Jewish people today, it's not popular, but it's true,
Jewish people today are not gonna go to heaven
because they're Jewish.
They will go to heaven if they trust Jesus Christ
as their personal savior.
The same way that Gentiles are not going to hell
because they're Gentiles,
they will only go to hell if they don't accept Jesus Christ
as their personal savior.
Does that make sense?
And so every single person upon the face of the earth
can be brought into two categories, saved or lost.
Born again or lost.
That's it.
There's no other category that matters.
In fact, Paul would say to the churches
in the region of Galatians,
he's writing in the book of Galatians,
that neither Jew nor Gentile,
I mean, circumcision availeth nothing,
uncircumcision availeth nothing.
Listen, stop worrying about that.
It matters what you've done with Jesus.
Have you accepted Jesus Christ as your personal savior?
If you have this morning, then you're part of the redeemed.
If you have not, you're lost.
But can I tell you that every single person
that's part of the redeemed, one day was part of the lost.
Amen?
Why?
For all have sinned and come short of the glory of God.
Every single person is born a sinner
in need of the only savior, Jesus Christ.
And there was a day in my life,
in fact, for 17 years,
I lived in that category of being lost.
And then on one glorious day,
I understood that I needed to be saved
and I trust that Christ is my savior
and I got put into that category of being redeemed,
being born again, not because of anything that I did,
all because of what Jesus Christ did
and the gift that he offered, which is eternal life.
And he offers that gift today to everyone, Jew or Gentile.
But specifically, as we look at the book of James
and we study through the book of James,
it is important for us to understand
who is writing James, being an extremely Jewish man,
writing to the Jews that are scattered,
an extremely Jewish audience.
But it's part of the canon of scripture.
So there's a benefit from this book for every child of God,
because the Jews that he's writing to
are not just Jews broadly,
they're Jewish people that have been saved,
that have been born again.
In fact, as I mentioned earlier in James chapter number one,
he speaks about the importance of being saved
and that truth that we find.
And he understood what it was to be born again.
In fact, if Jesus would say to so many as he did
during his earthly ministry, that you must be born again,
and he would preach the gospel,
no doubt his own brethren heard that message.
And they believed.
The believers, these believers encountered much difficulty
and God would use James to instruct and to encourage them.
The book that we're going to study here in 2026,
it's hard to say that by the way, 2026, man, it's amazing.
But the book is extremely practical in nature,
extremely practical.
It encourages the believers to live out their faith,
to do as we have here as our theme,
to be doers of the word.
It's not enough to just hear God's word.
It's not enough to just know about what God's word says.
Over and over throughout the scriptures,
we find that there's an emphasis that is placed
on applying God's truth in your life personally,
of living out your faith, being a doer of the word.
There are many subjects in which James will address
as we go through this book.
And again, being extremely practical in nature
and giving all of these practical instructions
with regard to so you believe.
What does it mean?
What does that look like?
If you believe, if you have faith,
how does that manifest itself?
So many times the book of James is misunderstood
as being a contradiction to the writings of Paul.
Why?
Because Paul focuses on faith and grace
and James has an obvious reference
throughout the book of works.
But can I tell you that Paul also speaks about good works?
If you read the book of Titus,
you see it repeatedly as Paul is writing to Titus
about good works, but we understand that those good works
never can save us, nor can those good works keep us saved.
It's simply the fact that because I have faith,
it manifests itself in good works.
Does that make sense?
What you believe impacts how you behave.
I told someone years ago, I was working,
I was in college, I was working at Payless Shoe Store,
they don't even exist anymore.
I was working in the mall on the second level,
I never worked in that mall, I didn't work there regularly,
I was filling in for someone and during the lunch break,
I was sharing the gospel with a person
and they said, I don't believe anything.
I mean, they were just really arrogant about it.
I said, really, you don't believe anything?
Nothing.
I was like, what about gravity?
Nah.
I was like, all right, step over this railing.
And they said, well, I'm not gonna do that.
Well, why not?
Because you believe in gravity.
Even though you say you don't.
You understand what I'm saying.
And so James is focusing on how does our faith impact us?
How is our faith manifested?
What does it look like in your life?
Listen, I don't come to church
so that I can be saved or stay saved.
I don't tell people about Jesus
I don't put an offering in the offering plate
so that I can be saved or stay saved.
No, all of those things are the result.
I don't read my Bible so that I can be saved.
We do it because we have faith.
We believe God.
We've taken God at his word.
Does that make sense?
And so the book is not.
Not to be misunderstood, there's not any discrepancies or contradictions.
We find that someone has referenced it this way, Paul might address more the root, where
James addresses more the fruit.
I think it's a good way to look at it.
And this morning as we talk about the fact that the book is extremely practical in nature,
it encourages the believers to live out their faith, spiritual maturity is in view.
Spiritual maturity, Warren Wiersbe said this, not all that grow old, grow up.
That's a pretty good quote.
Not all that grow old, grow up.
He went on to emphasize the difference between age and maturity.
There's a difference between age and maturity physically, but can I tell you this morning
there's a difference between age and maturity spiritually.
There's a difference.
I've been saying it for 47 years, praise God.
But if you're still a babe in Christ, you need to grow for the time that you ought to
be teachers.
I don't say that being harsh, I'm just quoting the Bible.
But the reality is that age doesn't equal maturity.
But what we're looking for is some mature believers, some individuals that are living
out their faith.
Can I tell you when we live out our faith we make a difference, we really do.
People can see our faith, they can see it in action, they can see that we truly believe
what we confess with our lips.
I said this before and it's not original with me, but the message of your life is louder
than the message of your lips.
That's why Paul says, and the things that ye have seen in me do.
Oh, he already had talked about the things that they heard from him, but he emphasizes
and the things that ye have seen in me do.
For the remainder of our time this morning I've given you a lot of information to really
kind of set the table, if you will, to set the foundation for our study in the book of
James.
But I want to go back to the book of James in the first chapter and I want to focus on
the opening words of this letter.
I've used it as the title this morning, just the first three words, but I'll read the total
statement, not the entirety of the verse.
James 1 and verse 1, the Bible says, James, a servant of God and of the Lord Jesus Christ.
What does it mean to be a servant?
There are several Greek words that are used in our New Testament that are translated servant,
several.
But there's one in particular, doulos, that is the most prevalent or prominent word that's
used and it's the word that's used here and it literally means a bond servant or a bond
slave.
You begin to think about understanding being a slave or a bondman and a couple of simple
definitions to help us understand.
It's one who gives themselves up to another's will.
It's one who is devoted to another to the disregard of one's own interests.
Literally bond servant, Christ has purchased us from the slave market with his own blood
and has set us free to serve him forever.
Begin to understand as we think about this truth here of what does it mean to be a servant?
If you're reading through the Bible book by book, you may have today or yesterday read
there at the Tower of Babel in the book of Genesis and it's very interesting as you would
look at, you don't need to turn back there, I'm just going to reference one phrase there,
but in verse number 4 of chapter 11, it says, and let us make us a name.
There's a lot of people today that are trying to make a name for themselves, a lot of people
today that are concerned about their position, their title, a lot of people today, I think
about James, he could have said James the half brother of Jesus.
Now I understand all scriptures given by inspiration of God, he could have said James the pastor
at Jerusalem, he could have said James a pillar of the first church.
James a servant, James a servant.
What does it mean to be a servant?
I think there's a great example or illustration in Matthew chapter 8.
In Matthew chapter 8, the Lord Jesus Christ is confronted during his earthly ministry
with an individual that has a need.
This individual is a centurion and he has a need and the need is that he had a servant
that was sick of the palsy.
The Bible goes on to tell us that he was grievously tormented and Jesus said this in Matthew 8
in verse number 7, I will come and heal him.
Could I tell you this morning that I think those words should bring great comfort and
encouragement and excitement when he beseeches the Lord that he has a servant that is sick
of the palsy, he's grievously tormented and Jesus says I will come and heal him, praise
God.
But the centurion says, I'm not worthy that thou shouldest come under my roof.
And he goes on to explain the authority that he had as a centurion and acknowledging the
authority that Jesus Christ, God in flesh had as being God.
And in Matthew chapter number 8 in verse number 9, he illustrates what it means to
him to be the centurion, the master if you will, but how the servant behaves and I'm
asking this morning, what does it mean to be a servant?
Well notice in verse number 9 of Matthew 8, it says for I'm a man under authority, having
soldiers unto me and I say to this man go and he goeth and to another come and he cometh.
And notice it says this, and to my servant do this and he thinks about it.
It's not what it says.
Do this and he doeth it.
Is that what your Bible says?
Why?
Because he's a servant and a servant obeys his master.
Amen?
Are we tracking?
Was it mean to be a servant?
Jesus would say this, we see it here in Matthew chapter 8 illustrated, but look over at the
book of Luke if you will in chapter number 6.
In Luke chapter number 6, understand that the Old Testament word Adonai, the name of
Jesus is master, or the name of the Lord is master or Lord.
Kiros is the Greek word that's used Lord in the New Testament that means master.
And we find here in Luke chapter number 6, now again keep in mind what does it mean to
be a servant?
Keep in mind what that centurion said.
That centurion's talking about the physical realm.
That centurion's talking about his authority as being a centurion and having soldiers but
also having servants and he says specifically that I say to the servant do this and he doeth
with it.
That's the physical realm.
But Jesus says this in Luke chapter number 6, in verse number 46, and why call ye me
Lord, Lord, master?
Why do you call me Lord, Lord and do not the things which I say?
Isn't that a convicting verse of Scripture?
I mean it truly is.
And when we think about the theme, be doers of the word, it's the idea if we could take
that physical illustration of the centurion in Matthew chapter number 8 and make the spiritual
application for us that Jesus is my savior but he is my Lord and my master.
And by the way, he is a good master, amen?
I mean he is a gracious master.
He is a good master.
And we find that as you begin to understand the truth that the Lord Jesus Christ, he gives
us this truth.
He says, come unto me all you that labor and are heavy laden and I will give you rest.
Take my yoke upon you and learn of me for I am meek and lowly in heart and ye shall
find rest for your souls for my yoke is easy and my burden is light.
In Matthew chapter number 11.
And if we make the spiritual application, Jesus says, why are you calling me Lord, Lord?
But you don't do the things that I say.
How easy at times is it for us to obey physically those people that have authority over us.
But we fail to obey our savior, our Lord and our master.
We are the doers of the word.
So we understand what it means to be a servant.
But let me say this to you as we look at James, just a couple of specific points.
You say, I already got a bunch of points.
Well, I don't.
This is my first point.
That was all introduction, amen?
It's going to be fast from here on out.
Can I tell you this?
There's a privilege of being God's servant.
There's a privilege to be God's servant.
James recognized this truth thus.
When you read...
James, a servant of God and of the Lord Jesus Christ.
I mentioned earlier that too often people are concerned about their titles and their
positions, but what we need to do as the people of God, those that have been saved by the
grace of God, we need to recognize and then rejoice that we are God's servants, that we're
God's servants.
And when we understand the privilege, listen, I'm not embarrassed to say I'm God's servant.
The fact is you read many of the New Testament books, you'll find that many of the writers
of Scripture, they begin their books by speaking about the fact that they are a servant of
the Lord Jesus Christ.
Why?
Because they understood the privilege of that position.
It's not a position to be downtrodden, it's not a derogatory statement, no, I'm a servant
of the Most High God.
He is King of kings and Lord of lords, he saved me, he's adopted me, yes, I'm a child
of his and I'm adopted, hallelujah, I'm a joint heir with Christ, but I'm a servant
of Jesus Christ.
And what a blessing, and what a privilege.
And we see that the privilege of being God's servant is in view here as we see that James
is a servant of God and of the Lord Jesus Christ, but I want you to consider with me
also really number two, if you will, the perspective of a servant.
What is the perspective that we must have?
My life is yours, Lord.
I'll say yes, Lord, yes.
We sing that little chorus.
I'll do what you want me to do, I'll go where you want me to go, why?
Because I understand that I'm a servant, amen?
I understand this.
If you look at 1 Corinthians chapter six, the perspective has to come from biblical
truth and the Bible provides us with instruction that will help us to understand this morning
the perspective that we need to have as a servant.
How many times we hear people, and I understand we hear people in the world say this, but
too often we hear people that have been saved by the grace of God that say something like
this, hey, it's my life, I can do what I want to do, I'm going to make my plans, I'm going
to do, no, no, no, no, no, no, no.
It's not my life.
If I understand my position as a servant, I must have the perspective of a servant.
It's a privilege.
But notice in 1 Corinthians chapter six in verse number 19 and 20, they're familiar verses
of scripture, but in verse number 19 the Bible says what?
Know ye not that your body is the temple of the Holy Ghost which is in you, which ye have
of God?
Notice this, and ye are not your own.
Why?
For ye are bought with a price.
Therefore glorify God in your body and in your spirit which are God's.
I'm not my own.
There was a day, listen, Jesus Christ paid for my sins over 2,000 years ago on the cross
of Calvary.
But there was a day that I accepted Him as my personal Savior, and on that day I was
bought with that price.
I understand, I'm no longer my own.
It no longer was right thinking for me to consider what am I going to do with my life,
what am I, no, no, no.
I now belong to Christ.
He's my master.
And here we find in 1 Corinthians 6, 19, and 20 this great truth, this great principle
that really is a life-altering principle that we understand and it guides us, it's
a guiding principle, I'm not my own.
When we sing so many of those wonderful hymns of the faith about surrendering all and living
for Jesus, it's all because we understand this principle that we find here that I'm
not my own.
I've been bought with a price.
By the way, aren't you thankful that you were paid, that you were valuable enough to God
that He paid for your sin?
Praise God.
Where would we be?
Lost on our way to hell.
That's where we'd be.
But I want you to also notice in Romans 6 when we talk about the perspective of a servant.
What is the perspective that we must have?
Well, in Romans 6, God gives us a truth here that's important for us to understand foundationally.
I don't have time to go through the entirety.
Verses 1 through 14 are great verses of Scripture.
In verse 14, the Bible says, for sin shall not have dominion over you for you're not
under the law but under grace.
But then notice in verse 15, what then?
Shall we sin because we are not under the law but under grace?
God forbid.
Know ye not that to whom ye yield yourselves, notice what it says, servants to obey, his
servants ye are to whom ye obey, whether of sin unto death or of obedience unto righteousness.
Notice verse 17 and 18.
Notice the contrast here.
But God be thanked that ye were the servants of sin.
Were is past tense.
He's writing to save people.
Some of you, if you're not saved this morning, it would say that you are the servants of
sin.
Why?
Because you're lost.
You haven't trusted Christ as your Savior.
So for those that have been born again, the Bible says, but God be thanked that ye were
the servants of sin but ye have obeyed from the heart that form of doctrine which was
delivered to you.
What's that?
The gospel.
And so I was the servant of sin but then notice in verse 18, being then made free from sin,
you became the servants of righteousness.
I wasn't free from being a servant to just be what I want to do.
I was made free from being a servant of sin and made a servant of righteousness.
So I'm still a servant.
And by the way, I'd rather be a servant of righteousness than a servant of sin.
Amen.
Sin shall not have dominion over you.
And we look here at this text of scripture and we say, praise God.
And that's why he begins in verse 17, but God be thanked.
Listen, I'm so thankful for the gospel that was delivered to me and no longer it's past
tense that I was a servant of sin, but now I've been made free from sin and I'm the servant
of righteousness.
So that perspective of being a servant is so important.
Yes Lord.
I mean really that should be our answer.
Is it not true?
We read the Bible when God's Spirit speaks to us.
Yes Lord.
The centurion, he said, I have servants and I say do this and they question me and they
disobey me and they delay and they, no, they do it because they understood what it was
to be a servant.
And I think what has happened so often in our generation today is we've forgotten what
it means to be a servant of the most high God.
And it is a privilege to be his servant and we must have that perspective that I'm just
a servant.
It's not about making a name for ourselves as we read there in Genesis 11.
It's not about what my position or what my title, it's about I'm a Christian and I'm
a servant of God and of the Lord Jesus Christ.
Can I say this to you in closing this morning?
The instruction that is given to us in the book of James is delivered to us humanly speaking.
We understand the inspiration of Scripture.
Please don't misunderstand what I'm saying.
We understand all Scripture is given by inspiration of God, but God used men.
In this book, the book of James, the instruction that's contained therein was delivered by
a servant of God and will best be received by those who recognize that they too are servants
of God.
If I don't recognize that I'm a servant of God, I'm going to have a hard time taking
and being a doer of the Word.
I'm going to have a hard time applying into my life the principles that James deals with.
Why?
Because God is above a servant.
You tracking?
So it's written by a servant and will be best understood by those who also recognize they
too are servants.
So we deal with all of the introduction to the book.
We talk about who's writing and who's being written to and all of the nature of the book,
but when it comes down to the first message of the book of James, it's James a servant.
And my question for you this morning, do you view yourself as God's servant?
Do you have that perspective that James is communicating to us in the very opening words
of this wonderful book, do you too say, I'm a servant.
I'm a servant of God and of the Lord Jesus Christ.
If not, can I encourage you?
Change your perspective.
He's your savior, but he wants to be your master, your Lord, and he's a good master.
He wants us to have that perspective.
that I am His servant. Think about that centurion. Do this and he does it. Our God says, I want
you to do this. You say, yes, Lord. Yes, Lord. Because my idea is that I want to be a doer
of the Word. I don't want to argue with God. I don't want to, well, that's the way that
you interpret it. I understand Peter talks about there's some things that Paul wrote
that are hard to be understood, but sometimes people take that kind of approach with very
simple straightforward teaching. Well, that's just your, no, no, no. You just don't want
to be a servant. You just don't want to obey God. And this morning, I hope that each of
us would have that perspective. Put your name in place of James. Chris, a servant of God
and of the Lord Jesus Christ. And you put your name there because really that's the
perspective that each and every one of us must have. You say, Pastor, I'm not sure of
heaven this morning. I've never been saved. You talked about being born again. You talked
about going to heaven and I just don't know. That's okay. I was there once too. In fact,
all of us were. In just a moment, we're going to have an invitation. We do it at the end
of each of our services. And what we do is we stand and we close our eyes and the piano
plays quietly. And as that all happens, this altar here is open for people to come and
pray and maybe they got a burden on their heart and they want to come and pray, but
also an opportunity for you, if you're not saved, to come and we'll have somebody take
a Bible, a man with man, a lady with a lady, and show you how you can know for sure that
heaven is your home. Why? Because I don't want you to leave here. I don't want you to
leave here without knowing for sure that heaven is your home because it's the most
important thing in all of the world. Let's pray together. Father, we love you. We thank
you so much for loving us. We thank you for the Word of God. We thank you for the truth
that's contained therein and for the opportunity that we've had to study it just a little bit
this morning. Lord, I pray that you would help those that are saved this morning to
have the perspective of James, that we're servants, we're privileged. Help us to have
that proper perspective, to be mindful day in and day out that we've been bought with
a price, that we're not our own, that God, we would magnify and exalt you with our lives,
that we would be doers of the Word and not hearers only. Lord, I pray, maybe there's
one here this morning, maybe one tuned in via live stream that's not sure of heaven,
if they were to die today, they have no idea that heaven is their home. They hope so. They'd
like to think so, but they just don't know. God, I pray that you would move in their hearts
and help them to come so that we could take a Bible and show them how they could know
for sure they'd be saved, be born again. Lord, I pray that you would be honored and glorified
through every decision that's made. For it's in Christ's name we pray. Would you stand
with me? Heads are bowed, eyes are closed. No one's looking around. I'd never embarrass
anyone, but we want to give you an opportunity to respond. Maybe this morning someone wants
to come and just thank God that you're a servant of His, that He saved you, that you're no
longer a servant of sin, but a servant of righteousness. Maybe this morning you're not
sure of heaven. Holly's here. If you're a lady, she'll take a Bible and show you how
you could know for sure. Mark is here. If you're a man, take a Bible, show you how you could
know for sure. Kimberly's going to play quietly on the piano, and as she does, the altar is open.