Chapter number 3, as you've got your place there, I want you to also, if you would, hold
your place in Ephesians chapter number 5.
We will make some reference back to the 5th chapter of the book of Ephesians, and really
into the first few verses of chapter number 6 this morning as well, as we look at this
portion of Scripture.
You'll remember that in Colossians 3, verses 5 through 14, as we've been studying over
the last several weeks, that we have been instructed to crucify our flesh, to put off
the old man and his deeds, and to put on the new man.
We find that the process of sanctification is in view in this passage of Scripture, and
I believe that we are given practical insight regarding our walk with the Lord.
Truly, we find that we have the responsibility to walk in the Spirit so that we do not fulfill
the lust of the flesh.
And we find that as we look at this portion of Scripture that we've studied over the last
several weeks, you continue to read through the passage, and you find even as we looked
last week at verses 15 through 17, that it appears quite obvious that as we take heed
to the instruction given in verses 5 through 14, that it will have an impact on our behavior.
When we crucify our flesh, when we put off the old man, the flesh, and the deeds, and
we put on the new man, and we walk in the Spirit, we find that it will impact, it will
affect the way that we live, it will affect our behavior.
I've often said over the years that belief impacts behavior.
It is true also that behavior reveals belief.
And we find this morning that as we look at this portion of Scripture that even as we
discussed last week in verses 15 through 17, we noted the behavior of God's people in God's
house.
And I'm thankful that God gives us instruction for behavior in the house of God.
And we find that as we looked at this portion last week, we said that our behavior in the
church house should be characterized by five things.
By peace, by unity, devotion.
Let the Word of Christ dwell in you richly in all wisdom.
We talked about that devotion and how appropriate to hear Brother Savalle share about the Word
of God making such an impact in the believers in the church.
And that's how it's supposed to work, amen?
And so we see peace and unity and devotion, and then purpose.
All that we do is to bring honor and glory to the Lord Jesus Christ that He alone would
be exalted.
And then finally, we looked at that last idea from really all three of the verses that our
behavior should be characterized by praise.
And we are to enter into His gates with thanksgiving.
Let everything that hath breath praise the Lord, praise ye the Lord.
He is worthy of our worship.
He is worthy of our praise.
And so we find that the first aspect of our behavior that is dealt with in this portion
of Scripture is with regard to our behavior in the church house.
This morning we'll be focusing on verses 18 through 21, and as we look at these few verses
of Scripture, we find that the focus now shifts to the home.
We know, we understand biblically that it was God that designed the home.
You understand that all the way back in the Garden of Eden, as we read the book of Genesis,
that God instituted the home.
I'm thankful that the home is not the idea of man, that we're not relying upon the instruction
of man.
We find that God is the author of the home.
He's intended for the home to follow the instruction that He has provided in His Word.
And we find that as we would take the instruction that He's provided in His Word with regard
to the home, I believe this morning that we can have a home that thrives, not just
survival mode.
You know, there are a lot of homes in America today that are on survival mode.
There are a lot of homes...listen, the home is under attack.
Amen?
We see it all around our society.
We see it everywhere in which we go.
You do not have to look very far.
It's very apparent that the home is under serious attack.
We understand that the enemy attacks everything that God designs.
Amen?
And God designed the home, and we find that the home is now under attack.
And we find that as we consider the home, and we consider this which is in front of
us this morning, I believe that we can have a home where the Lord is honored.
And that's the title for the message this morning, a home where the Lord is honored.
I want you to notice with me as we look at this portion of Scripture, begin with me in
verse number 18.
The Bible says this,
Wives, submit yourselves unto your own husbands, as it is fit in the Lord.
Husbands, love your wives, and be not bitter against them.
Children, obey your parents in all things, for this is well-pleasing unto the Lord.
Fathers, provoke not your children to anger, lest they be discouraged.
I believe this morning that a strong church is made up of strong families.
That's one of the reasons why the family is under attack.
Because as the family breaks down, the church also breaks down.
I believe this morning that before we ever have revival in the church, that we have to
have revival in our homes.
And I believe that God has given us instruction as we look at this portion of Scripture.
It seems so easy, and really the thoughts this morning are quite basic.
Number one, if you're taking notes, think of this.
Instruction has been provided.
Now, I want to say this right at the beginning of the message.
I am thankful that God has given instruction.
We ought to agree this morning that our God has been faithful to provide us with instruction.
Have you ever attempted to put something together?
Maybe you've purchased something.
Maybe you've made the decision to purchase something from IKEA, and you got it, and
there's 5,000 little pieces and all of this stuff that you need to put together.
And you say, man, alive, this is a project.
And I heard about the president of IKEA, all of the senior management got together for
his birthday to provide him with a cake, and they gave him a couple of eggs and some oil
and some water and some flour and said, here's your birthday cake, right?
And it was quite comical.
But the reality is that sometimes instructions can be one thing.
We look at them and say, what in the world?
Right, Joseph?
He does some projects with me.
And sometimes I look at the instructions and I'm like, I don't get it.
It just does not make sense to me.
I'm not following what I'm supposed to do here.
What is this part for?
What is this thing for?
When we think about the instructions that God has provided to us, we ought to be thankful
that our God has been faithful to provide us with this instruction.
And as we consider this morning, not only the reality that God has been faithful, but
I also want you to think about this and acknowledge this truth this morning, that the instruction
is indeed from God.
This is not just Paul's instruction to the families in Colossae.
This is not just my instruction to the folks in our church this morning.
No, this is God's instruction.
We believe this morning in the inspiration of God's word, that all scripture is given
by inspiration of God and is what is profitable.
And I believe this morning that as we consider the word of God that is before us, that we
must acknowledge that this is the word of God.
And as God has given, we're not going to attack, well, Paul just didn't understand in this.
No, it's God's word.
Amen.
And when we acknowledge that it's God's word and this instruction is from God, and we understand
this morning that it's profitable, then I believe that we also would come to this point,
and perhaps I would say this, we should agree this morning that God knows best.
Would you agree with that?
God knows best.
He is the author of the home.
He designed it.
He instituted the home.
And so who would know better about the home than God?
Right?
Listen, I understand this morning, there are a lot of books that have been written by a
lot of very good authors about the home.
I understand that.
And there are some valuable things that you can glean from some of those books that are
out there, but I would say this, that those truths must be in line with the truth that's
provided in this book.
Because God is the author of the home.
He is the designer, and therefore He knows best.
And when we agree this morning at the very onset of the message, when we consider this
instruction that's provided, is that first, I'm going to be thankful that God's given
the instruction.
I'm going to acknowledge that it's from God, and I'm also going to agree that He knows
best.
Then it helps us as we approach this portion of Scripture.
Amen?
Because all of a sudden, our perspective and our entrance into the verses that we see are
going to be received in a different manner.
Because we say, this is God's Word, and God knows best.
And I'm thankful that He's provided the instruction.
Notice with me, as we consider the instruction that's been provided, first we see in verse
number 18, He addresses the wives.
He says this, wives, submit yourselves unto your own husbands.
And it says this as it is fit in the Lord.
The word submit, we understand it to be a word that means to arrange under rank.
In fact, it would be a word that would be often used with regard to military type of
reference.
But we find that it means to arrange under rank.
It does not mean slavery, amen?
It means to arrange under rank.
And we consider this truth that's been given here, we must understand that our God is a
God of order.
Everything that our God does...
is with order.
You read Genesis chapter number one
as you read about the creation of all that he did,
and you see the order in creation,
and you find that God says in the church in Corinth
that everything is to be done decently and in order.
Why?
Because our God is a God of order.
You find that the enemy is the designer
of chaos and confusion.
He is not about order, but our God is about order.
And so therefore, as he's providing this instruction to us,
we find that he's giving us order for the home.
And as we consider, first he speaks to the wives
about this subject of submission,
and then he finishes the verse by saying,
as it is fit in the Lord.
It is fitting as a wife would fulfill her responsibility
to submit to her own husband.
It's pleasing to God.
We find that as you not only consider
that it's pleasing to God,
I believe it also would carry with it the idea
that it is appropriate in God's eyes.
In other words, it's not for a wife to submit
to do something that would be contrary
to what God's word has said.
That some husband can say,
well, you're supposed to submit,
and so do this, so on and so forth.
That's not the idea of submission.
And really what happens is the enemy wants
to get that little thought in your head
so that when you hear the word submit,
you have both arms out in resistance.
But when we take the approach that this is from God,
and that God knows best,
and that God has been faithful to give the instruction,
all of a sudden, I'm going to receive the instruction
and understand that it is best for me
to follow the instruction.
Look over, I asked you to keep your place in Ephesians 5.
Notice in Ephesians 5, in verses 22 through 24,
we find that God gives instruction
to the believers in Ephesus.
Again, he begins with the wives.
He says this, submit yourselves unto your own husbands.
Look at what he says, as unto the Lord.
Understanding, again, that God has given order.
And I know that there's some that say,
I just don't wanna, I just can't submit to him,
and so on and so forth.
You understand that he's responsible to God.
And as you submit and you fulfill
your responsibility to God to submit,
then that responsibility ends with the husband.
And really, there's a valuable level of protection
for the wife as she submits unto her husband
as unto the Lord.
Notice in verse 23, for the husband is the head of the wife
even as Christ is the head of the church,
and he is the savior of the body.
Therefore, as the church is subject unto Christ,
we'll let the wives be to their own husbands in everything.
And so we find that the instruction is provided
first to the wives.
Number two, to the husbands.
Notice back in Colossians 3, in verse number 19,
the Bible says this, husbands.
It says, love your wives and be not bitter against them.
We find that the truth in Ephesians 5
with regard to this instruction for husbands
to love our wives, it says this,
it gives us the manner in which we're to love our wives.
In Ephesians 5, in verse number 25,
husbands, love your wives even as Christ
also loved the church and gave himself for it.
That's the highest form of love.
It's the Greek word agape.
It's the word that's denoted,
that's used regarding the love of God.
And we find that we are to love our wives, husbands,
as Christ loved the church and gave himself for it.
It is a sacrificial love.
And let me say this this morning,
maybe perhaps as a question,
does your wife, husbands,
does your wife know that you love her in this manner?
Does she know that you love her?
Are you demonstrating, are you showing her your love?
This is our responsibility.
Husbands, love your wives
even as Christ loved the church and gave himself for it.
We find that the instruction continues in Colossians
and it tells us this with regard to the truth
of the husbands, it says,
and be not bitter against them.
Be not bitter against them.
The reality is that there are times even as we mentioned
with regard to the behavior in the church
and the peace that should be prevalent
in the church of God because of that crucifying our flesh,
because of the putting off and the putting on,
that one of the references that was given
with regard to the put on was in verse number 13
forbearing one another,
literally putting up with one another
and forgiving one another.
And then it said this,
if any man have a quarrel against any,
even as Christ forgave you, so also do ye.
You know, our home, husbands, when it says
and be not bitter against them,
we need to be careful that our home is a place
in which we are practicing forgiveness,
that we're not allowing the sun to go down upon our wrath,
that we're speaking the truth in love,
that we're open dialogue one with another.
I know that there are times in relationships,
no matter what the relationship is
and specifically as we're focused on the home this morning,
that there will be some level of quarrel,
there's a contention, there's a problem,
there's something that just doesn't go the way
that we planned for it to go, right?
I told you about the fellow that I heard preach
at a pastor's meeting not long ago
and he stood there and said, I can tell you,
I can stand here, Brother Savalle, he said,
in all honesty, I've been married for 35 years
and I've never said one thing to my wife that I regret.
I've never had one argument with my wife,
I've never raised my voice to my wife one time
and all the preachers are like, man, this is amazing.
And then he said this, but there've been plenty of times
that I just didn't talk to her for days.
Well, that's not the answer either, right?
That's not the way it's supposed to work, amen?
But what was he doing?
He was really saying, look, I didn't do this,
but I did this.
Well, what he did wasn't right and he acknowledged that,
he was just being funny with regard to his own behavior
and his shortcoming and his need to allow God
to work in his life.
Listen, we need to be careful and guard against bitterness,
against brother and sister, church member,
against husband and wife, parent and children.
I mean, bitterness is a terrible thing.
Bitterness destroys.
I've often said this, it destroys the vessel
in which it's stored more than the vessel
in which it's poured.
We find that bitterness is a terrible thing
and God says to the husbands, not only to love your wives,
but then he says, and be not bitter against them.
Now the focus turns to children in verse number 20,
the instruction being provided.
Notice in verse number 20, he says,
children, obey your parents in all things.
And now the parents get a little excited
because the wives say, man,
you're not dealing with the wife anymore.
The husbands say, not dealing with the husbands anymore.
Now we're dealing with the children.
And so, hey, kids, listen up, right?
Kevin's back there, Ian and Isaiah,
you listen to the preacher, amen.
He's talking about the children now, right?
Amen, right?
He turned me off when I talked about husbands,
but man, when he heard children, he said, listen up, boys.
I'm just teasing, I'm just teasing.
But listen, he says, children,
obey your parents in all things.
Not some things, not most things,
not the things that you like,
the things that you agree with,
but in all things, right?
There's a level of protection for the children,
just as I mentioned the protection for the wife
and submission because the husband is accountable.
Biblical proof for that, when Sarah laughed,
who did God go to?
Abraham.
Abraham, why did Sarah laugh?
It's interesting that he didn't ask Sarah why she laughed.
Why, because the husband is responsible.
Children have a safety net, if you will,
in obedience to their parents.
Obey your parents, it says, in all things,
but then I want you to catch this, it says this,
for this is well-pleasing unto the Lord.
That's encouraging for a child.
I understand that obedience doesn't come natural
for a child.
Any of you that have had children,
you understand the fact that we are born sinners, amen?
It's not hard when you talk about the truth
of giving the gospel presentation for all have sinned.
You say, man, I got some kids,
and we didn't have to teach them to sin.
They were born sinners.
It doesn't come natural for children to obey in all things,
but we find that the truth that's given here
is that this, obedience to your parents,
is well-pleasing unto the Lord.
We find that we understand that God has given instruction,
I asked you to be in chapter five,
this goes down into chapter number six.
In chapter number six, in verses one through three,
the Bible says this, children,
obey your parents and the Lord,
notice, for this is right.
It then says this, honor thy father and mother,
and then notice, he says,
which is the first commandment with promise.
He goes back to the Exodus chapter number 20,
we'll look at it in just a moment.
And then it says this, that it may be well with thee,
and that thou mayest live long on the earth.
Well, so when I understand all that God is telling me,
again, he's the one that's designed this.
He's the one that knows what is best,
and he's been faithful to give us the instruction.
I say, well, this just makes sense that I would do this.
It's gonna be better for me.
It's going to result in living a long life.
life that would be longer, that would bring honor to God, it says in Exodus 20
and verse 12, honor thy father and thy mother that thy days may be long upon
the land which the Lord thy God giveth thee. I am thankful to be living in New
Testament era, aren't you? If you say I'm not so sure about that, read the book of
Leviticus this afternoon and perhaps you'll come back tonight with a
different idea. I'm thankful that we're no longer under the law. Christ has
redeemed us from the law, amen? Now we understand that it's still valuable and
there's still instruction that we learn from it, but I'm thankful to not be under
the law. Listen, the law could never save. Galatians is very clear about that. If
righteousness came by the law, then Christ is dead in vain, but I want you to
understand some things about the Old Testament that there are many things.
Listen, children would be put to death for some of the behavior that is
tolerated today. Again, I'm thankful to live in the New Testament, amen? And I'm
thankful for God's grace and for God's mercy, but you understand that as we look
at these truths that what God is doing is God is trying to, I shouldn't
say trying, God is providing instruction that is profitable, right? You think about
those in the Old Testament, there are portions of scripture that you can read
about children that were stoned because of their sin, because of their
disobedience, their lack of honor, so on and so forth, and as you look at those
situations, you say, well the commandment was, honor thy father and mother that thy
days may be long upon the earth. They were cut short because of your sin,
because of your disobedience, right? And so we find here that in the New
Testament that God is giving us this instruction. We notice that he says again
that this is well-pleasing unto the Lord. Finally, we come to verse number 21 as we
think about the instruction that's been provided. We find that the passage
now addresses fathers. We see wives in verse 18, husbands in verse 19, children
in verse 20. In verse 21, fathers. It says, provoke not your children to anger lest
they be discouraged. Provoke not. We see this also in the book of Ephesians in
chapter number 6, and we find that there the Bible says, and ye fathers, provoke
not your children to wrath, but bring them up in the nurture and admonition of
the Lord. I believe this morning that consistency is key. I believe that one of
the easiest ways for us to, as fathers, as parents, to provoke our children to
anger, to wrath, is through inconsistency. I believe that it's important that we
understand that our children are a blessing from God. Amen?
Lo, children are an heritage from the Lord. They're a blessing from God, and we
have been, for a season of time, we have been entrusted by God to instruct our
children, to bring them up in the nurture and admonition of the Lord, and we need
to be careful to understand that they're a blessing from God and that we play a
vital role in their development, and that we help them to understand much about
who God is and how God operates. And the consistency in the lives of parents is
essential, that we would not provoke our children to anger, to wrath. Notice the
last part of verse 21. It says, lest they be discouraged. The word discouraged means
to be disheartened. It means to be broken in spirit. Oftentimes, we've heard people
speak about the necessity, perhaps, of breaking a child's will. You've
heard somebody use that terminology. They're strong-willed, or whatever the
terminology would be that someone would use, and they need to have their
will broken, and we will use that terminology. That's quite different than
breaking their spirit. We need to be careful that we understand this. Let me
say, as we look at the instruction provided, that each one of us here this
morning find ourselves in a category, and as we would look at the categories that
are provided, we must thank God for the instruction that's been given, and as we
look here, wives, husbands, children, fathers, we see that the instruction has
been provided, and then I would ask this, or say this as our second point this
morning, instruction provided, instruction understood, and I'm gonna say
question mark. Do you understand the instruction? So, I think this morning that
as we look at these four verses of Scripture, that it would be very easy for
us to agree that the truth that is given is not complicated, right? It's not like
some of those instruction booklets that you've received on some of those
products that you've purchased, and you don't know which one. I'm like, man, maybe
I'll read the Spanish side of this, because it might make more sense, you
know? I mean, it just can be so confusing. I told you about the the ceiling fan I
tried to put together. I mean, it was an absolute nonsense, but it made sense
once I followed the instructions, but the instructions made no sense in the
beginning, because I've put together tons of ceiling fans, and it's always followed
the same exact process until I got this one, and I was glad that I used the
illustration, because I saved brother Ron Adams some time as well, amen? Because he
got one of those same silly fans that has the crazy instructions, but the
reality is that there are times in which instructions can be complicated. You ever
wonder why the folks at Microsoft decided you got to push control alt
delete? Right? Like, I mean, why do I have to? Why can't there just be one button?
That's what they decided. I don't know, the computer science guys are
gonna come give me answers after the service, right? This is why you have to do
it this way, but the reality is that, listen, we understand instructions being
provided, and there are times in which we can say, man, that's complicated, but this
morning this is basic. This is easy to understand, and my question for you this
morning is, do we understand the instruction that God has given? Again,
we're agreeing at the onset of the message that God knows best. We're
agreeing on the onset of the message that this is God's Word. This is, yes, God
used the Apostle Paul to be the human penman of this particular book, but all
Scripture is given by inspiration of God, and it's profitable, and we find here
this morning that this instruction, it's not hard. You know, there are people that
criticize the Bible and say, oh, it's so complicated, it's so difficult. The
reality is that much of the Bible is very easy to understand, and when you
couple that with the fact that we have the Holy Spirit of God that is the
Teacher that dwells within us and He illumines the Scriptures to us, it makes
it that much easier for us to understand the Word of God. And this morning, I don't
think anyone that's here could honestly say, I just don't understand, because the
instruction is easy to understand. So it leads me to my final thought this
morning. Instruction must be embraced and applied. Instruction must be embraced
and applied. The instruction has been provided. Instruction can be understood,
but can I say this this morning? Understanding does not equal applying.
We can understand something and not apply it, correct? We can understand
something and not apply it. So understanding does not equal applying.
But this morning, when we look at this portion of Scripture, if we truly desire
to have a home where the Lord is honored, where we have a harmonious home, where we
aren't just in survival mode, but we're thriving with the blessing of God, and
we're going through life enjoying all that God has designed for us to enjoy,
then we must apply the truth that has been given. It's not enough to just say
that God's provided the instruction. Oh, we're thankful that He's provided it. What
a tremendous blessing. I mean, can you imagine if God did not provide
instruction for your home? We wouldn't know how to behave. We wouldn't know who's
supposed to do what, and so on and so forth, and it could be very chaotic. But
God has graciously provided the instruction, and it's very easy to
understand. But understanding does not equal applying, and we find that I must
embrace this truth, and as I embrace the instruction, I then apply it in my life.
The wives apply the truth of verse 18. The husbands applying the truth of verse
number 19. The children applying the truth of verse number 20. The
father's parents applying the truth of verse number 21. And listen, here's what
I find this morning. My flesh and your flesh probably have a hard time with
some of the instruction that's provided here, but that's why the preceding text
is so important. Mortify, therefore, your members which are upon the earth.
Literally crucify your flesh. Put off the old man, all of these things. Put on
the new man with all of these things. Now your behavior in the church house is
going to be characterized by peace and unity and devotion and purpose and
praise, and now your home is going to be a home where each individual is
fulfilling the plan that God has. It's possible in the power of God. I will say
this. Husbands, you're
Your wife will have a much easier time submitting
if she knows you love her.
Amen?
It's the way it works.
Wives will have a much easier time submitting
when they know that their husbands love them,
that their husbands are walking with God,
that their husbands have put off the old man
and put on the new man
and are walking in the power of the Holy Spirit of God.
Children are gonna have a much easier time
obeying their parents
as they know that their parents love them
and that their parents are seeking the face of God
and desiring to please God.
There are times in which perhaps we can tell our children,
give them an answer with regard to something
that they desire to do,
and we can take them directly to some verses of Scripture
and explain to them why we're not going to engage
in such and such of behavior and so on and so forth.
And there are other times that we just might be like,
hey, listen, can you just trust me on this?
We just don't have a piece about this.
And if our children know that we're walking with God,
if our children know that we love them,
that we're not seeking to provoke them to anger,
that we're not living a life of hypocrisy,
that we're not seeking to be contentious and inconsistent,
then they can have an easier time of obeying.
But if we do all of that
without putting off and putting on,
we're gonna struggle
because it's gonna get old real fast in the flesh
trying to do that.
It's very interesting to me
that the truth that is given to us,
the instruction provided in verses 18 through 21,
in this portion of Colossians is preceded
by that which we've dealt with in the last several weeks.
It's also of interest and noteworthy
that in Ephesians five and six,
the portion that we were looking at earlier,
where the same instruction is provided,
I want you to be understanding this morning
of the preceding passage
that deals with this truth in Ephesians five.
Before he gets to wives and husbands and children
as he's addressing the church in Ephesus,
he says this in verse number 18 of Ephesians five.
And be not drunk with wine,
wherein is excess.
Notice, but be filled with the Spirit.
I believe this morning that what is summarized
in those few words at the end of verse number 18,
but be filled with the Spirit,
is what is illustrated to us in detail
in Colossians three verses five through 14.
Mortify therefore your members which are upon the earth.
Put off the old man, put on the new.
That's the idea of being filled with the Spirit of God.
That's the rubber meets the road truth
of okay, how do I do this?
The application.
We find that he says, but be filled with the Spirit.
Notice, speaking to yourselves in psalms and hymns
and spiritual songs, singing and making melody
in your heart to the Lord,
giving thanks always for all things unto God
and for the Father in the name of our Lord Jesus Christ,
submitting yourselves one to another in the fear of God.
Then he addresses the wives and the husbands
and the children.
And so as I'm walking in the Spirit,
it is God who enables me to apply the instruction
that he's given me with regard to the home.
I can't do it in my own power.
You understand something this morning?
You can't live the Christian life in your own power.
You can try for a little while.
You're gonna get frustrated.
You really are.
You're gonna just get sideways in life
and you're gonna get frustrated
because you're trying to do it in your own power.
Paul said, I know that in me that is in my flesh
dwelleth no good thing, right?
He says, the things that I would, I do not.
The things that I would not, that I do.
Listen, you try to live the Christian life in your own power
and we become miserable.
But it's amazing when God, when we come to that place
of surrender, submission to God, walking in the Spirit
and how he enables us to implement,
to apply the instruction that he has provided.
This morning, I would hope that each and every one of us
would stand and testify and say,
I want a home where the Lord is honored.
I want a home where God is honored.
The home, I've often said this over the years,
is that haven, that safe place.
I remember when I worked in the corporate world,
it's a little bit different now as a pastor of a church.
My office is kind of a haven of rest as well
until some people wanna meet.
No, I'm just teasing.
But the reality is that, listen,
when I worked in the corporate world,
I worked in the corporate world for years.
I understand what it is to work in the corporate life.
And oh, how I love to come home,
to come to that haven, that safe place.
I'm not in any way saying that my home is perfect,
but I desire to have a home that honors God.
And this morning, if you wanna have a home that honors God,
if you desire that, we understand that God's provided
the instruction and we ought to be thankful for that.
It's easy to understand,
but oh, how we must embrace it and apply it.
And when we do, I believe the result will be a home
where the Lord is honored.
Maybe this morning for our invitation,
we need to have some families just gather together
and pray together.
Maybe visit the altar together, husbands and wives.
I know most of the children,
the young children are downstairs.
But just ask God to help us, to enable us.
We can identify a place in our lives and say,
man, I've struggled in this area.
Oh, that God would help me in this area
so that we can have a home where the Lord is honored.
Let's pray.
Father, how we love you and how we thank you
for the instruction that you've provided.
We acknowledge this morning that this is your word.
And you designed the home
and you've provided the instruction
for each member in the home.
I believe this morning it's simple.
It's easy to understand.
But oh, how we understand this morning
that to understand something
does not mean to apply something.
We're challenged by the truth of James 1
that we would be doers of the word and not hearers only.
Our homes are under attack.
If we're not careful,
we begin to listen to what the world says
about how a home should operate.
We begin to receive counsel from individuals
that would speak to us about the role
that we should play in our homes
instead of listening to the voice of God.
I pray that you'd move and work this morning
in each family that's present.
Perhaps they would have the opportunity
to come to this altar as a family and just pray.
God, we pray that you would have your will and way,
that decisions would be made this morning
that would honor you.
Maybe some commitments that would be renewed
maybe some commitments that would be renewed this morning
so that we truly could have a home where you are honored.
We will thank you for all that you'll do
for it's in Christ's name we pray.