like to be a grandfather? And if you have grandchildren, you've been asked that question,
whether you're a grandmother or a grandfather. And I've been asked that question many times,
what's it like, so on and so forth. And certainly thankful to have grandchildren. Do not misunderstand
what I'm saying. But the reality is that being a father is such a blessing and such a privilege.
And as a father, the Bible teaches us that we're to bring up our children in the nurture
and admonition of the Lord. If we as fathers are active in doing and fulfilling what God
has called us to do, we have a much greater influence in the life of our children, even
though or even more so than we do in our grandchildren. And I've enjoyed parenting. I'll tell you,
it's a challenge to think about where we are personally with Joseph being 18 and graduating
high school and just kind of thinking about these years. I mean, it seems like it goes
by so quickly. I know that you hear that and I know that I heard that many times and many
people have said, well, around that two-year-old mark, it kind of slows down a bit and then
it speeds back up. But I'll tell you that every phase of parenting is enjoyable. It
really is. Every phase of parenting has with it its own challenges and its own rewards.
I've been asked many times now with regard to having adult children, what's the hardest
phase of parenting? And if you've been one that's asked me that question, you know my
answer and I'll say it publicly, that the hardest phase of parenting is whatever phase
you're currently in. It really is. And you never stop being a parent. Those of you that
have children and grandchildren and great-grandchildren, you never stop being a parent. And what a
great blessing and a great privilege. I'm thankful that the Bible provides for us much
instruction with regard to parenting, with regard to fatherhood. And we're reminded of
the call that's been placed upon us. As we examine the passage of Scripture this morning
in 1 Kings chapter 2, we see that David, the king of Israel, is seeking to influence and
instruct his son Solomon just before he dies. Now, as you know, this is, I don't know, 15
years of preaching Father's Day messages now and Mother's Day was just a few weeks ago.
And my desire for each service that we have that's either a holiday or what have you,
Mother's Day, Father's Day, is don't tune me out this morning if you're not a father.
And I ask that during Mother's Day. Why? Because the truth from God's Word is applicable to
every single one of us, no matter what phase of life we're in and no matter who you are.
And the truth is here and I hope this morning that God will allow me to deliver the message
in such a way that if those that are fathers would be able to make application, but those
that are not, whether you've never had children, whether you're not married, whether you're
a lady, that you'd be able to take the biblical truth and apply it in your life today. God's
Word is profitable. I believe that. And God has given it to us. He's recorded it for us.
And what a blessing. Notice in verse number one, the Bible says, Now the days of David
drew nigh that he should die. Can I tell you just by way of introduction this morning,
this truth that opens up chapter two is going to be the truth for every one of us. There's
going to come a time in your life and in my life that it's going to draw nigh that we're
going to die. Now for David, there's an opportunity because of the way that he will enter into
eternity that he has opportunity to be able to influence and to call his son and to speak
to him. But the reality is that not all of us will face the same kind of death. The reality
is that some people will die in just an instant, in a moment. There's some tragic accident
or something that happens where someone will die so quickly and others may go through a
period of long sickness where they are on their deathbed for months or even longer.
And we understand that. But the reality is that we must acknowledge this morning, are
we prepared for that day? The Bible says, As it is appointed unto man, once to die after
this the judgment. And we're all going to face death. We understand that. For David,
it's recorded for us in what takes place as it comes near for him to take his final breath
here upon this earth. You say, I don't like to think about death. I understand that. And
the reality is that prior to being saved, I was afraid of dying. And the Bible talks
about in Hebrews chapter number two, how Jesus delivered us from that fear of death. Why?
Because he conquered death. He conquered sin, death, and the grave. And this morning I can
stand before you, not anxious to face the process of dying, but honestly being able
to stand before you and say, I'm not afraid of dying for to be absent from the body is
to be present with the Lord. Paul says, as he's writing to those in Philippi, that he
was in a difficult situation. He was in a strait betwixt two. And what does he say?
Why is he in a strait betwixt two? Because he had a desire to depart to be with Christ.
Notice what he says, which is far better. I wonder this morning, are you a hundred percent
sure that heaven is your home? I hope that you are. If you're not, we'd love to take
a Bible and show you how you could know for sure that heaven is your home. Now, the days
of David drew nigh that he should die. And he charged Solomon, his son, saying, I go
the way of all the earth. Be thou strong therefore. And this is where we get the title this morning.
And show thyself a man and keep the charge of the Lord thy God to walk in his ways, to
keep his statutes, and his commandments, and his judgments, and his testimonies, as
it is written in the law of Moses, that thou mayest prosper in all that thou doest. And
whithersoever thou turnest thyself, that the Lord may continue his word which he spake
concerning me, saying, If thy children take heed to their way, to walk before me in truth
with all their heart, with all their soul, there shall not fail thee, said he, a man
on the throne of Israel. As we look at this passage of scripture this morning, I want
you to notice first of all, if you're taking notes, notice the charge from a godly father.
We understand that David is referred to in the book of Acts as being a man after God's
own heart. The Bible records for us the sin of David. David's not a perfect man, but he's
a man that sought after the Lord. He's a man that after he's confronted with his sin, he
confessed and he forsook and he wept before the Lord, recognizing against thee and thee
only have I done this wickedness in thy sight. And we find that David now as a godly man
is going to charge his son. I believe this is a significant moment in the life of David,
but also in the life of Solomon. I believe this morning that God has graciously recorded
for you and for me these few verses of scripture, and we have an opportunity to see the private,
intimate moment, if you will, between a father and his son before he would take his final
breath here upon this earth. There are some of us that would have desires that I would
like to be able to say this to this person or this to that person before I die. Could
I encourage you this morning to say it now? Why? Because you don't know that you're going
to have the opportunity that David has here in this passage of scripture that he's able
to call for his son and to give him this charge. It would be far better that we speak those
things at the moment that we have, for there's no promise of tomorrow. And we find that God
is giving us the opportunity. We are to not only understand the charge that's given here
to Solomon, but we're to be impacted by it. We're to look at this charge that is given
from a godly father to his son Solomon, and yes, we can study the aspects of what does
David tell his son in those dying moments. What one thing would you want to give to someone
else in those dying moments? But not only do we analyze it, but we want to apply it.
We want to learn from it. And we find that as we look at the passage of scripture that
this charge is given, and we really see it. Notice in verse number one, the Bible says
that he called, it says, now the days of David drew nigh that he should die, and he charged
Solomon his son. And notice what he says, I go the way of all the earth, and then he
tells him this, be thou strong therefore and show thyself a man. Can I tell you this morning
that our society defines manhood in a variety of ways. In fact, if you look at the culture
in America, there are some that would seek to define manhood in a way that is completely
contrary to what God says that true manhood is. What does it mean to be a man when God
says show thyself a man? But I want you to understand this morning that he says prior
to that, he says, be thou strong. Can I tell you this morning that he's not simply speaking
of physical strength.
The reality is that as men, often time when we think about manliness and manhood,
we do often think about that physical strength aspect,
but can I tell you this morning that what God is really referring to,
and many times when we see about strength throughout the Bible,
He's talking about that spiritual strength.
Can I tell you this morning that every single one of us,
every young person in the room this morning,
every man in the room this morning,
every lady in the room this morning,
we need to be strong spiritually.
We are engaged in a spiritual battle, in a spiritual warfare,
and we wrestle not against flesh and blood.
We wrestle against spiritual wickedness in high places.
He tells us that we're to put on the whole armor of God.
He says be strong in the Lord and in the power of His might.
The Bible tells us that our strength, our spiritual strength,
is renewed in the inner man and the Holy Spirit of God
will work in your life and in my life.
Where does that strength come from?
It comes from God's Word.
It comes from a proper relationship with the Lord
and walking with God daily and spending that time with God
and being nourished by God's Word,
and the Holy Spirit of God lives in you if you're saved this morning,
and He lives in me, and we have the opportunity to be strong.
Some of us this morning,
we can acknowledge that our physical strength has waned.
I'm not as strong as I used to be.
In fact, Joseph reminds me regularly,
I'm getting stronger than you.
You know what I said to him recently?
You should be.
He's 18, I'm almost 45.
I still can beat him, but he says,
I'm going to beat you in arm wrestling soon.
He should.
Now, we tried it a few weeks ago, and I still won, amen,
just for the record, just for the record, amen.
But there's going to come a day, Ron,
that he's going to beat me in arm wrestling.
And guess what? That's okay.
That's okay.
Kevin says, no, it's not okay.
It's okay.
But spiritual strength.
My physical strength, because as we get older,
our physical strength just, it wanes away.
But the reality is that spiritually are we strong.
Spiritually.
We're facing some things in this world today
that we need spiritual strength.
There's a lot of things going on in our world today,
things that we need to pray about and be aware of.
But we need God's strength as we go through those things.
See, we as God's people, when we have God's strength
in our lives, when those times of difficulty
come in our lives, we don't fall apart.
Why? Because we have God's strength
and we're strong spiritually.
It's not my strength, it's his strength in me.
We understand, as he says, and oftentimes
Philippians 4 is used out of context,
I can do all things through Christ,
strengtheneth me, right?
And it doesn't mean I can do all things,
that I can go dunk a basketball or do this,
that or the other thing.
You see so many of these Christian schools
that put that verse of scripture on their warm-up jerseys,
et cetera, and I'm not trying to take notes
or take argument with them, but the reality is
he's talking about spiritual things.
God gives us the strength in the charges,
be thou strong.
Can I encourage you this morning, every one of us,
we need to be strong in the Lord.
And then he says, show thyself a man.
I think of the significance of this charge
and I see that there's an aspect of significance
with regard to David.
Look, if you will, at Psalm 71
and hold your place there,
we'll be back to 1 Kings in just a moment,
but look at Psalm 71
and I want you to just look at a couple of verses
this morning in Psalm 71
and notice this heart desire of the psalmist.
Now, Psalm 71 is not specifically attributed to David.
We're not sure who the human penman is,
but I do believe that as I read these verses of scripture
and couple them with other verses that we know
that David is the human penman of,
such as Psalm 145 verses four through six,
I believe that this is the heart of David.
Even if David didn't pen these words humanly,
I believe this was still his heart.
Notice in Psalm 71, notice what he says in verse 17.
Oh God, thou hast taught me from my youth,
and hitherto have I declared thy wondrous works.
Now also when I am old and gray-headed,
oh God, forsake me not, notice what he says,
until I have showed thy strength unto this generation
and thy power to every one that is to come.
That's an honorable desire, is it not?
The psalmist says that thou hast taught me from my youth.
You think about how God has taught us
and I think, again, if this is David as the human penman,
as a youth, what God was teaching him.
And we can read of his life and we can understand those things
and then he says that he's declared thy wondrous works
throughout the Psalms.
We see so many areas in which David is declaring
the wonderful works of God
and he's exalting and magnifying the name of the Lord,
but he has this desire when he's old and he's gray-headed.
He says, God, I desire to show thy strength
unto this generation and thy power
to every one that is to come.
God allowed him in 1 Kings chapter number 2
to have this desire fulfilled
in being able to charge his son Solomon.
I think that's significant.
I think that the event is significant to not only David,
but I think it's significant to Solomon.
Turn to the book of Proverbs, if you will, in chapter number 4
and I want you to see as we think about the significance
of this event that is recorded for us,
this moment between father and son in 1 Kings chapter 2
and we see the significance to David.
He had this heart that he wanted to show
to a generation to come.
Can I tell you this morning that yes,
desiring to show to a generation to come,
but to your own children.
I want to impact a lot of people, I really do.
I want to have an opportunity to influence and impact
as many as God would give me the opportunity
to influence and impact, but I have three kids
and they're at the top of the list of those
that I want to influence and impact.
Amen?
Does that make sense to you this morning?
I'm not saying that your kids aren't important for me
to impact or influence or that you aren't,
but they're at the top of my list
and your kids should be at the top of your list,
but the reality is that there's many more to influence as well.
Oh, David, he wanted to influence a whole nation,
but it starts with his own son.
But then for Solomon, notice in Proverbs chapter number four,
pick it up with me in verse number three.
For I, Solomon speaking, was my father's son,
tender and only beloved in the sight of my mother.
Notice these words, he taught me also.
He taught me also.
This is David teaching Solomon.
Solomon's writing this here in Proverbs chapter four
and he talks about his father and how he taught me
and said unto me, Let thine heart retain my words,
keep my commandments, and live.
Get wisdom, get understanding, forget it not,
neither decline from the words of my mouth.
Forsake her not, and she shall preserve thee.
Love her, and she shall keep thee.
Wisdom is the principal thing.
Therefore, get wisdom, and with all thy getting,
get understanding.
Exalt her, and she shall promote thee.
She shall bring thee to honor when thou dost embrace her.
She shall give to thine head an ornament of grace,
a crown of glory shall she deliver to thee.
Do you see how Solomon, it was significant to Solomon
that David there on his deathbed,
that he calls and he charges his son to do what?
Be strong, show thyself a man, walk with God.
We find that Solomon then says in the next text of Scripture
in verse number 10, notice the perpetuity of this
in the next generation.
He now says, hear, O my son.
Who's Solomon talking to?
Well, Rehoboam.
Hear, O my son, and receive my sayings,
and the years of thy life shall be many.
Notice what he says.
I have taught thee in the way of wisdom.
I have led thee in right paths.
Wow.
The opportunity for us to read this passage
in 1 Kings chapter 4, and we see the significance
of this charge.
We note the charge from a godly father.
It was significant to David.
It was significant to Solomon.
But I believe that it was significant to the Lord.
I believe that's why God recorded it for us.
You know, in Deuteronomy chapter 6,
we won't take the time to look there,
but in verses 1 through 7, God gives a charge
with the importance of fathers teaching their children.
We see in Psalm 78, verses 4 through 7,
it's referenced again how that one generation
is to teach a next generation.
We read in the book of Ephesians, in fact,
I believe that it's there on our bulletin cover this morning,
Ephesians 6 and verse number 4,
bring them up in the nurture and admonition of the Lord.
We see this consistent message that God gives,
and can I tell you that when we do what God calls us to do,
that God is pleased with that.
God has given to us an opportunity and a responsibility
to teach a future generation,
those of us that have children,
to literally teach our children these biblical truths
to help them in their journey with life.
Significant.
this passage of Scripture.
Not only do we notice the charge from a godly father, but I want you to notice, number two
this morning, the characteristics of a godly man.
We could say this morning the characteristics of a godly individual.
Make the application whether you're a father or not, whether you're a man or a lady this
morning.
The reality is that the characteristics that we find in 1 Kings chapter number two are
characteristics of a godly individual.
The reality is that God is looking for people that would live godly.
The grace of God that bringeth salvation hath appeared to all men, teaching us to live how?
To live how we want?
No, to live godly.
To live righteously, to live soberly in this present world, right?
And that's what the Bible teaches us.
And the reality is that as we read that truth, as Paul was instructing his own son in the
we understand this morning that we're to live godly.
Why do we live godly?
Do we live godly so that we can be saved, so that we can go to heaven?
Do we live godly so that we can keep our salvation?
No.
We live godly so that we can please Him.
You know, before I got saved, I could not live godly.
I was not capable of living godly.
Why?
Because I was lost.
But after I was born again, the Holy Spirit of God lives within me.
If you're saved this morning, now you can live godly as well.
God is pleased with us when we live godly.
When we live in a manner in which He is exalted and magnified, where we're lifting up the
name of Christ and we're to walk in the ways of the Lord.
If we're to summarize the entirety of these characteristics of a godly individual, it
would be simply that, to walk in the ways of the Lord.
God said it, that settles it.
Don't take the Bible and look at it as just being a list of do's and don'ts.
No, it's teaching us what pleases our God and what displeases Him.
It's teaching us how to live a life that is pleasing to Him, a life that we can hear,
as the preacher said during the missions conference last week, his greatest desire
is to hear, well done thou good and faithful servant.
And we find here in the text of Scripture in 1 Kings chapter 2 and verses 3 and 4, that
the list is provided to us specifically here in verse number 3.
Notice what the Bible says, and keep the charge of the Lord thy God, notice, to walk in His
ways.
To walk in His ways.
And then we find that there's four particular things that are listed.
He says, to keep His statutes.
Now we must understand that as David is writing to Solomon, as we read the Bible, we must
understand that these are God's words, amen?
Many times we'll hear individuals say something to us, something like this, well the Bible
is just a bunch of man's words.
No, the Bible is God's word.
Only men of God spake as they were moved by the Holy Ghost.
All Scripture is given by inspiration of God.
Every word of God is pure.
And so we find that this is God's word and in each of these instances you see that David
says keep His statutes, judgments, commandments, testimonies, we'll look at all of those in
just a moment.
But notice he says first, keep His, God's, statutes.
These are specific written commands or laws.
His statutes.
We find that he then says this in verse number three, keep His statutes and His commandments.
These are basic commands or basic orders.
He then says this, and His judgments.
Maybe you're going to think about judgments.
These are righteous statements that give, we as the people of God, those that would
read the Bible, these are righteous statements that give discernment of right versus wrong.
His judgments.
We begin to see God's judgments in His word and it helps us to have that discernment between
what is right and what is wrong.
And we see the consequences of such behavior.
He then says this, and His testimonies, the laws or precepts of God.
And then he says this as it is written in the law of Moses.
I'm thankful that we still have the Pentateuch today.
I'm thankful that God has preserved His word for us and that we can go and we can take
the same charge that David delivered to Solomon and we can understand this morning that we
too must walk in the ways of the Lord.
The characteristics.
What makes someone, as we look at their lives, as we begin to analyze the characteristics
of our own lives, of others' lives, what would be necessary to be in their lives in order
for us to say they're a godly person?
Why is it that in Antioch they were first called Christians?
What was it about those people that were called Christians that prior to then were referred
to as being disciples?
What was it about their behavior, their character, that they said they're Christians?
What is it about our lives that would say that we are godly?
What are the characteristics in our lives?
You think about the need for us to be like Christ.
In fact, turn to the book of Romans chapter number eight very quickly.
And so often we look at verse 28 and we should.
It's a great verse of Scripture, a great promise that is given to us with regard to God's sovereignty.
But I want you to really look at verse number 29 with me this morning and I want you to
see God's plan for your life and for my life.
Listen, if you've been saved this morning, then God has a plan for you to live a life
that is honoring in His sight.
The book of Ephesians tells us that we're to prove what is acceptable unto the Lord.
And notice here in Romans chapter number eight, I'll read verse 28, it's a verse that we often
reference.
It says, and we know that all things work together for good to them that love God, to
them who are the called according to His purpose.
Now, pause with me just for a moment.
What is the biblical tester that God gives us for those that love God?
Just those that profess it?
Yeah, those that keep His commandments, right?
He says, if you love me, keep my commandments.
And so there's a lot of people today that run around saying, I love Jesus, I love God,
but they don't keep His commandments.
They many times don't even know His commandments.
And the reality is that if we love Him, we're going to keep His commandments.
And so in verse 28, he talks about them that love God, we're keeping His commandments.
God has a plan and a purpose in your life and my life.
But then notice this in verse 29, who, for whom He did for know.
Now, let me pause just a moment because a lot of times these words today are taken out
of context and redefined.
There's this teaching that has become more and more prevalent of Calvinism.
And we reject Calvinism and all of its tenants.
And the reality is that they take words that are Bible words and they redefine them to
mean something than what they truly mean biblically.
God has all foreknowledge.
Do you believe that this morning?
He's outside of time.
God sees everything and He knows everything.
He is alpha and omega.
He is the beginning and He is the ending, okay?
So God is outside of time.
He sees everything.
He knows everything.
But He does not make everything happen the way that it happens.
He's given to man free will.
But God knows those that will trust Him as Savior.
Why?
Because He knows all things, right?
What happens is our finite minds are trying to figure out an infinite God.
And the reality is that He transcends us, amen?
And so we look at it from being trapped in time and trapped in our finite minds and we're
trying to figure out an infinite God and we get all messed up and we try to redefine.
But the reality is that God can know that I was going to get saved on August 31st, 1997,
but He didn't make me get saved, amen?
He knew, but He didn't make me.
But then notice, for whom He did foreknow.
If you're saved this morning, He knows that you were going to get saved.
He knew that.
Notice, He also did predestinate.
Oh, that's another one of those words that they like to use.
And here's how they like to use the word, that you were predestinated for heaven.
It's not what the Bible says.
The word predestinate is not a word that we need to be afraid of, biblically.
When you look at Ephesians chapter number one, many times they want to run there and
mess with things.
And the reality is that in Ephesians chapter number one, God is revealing to us that God
did determine before the foundation of the world how mankind will be saved.
There's only one way to be saved and that's through Jesus Christ.
Ephesians chapter number one is not talking about the who of salvation, but the how of
salvation.
And so notice, He says, whom He did foreknow, He also did predestinate.
That's what it says, to be conformed to the image of His Son, that He might be the firstborn
among many brethren.
The truth is that God's plan for every Christian is that we would be like Christ.
That's God's plan for every Christian.
that we would be like Christ.
So when we begin to understand that Christ is the one
that we're pursuing and he is the one
that we're seeking to be like,
the reality is that there's gonna be some unity
and some conformity, if you will,
if we can use that word this morning, amongst Christians.
Why?
Because we're all trying to be like Christ.
It's not that you're trying to be like me
or I'm trying to be like you
or whoever the person might be, no.
We're all, as Christians, God's plan for us,
he predestinated it, he determined ahead of time
that those that would be saved
are supposed to be like Christ.
So how's that accomplished?
The Holy Spirit of God lives within us
and he begins to work within us
and he is doing a work in your life and in my life
and we're all at a different place in our Christian lives
and we're all at a different growth point
but the reality is that he's working in us.
I'm confident, as Paul says to those in Philippi,
that God is working in you,
being confident of this very thing
and Paul is trying to help these believers in Philippi
to understand God's work, what was it?
That he which hath begun a good work in you
will perform it until the day of Jesus Christ.
We sing the song, he's still working on me and he is.
Hallelujah, I'm never gonna be sinless
this side of heaven and neither are you
but the reality is that we're to be like Christ.
So we notice in the text of scripture
not only the charge from a godly father
but we notice the characteristics of a godly individual.
David tells Solomon that this is how to be a real man.
Show thyself a man is what he says in verse number two
and then he tells him,
how are you gonna show yourself a man?
Walk in God's ways, walk in God's ways.
Oh, this morning, we need some people
that are gonna walk in God's ways.
Men, fathers, young people, ladies, mothers,
there's some people that are gonna be godly.
They're gonna walk in the ways of the Lord.
It's not gonna happen on accident.
We're gonna be purposed, submit, surrender, yield,
all those wonderful words that are biblical words
that are necessary for us
if we're going to do what God's called us to do
but we live in a society that pumps into our minds,
it's your life, it's your way.
Have it your way, do what you want, do what,
no, God says that being godly is his plan
for your life and for my life.
By the way, our world needs to see some people
that are truly godly.
Our world needs to see some people that are godly.
Our world has an idea and that idea was not just born out
of no evidence whatsoever of Christians being hypocrites.
There's some that have been experiencing
in that situation and it's sad.
I have a relative that would tell if they were asked
and they have the responsibility of making it known
that the worst tenants they ever had
when they rented out their house were saved people.
Not the lost people they rented their house to
but the saved people, fellow church members.
He said, that shouldn't be that way, I understand that.
He said, we need to be godly and David says to Solomon,
be strong, show thyself a man and he gives him this charge
to walk in the ways of the Lord, to keep his statutes,
his commandments, his judgments, his testimonies.
Now, interestingly enough, David was a king
and Solomon was gonna be the king.
The book of Deuteronomy, Moses gives the instruction
that kings had the responsibility of writing out
the law of the Lord.
How important that would be.
As you write out the law of the Lord,
I mean, it's a tedious task, a time consuming task
but how important and how impactful it would be
if they would actually do that.
For you and I this morning, we don't have to necessarily
write out the words that we read in the Bible
but we must be reading them and applying them.
We must be digging into the word of God.
Notice this morning, number three, as we conclude,
notice the consequences of godly living.
The consequences of godly living.
At the end of verse number three, he says,
as it is written in the law of Moses
back in 1 Kings chapter two, then notice this phrase,
that thou mayest prosper in all that thou doest
and withersoever thou turnest thyself.
Can I tell you this morning that there's a lot of people
in our world that are looking for prosperity?
Can I tell you this morning that prosperity in God's view
or God's eyes is not the same as prosperity
in man's view or man's eyes?
When we look here and the Bible says that thou mayest
prosper in all that thou doest,
I believe that we could summarize that this morning
or maybe restate it this way, that it would be
that you would have God's blessing
and God's favor in your life.
I wonder this morning, do you want God's favor in your life?
Do you want God's blessing in your life?
I mean, you want God to smile upon your life,
to be pleased.
The reality is that most of us this morning,
I know that I personally have this as my personality,
I like to please people.
I don't like it when people are not pleased with me,
but I've had to learn in leadership that you're not gonna
please all the people all the time and it's just part of it,
but the reality is that I like to please people.
I don't like it when somebody's not pleased,
but the reality, how much more important
that we please God.
I preached a message a couple of years ago
for the audience of one.
The reality is that we live our lives singular purpose
to please our God.
If we please God and if his favor and his blessing
and his smile would shine upon us,
oh, that's what it's all about.
And this morning when we look at the consequences
of godly living, we understand that this does not happen.
This recipe that if we could call it that this morning,
that's outlined for us this morning,
the prosperity doesn't come in Solomon's life
just by chance.
No, it's by following the charge that has been issued.
I think of Nehemiah in Nehemiah chapter two
in verse number eight when he makes the statement
about God's favor being in his life.
He says this, at the end of the text,
it says, and the king granted me according
to the good hand of my God upon me.
I don't think Nehemiah was boasting.
I don't think Nehemiah was saying look at me,
God's hand is upon me.
No, Nehemiah was recognizing that all of those things
that had transpired after he had wept
and poured his heart out to God in Nehemiah chapter one
and after he stands before King Ahasuerus
and God's favor is evidenced and he has that privilege
of being able to return, he recognizes
that God's good hand was upon him.
Why?
Because he sought the Lord, because he obeyed the Lord.
There was confession, there was just a brokenness
in the life of Nehemiah in chapter number one
and you see God's favor in his life.
We see it in Joshua, in Joshua chapter number one.
We understand that God's favor comes in the lives
of those that are obedient to the precepts of this word.
Why do we get into the Bible?
Why do we study the Bible?
Why do we want to know the Bible?
So that we can win some kind of a Bible quiz game.
No, it's so that we can apply the truth in our lives
so that we could be like Christ, so that we could please him.
I want you to understand this morning
that we find here the consequence of godly living,
but I think it's necessary to make a contrast
just for a moment this morning
and see the consequence of worldly living,
of forsaking the ways of the Lord.
Because there's a real danger that people would forsake.
Solomon is standing there before his father, David,
when David is ready to die and David gives a charge,
but can I tell you that he has no control
on whether Solomon will actually apply it in his life.
Solomon has to have a measure of faith
in the message that is being delivered to him by his father
as being a right message that he would then embrace
and apply in his own life
so that he could have God's favor.
Unfortunately today, for every single one of us,
we can forsake the teachings of God.
You know how many people say,
well, it's not gonna happen to me.
It's not gonna happen to me.
I'm gonna be the exception.
It doesn't happen that way very often.
I want you to notice what the Bible says
in the book of Proverbs.
I'm gonna read two verses of scripture
just to make a contrast quickly.
We see the consequences of godly living
that thou mayest prosper in all that thou doest,
that we'd have God's blessing and God's favor,
but I want you to understand.
We have to understand that in Proverbs 13, in verse number 13, the Bible says,
Whoso despiseth the word shall be destroyed.
That's strong language.
Whoso despiseth the word shall be destroyed, but he that feareth the commandment shall be rewarded.
What a contrast between the one who despises and the one that fears, the one who rejects
and the one who receives, the one who is destroyed and the one who is rewarded.
It continues in verse 14.
The law of the wise is a fountain of life to depart from the snares of death.
Good understanding giveth favor, but then notice this, but the way of transgressors
is hard.
Proverbs 28.
We see the contrast, oh, this morning I hope that we would determine that we'll follow
the charge.
Every single one of us, we know contextually that it's David speaking to his son Solomon,
it's Father's Day, show thyself a man, but the application for every one of us this morning
that we would be strong in the Lord, that we would live godly lives, that we would see
the consequences of godly living, that God's favor would be upon our lives, that we would
not despise or reject the commandment of the Lord, but that we would receive it and apply
it in our lives so that we might have God's favor.
Notice in Proverbs 28, notice in verse number 13, he that covereth his sins shall not prosper,
but whoso confesseth and forsaketh them shall have mercy.
This morning, I want God's favor in my life.
I believe this morning that you too would stand and say, I want God's favor in my life.
But understand, there's a pathway, we have to follow His way, we have to follow the path
that God has given to us.
I am so thankful that God inspired His Word and then preserved His Word and that His Word
is a lamp and it's a light, that His Word guides us and directs us, that we have this
precious book so that we can know how to live a life that's pleasing to Him.
Oh, we understand that the book teaches us the way of salvation.
Without this book, I'd never know how I could approach a holy God.
God gives us His Word and tells us what He did for us so that we could know Him, so that
we could be saved, and then how we live for Him because He's our heavenly Father.
And what a blessing this morning.
Yes, I've titled the message, Show Thyself a Man.
But I want you to understand, I hope everyone here this morning would take the truth of
1 Kings chapter 2 and we analyze this moment between a father and a son, literally on his
deathbed, going the way of all the earth, but delivering this charge.
The significance of the moment in 1 Kings chapter 2 must not pass us by.
We must see it, we analyze it, but then we apply it.
How am I doing?
Keeping His commandments, His statutes, His judgments, His testimonies, how am I doing?
Walking in the ways of the Lord.
Oh, I think all of us would say, I want God's favor and I want God's blessing.
But the pathway to blessing is obedience.
The pathway to blessing is obedience.
Let us pray.
Father, we love You.
We thank You for loving us.
We thank You this morning for Your Word and for the truth of Your Word.
We thank You that You have recorded this passage of this moment between father and son, David
and Solomon.
God, I pray that as we take time this morning to analyze it, that we would be careful to
apply truth in our lives, that we would evaluate our own lives to see how we're doing in our
walk with You.
Lord, help us to live lives that are obedient.
Lord, help us to have a desire to influence and impact a future generation, that they
would not only hear our words as we see in the life of Paul, that they would hear, but
also that they would see in us a life of obedience.
Lord, we want Your favor.
We want Your blessing.
Lord, we know that that pathway to blessing is marked by obedience.
I pray that You would work in hearts and lives this morning.
We started out by talking about the fact that David was going to die.
Maybe this morning, you're here and you do not know that heaven is your home.
In fact, you might say that I hope that when I die, I'd go to heaven.
I think so.
I hope so.
But the reality this morning is that you just do not know with certainty that heaven is
your home.
There's never been a time in your life that you were born again, that you were saved by
the grace of God.
Can I tell you this morning that we'd love to take a Bible and show you how you can know
for sure that heaven is your home.
I would not embarrass you.
I'm not going to ask you to raise your hand or any of that sort of thing, but we would
invite you to come in our invitation time so that we might take a Bible and show you
so you could leave here knowing with certainty that heaven is your home.
How about you, child of God?
Is your life marked by obedience, keeping the statutes, commandments, judgments, testimonies
of the Lord, doing, walking in the ways of the Lord, seeking to please, honor, and glorify
Him?
Lord, I pray that You would work in the moments that follow, that You'd have Your will in
one way, that You'd be honored and glorified through every decision, and we'll thank You
for it.
In Christ's name we pray.
Would you stand with me?
Heads are bowed.
Eyes are closed.
Kimberly's going to play quietly on the piano.
As she does, the altar is open.
If you're not sure of heaven, please come.
We take a Bible and show you how you can know for sure that heaven is your home.
If you're saved this morning, say, I want God's favor in my life.
I want to walk in the ways of the Lord so that I can have God's favor.
As Kimberly plays, the altar is open.