not have a Bible readily available for them
in their own language, people that need to share the Bible,
folks that only have parts of a Bible.
And I'm so thankful to have a Bible, amen.
And the Bible is just a precious book.
There's nothing like it in all the world
and it's God's word and what a blessing it is
to have a Bible, be able to preach the word,
be able to sing about the word and we're grateful.
Everything that you know to be true about God
and about life, you know from the Bible, amen.
And what a blessing and I'm so thankful.
Acts chapter number four this morning,
Acts chapter number four,
and to be looking at a portion of scripture here,
and I'm gonna kind of by way of introduction,
kind of journey through chapter three
and into chapter number four.
And so we'll just kind of reference a number of things.
I'm not gonna read a bunch of the verses
as we go by way of introduction,
but if you're familiar with the book of Acts,
you know that in Acts chapter number three,
a great miracle is recorded.
And the Bible tells us that Peter and John,
they're heading there to the temple.
And of course, there's that man that is just lame
and he calls out and he asked for help.
And Peter looks upon him and he says,
silver and gold have I none,
but such as I have in the name of Jesus Christ of Nazareth,
rise up and walk.
And that man was healed.
And the Bible says that he went into the temple
and he was leaping.
The Bible says walking and leaping and praising God.
Verse nine of Acts three says this,
and all the people saw him walking and praising God.
And they knew, verse number 10,
that it was he which sat for alms
at the beautiful gate of the temple.
Now this great miracle that is recorded here
had a great impact and effect.
We find that thousands of people will trust Jesus Christ
as their personal savior as a result of this great miracle.
Why?
Because after the miracle,
their people gathered together and guess what happens?
Peter preaches the gospel, amen.
And often as you study through the book of Acts,
you find as you begin to read about the miracles,
how God would confirm the word with signs following.
We read that in the gospel of Mark
and we find that the Lord Jesus Christ
allowed for these miracles to take place.
Some of these temporary sign gifts
so that people would be open to hearing
the preaching of the word of God.
And the great company gathers together 5,000,
above 5,000 trust Christ as their savior.
And what a blessing to think about this amazing miracle
and the impact of this miracle.
We understand though that the religious leaders,
they were angered and the disciples experienced persecution
as a result of what was taking place.
And as you get into chapter number four,
you find that that persecution is outlined for us
and the threatenings that are given to the disciples.
It's very interesting as you read through the fourth chapter
of the book of Acts, we find that on two occasions,
the Lord purposefully uses this phrase,
filled with the Holy Ghost,
filled with the Holy Ghost.
We find the first reference in Acts chapter number four
is with regard to Peter as they are called
before the religious leaders and in verse number seven,
it says when they had set them in the midst
and so the religious leaders are there,
they set the disciples and they asked by what power
or by what name have ye done this?
And the Bible then says in verse number eight,
then Peter notice filled with the Holy Ghost,
said unto them, ye rulers of the people
and elders of Israel.
He then begins to provide them with an answer
to the question by what power or by what name
have you done this?
In verse nine, if we this day be examined
of the good deed done to the impotent man
by what means he has made whole.
So that's the miracle of chapter three.
The Bible says in verse number 10,
be it known unto, notice what he says,
be it known unto you all and to all the people of Israel.
Notice that by the name of Jesus Christ of Nazareth,
whom ye crucified, whom God raised from the dead,
even by him doth this man stand here before you whole.
Now that's some boldness, amen.
That's the result of being filled with the Holy Ghost.
In fact, the Bible will tell us in verse number 12
that Peter will then say this,
neither is there salvation in any other
for there is none other name given under heaven,
given among men whereby we must be saved.
Now notice verse 13, these religious leaders
that are interrogating if you will,
the Bible says now when they saw the boldness
of Peter and John and perceive that they were unlearned
and ignorant men, they marveled.
And then notice the end of verse number 13,
and they took knowledge of them
that they had been with Jesus.
We find that here the result of being filled
with the Holy Ghost as the Bible tells us
in verse number eight is that Peter stands up
and with great boldness, he answers those
that are interrogating and he declares
the glorious gospel of the Lord Jesus Christ.
He says with boldness that every single person
that was sitting on that council,
every single person in Israel needed to know the truth
that he was going to declare.
Furthermore, he says that there's salvation in no other.
Aren't you thankful that Jesus is the way,
the truth and the life and no man cometh
unto the Father, but by him.
And we find that here, the first references given to us
in Acts chapter number four of Peter being filled
with the Holy Ghost after the conversation takes place,
after the preaching is given by Peter,
the interrogation continues.
And we find that the threatenings intensify
and the disciples are told to go and to preach
or to speak no longer in the name of the Lord Jesus Christ.
And we find that the disciples answer for we cannot
but speak the things which we have seen and heard.
Oh, that some of God's people today would have
that same perspective that they say in verse number 20
that we cannot but speak the things
which we have seen and heard.
Oftentimes today in 2026, the Christians are silenced
without being threatened.
I don't know if you believe that, let me say it again.
The Christians are silenced without being threatened, amen.
These folks are threatened,
they've already spent a night in jail and they're threatened
and they're told not to speak any longer.
And they say, we cannot but speak the things
which we have seen and heard.
Oh, praise the Lord, we need some of that in 2026, amen.
We need to get so filled up,
we need to spend so much time with the Lord
as it says in verse 13, that they had been with Jesus,
that it's just that overflow.
We can't help but talk about how wonderful our Savior is
and what He's done for us
and what He wants to do for others, amen.
And we find that they eventually
after being threatened some more, they are departed.
And the Bible tells us in verse number 23,
that they returned, that they went to their own company.
And as they go and they gather together
with the other believers there,
the Bible tells us that they prayed,
that they opened up their voice
or they lifted up their voices,
they opened their mouths in verse 24.
And when they heard that,
they lifted up their voice to God with one accord
and said, Lord, thou art God,
which has made heaven and earth
and the sea and all that in them is.
And they will continue to pray.
And we find that very specifically,
a request is given in verse number 29.
The Bible says in verse 29,
and now Lord behold their threatenings.
Notice the request is this,
and grant unto thy servants,
that with all boldness, they may speak thy word.
We could spend time today looking at verse 29
and examining the request of the disciples
and understanding how amazing it is
that they did not pray for those that are persecuting.
They did not pray that God would judge them.
They did not pray that they would be removed
from that difficult situation.
No, in the midst of great difficulty,
they simply prayed for boldness.
They asked the Lord, Lord, give us boldness to what?
To speak thy word.
And we find that the specific prayer request is answered
in verse number 31, when we read the second reference here
with regard to the subject
that we're dealing with this morning,
being filled with the Holy Ghost.
Notice in verse 31,
and when they had prayed,
the place was shaken where they were assembled together.
Notice what it says,
and they were all filled with the Holy Ghost,
and they spake the word of God with boldness.
And this morning, as we think about this statement
that is repeated twice in Acts chapter number four,
once in verse eight, once again in verse number 31,
they were all filled with the Holy Ghost.
I wanna preach just a little bit this morning
about being filled with the Holy Ghost.
Last week, we talked about being free,
made free.
from the law of sin and death,
and talked about the idea of being saved
by the grace of God.
And I'm so thankful to be saved.
And at the moment, if you're here this morning,
at the moment that you trust that Jesus Christ
is your personal savior,
something amazing took place,
and that is that the Holy Spirit of God indwelled you.
The Bible teaches us about the indwelling
of the Spirit of God.
The Bible tells us the Holy Spirit,
the Holy Ghost is the earnest of our inheritance.
The Bible tells us that we're sealed with the Holy Ghost.
And I'm thankful this morning to understand
the teaching biblically with regard
to the indwelling of the Holy Ghost.
But this morning, we're not talking about
the indwelling of the Holy Ghost,
we're talking about the filling of the Holy Ghost.
And it's a different thing.
It's different to be indwelled by or to be filled with.
And we find that if you're saved this morning,
if you've trusted Christ,
that every single one of us
would be able to stand up with assurance and say
that I am indwelled by the Holy Ghost.
The Bible tells us in 1 Corinthians 6,
in verses 19 and 20,
that our bodies are the temple of the Holy Ghost, amen.
And we understand that truth and that principle.
But here's the difference.
Not every one of us can stand up
and say that we're filled with the Holy Ghost.
There's a difference between being indwelled with
and being filled by.
And so this morning, I wanna spend a little time
looking at this subject.
And before we jump into the points,
let me just make one side note.
In verse 31, the Bible says,
they were all filled with the Holy Ghost.
And then notice what it says,
and they spake the word of God with boldness.
And as we look at that statement
at the end of verse number 31,
it helps us to understand
and really to be able to combat some false teaching.
There's false teaching.
Sometimes we get a little bit shy
about preaching about the Holy Ghost,
about preaching about the Holy Spirit.
And here's the reality.
We believe in the Trinity, amen.
God, the Father, God, the Son, and God, the Holy Ghost.
In fact, in just a little bit here in chapter number five,
we find that there's a situation with Ananias and Sapphira
and Peter's gonna call them out.
Why? Because they lied.
And notice what the Bible says
in chapter five in verse number three.
But Peter said, Ananias, why hath Satan filled thine heart?
Notice what it says, to lie to the Holy Ghost.
Right, is that what your Bible says
in Acts five in verse number three?
And so very plainly,
we understand that God had revealed to Peter
what was taking place.
And we find that as Peter confronts there Ananias
in verse number three,
he tells them that he's lied to the Holy Ghost.
We then continue to read in the portion of scripture.
And we find that in verse number four,
the Bible says this, speaking about the fact
that they didn't give all the money,
they didn't have to, there was no requirement to,
but they lied about it.
In verse number four, while it remained,
was it not thine own?
And after it was sold, was it not thine own possession?
Excuse me, thine own power?
Notice this, why hast thou conceived this thing
in thine heart?
Thou hast not lied unto men, but unto,
what does your Bible say?
God.
So in verse number three, who did he lie to?
The Holy Ghost.
In verse number four, who did he lie to?
God.
Is there a problem?
No, because the Holy Ghost is God.
But we sometimes get shy about preaching
about the Holy Ghost or the Holy Spirit, why?
Well, because of some of the Pentecostal things
that go on around our society,
some things that we've been confronted with.
We don't know how to answer the question
with regard to speaking in tongues.
We get all kinds of twisted up.
We don't understand what the Bible says.
And here's oftentimes what they'll say.
If you're filled with the Holy Ghost, you speak in tongues.
That's always what happens.
Acts chapter number four, verse number 31.
They were filled with the Holy Ghost
and they spake the word of God with boldness.
Can I tell you, you just need to know the Bible.
You just need to know the Bible.
And if you know the Bible, it will help you immensely
as you chart the waters and navigate
through dealing with false teaching and all sorts of things.
Listen, I'm thankful this morning
that the Holy Spirit of God indwells me,
but I'm thankful that I can be filled with the Holy Ghost.
And it's not something that we need to shy away from.
It's not something that we need to be
all kind of spooked out over.
No, the Holy Ghost, the Holy Spirit is God.
And so as we look at the text of scripture this morning,
we find here in Acts chapter number four,
but we're reminded, and I'll reference
throughout the message this morning,
the instruction that Paul gives to the believers in Ephesus.
In fact, if you take your Bible quickly
and turn over to the book of Ephesians in chapter number five
and again, it's a verse of scripture
that many of us would be familiar with,
perhaps be able to even quote this morning.
But I want you to notice in Ephesians chapter number five
in verse number 18, Paul is providing instruction
to these believers at Ephesus.
And notice he says in verse 18,
under the inspiration of the Holy Spirit of God,
and be not drunk with wine, wear it as excess,
but be filled with the Spirit.
This morning, if you're taking notes,
the points are a little bit lengthy,
so give yourself enough room.
There's only three points,
there's a little bit verbiage there.
But number one, if you're taking notes,
it is God's plan, it is God's plan
for every New Testament believer
to be filled with the Holy Ghost.
It is God's plan for every New Testament believer
This is not just for the apostles,
it's not just for the disciples,
it's not just for the pastors,
it's for every child of God, it is God's plan.
I could say it this way, it is God's will
for you and for me as his people
to be filled with the Holy Ghost.
We find here as we're looking in Ephesians 5
in verse number 18, and we notice very interesting
the verbiage of this instruction here is of great interest.
In fact, the idea here when it says
be filled with the Spirit,
it's a present passive imperative.
And I don't get into this too often,
but it's quite interesting as you look
in Ephesians 5 in verse 18,
because we find that what this means
in the structure of this command here
is that we find that it's a command
to be continuously followed.
Let me say it this way, I'm indwelled
with the Holy Spirit the moment I get saved.
But the filling of the Holy Spirit
is something that is to be done continuously.
You might have been filled with the Spirit yesterday
and filled with self today.
You might be filled with the Spirit today
and filled with self tomorrow.
You might be filled with the Spirit this moment
and filled with self in another 30 minutes
because something happens and someone says something
and whatever, and the old man rises up
and all of a sudden you're filled with self,
you're no longer filled with the Holy Ghost
and controlled by the Spirit of God.
And so we find that the structure of the command here
reveals to us that it's a command
to be continuously followed.
It literally means to fill to the full.
It means to be constantly being filled.
It's passive.
I said that it was a present passive imperative.
It's passive because it's not something
that you or I can manufacture on our own.
Amen?
Can I tell you in some of the Pentecostal movements
and some of the things that go on,
there's a measure of manufacturing
that evidence, quote unquote,
of being filled with the Spirit.
I've spoken to people personally, individually
that have mentioned being part of a Pentecostal church
and they've had the pressure from others
within the assembly that say hey listen,
if you don't speak in tongues,
then you're not really filled with the Holy Ghost
and there are times in which they literally teach people
how to speak in tongues.
I'm sorry but you're taking a text of scripture
from Acts number two and you're totally misrepresenting
the whole miracle of Acts chapter number two.
Those disciples notice a couple of things.
They were never taught how to speak in tongues.
Number one.
Number two, they were known languages.
And here's what the Bible says.
Every man heard him in their own tongue.
So really the miracle is more with the ear
than it even is with the tongue
because every man heard him.
And notice the Bible says that they heard them speak what?
The works of God.
And so we begin to understand that this is not something
that we manufacture on our own.
This is not something that we just kinda try to build
this thing up in us that we're filled with the Holy Ghost.
No, we find that it's passive because it is a work
that God does in us.
It is a work that God completes.
When does he complete the work?
When does he do the work?
Well, it's when we yield and surrender to him.
When we yield and we surrender to him.
If I understand this morning that it's God's plan
for every New Testament believer to be filled
with the Holy Ghost, then I have to understand
that as God would have the desire,
it's his will that his children would be filled
with the Holy Ghost.
Here's the reality.
If that's God's will, then that means he wants it to happen.
So why isn't it?
Because I'm filled with self and you're filled with self
and we're so filled up with self,
we're so filled up with junk,
we're so filled up with the world
that we can't be filled with the Holy Ghost.
Because if you have a vessel that's filled
with some content, whatever that vessel may be,
and you have that vessel filled with something,
you cannot fill it with something else
until it's emptied.
It's pretty simple.
There's a bottle of water here.
It's not yet been opened.
And this bottle of water, it's not filled to the full,
but it's filled pretty high.
If I wanted to put some sweet tea in here, amen.
And I love sweet.
tea. I was at lunch yesterday with a couple from our church and they got me
my special couple of bottles of sweet tea, amen, and praised the Lord for their
kindness. And they said, well you just take it home with you because we're not
gonna drink it. And I said, you don't know what you're missing. And here's the
reality is that if I wanted to put sweet tea in this thing, I got to first empty
it, right? It's a simple illustration, but it's something that each of us can
relate to. You know what's gonna happen if I try to just start pouring sweet tea
in here? Not only am I gonna have a mess, but it's gonna be really diluted. You
ever have diluted drinks? I mean I know we give the kids like diluted apple
juice because we don't want them to have all the sugar or whatever and we'll kind
of mix it half and half with the kids. Sometimes you do that. Listen, I don't
want my sweet tea half and half. Amen? You know what I'm saying? I want the
whole, like I either want unsweetened tea, just give me water. I don't even want to
drink it. I just want water or I want sweet tea. And we find that we're so
filled with self. We're so filled with the world. We're so filled with junk that
though God wants us to be filled with the Spirit, though God's will and God's
plan is for every New Testament believer to be filled with the Holy Ghost, he
can't do it until we yield and surrender. Now let me explain the fact that he
can't do it. Understand that the Bible says that our God can do all things, but
the Bible also says that they limited the Holy One of Israel in Psalm 78. You
know how we limit God today? We limit God by being filled with self, by being
worldly and being carnal. We limit God. And so we find here that this is such an
important thing. The biggest hindrance to being filled with the Holy Ghost is that
we're filled with self. We're so prideful and we're so arrogant and it's
all about me and it's all about what I want. It's all about, and it's a
problem. And we never get the opportunity to fulfill the plan that God has for us
to be filled with the Holy Ghost because I stay filled with self. Can I tell you
it's really kind of a consequence of the society in which we live. Now I don't
want to blame society. I don't want to excuse our disobedience and just say
well simply it's the society, the culture that we live in. Help me or I hope that I
can help you understand this morning what I mean by that. The culture and the
society that we live in is all about you and all about self. It's such a prideful
and worldly philosophy that we have in the world in which we live and we find
that we have to combat that. That's why the Bible says and be not conformed to
this world but be transformed by the renewing of your mind that you may prove
what is that good and perfect and acceptable will of God. It is God's will
that you're filled with the Holy Ghost. It is God's plan for every New Testament
believer and we need to be sure that we're not just getting to the
place where we're conformed to the image of this world and we find here
this morning that if you are saved, if you've trusted Jesus Christ as your
personal Savior on the authority of the Word of God I can tell you that it is
God's plan, it is God's will that you are filled with the Holy Ghost. Not only do
we see number one that it's God's plan for every New Testament believer to be
filled with the Holy Ghost but I'd say this number two it is a privilege for
every New Testament believer to be filled with the Holy Ghost. It's a unique
privilege that we have in the church age. You understand this morning that a lost
person cannot be filled with the Holy Ghost. It's impossible. They can't be
filled with the Holy Ghost. The lost people cannot be filled with the Holy
Ghost. We find that it's a privilege for the New Testament believer but we also
understand that the ministry of the Holy Ghost is distinctly different in this
era of history known as what we refer to as the church age than it was in the
Old Testament. In the Old Testament we understand that Old Testament saints you
can read about Saul and others, how the Spirit would come upon them and the
Spirit would depart from them and all of that sort of thing and we understand and
now listen as New Testament believers it is a unique privilege for us to be
filled with the Holy Ghost and I'm thankful again to be indwelled with the
Holy Ghost but the idea here this morning of being filled with the Holy
Ghost, go to the book of John if you will, go to the Gospel of John in chapter
number 14. I'm going to look at a little bit of instruction that the Lord Jesus
Christ gives before he would go to Calvary in these few chapters in chapter
14, 15, and 16 we'll look at some references in each of these chapters. We
find that the Lord had let them know after washing the feet of the disciples
in chapter 13 that he would soon be going to Calvary, fulfilling the purpose
for which he was born and that was to die in the place of humanity. He tasted
death for every man so that he could conquer sin, death, and the grave. He paid
for the sins of humanity and we rejoice in that and within the teaching he
talks often in these few chapters about the Holy Ghost. Notice what he says in
John 14 in verse number 16, and I will pray the Father and he shall give you
another Comforter. You notice that the word Comforter is capitalized there
because it's a word that is given to a name that's ascribed to the Holy Ghost
or the Holy Spirit, the Comforter, that he may abide with you forever. Verse 17,
even the Spirit of Truth, another name that's given to the Holy Spirit known as
not only the Comforter but the Spirit of Truth, whom the world, notice what it says,
cannot receive because it seeth him not, neither knoweth him, but ye know him for
he dwelleth with you and shall be in you. Verse 18, I will not leave you
comfortless, I will come to you. Aren't you thankful for the ministry of the
Holy Ghost? He is the Comforter. It says in verse number 26 of chapter 14, notice,
but the Comforter, which is the Holy Ghost, whom the Father will send in my
name, he shall teach you all things and bring all things to your remembrance
whatsoever I have said unto you. Now begin to understand again, as I've
mentioned a few times already this morning, the indwelling of the Holy
Ghost versus the filling of the Holy Ghost, and I'm thankful that at the
moment of salvation we're indwelled with the Holy Ghost, but this idea of being
filled with the Holy Ghost, we understand as we would study through the Bible that
as believers we can quench and grieve the Holy Ghost, and we ought not quench or
grieve the Holy Ghost, but we find that through our actions and through our
responses to the leadership of the Lord and through the work of the Holy Ghost
that we can quench and grieve the Spirit of God. And so we find that here the Lord
Jesus Christ is providing instruction to the disciples with regard to, yes, he
would be leaving the Lord Jesus Christ because he was gonna go to Calvary, he
was gonna go to the grave, he was gonna rise again, of course after 40 days he
would ascend to heaven, but he says I'm not gonna leave you comfortless, and he
talks about the ministry of the Holy Ghost in chapter 15. Notice, if you will,
here in chapter 15 in verse number 26, again he's reiterating this. Why is he
saying, by the way, the teaching in chapters really 14, 15, and 16 is really
concise as far as timing is concerned. It's one big period of instruction
that Jesus is giving to the disciples, and we find in verse 26, but when the
Comforter is come, whom I will send unto you from the Father, even the Spirit of
truth, which proceedeth from the Father, he shall testify of me, and ye also shall
bear witness, because ye have been with me from the beginning. And so you think
about the ministry here, even as we looked at it in Acts chapter number 4,
they were filled with the Holy Ghost, and then what do they do? They spoke the
Word of God with boldness. Here the Lord Jesus Christ says that when the Comforter
is come, whom I will send unto you from the Father, even the Spirit of truth,
which proceedeth from the Father, he shall testify of me, and ye also shall
bear witness. Remember in Acts chapter number 4, you're telling us to stop
talking, we can't help but talk. Why? Because he was filled with the Holy
Ghost, amen? And we find that in chapter number 16, here in the Gospel of John, he
continues to teach about the ministry and the sending of the Holy Ghost. He says
in verse number 7, here in John 16, nevertheless I tell you the truth, it is
expedient for you that I go away. For if I go not away, the Comforter will not
come unto you, but if I depart, I will send him unto you. Now I like the way that
we read verse number 7, because obviously the disciples, they have walked with the
Lord Jesus Christ for some years now. There's been some time in which they've
enjoyed the opportunity to walk with the Lord Jesus Christ, physically present on
earth. Now understand, there's only one just little period of human history where
that was possible.
and these individuals had that privilege
to walk with the Lord bodily while he was here on earth.
And he says to them, it is expedient for you
that I go away.
Now, can you understand?
They don't want Jesus to leave, right?
They've enjoyed being with Jesus.
They don't understand everything.
And Jesus so plainly and so specifically says to them,
it is expedient for you that I go away.
It is in your best interest.
It is beneficial for you.
It is expedient for you.
It's better for you.
It is to your advantage.
And we find here that he says, for if I go not away,
the comforter will not come unto you.
But if I depart, I will send him unto you.
And notice as we continue reading
through the next several verses of John 16,
the Bible says in verse number eight, and when he has come.
See, Jesus knew that he was gonna go away
and he knew that he was gonna send.
He's helping send the comforter, the Holy Ghost.
He's helping the disciples to understand
that it was necessary for that to take place.
And he says in verse number eight, and when he has come,
notice he will reprove the world of sin
and of righteousness and of judgment.
Now, this specifically is the work of the Holy Ghost
with regard to lost people.
The work of the Holy Ghost with regard to lost people
is different than the work of the Holy Ghost
with regard to his children, those that have been saved.
So here's the reality.
If you're saved here this morning,
it's because the Holy Ghost worked
as we see in verses eight through 11.
He worked that way in your life when you were lost.
Amen?
If you're lost here this morning
or you're tuned in via live stream
and you're not sure of heaven,
then the Holy Ghost is doing the work
of verses eight through 11.
We see it's distinct from the work that he does
in the life of a believer.
What does that work?
Well, the Bible says that he will reprove the world of sin
and of righteousness and of judgment.
Why?
It kind of explains that in verse number nine,
of sin, because they believe not on me.
Listen, the Holy Ghost,
what he does is he convinces sinners that they're sinners,
that they're guilty.
Here's the reality this morning.
It's, for lost people, for me personally, my own testimony,
it was not hard for me to acknowledge
the fact that I was guilty.
I found very few people that will acknowledge
that they're sinners, that they're guilty.
They wanna talk about the fact
that they're not as bad as someone else
and all that sort of thing,
because that's the only way that they can have
some level of comfort or hope
is that they're not as bad as somebody else
and therefore in their mind of kind of that weights
and balances that they might be able to make it.
But we understand that that's not true biblically.
So what does the Holy Ghost do?
Well, he reproves of sin.
Notice not only of sin, but it says of righteousness,
because I go to my father and you see me no more.
Listen, the Holy Ghost is the one that reproves
or convinces us that Jesus alone is righteous.
It's not by mine own righteousness, amen.
It's nothing that I could do.
We find that Daniel or excuse me,
Isaiah would make it very plain
that all of our righteousness are as filthy rags.
We find that the scriptures teach us
that he hath made him to be sin for us, why?
So that we could be made the righteousness of God in him.
And it's the Holy Ghost that convinces lost people
of that truth, that I'm a sinner,
that Jesus Christ is the only righteous one
and I need his righteousness imputed to mine account.
We find this verse number 11 of judgment,
because the prince of this world is judged.
The reality is that judgment is real.
It will come.
Lost people sometimes are living
as if everything is wonderful
and they have all of these quote unquote blessings
and benefits and life couldn't be any better.
But judgment is coming.
And you know who the one is that convinces them
of judgment is the Holy Ghost.
Death and hell were cast in the lake of fire.
This is the second death.
Judgment will come.
I was walking through the store one day
and there's this guy that had this shirt
that said only God can judge me.
I had two thoughts at that moment,
it's true and it's fearful.
Those were my two thoughts.
I was sitting in a drive-through the other day,
met a pastor friend and was sitting there
and a guy walked into the establishment
and he had this shirt on and on the back of his shirt
he said I'm a child of hell.
What in the world does that even mean?
I was in my car and they were inside,
I didn't have an opportunity to be able
to have any interaction whatsoever with the individual.
But the reality, listen, judgment day is coming.
Can I tell you this this morning?
This world, this world is the best
that a lost person will ever experience.
It's the best that the lost person will ever experience.
The flip side of that is it's the worst
that God's people will ever experience.
Isn't that awesome?
But that's the work of the Holy Ghost
and if you're saved this morning,
he did that work in you at some point.
He convinced you of sin, of righteousness,
of judgment to come.
We find in verse number 12 he says,
I have yet many things to say unto you,
but you cannot bear them now,
how be it when he, the spirit of truth has come,
he will guide you into all truth,
for he shall not speak of himself,
but whatsoever he shall hear,
that shall he speak and he will show you things to come.
He shall glorify me for he shall receive of mine
and shall show it unto you all things
that the Father hath are mine.
Therefore said I that he shall take of mine
and shall show it unto you.
Those verses will help us understand
the ministry of the Holy Ghost in the life of a believer.
And so we find this morning as we look here
and we consider the thought that they were filled
with the Holy Ghost, Peter filled with the Holy Ghost,
those others when they went to their own company
and they prayed and they sought the Lord
and they prayed for boldness
and they were all filled with the Holy Ghost,
this is not only God's plan for every New Testament believer
to be filled with the Holy Ghost,
but it is a privilege for every New Testament believer
to be filled with the Holy Ghost.
Again, a lost person can't be filled with the Holy Ghost,
can't be done.
The Old Testament, those that went before us,
different ministry of the Holy Spirit
in the Old Testament versus here
in the New Testament in the church age.
And I'm so thankful for the privilege that we have.
Now, here's the reality.
If there's a privilege before us,
why do we continue to be filled with self?
I mean, and I don't wanna get too logical
because it's not really just a logical argument
that you can provide.
Now, logically, it makes sense,
but we understand it's a spiritual truth.
But logically, if we understand what it produces
when we're filled with the Holy Ghost,
when we understand that it's God's plan
for us to be filled with the Holy Ghost,
when we understand that it's a privilege
to be filled with the Holy Ghost,
why do God's people continue to run around
and be filled with self?
Because there's a battle between your old man
and the new man.
There's a battle.
There's an absolute battle that takes place.
At the moment that you got saved,
at the moment that I got saved,
my flesh and your flesh were not eradicated.
We still have the old man.
That's why we read in the book of Ephesians,
again, in the book of Colossians,
the principle of put off and put on.
That's why the Apostle Paul says in the book of Galatians,
I am crucified with Christ.
That's why we read in the book of Colossians
that we're to mortify our members.
We're to reckon ourselves to be dead in deed to sin
is what we read in the book of Romans.
And we begin to think about those statements
and begin to understand really the conflict
that we deal with internally
in this idea of being filled with the Holy Ghost,
but you have your old nature and you have the new nature
and there's this constant struggle.
And here's what we find in the book of Galatians,
Paul would say it this way.
And Paul experienced this, he understood this,
and he's writing it under,
we understand all scripture is given by inspiration of God.
He's writing it under the inspiration of the Holy Ghost.
We find that he tells us in Galatians chapter number five,
he tells us this in verse number 16.
This I say then, walk in the spirit
and you shall not fulfill the lust of the flesh.
And then notice verse 17,
it's so important for us to understand.
For the flesh lusteth against the spirit
and the spirit against the flesh.
And these are contrary the one to the other
to the other, so that you cannot do the things
that you would.
If you skip down in verse number 24, it says,
and they that are Christ, notice what they've done,
have crucified the flesh with the affections and lust.
If we live in the spirit, let us also walk in the spirit.
And so we find that the apostle Paul,
he's already declared in chapter number two
that he.
has crucified the flesh and how he's walking in the spirit,
but then he's providing this instruction
and it's a great privilege for every New Testament believer
to be filled with the Holy Ghost.
Number three, this morning, to finish up the message,
if you're taking notes, number three,
God is pleased when we are filled with the Holy Ghost.
Listen, I wanna please the Lord with my life.
They that are in the flesh cannot please God.
That's what Romans says.
We read there in Hebrews 11 that without faith,
it's impossible to please him.
For he that cometh to God must believe that he is
and a rewarder of them that diligently seek him.
So we come to this idea this morning
of what we read in Acts 4 after this great miracle
in two statements, one with regard to Peter
and one with regard to the believers
that were assembled there,
that they were filled with the Holy Ghost.
In this filling, we find that in Ephesians 5,
we are commanded to be filled with the spirit
and when we are, God is pleased.
Now remember, it's a work that God does.
What's the work that we do?
Well, we crucify our flesh.
We surrender and we yield to him.
That's our part of the equation, if you will,
and God does the filling and we find that it pleases him.
We found over there, if we would begin to think
about what it produces when we're filled
with the Holy Ghost, we mentioned about the boldness
in Acts chapter number four.
Not only the boldness of Peter,
when he stood before those religious leaders
and he stands with confidence and boldness, why?
Because he was filled with the Holy Ghost.
When we think about the disciples,
they prayed for boldness and the Bible says
that they were filled with the Holy Ghost
and they spoke the word with boldness.
Listen, this morning, we need some boldness.
Can I tell you, it's amazing how bold lost people can be.
It's amazing how bold lost people can be
and how timid God's people can be.
I'm not talking about being ugly this morning.
I'm talking about being bold.
There's a difference between being bold and being ugly
and I'm not talking about being ugly.
I'm talking about being bold.
I'm talking about speaking the truth with boldness.
I'm talking about having the right position
and the right disposition.
We find that for the Apostle Paul, again,
even if you were to look and to understand
some of the ministry in which Paul had
and some of the work he talks about
in the book of 1 Thessalonians, how he came in there.
Listen, he cared for them.
He cared and nourished them like a nurse
and she cherished her children
is what the book of 1 Thessalonians tells us.
That was having the right position and the right disposition.
It's not being ugly, it's being bold.
And we need God's people today to be bold.
But the boldness doesn't come
because we work it up in our own selves.
The boldness comes as a result
of being filled with the Holy Ghost.
Again, I'm not talking about being ugly.
I've seen examples of people that are,
preachers that are ugly.
You say, well, I told them.
Yeah, and they didn't listen.
What's the Bible saying in Ephesians 4?
Speak the truth in love.
You know what's really hard for us?
To speak the truth in love.
It's easy for us to speak the truth, but not in love.
Listen, people need to know how much we love them.
We can hate the sin and love the sinner.
Amen?
And it's a result of being filled with the Holy Ghost.
We need that boldness.
Can I tell you that God is pleased
because when we are filled with the Holy Ghost,
that we're bold, but God is pleased
when we're filled with the Holy Ghost
because we're like Christ.
In Galatians chapter number five,
you may still be there in your Bible,
in Galatians chapter number five,
and we've read about a few of these verses here,
and we kind of jumped over verses 22 and 23,
but I want you to notice in Galatians five
and verse 22, and this is where we see
that God is pleased when we're filled with the Holy Ghost
because we'll be like Christ.
The Bible says, but the fruit of the Spirit is
love, joy, peace, long-suffering, gentleness,
goodness, faith, meekness, temperance.
Against such there is no law.
You're filled with the Holy Ghost.
This is the evidence.
Listen, we've mentioned this before,
that when you talk about I love Jesus,
that there's some evidence, there's some biblical truth
that would tell us if you're truly loving Jesus,
but there's biblical evidence that tells us
if you're filled with the Holy Ghost,
the fruit of the Spirit.
I'm filled with the Holy Ghost, what's the evidence?
The fruit of the Spirit, the boldness.
Can I tell you that it produces praise and worship?
In Ephesians chapter number five,
and I'm not using that phrase in a contemporary sense,
so don't get worried about that.
I'm using it in a biblical sense, amen?
And the Bible is full of praise and worship, amen?
Don't get afraid of the phrase.
It's a Bible truth, Ephesians five.
Notice we looked at verse 18.
And be not drunk with wine when it is excess,
but be filled with the Spirit.
But look at verses 19 and 20.
The Bible says speaking to yourselves
in psalms and hymns and spiritual songs,
singing and making melody in your heart to who?
To the Lord, amen?
I'm not singing for the applause of humanity,
for the applause of mankind.
No, I'm singing to the Lord.
Make a joyful noise.
And it's a joy to be able to sing.
It says this in verse 20,
giving thanks always for all things unto God and the Father
in the name of our Lord Jesus Christ.
Now listen, when you read verse number 20,
you know that that's a result
of being filled with the Holy Ghost,
because when you're filled with self,
you know what you do?
You complain.
Right?
But it says this, giving thanks, what's the next word?
Always, for what's the next word?
All things, two words.
That's the result of being filled with the Holy Ghost.
Praise and worship.
Understanding that I don't deserve anything,
but God is so good.
God is so good.
He's blessed us beyond measure.
He daily loatheth me with benefits.
When we're carnal, when we're fleshly,
when we're walking in the flesh, man, we're complainers.
Right?
I like this word even better, we're murmurers.
That's the Old Testament word.
They were murmuring.
Just sounds bad, murmur.
Yeah, bunch of complainers.
And we can criticize the children of Israel,
but you know what?
We're pretty good at imitating them, aren't we?
Come on.
We complain about everything.
Miss Mickey told me this morning,
I helped her out getting her into the building from her car,
and she said, isn't it a beautiful day?
I said, it really is.
And she said this, she said,
I don't know how anyone could complain
about this kind of weather.
I guarantee you someone somewhere would complain
about this kind of weather,
because that's just human nature.
Right?
And we find here this morning that it produces,
God is pleased, why?
Because of what it produces in us,
the boldness, the Christ-likeness,
the praise and the worship,
and we're pleasing the Lord.
In Acts chapter number seven,
you don't need to turn there, I'm wrapping it up.
The Bible tells us about Stephen.
We find that Stephen
is a man that gave his life
for the cause of Christ.
Refer to him as a martyr.
The first martyr.
It's interesting because in verse number three
of chapter six, when they're talking about
finding these seven men,
one of the criteria
is that they would be full of the Holy Ghost and wisdom.
And here's the question.
How would they know if they were full of the Holy Ghost?
How would they know?
We could say that God could confirm it, sure,
but there's the evidence of being filled
with the Holy Ghost.
The evidence, we just looked at several things.
The evidence, it's not something
that somebody manufactures,
it's a work that God does.
As we're surrendered and yielded,
as we are to that place of emptied of self.
And the Bible says that one of the criteria
that's listed there is that they'd be full
is that they'd be full of the Holy Ghost and wisdom.
And you get to chapter number seven
and we don't have time to deal with much of it,
but he preaches a message.
And oh, how sound the message is.
And how direct the message is.
And you really see the boldness of Stephen
in Acts chapter number seven.
And then the Bible tells us this in verse number 55.
But he being full of the Holy Ghost.
Something amazing about what happened in the first century.
With the spread of Christianity.
And I don't use the term to talk about it being spread
like some kind of religion,
but the gospel of the Lord Jesus Christ went forth,
people were saved, churches were established,
God was glorified.
We read that there were some people
that were full of the Holy Ghost.
Ghost. What we need in 2026, this 21st century, is to have some of God's people that would
be full of the Holy Ghost. Full of the Holy Ghost, emptied of self, recognizing that yes
I'm indwelled with the Spirit of God. If you're saved here this morning, it's not a question
about whether you're indwelled. It's a question on whether you're full of the Holy Ghost.
Have you been filled with the Holy Ghost? Again, it's a continuous thing. Listen, I've
experienced it in my own life where I was full of the Holy Ghost, something happens,
and that old man revived pretty quick. I'm just being transparent with you. I've experienced
it. What has to happen in that moment, I am crucified with Christ. Listen, there's nothing
like being full of the Holy Ghost. It's so much better than being filled with self because
when you're filled with self, no one wants to be around you. You say, that wasn't nice.
I'm just being honest. When we're full of the Holy Ghost, God uses and God works and
God is pleased. Listen, it is God's plan for every New Testament believer to be filled
with the Holy Ghost. It's God's plan. It is a privilege for every New Testament believer
to be filled with the Holy Ghost and God is pleased when we are filled with the Holy
Ghost. Would you this morning say, listen, it requires some soul searching, some honesty
before the Lord, some transparency. Am I filled with self or am I filled with the Holy Ghost?
God help me to be emptied of self so I can be full of the Holy Ghost that you would do
that work in and through me because I want to please you with my life. Let's pray. Father,
we love you. We thank you so much for loving us. We thank you for the teaching of the scriptures,
the truth that you have given to us with regard to the Holy Ghost. I'm thankful to be saved
and to be indwelled by the Holy Ghost. Lord, how we need to be filled with the Holy Ghost.
Help us, Lord, to be honest. In this moment of invitation, God, I pray that you'd work
in a very distinct way. Help us to be honest, to be humble. Lord, help us to be emptied
of self, to be filled with your Spirit. If there's one that's not sure of heaven, I pray
the Holy Ghost would do the work of reproving that we spoke of in John 16 of sin, of Christ's
righteousness, of judgment to come. What a joy it would be to see someone trust Christ
as their personal Savior. How desperately we need you, Lord. I pray that you'd work.
We'll give you the glory for it's in Christ's name we pray. Would you stand with me? Heads
are bowed, eyes are closed. Kimberly's going to play quietly on the piano. The invitation's
really already been given. If you're not saved, today's the day of salvation. If you're saved,
it's not a question of being indwelled by, it's a question of being filled with. Are
we emptied of self? Are we filled with the Holy Ghost? As Kimberly plays, the altar is open.