number 11 as we continue really this little mini series if you will it's a
brief study through the first few verses here in Luke chapter number 11 I trust
that these thoughts from this passage of scripture have had an impact upon your
prayer life I've said often over these last few weeks and obviously last week
with a missionary but I've made the statement that we need a revival of
prayer and we need it in our lives personally we need in our families we
need in our church and we need to return to prayer I was thinking this morning of
that great hymn I think we actually on Sunday evening Dean I think we sang that
song sweet hour of prayer and I was convicted as I was thinking about that
song and what a blessing to have the privilege of prayer but so often we would
if we would acknowledge the truth and be transparent with the Lord we neglect
that great privilege of communing with our God and spending time with him in
prayer as we have not only studied here in Luke 11 but also as we study the
book of Colossians of course in the first section of Colossians 1 we've had
the opportunity several weeks ago to read about the way in which Paul was
praying for the believers in Colossae and we have said that that passage of
scripture is not only exemplary but it's convicting to think about the ministry
of intercessory prayer and the way in which Paul was saying to these believers
that he'd never met personally he'd simply heard about their faith through
their minister through their pastor Epaphras and Paul says I am praying for
you and here's how I'm praying for you and we think about prayer and we have
noted as we go through this passage in Luke 11 that this request of this
disciple when he said Lord teach us to pray that the response that our Savior
gives is of utmost importance we understand and we recognize even as we
studied last time that the reason that we have access this reason that we can
go before the throne room of heaven is because of our relationship remember
Jesus said when you pray say our Father which art in heaven as we looked at that
portion of this particular passage of scripture we rejoicing and understanding
that he is the Lord God omnipotent that is the Creator God the sustainer of all
things yet he is our father and the access that we have because of
relationship and what a joy that is and we understand that as we look at this
passage of scripture and I just want to remind us this evening that this
response of Jesus as he provides this instruction here that in no way was he
this isn't the prayer of Jesus so many people refer to this passage and the
sister passage in Matthew as being the Lord's Prayer it's not the Lord's Prayer
it's a motto it's the framework for prayer in fact as you would think about
these particular words and this instruction the response of Jesus it was
never intended to simply be repeated in a given form it was not some type of
passage of scripture that Jesus is teaching to the disciples and they were
to memorize it and just recite it rehearse it verbatim in fact as you
study the New Testament you'll find that there are many records of the people of
God praying in fact we've studied some of the prayers of Paul we've studied in
Colossians 1 a couple of years ago as we study through the book of Ephesians you
see that there are two prayers in part specifically there that Paul gives in
chapter 2 and 3 of the book of Ephesians where he is providing actually
I think it's chapter 1 and 3 where he's providing the record of how he's praying
for the believers in Ephesus you will know that as you study the prayers that
are recorded in the New Testament by the people of God that never not one time are
these words quoted verbatim but yet you have people that think that this is
supposed to be something that is just quoted rehearsed recited verbatim as
being the Lord's Prayer but God is giving a model he's giving framework for
prayer as we continue our study we're gonna look at the latter part of verse
number 2 where the Bible says this I'll read the entirety of the passage in
verse 1 and it came to pass that as he was praying in a certain place Jesus was
praying when he seized one of his disciples said unto him Lord teach us to
pray as John also taught his disciples and he Jesus said unto them the
disciples collectively it was one disciple that asked the question but
Jesus now answers and gives all of the disciples this instruction when you pray
not if you pray but when you pray say our Father which art in heaven the text
that we'll be looking at this evening begins with this next phrase hallowed be
thy name thy kingdom come thy will be done as in heaven so in earth if you're
taking notes and you'd like to give a title I've simply titled it hallowed be
thy name we're gonna look at two aspects from these truths this evening in verse
number two of really our attitude of prayer how it is that we approach prayer
and I would say number one is we look at this phrase hallowed be thy name we
enter into our time of prayer into that season of prayer with an attitude of
reverence an attitude of reverence the Bible says hallowed be thy name the
word hallowed carries with the idea of being sanctified but really gives us the
idea of holy we understand that our God is holy the attribute of God's holiness
is found throughout the scriptures you find there in the book of Leviticus in
particular that God is giving his people the children of Israel the truth with
regard to his holiness and he says be ye holy as I am holy we find that it's
there in Isaiah chapter number six as Isaiah sees God high holy and lifted up
in his train filled the temple that the angels say holy holy holy Peter tells
those that he's writing to in first Peter as he's giving them the admonition
and the instruction of living lives of obedience and holiness he refers back to
that passage or those passages in Leviticus when he says be holy even as I
am holy we find in the book of Revelation once again when the throne
room of heaven is in scene and you begin to read in chapter number five and you
read about holy holy holy our God is holy and we think about this attitude of
reverence as we think about the holiness of God it is important I believe
imperative that when we enter into our time of prayer that yes we're praying to
our father but we must be mindful of the fact that he's holy he's a holy God
this evening as we think about the holiness of God and we're mindful of his
holiness we would understand that the reality of that truth should have a
profound impact and influence upon our lives as individuals I don't know
perhaps some of the parents here you've been in a situation before or maybe some
of the adults here you remember when you were a teenager that you were in this
situation when you were speaking to your parents and they said hold on a
minute who are you talking to I'm not your friend I'm your parent has that
ever happened listen sometimes if we're not careful in everyday conversations
and interactions we might kind of forget who we're talking to or addressing in
which manner and so on and so forth we understand as Jesus is giving this
answer this response of the disciples he says our father which art in heaven
hallowed be thy name the name of God what a wonderful name we've been
studying in the book of Genesis on Sunday evenings in fact this past Sunday
night we're dealing with Genesis 17 and verse number one the Almighty God El
Shaddai and you find that as you look through the life of Abram and his name
will soon be changed to Abraham as we're studying through the book of Genesis you
find that God regularly is revealing names of himself to Abraham he's through
those names through the names of God we find that is how God is revealing to us
who he is that we may more clearly understand who he is he's the Lord God
omnipotent he is Jehovah Jireh the God who provides he's I mean we could go
through all the names of God and just understand the fullness of who he did
who he is the all-sufficient one we sang this evening Savior like a shepherd lead
us how do we get that idea how did the songwriter get that idea well the Bible
says that the Lord is the Good Shepherd that he's the Great Shepherd that he's
the Chief Shepherd we find that the the sweet psalmist of Israel David he says
the Lord is my shepherd and we find as we think about the name of God hallowed
be thy name that when we enter into prayer that we enter with an attitude or
a spirit of reverence our God is holy he's holy I'm thankful that I can
approach him but you know the only reason that I can approach him is
because I have been born again I've been redeemed I'm clothed in the righteousness
of Christ I can't approach him in my own righteousness but I because he's my
father I can approach him I've access but I must be mindful of the truth that
he is holy it's interesting to me you don't need to turn there you can if you
want but in Psalm 30 hold your place there if you are gonna turn because
we'll be back to Luke in just a moment but in Psalm 30 the psalmist gives us a
truth that I think is of significant importance and I believe that as you
would use the the correlation here between this truth in Psalm 30 and the
answer that Jesus gives to the disciples with regard to prayer notice
what the psalmist says in Psalm 30 in verse number four he says this sing
unto the Lord O you saints of his and give thanks at the remembrance of his
holiness you know when we pray and we recognize we're mindful of the fact
again it's not just verbatim repeated words but we enter into with that
attitude that spirit of reverence and we begin to just worship God for who he
is how he's revealed to us his person his character his nature through his
word that we are mindful of his holiness and it leads me to a spirit of
thanksgiving because I am begin to rejoice at the remembrance and I'm
giving thanks at the remembrance of his holiness and so when Jesus says hallowed
be thy name sanctified or holy then I once again I'm being mindful of the
attributes of God and I begin to rejoice that our God is holy aren't you
thankful that our God is holy he's revealed that to us he's just he's
righteous and he's love I mean we see all of his attributes but here in this
response of Jesus he says hallowed be thy name we enter into that time of
prayer with a spirit of reverence the spirit of reverence I hope this evening
that when you pray that at times in your life that you just get caught up in
worshiping God standing in awe of who he is I mean truly you understand that
prayer is not really a list of our demands sometimes I think we kind of get
it backwards where we just think that prayer consists solely or entirely of
just my wants what are my needs I'm just bringing my list of needs to God but you
know that when you begin with a spirit of thanksgiving when you begin with a
spirit of praise and standing in awe of who God is all of a sudden that's going
to influence and impact really that list of needs that you had because you just
begin to get into the presence of God the psalmist said that in thy presence
is fullness of joy fullness of joy and as you begin to pray as you have your
time of prayer I wonder how often do we just worship God just be mindful of who
he is and his attributes and leads to a spirit of thanksgiving back in Luke 11
not only do we see an attitude of reverence hallowed be thy name but I
believe that we see an attitude of submission number two an attitude of
submission the Bible says that the end of verse number two of Luke 11 thy
kingdom come thy will be done as in heaven so in earth an attitude of
submission I believe that this attitude of submission is a direct result of our
understanding of who God is when we enter into that time of prayer with an
attitude of reverence it's going to have a profound impact on our attitude of
submission because we're understanding who he is we're saying that he's holy
that he is the Lord God omnipotent the reality is that sometimes maybe I should
say many times for many people when we enter into or even just generally in
life we want what we want no one had to teach you to be selfish those kind ladies
in our church that serve in the nursery ministry you would understand no one
ever had to teach those kids to be selfish it's amazing how you can get
just a couple of kids in a room and you can have 40 toys but whichever toy Johnny
is playing with that's the same toy that little Alex wants or whatever the
names are right man they can be selfish sometimes as adults we know how to kind
of make our selfishness look a little bit more shiny a little bit more you
know acceptable if you will but the reality is that it's not really about
what I want it's about God's will being accomplished and sometimes if we're not
careful we're playing we're praying according to my will not the will of God
I think about Paul he prayed thrice that that thorn in the flesh would depart
from him what did Jesus say my grace is sufficient for thee my grace is
sufficient for thee you know the reality is that I and I've said this
many times over the years God can deliver us from anything he's God he's
the Lord God omnipotent there's nothing too hard for him but sometimes he wants
to develop us through that something instead of delivering us from that
something and I understand that's not always easy I understand it's not always
enjoyable for us to go through the storm as opposed to just simply avoiding
the storm altogether and if we'd have our way we'd probably like to just
avoid the storm altogether but we find here the Bible says thy kingdom come thy
will be done as in heaven so on earth I mentioned on Sunday the fact that God
has given us in his word some truth with regard to the timeline of the end day in
times the last days and God has revealed to us in his word some things
that are going to come to pass and I made this statement that there are many
today that are saying as they're looking at the things that are taking place in
our world that the things are falling apart and I understand people that look
at it from that perspective but you can look at it from a perspective to see
that fault things are falling in place things are falling in place and we
understand that Jesus is going to return and the Bible says that in the
last days perilous time shall come the Bible says that evil men and seducers
shall wax worse and worse they're not gonna get better and better you know
worse and worse so how do we pray the will of God to be accomplished thy will
be done as in heaven so in earth and we find that that God has a plan and God's
plan will come to pass we understand that but the reality is that as we're
praying for the will of God to be accomplished and we're desiring to know
the will of God for our lives and we're praying in that spirit of submission
it's going to really affect how we look at the circumstances in which we're
dealing with our God is he is able he is able to do exceeding abundantly above
all that we ask or think I was listening to a song recently about praising the
Lord and many songs carry with it this idea but this particular song put it in
a very interesting format of speaking about whether I'm on the mountain or in
the valley I'm going to lift my praise to God so that people would know who he
is it's sometimes it's easy for us on the mountain to praise God and not so
much in the valley but what if in that valley is what the will of God is at
this moment for us in our lives I mean Paul says in Philippians 1 that the
things that happened to me happened for the furtherance of the gospel I spoke
with a man not long ago right here in our auditorium and as I spoke with that
individual he shared with me a tragic event that he experienced in his life in
an event that I don't think any of us would ever want to endure and he looked
at me as serious as could be after going through that event of great tragedy very
much physical pain extended period of time in the hospital a number of
surgeries he said I'd do it all over again do you know why because while I
was in that place I got to share the gospel with people that otherwise I
never would have been able to share the gospel with there were nurses that got
saved there was a doctor that got saved he said it was the worst pain I ever
experienced in my life but I'd do it again to be able to share the gospel
with those people man that's the spirit of Paul in Philippians 1 that's
understanding the will of God see God is so much greater than than we are I like
to plan many of you know that I mean I'm a planner I got things tried to
figure out I got missionaries that call me all the time saying I'm gonna be in
your area next week I'm scheduled out to the next year I got evangelists lined up
for three years worth of revival meetings I like to plan but sometimes my
plans don't always line up with God's plans but God's way is always best God's
way is always best always I think about turn over the book of 1st John and we're
gonna be done so we can have some prayer time this evening I told you before when
we started this series it's easier to talk about prayer it's easier to teach a
lesson on prayer and to preach on prayer than it is to pray it really is we can
talk a whole lot about prayer in fact I can talk to you about exercise a whole
lot too but I don't like to do it amen I can give you a good regimen of what
you should do how you should do I don't want to do it prayer is work laboring
in prayer 1st John chapter 5 I love the Word of God every word is pure and you
think about the specifics of the words they're so important notice what John
says in 1st John 5 in verse 14 and this is the confidence I mean don't you like
having confidence the man that I got to share the gospel with today I looked at
him I said are you a hundred percent sure that if you die today you go to
heaven well if you put it that way that's kind of how I responded right
because I listen I'm not asking you if you're 97% sure are you a hundred
percent sure and here John says this is the confidence that we have in him that
if we ask anything look at those next words according to his will he heareth
us and if we know that he hear us whatsoever we ask we know that we have
the petitions that we desired of him this evening as we think about this
truth of an attitude of reverence followed by an attitude of submission
and we see here what John says with regard to having this confidence and
asking according to his will that he heareth us and what a blessing to know
that that God hears and answers prayer and to have the understanding this
evening that that as we enter into his presence with the spirit of reverence
this attitude of reverence this attitude of submission thy will that he hears us
listen I believe this evening that there are some prayers that you can absolutely
have answered because you're praying according the will of God teach me thy
word O Lord open thou mine eyes that I may behold wondrous things out of thy
law Lord I'm gonna open your word and I'm gonna read it today and I'm asking
that your spirit would teach me the Word of God help me to understand it illumine
the scriptures to me I believe that God delights in answering that prayer why
because it's according to his will Lord give me an opportunity to share the
gospel with someone help me to have the boldness that only comes through the
empowerment of the Holy Spirit of God so that I could share the gospel with an
individual God's gonna he's gonna answer that prayer according to his will
preach the gospel to every creature we could go on and on this evening and look
at a number of examples but we find tonight that it's so important that when
we look at the framework and model by which Jesus responded to the request of
the disciple our Father which art in heaven he says hallowed be thy name
sanctified holy all that we'd enter with a spirit of reverence a spirit of
reverence understanding the holiness of God and at the remembrance of his
holiness giving thanks followed by a spirit or an attitude of submission
Jesus as he prayed in the garden not my will but thine be done
good example we find that this evening we ought to be more concerned about the
will of God than our own desires then are even our own conveniences or
comforts and I like to be comfortable and I'm pretty sure if you'd be honest
you like to be comfortable too but sometimes God's gonna bring us out of
our comfort zone to accomplish his will an attitude of reverence an attitude of
submission as we seek the face of God let's pray father we love you we thank
you for loving us we thank you so much for your word and for the framework that
you give us here in this passage with regard to prayer we know that it was not
intended to be something that is just mindlessly repeated its framework we
thank you that we have access because relationship because of the sacrifice of
our Savior the cross of Calvary is death burial glorious resurrection we're
thankful tonight you're holy we pray that as we approach you we'd have this
attitude of reverence and submission I pray the bless our time of prayer we do
thank you for the privilege pray that you'd work in our midst and we'll thank
you for it in Christ's name we pray