Looking at a single verse of scripture
as we kind of use as a springboard here this evening
into this thought I mentioned
at the closing of the service this morning,
the title for the message, someone is watching you.
Someone is watching you.
Have you ever been in a situation
where you could feel that someone was watching you?
Have you ever, can you relate to that?
You perhaps, maybe somebody asked you to do something,
there was a particular task that you were trying to do
and all eyes were on you, the reality,
the pressure that was mounting
because everyone was looking at you became overwhelming
and maybe you said something like this,
stop watching me, stop looking at me.
I can't do it if you're watching me.
And maybe you can relate to that
and we understand that that reminds us
that people are watching us.
How about this?
Maybe there's been a time in your life
where someone came to you and said they saw you
or they watched, observed you do something
and yet you had no idea that they saw you.
You had no idea they were even there.
You had no idea that they were even watching you
but sure enough as they rehearsed
and they recounted the events that they observed,
you can be assured of the fact
that they were observing you, they saw you.
This evening, both of those scenarios
teach us a valuable lesson and that lesson is this,
someone is watching you.
Years ago, I was driving through the neighborhood
just off of Germantown
and I was driving through that neighborhood
and as I was driving through that neighborhood,
I saw a sign that was in someone's yard.
In fact, as I continued to drive,
I saw a few of them in that same neighborhood
and the sign read this way.
It said drive like your kids live and play here
and I thought that was quite interesting
because obviously they had some people
cutting through the neighborhood there
trying to avoid lights and what have you
and they weren't driving real carefully
and so parents put up signs and they said drive
like your kids live and play here.
They were trying to communicate a message
to those drivers of the importance of being careful, why?
Because there are kids that live and play
in that neighborhood.
Immediately upon reading that sign,
I had this thought that we are to live
like someone is watching us.
Why?
Well, because they are.
Because they are.
Someone's watching you.
Someone's watching me and I am aware of that.
I know that many times we go through life,
we can maybe think that we're isolated
and maybe we can have the idea that no one notices,
no one sees but I can assure you
that there are people that are watching you,
people that are observing your behavior.
In fact, I know that it's been said
that there are times that we could look to
and we can see that neighbors,
they observe that you go to church.
They see you leave your house.
They see you leave on Sunday morning,
on Sunday night, on Wednesday night,
missions conference, you're leaving each night.
They observe it and by the way,
they notice when you don't leave to go to church.
Amen?
I mean, they know, they're watching.
They may not say something but they're watching.
They know, they're observing and they see that
and this evening as we look at this portion of scripture,
a single verse of scripture in Proverbs 23
and verse number 26, notice what the Bible says.
My son, give me thine heart
and let thine eyes observe my ways.
Now we understand that in this verse of scripture
that Solomon makes an appeal to his son.
In fact, he extends an invitation to his son
not only to give him his heart
but to let his eyes observe his ways.
Now we understand some things about Solomon
and unfortunately, he was a man that just did some things.
Of course, as you study his life,
he forsook the path that he should have stayed on.
He had many wives and concubines,
began to serve and what have you
with regard to the false gods and deities
and making places of worship and offering
and so on and so forth and we understand
he was a man who was fallible.
I said this this morning when we look at the truth
of the book of Proverbs, the book of Proverbs
is a book in which God allowed Solomon
to be the human penman and if we take it just at face value,
we see that Solomon is instructing Rehoboam, his son.
Now we understand that this book
is part of the canon of scripture
and we understand that all scripture
is given by inspiration of God
and as much as we look at this book
and we see that Solomon is speaking to Rehoboam,
that there is a spiritual application
from the book of Proverbs that God, our father,
is speaking to us as his children
and we find this evening that as we look
at this verse of scripture and we can see Solomon
speaking to his son Rehoboam and we can understand
that he makes this appeal, he gives this invitation
for his son to observe his ways.
The reality this evening is that Rehoboam
was gonna watch and observe his dad
whether he ever extended an invitation to him or not.
Why?
Because boys watch their dads, it's what they do.
Young people watch, why do the young people
start doing the same thing the teenagers are doing?
Because the young people are watching the teenagers.
Is it not true?
We see it, this is a cycle of life,
we've been aware of this for many years,
most of us this evening and we see this
and we understand this.
As we look at the text of scripture
and we think about the spiritual application,
I'm reminded this evening that our savior
came to the sin-cursed world and he lived
a perfect and sinless life and he left us an example
that we too can look at his life and we can be challenged
through the things that he did and the things that he taught.
This evening as we consider this thought,
someone is watching you, I want you to consider
a few passages of scripture from the New Testament
and then we're gonna go back to an illustration
from the Old Testament as we wrap up this evening.
Turn to the book of Acts if you will,
Acts chapter number one and really the thought tonight,
someone is watching you, therefore we ought to do and teach.
We ought to do and teach, why?
Because someone is watching you.
In the book of Acts in the first chapter,
we find that the introduction is given
but God gives us a bit of an insight
with regard to the life and ministry
of the Lord Jesus Christ.
Of course we know as you come to the book of Acts
that the Lord Jesus Christ had completed
his earthly ministry, over three years walking
during his earthly ministry, of course over 30 years
of his total life on earth but three years
of his public earthly ministry, three and a half years or so
and we find that after that he was crucified,
he was buried, he rose again.
We come to the book of Acts in the first chapter,
we read of the ascension of Jesus Christ
but before that I want you to notice in verse number one,
the Bible says the former treaties have I made,
O Theophilus, of all, notice this phrase,
that Jesus began both to do and teach
until the day in which he was taken up
after that he through the Holy Ghost
had given commandments unto the apostles
whom he had chosen, to whom also he showed himself alive
after his passion by many infallible proofs
being seen of them 40 days and speaking of the things
pertaining to the kingdom of God.
As we zero in on that phrase in verse number one,
of all that Jesus began both to do and teach,
I would say this evening that Jesus is the master teacher
and no one's ever taught like Jesus.
In fact, we understand that as you read the scriptures,
as you read the gospel accounts,
that there are times in which the Jewish people
after hearing the Lord Jesus Christ teach,
they said no man spake like this man.
He speaks as one that has authority.
I like that truth, I like that declaration, why?
Because he does have authority,
he has all power and all authority,
he is God in flesh and truly no man spoke like him.
No man taught like him.
He was a wise master teacher, why?
Because he's God and we find that as you study
through the gospel records that he was teaching,
he was instructing, he was influencing
those that he was called to influence
but it wasn't just that he was teaching, he was doing.
He was doing.
We've often heard and I've said over the years
that the message of your life speaks louder
than the message of your lips.
We can say a whole lot of things
but if we're not doing what we're saying,
the message falls flat.
It's as if it falls on deaf ears.
We find this evening that the Lord Jesus Christ
that he was not only the master teacher
but we find that he practiced that which he taught.
We find that the truth is given to us
in 1 Peter chapter number two, notice if you will,
a familiar verse of scripture this evening
as we look at this truth with regard to the life
and ministry of the Lord Jesus Christ.
In 1 Peter chapter number two,
Peter of course had the opportunity to walk on this earth
during the earthly public ministry
of the Lord Jesus Christ with Jesus.
Now we understand that Peter, in fact,
of us can relate to Peter, and oftentimes,
we look at the various events in Peter's life
as he's walking with the Lord,
and we may say something like this,
that he was often the first one to speak up,
he was often the first one to put his foot in his mouth,
and so on and so forth, but Peter was a man
that was passionate, Peter was a man
that was following Christ, and we find that Peter,
as he walked with the Lord, he was in that inner circle,
if we could call it that this evening.
When you really think about the ministry
of the Lord Jesus Christ, we're of course aware of the 12,
Judas was a traitor, so 11, but with that group of people,
there was really an inner circle, Peter, James, and John,
they were the three that went up with Jesus
on the Mount of Transfiguration,
they were the ones that had the opportunity to see
even more than some of the other disciples
had the opportunity to see, and as God would use Peter,
now remember, Peter denied the Lord
before the crucifixion, Jesus told Peter that he would,
and Peter said, no way, not me, I'm not gonna deny you,
I'll die with you, for you, but Peter denied the Lord,
denied him thrice, three times, but you know,
the Bible says that when the cock crew and Jesus
looked at him, that he, Peter, wept bitterly.
It's very interesting when Jesus in the Gospel of Luke
tells Peter about the fact that he would deny him,
he says to him, he says, Peter, Satan hath desired
to have you that he may sift you as wheat,
but I've prayed for you, when thou art converted,
strengthen the brethren, and now God would use Peter,
of course, we understand that Peter, in John chapter 21,
he says, I go a fishing, and Jesus spoke to Peter,
and ministered to Peter, and he said, Peter, do you love me?
Peter, do you love me?
And we know that God used Peter, I mean,
Peter's the one that stands up on the day of Pentecost,
filled with the spirit of God, and preaches boldly
a great message, and souls were saved,
3,000 added to the church, and you trace the steps
of Peter through the book of Acts in the early church,
and God was using Peter, and now we find that Peter
is being used of the Lord to pen 1 and 2 Peter
under the inspiration of the Holy Spirit of God,
and I want you to notice what Peter says
in 1 Peter 2 and verse 21, for even here unto
were ye called, because Christ also suffered for us,
leaving us an example that ye should follow his steps.
Should follow his steps.
The example that Jesus left is a perfect example,
it is the perfect example, why?
Because he's God.
I wonder this evening, when we look at this text
of scripture, and we understand this truth
of do and teach, coupled with the idea
from Proverbs 23 and verse 26, someone is watching you.
Yes, in Proverbs 23, Solomon is speaking
to his son, Rehoboam, but the reality this evening
is that this message, this thought, though contextually
it's a father speaking to a son, this truth
is for every one of us this evening,
someone is watching you, and I wonder tonight
if the example that you're leaving is an example
that others should follow.
That's a convicting thought.
That's a question, a statement that requires
some inspection, some stop and evaluate and examine.
Is the example that I'm leaving an example
that I want someone else to follow?
Peter says Jesus left us an example
that we should follow his steps.
We think about the apostle Paul and a great example,
obviously the greatest example is the Lord Jesus Christ.
We think about the apostle Paul, we find that many times
we would look at the life of the apostle Paul
as God has given us many just truths with regard
to his life and ministry, and much scripture
is given to us with regard to his life,
and we might say something like this,
that he's the greatest Christian that ever lived,
but Paul himself said that he was the chief of sinners.
Paul was a man that was saved by the grace of God.
He never forgot what happened on the road to Damascus.
How do I know that?
Because every time he had opportunity to begin to preach
and to give his testimony, you know what he always
went back to?
He went back to his conversion.
He never got over the fact that he was saved
by the grace of God.
He says to the believers in 1 Corinthians 11
and verse number one, be followers of me,
but there's not a period there.
He says, even as I also am of Christ.
See, the apostle Paul was a man that wanted to follow
the Lord Jesus Christ, and so much as he followed the Lord,
he was also providing an example that others could look
at his life and follow him.
There have been times in my life that I have observed
parents saying to children, hey, don't do that,
or maybe they'll say, I don't know where they learned
that from.
If you'd give me an opportunity, I'll help you understand
where they learned that from.
What do I mean by that?
Well, they observed it in your life.
They observed, they heard you.
I don't know where they heard anything like that.
Really?
Because I've heard you talk like that, and so they picked
it up right there at home, amen?
And people don't like that, they get embarrassed by it,
but the reality is that we are giving an example to others.
Notice what Paul says in the book of Philippians
in chapter number four.
Philippians chapter number four, of course,
Paul writing here to this church that was started
in Philippi, a church that God gave him personally
the opportunity to see established, and he's writing
to these believers about the importance of rejoicing
and continuing and being a light in a dark world
and so on and so forth, and we find that as we come
to the fourth chapter, in verse number nine,
I want you to notice what the Bible says.
Those things which ye have both learned and received
and heard and seen in me do.
The God of peace shall be with you.
I have that entire verse underlined in my Bible.
If you were only to underline a portion of that verse,
I personally like the seen in me part of it
because the Apostle Paul was not just a follower of Christ
that taught a message, but he lived the message
that he taught.
We find that the Apostle Paul, many times,
he would tell people about the importance of prayer,
and he would tell people about the importance
of praying for him, but then you read about how
the Apostle Paul was praying for others,
and it's recorded in the pages of scripture
how he prayed for the believers, for he prayed
for the individuals, for the churches.
We find that Paul would tell the churches,
he would tell individuals the importance of rejoicing
and praising God and thanking God,
but yet, as you read the epistles that are penned
by the Apostle Paul, you find that he's a man
that's praising God, that's giving thanks unto the Lord,
and so we find that Paul, he was a man that gave truth.
He taught, he instructed, he diligently fulfilled
the task that God gave him to do,
but he did not simply teach, he was a man that did
as well as teaching the truth.
He says, not only the things that you have learned
and received and heard, but he says, seen in me.
Do, and the God of peace shall be with you.
Again, I wonder this evening, if we were to examine
our lives, if we were to consider as we see
in the lives of others, if we find somebody
that's walking behind us and they're doing
the same things that we're doing,
if they're emulating what they're seeing in us,
is that a good thing or is it a bad thing?
Is it an example that we would be thankful and happy
that they would be following our steps?
We find that as you look through the pages of Scripture,
there is much truth that is given with regard
to the importance of not only teaching truth,
but that we would do that which we are teaching,
that the message of our life would align
with the message of our lips.
I know that you've heard and I've heard as well
about parents that will say, hey, don't do this
as they're engaging in that very activity.
It's bad for you, don't do this, you don't wanna
go down this path, but yet they're doing,
they're consuming, they're participating,
and the reality this evening is that that message
of don't do this is a shallow message
because the example that is being seen
carries so much more weight.
I want you to look over the Old Testament,
look of 2 Chronicles, if you will,
and I want you to look at this example,
and I'm gonna tell you it's a negative example,
but I believe that we learn from this example
in 2 Chronicles chapter 33.
I wish I had the time to read the entirety
of the chapter, I do not, but I'm gonna just
kind of pick my way through the chapter here.
And I want you to see a great lesson
from this portion of Scripture that's a negative example.
but I hope will help us to see the importance
of the fact that others are watching us.
Someone is watching you and the impact of your influence.
Beginning in verse number one of 2 Chronicles 33,
the Bible says Manasseh was 12 years old
when he began to reign,
and he reigned 50 and five years in Jerusalem.
Now, I want you to understand that here,
Manasseh is the king after Hezekiah.
Now, Hezekiah was a good king.
Hezekiah was the one that we understand
that as the Assyrians come,
he comes to the Lord and he lays it all out
and he trusts the Lord and God blesses
and God works and delivers them from the Assyrians,
the people of Judah,
but we understand that Hezekiah was told from Isaiah
that he would die.
Hezekiah prayed and he requested that he would not die
and he was granted 15 more years.
In those 15 years,
we understand if you were to read that the Babylonians,
there's an entourage of people that come from Babylon
and Hezekiah shows all of the things within his realm.
We find that Isaiah comes and says,
he inquires about what has taken place
and we find that the truth is given to Hezekiah
that the Babylonians would take captive.
It would not happen in his day,
but in his descendants day.
And unfortunately Hezekiah made a statement such as this,
well, good that there's peace in my day.
And now the Bible tells us in chapter 33
that Manasseh begins to reign.
Did you notice how old Manasseh was?
He was 12.
Do you remember as I just told you just quickly,
how many additional years Hezekiah had?
15.
Manasseh was born during those 15 years,
he's only 12 when he begins to reign.
And the Bible says in verse number two,
but did that which was, notice what it says,
evil in the sight of the Lord,
like unto the abominations of the heathen
whom the Lord had cast out before the children of Israel,
for he built again the high places
which Hezekiah and his father had broken down
and he reared up altars for Balaam
and made groves and worshiped all the host of heaven
and served them and he built altars
in the house of the Lord,
whereof the Lord had said in Jerusalem,
shall my name be forever.
And he built altars for all the host of heaven
in the two courts of the house of the Lord.
Do you understand what God's telling us here?
In the temple, in the very place where God
allowed Solomon to build the temple,
the place where you think about the holy of holies,
we understand the tabernacle,
but then after the reign of David,
when David says, I wanna build a house
and the prophet Nathan says,
go and do all that's in thine heart,
but God says that night, no, no, no,
David's not gonna build a temple,
but Solomon, his son will build a temple.
It's this temple that we're speaking about,
the temple that contains all the brazen altar,
the labor, you think about in the holy of holies
with the mercy seat on the Ark of the Covenant,
all that takes place and you think about this
and here, the Bible tells us that Manasseh
in that place, the holy place,
he reared up altars to all of the host of heaven.
Do you understand what that means?
All of the false gods, all of the idols,
all of this idolatry that would take place,
this is what Manasseh does, wicked, ungodly.
Skip down if you will,
we don't have time to read all of it,
maybe you get to read it this week on your own,
but I want you to skip down in verse number nine,
the Bible says, so Manasseh made Judah
and the inhabitants of Jerusalem to err
and to do worse than the heathen
whom the Lord had destroyed before the children of Israel.
I mean, it was a bad time.
The Lord spake to Manasseh and to his people,
but they would not hearken.
God is so gracious.
I said this morning, you can hear,
but it doesn't mean you receive.
Hearing and receiving are two different things.
And here we find the Bible says
that the Lord spake to Manasseh and to his people,
but they would not hearken.
Wherefore, the Lord brought upon them
the captains of the host of the king of Assyria,
which took Manasseh among the thorns
and bound him with fetters and carried him to Babylon.
And when he was in affliction, notice this in verse 12,
he besought the Lord his God
and humbled himself greatly before the God of his fathers.
Now I'm thankful for verse number 12,
but I would submit to you this evening
that it's far better that we humble ourselves
and seek the Lord before the time of affliction,
before the time of judgment,
that we take heed to the voice of God, to the word of God,
that we hearken to his voice
as they should have in verse number 10.
And we do not have to deal with what is recorded to us
in verse number 11.
But in that time of affliction,
the Bible tells us that he, Manasseh,
he besought the Lord his God,
he humbled himself greatly before the God of his fathers.
And he prayed unto him and he was entreated of him
and heard his supplication.
Oh, isn't God so gracious?
God is so merciful.
His mercy endureth forever.
He is long-suffering.
What a joy to understand that.
But I tell you this evening, do not tempt the Lord.
Don't go as far as you can and be like,
well, God will forgive me.
God will be merciful to me.
God is long-suffering.
No, it's far better to continue
to walk in obedience to God.
It says in verse 13 that God was entreated of him
and heard his supplication
and brought him again to Jerusalem and to his kingdom.
Then notice this statement at the end of verse number 13.
Then Manasseh knew that the Lord, he was God.
Now, after this, he built a wall without the city of David
on the west side of Gihon and the valley,
even to the entering in at the fish gate
and compassed about Ophel and raised it up
a very great height and put captains of war
in all the fenced cities of Judah.
He took away, notice in verse 15,
he took away the strange gods and the idol
out of the house of the Lord and all the altars
that he had built in the mound to the house of the Lord
and in Jerusalem and cast them out of the city.
Praise God.
That's a good thing, is it not?
I mean, Manasseh is getting right with God.
Manasseh did evil in the sight of the Lord.
As we begin the chapter, we see all of this behavior,
but now we find after he recognizes that the Lord,
he is God after God's grace and his mercy
that he cast all of these things out of the city.
He cleanses really the temple
and he gets rid of all this stuff.
In verse 16, he repaired the altar of the Lord
and he sacrificed there on peace offerings
and thank offerings and commanded Judah
to serve the Lord God of Israel.
Now, in verse 16, we find that Manasseh
was doing a good thing.
Manasseh was making sacrifices
according to what God had commanded in the law.
Manasseh makes a decree.
The decree is this, that all the people of Judah
were to serve the Lord God of Israel.
Can I tell you this evening,
you cannot legislate righteousness.
You can't do it.
You can't legislate righteousness.
You can't force people to serve God.
You can't do it.
It's a matter of the will.
It's a matter of the heart.
And here the Bible says, nevertheless, in verse 17,
the people did sacrifice still in the high places
yet unto the Lord their God only.
Now the rest of the acts of Manasseh
and his prayer unto his God,
so Manasseh's life is gonna end.
In verse 20, it says, so Manasseh slept with his fathers.
They buried him in his own house
and Amon, his son, reigned in his stead.
Now, I want you to notice about this man, Amon,
his son that's gonna reign.
It tells us in verse 21 that he was two and 20 years old
when he began to reign and reigned two years in Jerusalem.
But I want you to notice what the Bible says about his son.
In verse 22, it says, but he did that which was evil
in the sight of the Lord.
And then notice what it says, as did Manasseh his father.
Do you see it there?
For Amon sacrificed unto all the carved images
which Manasseh his father had made and served them
and humbled not himself before the Lord
as Manasseh his father had humbled himself,
but Amon trespassed more and more.
I've written in the margin of my Bible,
Manasseh returned to the Lord,
the son, Amon, transgressed greatly.
How sad to consider the behavior of those we may influence.
You know, you understand this evening
that you might come back to God as Manasseh did.
But what about the people that you're influencing
that might not come back to God?
It's a negative example.
I told you that before we got to it this evening,
but it's an example that helps us really nail down
the point this evening that someone is watching you.
Could I submit to you this evening
that Amon was watching Manasseh when he did evil
and most likely he was watching Manasseh when he did right?
And I believe this evening with all of my heart,
I cannot prove it scripturally,
but I believe in my heart, if you disagree,
that's perfectly fine.
I've acknowledged to you that I can't prove it
from the Bible, but I believe that Manasseh
would have desired for his son
to follow the example of his latter days
and not his former days.
Would you agree with me?
me this evening? I don't think for one second of time that Manasseh would
desire that his son Amon would follow the example of his early days. In his
days of idolatry, in his days of wickedness, I don't think for one moment
of time Manasseh would want for his son Amon to follow that example. I think that
if Manasseh had his choice, that if Manasseh could have it his way, he would
desire that Amon, his son, would serve the Lord, would follow God, would serve as
he made the command in verse 16. He makes the command that all Judah should serve
the Lord God of Israel. No doubt if that was his heart and his concern for the
people, the inhabitants of Judah, it was most certainly his heart for his own son
in his own house. But Manasseh had no control over what his son would do. There
was an example that was given. Unfortunately, when we look at the
example of Solomon, though he was the one used to pen the words in Proverbs 23
and verse 26, let thine eyes observe my ways. He did not leave the best example. He did
not lead a life that was most honorable. But he did influence his son. And this evening,
whether you give someone permission to observe your ways or not, there are people watching
you. You don't have to grant someone permission to observe your ways. They're simply a group
of people that are watching you this evening. And I wonder how often, as we live our lives,
do we live with this awareness that someone is watching me? What kind of an example am
I giving to them? Would I be pleased if they did what I do? If they live how I live? Paul
said, not only the things that you learned, but the things that you've seen in me do.
The greatest example, of course, is the Lord Jesus Christ. As Peter said it in 1 Peter
2 21, he left us an example that we should follow his steps. But I wonder tonight, are
we able to say as Paul did to the church at Corinth, be followers of me, even as I also
am of Christ. Because if we're following Christ, we're not going to be perfect. But we can
leave an example that is worth following. Someone is watching you. Let's pray. Father,
we love you. We thank you for loving us. We thank you for the privilege to gather this
evening. We thank you for the singing and just the opportunity to praise you and to
be challenged from your word. And God, I pray that the truth of this message tonight, Lord,
would help us in our daily lives to consider the fact that someone, in fact, many someones
are watching us. God, I pray that we would live in such a way that we would not be ashamed
or embarrassed if those individuals followed our example. I pray that you would move and
work in hearts and lives as only you can. We'll give you the glory for it. For it's
in Christ's name we pray.