13 this morning, John chapter number 13.
And as you're turning there,
and we're certainly thankful for this portion of scripture,
I'll dive into it here in just a few moments.
But as you know, I've already mentioned this morning,
you have the insert in your bulletin,
but our revival meeting, our annual revival meeting,
fall revival, as we often refer to it as,
is scheduled to begin next Sunday.
And I understand this morning,
and I hope that you do as well,
that an individual believer or a church
will not experience revival simply because
it has been planned.
And I planned this meeting a long, long time ago
with Brother Marshawn and got it on the calendar
and all of those things.
But the reality is that revival doesn't come
because you've planned it,
it doesn't become because it's on a calendar.
It's not going to be some magical thing
that's going to happen that you show up
and bam, there's revival.
We find that yes, we'll have a guest speaker,
we'll have more services,
we'll have service all day on Sunday,
we'll have Monday evening and Tuesday evening
and Wednesday evening.
But we find that those things in of themselves
do not, cannot bring revival.
And I've often said, as we have had revival meetings
over the years, that it is important
that we would be revival ready and not revival resistant.
And we find that we can read throughout the history,
not only of Israel, and I'll mention some things
during the message this morning,
but even throughout the history that you and I
can study of revivals that have taken place,
not only here in this nation,
the Great Awakening, the Second Great Awakening,
you can read of the Welsh revival that took place
right at the turn of the 20th century
and you can read of other revivals that have taken place
and you can see the work of God, the hand of God at work.
And revival really is an individual thing.
The fact of the matter is that we can have revival meeting
and some individuals that are in attendance
for that meeting, they can have,
they can experience revival and we can see
and have that work of God in our lives.
And it is my earnest desire that each of us,
every single one of us would be revival ready.
I hope that throughout this week,
we would prepare our hearts, that we'd prepare our schedules
that we would make it a point to pray daily
and seek the face of God, that we would be revival ready,
that our hearts, the Bible likens our hearts to soil
and various types of soil and we can understand
as you read through the word of God,
you can read of those that had hard hearts
and you can read of those that had tender hearts
and the Bible says of Josiah that his heart was tender
and therefore when the book of the law was found
in the house of the Lord and it was read,
Josiah responded in a certain way, why?
Because his heart was tender.
And I pray that God would help us
to have hearts that are tender,
that we would receive truth,
that we would quickly respond in obedience
to what the Lord is speaking to us about.
We could ask the question, what is revival?
We could ask the question, do we even need revival?
And I would say this, that revival is renewed
in more active attention to our personal walk with the Lord.
A renewed and a more active attention
to our personal walk with the Lord.
A desire as the songwriter said,
to truly have nothing between my soul and my savior.
Understand this morning that revival is not regeneration.
Revival is not redemption.
Redemption is through the blood of the Lord Jesus Christ.
When I trust Christ as my personal savior
and I'm born again, I'm born of the spirit,
that is salvation and I'm thankful for salvation.
And the individual that is saved,
there are times when we need revival.
We need, I would call it this in just a simple term,
an awakening and we need to have,
listen, sometimes we can get apathetic.
Sometimes we can get indifferent.
Sometimes we can fall into the trap
of the church of the Laodiceans
and think that we're full of all these things
and we really have need of nothing.
And the reality is that we need a fresh touch of the Lord.
We need to have this awakening.
We need to come into this place where I would say this,
I don't wanna be calloused.
I don't wanna be cold.
I don't want to simply exist.
I want to abound spiritually.
You know, some people are perfectly fine with just existing.
Some people are perfectly fine with just coasting through,
if you will, and just existing.
But man, I wanna abound.
I wanna thrive spiritually.
I wanna have that, if I mentioned that the truth
of salvation is really a relationship
that I become a son of God.
He's my father through redemption,
through that regeneration.
If any man be in Christ, he's a new creature,
then I'm made alive.
I am his child.
I am saved.
I am born again.
The reality is that there are times
that we need that revival,
that we would have that first love
that Jesus speaks of with the church at Ephesus.
And this morning, when we think about revival in Israel,
if we were to go back,
and we won't take the time this morning,
but if we go back to the book of 2 Chronicles in particular
and look at the time in which Jehoshaphat
is reigning over Israel,
if you were to look at the time in which Hezekiah
is reigning over Judah, Jehoshaphat over Judah,
Hezekiah over Judah, Josiah reigning as king over Judah,
and you look at each of those periods of history,
and you look at the revivals that take place,
you will find several consistencies.
Number one, there's an acknowledgement of
and repentance of sin.
If you look at all of those accounts,
you will find that there's an acknowledgement
and a repentance of sin.
The period of time was marked by cleansing,
cleansing of the temple,
cleansing of the individuals.
You think about us as individual believers today,
New Testament believers,
we are the temple of God,
according to what we read in the scriptures,
that our bodies are the temple of the Holy Ghost,
which is in you, what you have of God.
We read that, we understand that,
and so it was marked by cleansing,
it was marked by obedience,
a renewed commitment to obey what thus saith the Lord.
It reminds me of John chapter two,
when Mary, the mother of the Lord Jesus Christ,
says to those servants,
whatsoever he saith unto you, do it.
A renewed commitment to obedience,
it was marked by worship, by worship.
Listen, we don't just come to church to mark a,
check a box that I was in church.
I'm thankful that in our church,
there's a great fellowship that takes place,
how appropriate that the name of our church is
Fellowship Baptist Church,
and I believe that God has allowed us in our church family
to establish some really good connections,
and we have sweet fellowship one with another.
But listen, you don't come to church
just because you wanna see a friend,
that you wanna fellowship with someone.
No, we come to church to worship the Lord,
to worship him in spirit and in truth,
and there's a renewed sense of worship of the Lord
when we think about this truth of revival
and see it in Israel's history, in Judah in particular.
We find that God's word was preached,
that prayer was primary,
and we see that the people of God were responding
to the challenges that were issued this morning.
I don't, you don't need to turn there,
I'll read it for you,
but in Romans chapter number 13 and verses 11 through 14,
listen to what the Bible says in this portion of scripture,
then we'll dig into John 13.
The Bible says this in Romans 13,
and that knowing the time,
that now it is high time, listen, to awake out of sleep.
For now is our salvation nearer than when we believed.
The night is far spent, the day is at hand.
Let us therefore cast off the works of darkness
and let us put on the armor of light.
Verse 13, let us walk honestly.
Man, wouldn't it be a wonderful thing
if there was just a renewed level of honesty,
not only in our nation, but I would say in our churches.
Let us walk honestly, as in the day,
not in rioting and in drunkenness,
not in chambering and wantonness,
not in strife and envying,
but put ye on the Lord Jesus Christ,
notice this phrase to end the chapter,
make not provision for the flesh
to fulfill the lusts thereof.
You understand that your flesh has desires.
I don't care if you're saved, your flesh has desires.
I don't care how old you are, your flesh has desires.
And the Bible says that we're to make not provision
for the flesh to fulfill the lusts thereof.
And as we think about this portion of scripture
in Romans 13, by way of introduction,
we find that it says that we're to awake out of sleep
and the way that we're to put off and put on in our walk
and what it should be marked by.
And we find that we live in this sin-cursed world
and we live in this time in which we're constantly
bombarded by so many things.
But as we look at John 13, we find that the Lord Jesus Christ, He rises from supper and
He washes the feet of the disciples.
And as He washes the feet of the disciples and we look contextually at what happens in
John 13, yes, there are some valuable lessons and we'll mark them quickly, but I want you
to understand that there is a spiritual truth that is given to us in John 13 that is so
necessary for us to understand today.
I've chosen this morning to title the message in the form of a question.
You've probably read it already in the back of the bulletin, but the title for the message
this morning posed as a question is this, are your feet dirty?
Are your feet dirty?
In John 13, pick it up with me in verse number one, the Bible says this, now before the feast
of the Passover, when Jesus knew that His hour was come, that He should depart out of
this world unto the Father, having loved His own, which were in the world, He loved them
unto the end.
Aren't you thankful for the love of God?
Verse two, in supper being ended, the devil having now put into the heart of Judas Iscariot,
Simon's son, to betray Him, Jesus knowing that the Father had given all things into
His hands and that He was come from God and went to God, He riseth from supper.
First the Bible says He laid aside His garments and took a towel and girded Himself.
Can you imagine even at that point as the disciples would begin to see the Lord Jesus
Christ move and what He's doing and seeing that He lays aside His garments and He takes
this towel and He girds Himself?
And then the Bible says after that in verse five that He pours water into a basin.
Then it tells us that He began to wash the disciples' feet and to wipe them with the
towel wherewith He was girded.
Can you see it in your mind's eye?
God in flesh, the Lord Jesus Christ, rising up from supper, these disciples that are sitting
there, and He rises up and He puts off His garments and the Bible tells us that He takes
and He takes this towel and He girds Himself and He pours this water in a basin and He
begins to wash the feet of the disciples and the Bible says that He then wiped them with
the towel wherewith He was girded.
I want to remind you that these same disciples according to other gospel accounts when they
entered into the room, you know what they were arguing over?
Who was the greatest among them?
And here is God who after supper gets down and performs a task that was the task of a
servant.
I find this morning that as we look at just these first few verses that we can see the
valuable lesson of service.
I'm thankful that Mark's gospel reveals to us so vividly that the Lord Jesus Christ came
to be a servant.
He didn't come to be served but He came to serve.
What a privilege it is to be a servant of the Lord Jesus Christ.
What a privilege it is to serve the Master.
To know that He not only gave us an example of service here in this particular text of
Scripture but He also gave us an example of humility.
What a lesson on humility.
When you begin to think about the Lord Jesus Christ, the Bible teaches us that He left
all of the glory of heaven.
You think about all of the splendor and glory that He had for all of eternity, past.
And He leaves.
And at the appointed time God sent forth His Son, born of a virgin, why?
To redeem them that were under the law.
The Bible tells us that He humbled Himself and He became obedient unto death, even the
death of the cross.
And we see here in John 13 just before He would go to that cross of Calvary that He
is given this lesson to His disciples of service and humility.
In fact, if you skip down to verse number 12, the Bible says, so after He'd washed their
feet and had taken His garments and was set down again, He said unto them, know ye what
I have done to you.
He's gonna teach them this lesson of service and humility.
He finishes up the task and we're gonna go back and focus on verses 6 through 10 here
in just a moment.
But I want you to see that Jesus says, do you know, know ye what I have done to you
in verse 13.
And notice what He says, ye call me Master and Lord.
And ye say, well, for so I am.
You know, so many people today want to say, well, Jesus never claimed to be God.
You ever read John 13 and verse number 13?
Listen, if He's not God, why would He allow them to call Him Lord?
Why would He allow them to call Him Master?
And He says, you call me Master and Lord.
And notice what He says, and ye say, well, you are correct in calling me Master.
You are correct in calling me Lord.
Why?
For so I am.
It's an interesting study.
We won't take the time this morning, but if you were to study through the book of John
and reference the I am, right?
Jesus said before Abraham was, I am.
What's He referring to?
All the way back in the book of Exodus, right?
I am that I am.
And we find here that He says before, and ye say, well, for so I am.
Notice in verse 14, if I then, your Lord and Master, have washed your feet, ye also
ought to wash one another's feet.
For I have given you an example that ye should do as I have done to you.
Verily, verily, I say unto you, the servant is not greater than his Lord, neither he that
is sent greater than he that sent him.
And so we find that the Lord Jesus Christ performs this task that is a task that is
just a humiliating task, to clean the feet of the disciples, and He shows the service
and the humility.
But this morning, for just a few moments, I want to focus our attention on the interaction
that is recorded for us between Jesus and Peter in verses 6 through 10.
As we look at this portion within the greater context, I want to deal with the specific
application, but then also deal with a spiritual application that I think is so necessary for
each of us this morning.
Notice in verse number 6.
Now you know, as you've studied, as I've preached over the years, Peter is the one that often
stands up and speaks.
Peter is the one that stood up and made that great declaration when Jesus said, whom do
men say that I am?
And they answer, some say John the Baptist, some say Jeremiah, one of the other prophets.
And Jesus says, but whom say ye that I am?
And Peter stands up and he says, thou art the Christ, the Son of the living God.
Man, what a great, powerful truth that Peter stands up and gives.
Remember when Jesus is walking on the water and the disciples see Him and Peter says,
Lord, if it's Thee, bid me come to Thee.
Peter's the one that, out of all of the disciples of the boat, he's the one that speaks up.
When Jesus takes Peter, John, and James to the Mount of Transfiguration and shows them
His glory, it's Peter that says, man, it's good that we're here.
We should make some three tabernacles.
And we find that Peter, now in the midst of this room, and the disciples are there, and
I think that Peter probably says what all of them wanted to say.
And he says this in verse 6, then cometh he to Simon Peter, and Peter saith unto him,
Lord, dost thou wash my feet?
Now I think that's an appropriate question.
Peter understanding, I mean, he lived in that culture.
You and I this morning, we wear shoes and most of us wear socks and we don't walk on
everywhere we go.
It's not our mode of transportation is our feet.
We get in vehicles and we drive and for the most part we have clean roads.
We don't walk on dusty, dirty roads where the same animals traverse and we walk through
all of those things.
It was a different culture.
It was a different time.
And these feet, they were dirty and Jesus is washing the feet of the disciples.
I don't know which number Peter is, but he comes to Peter and Peter says, Lord, dost
thou wash my feet?
Peter knew that thou art the Christ, the Son of the living God.
Peter knew who Jesus was.
The God of the universe is going to wash my feet?
Jesus answered and said unto him, what I do thou knowest not now, but thou shalt know
hereafter.
Then notice what Peter says to the Lord Jesus Christ.
Can you see Peter?
He says, thou shalt never wash my feet.
Again, I can understand why Peter might say that.
No Lord, thou shalt never.
The verbiage that is used is so strong that it's underscored, no, never, never you're
going to do that.
And Jesus says, if I wash thee not, notice this, thou hast no part with me.
We'll get back to that in just a moment, but notice Peter's response to what Jesus says
in verse 8.
Then Peter says this, Lord, not my feet only, but also my hands and my head.
You see how quickly Peter goes from, no Lord, never, you're not going to do it.
And Jesus says, listen, if I don't wash thee, if I don't do this, then thou hast no part
with me.
And then Peter goes all the way to the other side and says, okay, well then not just my
feet, but like wash me all over.
Notice what Jesus says in verse 10.
This is so important for us to understand as we look at the spiritual application this
morning.
We'll be right back.
Jesus saith to him,
He that is washed needeth not save to wash his feet,
but is clean every wit.
And then Jesus says, and you are clean, but not all.
Now there's a distinction in the original language
that we have a difficulty of seeing this morning
in the English language, and I don't say that
to cause anyone to have confusion or doubt
or any of that sort of thing, but you understand
that some languages have multiple words
for different things that we in English
just have one word for.
We were talking to Tim after door knocking yesterday,
we were talking about mushroom,
and I don't even know how it came up,
but the word in French versus in Spanish,
but Armando has a different word for mushroom in Spanish
than somebody else has for the word in Spanish.
They just have different words.
The word love, we use the word love in English
that I love my wife, and I love pizza.
And you say, well that's kind of odd,
but we just have one word.
But you understand through the context of the statement
what we mean by it.
I hope that each of you would understand
that I love my wife in a different way
than I love pizza. Amen?
Even though she got me a little thing
that sits on my nightstand that says
tacos, and what a blessing,
because I know she loves tacos, amen?
But the reality is that sometimes
we lack multiple words.
Actually, the vocabulary for English
is much smaller than the vocabulary
of a number of other languages,
Greek as well.
And here in this text of Scripture,
Jesus says, he that is washed.
That first reference in verse number 10
is a different word altogether
than the word when he says
neither not to save, to wash his feet.
It's two different words.
And they mean something entirely different.
The first washed means to bathe,
and it means the whole person.
The second word wash simply means to wash,
and it means a part only.
Specifically referring to hands, feet, or face.
You ever say to somebody,
you need to go wash your face.
You need to go get washed up.
And so we may use the word bathe, right?
That you need to go get a bath.
And we find here that then Jesus says this,
notice, he but is clean every wit.
And ye are clean, but not all.
Now why does he say not all?
Well, because Judas is sitting amongst the disciples.
And Jesus knows that Judas is not clean.
What do I mean by that?
Well, he's not been washed.
That first word that is used in John 13 and verse number 10,
he's not been washed.
He's not been saved.
If I could use that terminology this morning,
and you would understand the application that we're making.
And so he says that ye are clean, but not all.
The eleven have trusted,
but there's one Judas that's not,
and so he's not clean.
Now he's going to have his feet washed,
but it doesn't do him any good,
because he's not clean.
Does that make sense to you this morning?
So here's the physical understanding
of what they would understand
with regard to this text of scripture
and what they would daily go through.
They, unlike you and unlike me,
they did not have indoor plumbing
with their own bathrooms.
They did not have an en-suite.
They did not have a master bedroom with a beautiful...
No, they didn't have all of that.
And so a lot of times in the villages and the towns,
they would have central bathhouses
that they would go to,
and that's where they would get washed,
where they would bathe themselves.
And then after they would bathe themselves,
they would have to walk home.
Guess how they would walk home?
They would walk home with sandals on.
And when they'd walk home with sandals on,
they'd walk on some dusty, dirty roads
that the shepherds just brought their flocks through.
Now I hope you can understand this morning
what flocks do.
Everyone good? You're tracking?
Amen?
And that's where you're walking.
So guess what happens?
Your feet are dirty.
So what do you have to do?
Well, typically, when you went into a house
in that culture, there was a servant
that their job was to wash the feet
of the people that entered into the house.
Culturally, custom, that's how it worked.
So Jesus, washing the feet of the disciples,
he's giving them this truth.
Peter says, no, Lord, you're not going to wash my feet.
Never!
And Jesus says, remember verse 8,
I said that I'd get back to it in just a moment.
Jesus says in verse number 8,
he says, if I wash thee not,
thou hast no part with me.
Now understand that that word in verse number 8
is the second word that he uses
in verse number 10.
So this wash that he's speaking of
in verse number 8,
the second use in verse number 10
is that part only.
It's not talking about redemption.
It's not talking about being washed
or the whole person.
He doesn't mean to wash the feet.
Why? Because they've gotten dirty.
And so he says, notice, if I wash thee not,
thou hast no part with me.
What does he mean by that?
He doesn't mean that you stop being my child.
He means that our fellowship with him
is hindered.
We've got dirty feet.
And dirty feet hinder my fellowship
with my Savior.
And sin in the life of a believer
is never going to cause them
to have to be saved again.
Why? Because we believe in eternal security.
The Bible says that my sheep hear my voice,
and I know them, and I give unto them
eternal life.
And then he says, and they shall never perish.
I mean, listen, he had just taught this
in John chapter number 10
about this very truth.
He says, they shall never perish.
He says, neither shall any man pluck them
out of my hand.
Which gave them me is greater than all,
and no man is able to pluck them out
of my Father's hand.
I and my Father are one.
Peter says that we're kept by the power of God.
That we have reserved for us in heaven
this inheritance that's corruptible,
that's incorruptible, excuse me,
that fadeth not away.
So we understand the truth of eternal security.
By the way, I'm thankful that I can't lose it.
Because if I could lose it, if you could lose it,
we'd have lost it.
People like to run to Hebrews chapter number 6,
I believe it is, and run to Hebrews chapter number 6
and say, see right there, you can lose your salvation.
You know what's funny about that?
Prior to and after that portion of Scripture
in Hebrews chapter number 6,
you know how the Lord talks about security,
about salvation, that he is the author
of eternal security.
So you mean to tell me that God's going to tell us
that he's the author of eternal security
and then tell us you can lose it,
and then tell us he's the author of eternal security?
It doesn't make any sense.
And so we find here this morning
that when Peter and the other disciples,
and again, we focus in on this conversation,
this interaction between Peter and the Lord Jesus Christ,
and Jesus is washing the feet,
and he's giving them truth,
and Peter says, no, Lord,
and Jesus says to Peter,
but if I wash thee not, thou hast no part with me.
Peter, it's not that he's going to lose his salvation
because he doesn't get his feet washed,
it's that his fellowship is hindered.
Remember I said this by way of introduction
a few moments ago,
that I want nothing between my soul and my Savior.
The Bible tells us that sin hinders
our fellowship with God.
It hinders our fellowship with God.
D.L. Moody said this,
sin will keep you from this book,
or this book will keep you from sin.
You know what happens when somebody is sinning?
They're not praying like they should be praying.
They're not reading the Bible
like they should be reading the Bible.
They're not in church like they should be in church.
Why?
Because sin keeps, breaks, hinders our fellowship.
The Bible says this in Psalm 66 and verse 18,
if I regard iniquity in my heart,
the Lord will not hear me.
You ever feel like you can't get your prayers answered?
You feel like, man, it has come to the place,
search me, oh Lord, show me.
I need to get my feet washed
because my feet are dirty.
Great picture in the Old Testament.
Turn to the book of Exodus, if you will.
Exodus chapter 29,
and we'll look at chapter 29 and 30
here in the book of Exodus.
A great picture in the Old Testament
of this truth that we're dealing with this morning,
and it's pictured, it's typified
in the Old Testament priest.
In Exodus chapter 29,
we read, and we won't take the time
to read the entirety of the chapter.
It's a lengthy chapter in Exodus chapter 29,
but we read in Exodus chapter 29
of the consecration of the priest.
When you read of the consecration of the priest,
it begins in verse number one,
and it says, and this is the thing
thou shalt do unto them to hallow them.
That means to consecrate them.
That means to sanctify them.
The word sanctify means to set apart.
It means to cleanse and to purify,
and we understand that these priests,
this consecration that was taking place
was a one-time event.
They were, this thing that they did
in Exodus chapter 29,
this is what took place.
This was the instruction
with regard to the consecration of the priest,
and as they would enter into the priest's office,
this was what took place.
the process. Notice the Bible says, take one young bullock and two rams without
blemish, verse 2, and unleavened bread and cakes unleavened, tempered with oil, and
wafers unleavened, anointed with oil of wheat and flour shalt thou make them.
Thou shalt put them into one basket and bring them in the basket with the bullock
and the two rams, verse 4, and Aaron and his sons thou shalt bring unto the door
of the tabernacle of the congregation, notice what it says, and shalt wash them
with water. That's at that moment of consecration, of that sanctification, of
them being set apart for that particular service. The Bible tells us about, as you
continue reading through here, about the killing of the ram, and verse number 20
talks about taking his blood and putting it on the tip of the right ear of Aaron,
upon the tip of the right ear of his sons, and upon the thumb of the right
hand, upon the great toe of the right foot, and sprinkle the blood upon the
altar round about. You would see from head to toe, they had been through this
process of consecration. It started with being washed, though, in verse number 4.
But then think about this, as they serve the Lord in the office of a priest, they
would serve in the tabernacle. When you serve in the tabernacle, the first piece
of furniture that you come to after you enter the single gate of the tabernacle
is the brazen altar, and we find that that represents the fact that sacrifice
is required. You can't ever get to the holy place without first coming to the
brazen altar. But then after the brazen altar, there's a laver. Exodus chapter
number 30, notice what the Bible says in verse number 17, in Exodus chapter 30, so
now that one-time consecration is done in Exodus 29, now in chapter
number 30, notice in verse 17, the Bible says, the Lord spake unto Moses, saying,
Thou shall also make a laver of brass, and his foot also of brass, to wash with
all, and thou shalt put it between the tabernacle of the congregation and the
altar, and thou shalt put water therein. And it says that Aaron and his sons
shall wash what? Their hands and their feet thereat. When they go into the
tabernacle of the congregation, they shall wash with water. Notice what it
says, that they die not. Or when they come near to the altar to minister, to burn
offering made by fire unto the Lord, so they shall wash their hands and their
feet, that they die not, and it shall be a statute forever to them, even to him
and to his seed throughout their generations. And we find here that in
in Exodus 30, verses 17 through 21, this laver served the purpose of washing, yes,
their feet, but also their hands, because of what they would be involved in. And
guess what? As they were making the sacrifice unto the Lord, they were
getting dirty feet and dirty hands. God said, use a laver for that purpose. So as
we go back to John chapter number 13, and we seek to answer the question, are
your feet dirty? Are your feet dirty? If you're taking notes this morning, all
that was introduction, but don't worry, I only have two points, it's gonna be quick.
Promise. That was the big part of the message. Number one this morning, the
reason our feet get dirty. The reason our feet get dirty. Number one, and quite
obvious, is because of sin. No doubt, sin in the life of a believer must be dealt
with. Sin causes us to have dirty feet. If we're looking at the same picture in
this illustration that we see in John 13, making this spiritual application, we
find that that sin will make us dirty. We understand the importance of dealing
with sin in the life of believer. I mentioned this last year as I was
preaching through the first, the book of 1st John, where a preacher was speaking
about sin in the life of a believer, and someone objected to the message that the
preacher preached, because he said, listen, sin in the life of a believer is
different than sin in an unbeliever. And the preacher responded and said, yes, it's
worse. It's worse. And what happens sometimes is we just kind of get
comfortable with living in the culture that we're living in, and everybody else
around us, we talked about that truth in Romans 13, that we'd walk honestly, and I
said, listen, that's good for our culture, but it's good for our church. It's
amazing how often we can just ignore sin in our life, and we don't recognize
it as being sin. We don't recognize it as being awful and causing us to have our
fellowship with God hindered. No doubt our feet get dirty when we engage in
sin, but really more of the application that I'd like to make this morning is
that I would say to you, and I'd say to myself this morning, that our feet get
dirty simply because we live in this world. Turn to the book of John. You're
there in John 13. Turn to chapter 17, if you will. In John chapter number 17, you
notice that we're in the world. When I say that we're in the world, we find that
we live in this sin-cursed world. You come into contact with people every
single day, and just like those people in the first century, those disciples that
Jesus is ministering to here in John chapter 13, that they would have
understood the daily routine, the weekly routine of going down to the bathhouse
and then having to walk through those roads and getting their feet dirty, and
the importance of regularly washing their feet. Why? Because their feet
regularly got dirty because they were walking in that place. Does that make
sense? And so this morning, when we understand the truth that we are in this
world, just because we're in the world, our feet get dirty. We get exposed to
some things. Listen, you might not have participated in the dirty jokes that
were told this past week at your workplace. You may not have even laughed
at them, but you were influenced by them. You heard them. You may not have
supported what you saw on that billboard, or on that sign, or on that
advertisement that came across your phone, or in your mailbox, or wherever it
might have been, but it impacts you. You get dirty. Does that make sense to you
this morning? And you might not have engaged in the sinful act, the sinful
behavior, but man, I have that. You know, we talk about be careful little eyes
what you see, be careful little ears what you hear. Why? Because it impacts us.
And Jesus says this in John 17. Notice what he says. I mean, this is a powerful
passage of Scripture. Really, it is the Lord's Prayer. He's going, he speaks
about the hour coming to start the passage of Scripture, but I want to skip
down to verse 14. He says, I have given them thy word. Praise the Lord that we
have the Bible. He says, I have given them thy word, and the world hath hated them.
Why? Because they are not of the world, even as I am not of the world. Listen, this
morning, I hope that you're so thankful that you're not of this world. I hope
this morning that you can rejoice in saying this world is not my home. I'm
just a passing through. Listen, I'm a pilgrim and a stranger. My citizenship is
in heaven, but I'm still in this world. I'm not of the world, but I'm in the
world. Notice what he says in verse 15. I pray not that thou shouldest take them
out of the world, but that thou shouldest keep them, notice what it says, from the
evil. They are not of the world, even as I am not of the world. Listen, this
morning, I know sometimes we would say, even as Paul said, I'm in a straight
betwixt two having a desire to depart to be with Christ, which is far better. Lord,
even so, come, as John prays in Revelation. But you understand that Jesus, in verse
15, he says, I pray not that thou shouldest take them out of the world, but
that thou shouldest keep them from the evil. Listen, why does Jesus have us here
still? Because we have a work to do. The world needs to hear the truth of the
gospel. Who's going to tell them? Listen, if the moment you got saved, you were
transported to heaven, there'd be no believers here. You think about who told
you the truth of the gospel. What if they were transported as soon as they trusted
Christ as their Savior? The gospel wouldn't have gotten to you. Does that make
sense? So, he has a plan for us, and I know sometimes we can get so sick of this
world. We get bombarded in this world, and we see all this wickedness that's going
on, and we rack our brains. How could this be? Do you read the news? Do you see the
stuff that's going on? It's absolute insanity, and it makes us dirty. It
doesn't mean that we have to engage in the sin, but it impacts us. That's why I
need to go to God, and go to His Word. I'm going to get to that in just a moment. I would
say that we're in the world, and just by simply being in the world, we get our
feet dirty. Get your feet dirty. I would say this, because we're in the world, sometimes
we get spotted, polluted, defiled. I think about the truth of the temple. I made the
statement already that we are the temple. We made a statement about Jehoshaphat,
Hezekiah, and Josiah, and how they were cleansing the temple. During the time of Jesus, at the
beginning of His earthly ministry, and then right before He went to the cross, He
cleansed the temple. Isn't it amazing that He had to do it twice? You know what happens
if we're not careful? Stuff can just kind of build up. My mother-in-law used to have
this sign on her refrigerator. I remember it said this, I cleaned my house yesterday.
I wish you could have seen it. How many of you ladies, I hate dusting, but some of you
ladies, you dust your house, and you say, man, I just dusted this house two days ago,
and there's dust all over the place. I hate dusting. I like vacuuming. I love it, but
I don't like any other house chore. The reality is this, if you're not careful, you're going
to get dirty just because you live in the world. The Bible tells us in James 1 and verse
27 that we're to be unspotted from the world. Guess what that tells me? I can be spotted
by the world. I can be impacted and influenced. If we're not careful, the thoughts of this
world begin to influence us.
impact our thoughts, and we need,
we see the reason that our feet get dirty,
yes, number one, sin, but number two,
just because we live in this world.
We live in this world.
So what's the remedy?
Number two, we see, number one,
the reason that our feet get dirty.
What's the remedy for dirty feet?
Well, right there in John 17,
he said that we're in the world,
but we're not of the world.
He said in verse 14 that I've given them thy word,
but then I want you to notice verse 17,
sanctify them through thy truth.
Thy word is truth.
That word sanctify, again, as I mentioned
from Exodus chapter 29, it means to cleanse.
It means to purify.
It means to set apart, and so I begin to think
about this truth of John 17 in verses 14 through 17,
and Jesus says I've given them thy word,
and then he gives this parenthetical statement
in a sense that the world hates them
because they hate me and that they're not of the world,
and I'm not of the world, and they're in the world,
but they're not of the world,
and then he says this, sanctify them through thy truth.
Thy word is truth.
Ephesians chapter five, verses 26 and seven.
Look at that passage, if you will, very quickly,
and we'll look at just a few verses,
and then I'll make a few statements,
and we'll close this morning,
but in Ephesians chapter number five,
within the context of Ephesians five,
it begins about really revival.
If you read this passage of scripture,
you see just a great truth and outline
with regard to revival and the truth
of being filled with the spirit of God,
and then he deals with the relationships in the home,
the home life, and verse 22 down through
deals with wives and husbands and children
in the beginning of chapter number six,
but I wanna draw your attention to verse 25,
really focus on verse 26 and seven
for the purpose of this particular message this morning,
but in verse 25, the Bible says,
husbands, love your wives, but then notice this,
and I don't mean to set that aside like it's not important
because it is very important,
but I want you to see that it says,
even as Christ also loved the church
and gave himself for it, the church, right?
So what is the church?
The church is not a building, the church is the people,
those that have been born again,
saved by the blood of Christ, that's the church, amen?
And we find that he says that he loved the church
and he gave himself for it, but then notice verse 26,
that he might sanctify and cleanse it, the church, how?
With the washing of water, how?
By the word, by the word,
that he might present it to himself a glorious church,
not having spot or wrinkle or any such thing,
but that it should be holy and without blemish.
This morning, yes, we understand
that our feet get dirty with sin
and we need the truth of 1 John 1 and verse number nine,
that if we confess our sin,
his faith will adjust to forgive us our sin
and cleanse us from all unrighteousness
and I'm thankful for the blood of Christ.
But when we understand this morning,
this truth of getting our feet dirty
because we live in this world
and we live in all this filth of this world
and it impacts us and it causes us to be dirty
and we need to have our feet washed,
this remedy is that we see that he says
that it's the washing of water by the word.
Listen, why does the preacher say,
read your Bible every day?
Not because we're trying to get certificates
to say who read their Bible in a year.
It's because you get dirty
and you need the cleansing of the word, amen?
Because it's the word of God that tells me what's right
and what's wrong and all of that truth
that we find that with regard to the Bible
and I'm so thankful that God's given it to us
and listen this morning, he says this truth in Psalm 119,
wherewithal shall a young man cleanse his way
by taking heed thereto according to thy word,
thy word have I hid in mine heart
that I might not sin against thee in verse number 11
and we find this morning that this truth,
the remedy for the dirty feet,
yes, the blood of the Lord Jesus Christ
and how thankful I am for the blood that was shed,
the blood that forgives,
I'm thankful that we have a God who's gracious and merciful
but I find this morning that the washing of water
by the word, sanctify them through thy truth,
thy word is truth.
Listen, we need the Bible.
Tim and I knocking doors yesterday,
I asked a lady, hey, do you read the Bible?
She's like, eh, you know, occasionally it's a good read,
you know, whatever.
No, no, man, I read the Bible every day.
Why, because you've never read it before?
No, I've read it countless times.
I can't, I've stopped keeping track
of how many times I've read the Bible through.
I don't say that in pride,
I don't say that to put myself up,
I'm just simply saying I've stopped counting
because I need it every single day.
Some people say I read the Bible through in a year,
that's wonderful but listen,
if you get done reading the Bible through on September 10th,
that's the date today,
it doesn't mean that you don't read it
the rest of the year.
You go back to Genesis one if you're reading it that way.
Amen?
Why, because we need God's word.
It cleanses us.
It washes us.
Listen, physically this morning,
as we look at John 13 physically,
it's easy to tell if you have dirty feet.
Right?
I remember kids coming in, playing outside barefoot.
They come in with dirty feet.
Sometimes my kids would play volleyball out here
with dirty feet on, dirty feet on.
I guess you can't take them off,
but with no shoes, right?
They just play barefoot.
And guess what happens when you play volleyball barefoot?
First of all, you got a problem
with getting something in your foot maybe,
but your feet get dirty.
So you know what I tell my kids?
You're not coming to my house with those dirty feet.
Joseph, is that what I say?
Not coming to the house with dirty feet.
You're playing outside with bare feet?
So you know what Brownie used to do?
She used to keep a pair of socks right at the front door.
And she put those socks on her dirty feet,
and then she'd go upstairs and she'd wash her feet.
You can tell if you have dirty feet physically.
It's obvious.
But can I tell you this morning?
At times, we can cover up our spiritually dirty feet.
We can pretend as if our feet aren't dirty.
We can pretend as if we've not been influenced
and impacted by living in this world.
We can pretend that we have no sin.
But he that says that he has no sin is a liar.
Remember, God didn't put your opinion in the Bible.
He didn't put my opinion either.
He just said his word.
And in 1 John 1, he said, if you say that you have no sin,
you're a liar.
The truth is not in you.
And then he says this, you make him a liar.
That's a problem.
And spiritually speaking, many times,
only you know if you have dirty feet.
I would say it this way.
Don't get used to dirty feet.
Don't be comfortable with dirty feet.
How many of you like it having dirty hands?
I know there's some mechanics.
Mr. Manuel makes fun of me and Pierre,
never can have dirty hands.
No, I don't like my hands being dirty.
I don't.
My battery died in my truck yesterday.
I had to change my battery.
I washed my hands like four times.
It's just crazy.
I hate wearing gloves.
Why?
Because when you wear gloves,
you can't feel that your hands are dirty.
During that whole COVID nonsense,
you ever have a waiter, waitress that comes and brings,
takes up all the dirty dishes from the other place,
uses the same gloves and then brings you your,
here's your dinner.
Are you kidding me?
You didn't go wash your hands
after you got all that junk on it
because you got gloves on and you can't feel it.
Amen?
I don't like dirty hands.
I don't like dirty feet.
What am I saying?
Don't get used to it.
Don't be okay with dirty feet spiritually.
Don't be okay with sin.
Don't be okay with being influenced
and spotted by this world.
Listen, we live in this world,
but we're not of the world.
And God gave us the remedy.
He said, I've given you the word.
Listen, every day of our lives,
we must determine that we're gonna spend time
in God's word.
Why?
Because you need it.
You need to be cleansed.
And you're cleansed through the word
with this idea of being dirty or defiled
just by living in this world.
To go back to the truth of John 13,
those disciples understood what it was
to get their feet dirty physically.
But Jesus said, I'm not only doing this,
but I'm teaching you a lesson.
Lesson on service and humility,
absolutely 100%.
But teaching us a lesson that, listen,
at times, your feet get dirty and my feet get dirty.
So I ask you this morning, are your feet dirty?
Are your feet dirty?
Do you need to confess some sin?
Do you need to just ask God to cleanse you
through his word?
I don't wanna be defiled by this world.
Listen, have you experienced that sometimes
you hear things that you really hoped,
wished you didn't hear?
Does it happen to you?
It happens to me.
You ever see something that you wish you didn't see
that you could unsee, that you could unhear?
You can't unhear it, you can't unsee it.
I know that's probably not good English,
but you understand what I'm saying.
But you know what you can do?
You can bring into captivity every thought
to the obedience of Christ.
You can renew your mind.
How are you renewing your mind?
Through the word of God.
this morning. Are your feet dirty?
Let's pray. Father, we love you. Thank you for loving us. Thank you for your Word.
God, I pray. I pray this morning that you would
work. Holy Spirit, would you convict?
Would you help us, Lord, to see? No pretense.
Help us to see that we have dirty feet.
Just by living in this defiled world,
we get dirty feet. God, would you help us to not get used to it?
Would you help us not to ignore it? Would you help us not to
try to make it look good? Help us, Lord, to be cleansed.
Help us to have clean feet. See,
we want to have that fellowship with you. When Peter heard those words, he said,
not my feet only, but my feet, my hands, my head.
Jesus, you said that he that is washed,
we'd understand that to mean being saved, born again,
cleansed by the blood of the Lord Jesus Christ,
save only to wash his feet.
That daily cleansing for service and fellowship.
Simply because we get dirty in this world. God, would you help us to be clean?
God, we want to have nothing between
our soul and our Savior. We want to be revival ready.
I pray in these moments of invitation that you'd have your will and way.
God, would you work? We'll give you the glory.
For it's in Christ's name we pray.