Chapter number 21, and we'll be looking at verses 8 through 21 this evening as we look
at this portion of Scripture.
And I'll just read a couple of verses and we'll get right into the message.
Of course, if you were here last Sunday evening, we looked at the first seven verses of this
chapter and we dealt with the fact that Isaac's birth is recorded here, and we noted as we
studied that portion of Scripture, the faithfulness of God and the obedience of Abraham.
I mentioned this, that I believe that this probably was one of the highest points in
Abraham's life, the birth of Isaac.
After 25 years of being promised and looking forward to that seed, that promise that would
come to see it fulfilled and to hold little Isaac, can you imagine just the joy?
Obviously, those of us that have had the privilege of having children, you think about the joy
of holding that newborn baby and what precious joy that is.
And to think about Abraham at this point in his life, 25 years again, from the time the
initial promise, of course, repeated often, but God always does what He says He will do.
And we're thankful for the faithfulness of God, thankful for the obedience of Abraham.
As we continue into the passage of Scripture, we find that the Bible tells us that Isaac
was weaned and Abraham made a great feast.
Notice in verse number 8, the Bible says, and a child grew, speaking of Isaac, and was
weaned, and Abraham made a great feast the same day that Isaac was weaned.
I want to preach a message that I've titled this evening from verse number 8, Abraham
made a great feast.
Abraham made a great feast.
Traditionally, it is believed and held that children in this particular culture would
be weaned between the ages of 2 and 3.
And 2 to 3 years old would be the age in which a child would be weaned.
Most scholars would lean towards 3 as being the age specifically.
And I say that by way of introduction so that we can build a little timeline here to understand
as we begin to look at the remainder of this passage.
And so if we go with the age of 3, then that would mean that Abraham at this time, when
he made this great feast, that he was 103 years old.
And so remember, Abraham was 100 when Isaac was born.
And so that's pretty easy math, 100 plus 3.
And so Abraham's 103 years old.
But we also would find that the Bible tells us back in Genesis chapter number 16 and verse
number 16 that Abraham was 86 when Ishmael was born.
And so he was 86 years old when Ishmael was born, and that would lead us to understanding
as we study this passage of Scripture that Ishmael is now 17 years old.
And so he's either 16 or 17 if you want to go with the 2 or the 3, however you want to
look at that.
But he's either 16 or 17 years old because Abraham was 86 when Ishmael was born according
to Genesis 16 and verse number 16.
And so as we understand kind of the timeline of what's going on, again the ages of these
folks, it helps us to kind of understand the full context of what's going to happen and
put it in proper perspective.
If you're taking notes, number one this evening, I just want you to note the historical account.
I'm really just going to read through it and make some comments, really verses 9 through
21, and look at the historical account that God gives us.
And then we'll go over to the New Testament and begin to look at an application.
But notice with me as we look and begin in verse number 8, the first highlight, if you
will, if you want to kind of put some things down.
Number one, we see that Isaac is weaned, and that's given to us in verse number 8.
And that's really the beginning of this historical context account that God is giving us.
And at that time of his weaning, we find that Abraham makes this great feast.
Now this was customary in this particular culture to behave in this manner and to celebrate
the growth and development of a child and to kind of make that next step and so on and
so forth.
And what a blessing that they would follow in that and understand those things.
In verse number 9, as we continue to read, we find that the Bible says,
And Sarah saw the son of Hagar, the Egyptian, which she had borne unto Abraham, mocking.
Now as we look at verse number 9, we note two additional aspects of this content in
this account that God is giving us.
Number one, we find that Ishmael is mocking.
The word mock here, it means to tease or laugh at in a scornful manner.
And we find that he is mocking, and Sarah observes this behavior.
It says in verse number 9 that Sarah saw the son of Hagar, the Egyptian.
We know that to be Ishmael contextually as you look through the book of Genesis and the
preceding chapters.
And so you find here that on this momentous occasion, you see what's happening, and Isaac
is weaned, and Abraham's making this great feast.
And there's this 17-year-old that has been to this point the only offspring of Abraham.
He'd been the only son.
Remember, Abraham cried out to God, O that Ishmael might live before thee.
Abraham no doubt loved Ishmael, and no doubt they had a relationship.
And now Ishmael's 17 years old, and the Bible says that at this momentous occasion that
he's mocking, and Sarah observes this.
Sarah's not very happy at what she sees happening.
She's not delighted with the circumstances.
We find that it begins conflict here.
It's very similar to what we find in the account back in Genesis chapter number 16, when she
had the idea that Abraham go and be married to Hagar, and then when Hagar was expecting,
there was strife.
There was contention between Hagar and Sarah.
And so we find here that as Sarah observes what's going on, she then responds, and notice
the response in verses 10 and 11.
The Bible says, Wherefore, she said unto Abraham, Cast out this bondwoman and her son.
For the son of this bondwoman shall not be heir with my son, even with Isaac.
And the thing was very grievous in Abraham's sight because of his son.
Again, you can understand the context of verse number 11.
That's where I mentioned the age.
He's 17 years old.
I mean, you think about the bond and the time that has been taken, and you find that Sarah
is not happy, and she responds, and her response is to cast out this bondwoman and her son.
She says that he, Ishmael, will not be heir with my son, with Isaac.
Now we understand contextually as we're reading this account, we understand a lot of what
God has already said with regard to the promises that God has made, that it was in the promised
seed of that God was going to bless Isaac.
His blessing would be in Isaac.
And we understand those things as we study the Scriptures, but as we know what's taking
place here, we can see the conflict within the family and the emotions that are going
on, and it's grievous in the sight of Abraham and all that's taking place.
But we find that as Abraham's trying to take in everything that Sarah has said, now God
speaks.
And the Bible says in verse number 12, and God said unto Abraham, I'm thankful that God
spoke to Abraham.
And as we look at the passage of Scripture, I'll say right at the beginning of really
this point of the message this evening, that I understand that we can get ourselves emotionally
involved within the content of what's going on here, and we can have all sorts of emotions
on whether we think it was right or wrong or why and all of that sort of thing.
But as we draw the conclusion this evening and go over to the book of Galatians and see
the application that God gives us, we see how God is providing for us this beautiful
picture of really the spiritual conflict that we can deal with, that we do deal with.
And so we see that God speaks, and He says unto Abraham, notice what He says, let it
not be grievous in thy sight because of the lad, and because of thy bondwoman, and all
that Sarah hath said unto thee hearken unto her voice.
For in Isaac shall thy seed be called.
You understand that God's plan does not change.
This has been the plan that God has given from the beginning.
We find that as Abraham would cry out in chapter number 17, as I mentioned a moment
ago, O that Ishmael might live before thee, that God says, I've heard what you've said,
I've heard thee, and I will bless him, and I will make of him a great nation, but my
covenant will I establish with Isaac.
And so here in chapter number 21, God reaffirms His plan that He's already given.
He says, for in Isaac shall thy seed be called.
And we find that He, God, gives instruction that Abraham, the first aspect of the instruction
is that He is to hearken unto the voice of Sarah, that He is to do what Sarah has said.
Notice it says here in the verse, it says, and all that Sarah hath said unto thee hearken
unto her voice.
Well, what was it that Sarah said?
Cast out this bondwoman and her son.
That's what Sarah said.
And God says, hearken unto her voice.
And He says this, for in Isaac shall thy seed be called.
Notice that God not only says hearken unto the voice of Sarah, He says that in Isaac
shall thy seed be called.
But I want you to notice what He says in verse number 13 with regard to Ishmael.
He says, and also of the son of the bondwoman will I make a nation because he is thy seed.
And so again, it's consistent with what God has already communicated to Abraham back in
chapter 17.
God had made this declaration, this promise. In fact, if you go all the way
back to chapter number 16 and you read what's taking place there after the
birth of Ishmael, you find that God had given promise there with regard to
Ishmael as well. And so as we look here at the context, we find again this
historical account that God speaks. Now when God speaks, we have to respond. We
have to respond. And we're gonna respond in one of two ways. Obedience or
disobedience. There's no middle ground. There's no halfway point. There's no
partial. We've said often, and perhaps you've said it to your children, partial
obedience is disobedience, right? To obey is better than sacrifice. That's what
Samuel tells Saul. And we find that here as Abraham would receive this
instruction from God, he now is left at a moment of decision. What is it that
he's going to do? Is he gonna obey or is he gonna disobey? Now, the reality is that
there are times in our lives in which God may ask us to do something that's
not easy to do. Which path are we gonna choose? See, this was a
relationship, his son, that had been built 17 years and God saying, no, hearken to
the voice of Sarah and this is how you're supposed to go forward. And we
find that Abraham is now left in this place of decision. We noted last week the
obedience of Abraham and we've noted that it really, if you study throughout
the scriptures, that you'll find often that the Bible speaks about the
obedience of Abraham. The reality is that Hebrews 11, when it speaks about Abraham,
it says that he obeyed after God called. He obeyed and he went out not knowing
whither he went. And so we find here that Abraham is going to then act, we notice
in verse number 14, the Bible says, and Abraham rose up early in the morning. He
didn't waste any time. There's no delay. See, sometimes we delay, right? Delayed
obedience. Well, I'll get to it when I get to it. And you know one of the problems
with delayed obedience is that sometimes we never actually get to it, right? We
just don't ever get to doing what we're supposed to do because something else
creeps in and something else does. And when God shows us, when God reveals to us
truth, as hard as it may be, as difficult and as challenging as it might be, we
need to obey. We need to obey immediately. And we find that the Bible says that he
rose up early in the morning, notice it says, and took bread and a bottle of
water and gave it unto Hagar, putting it on her shoulder and the child and sent
her away. And she departed and wandered in the wilderness of Beersheba. Again, I
understand the emotions that we could have as we read an account such as this
and we could question all that we want to question, but the reality is that
God's ways are not our ways. His thoughts are not our thoughts. And we find that
this is indeed the actual instruction that God has provided to Abraham and
would be later used as a great truth, a great spiritual truth for us to
understand. We find that as Abraham acted in verse number 14, that then we
continue throughout the context here looking at this historical account that
is provided, and we find that the water was spent and Hagar wept. It says in
verse number 16, excuse me, verse number 15, and the water was spent in the bottle
and she cast the child under one of the shrubs and she went and sat her down
over against him a good way off, as it were a bow shot, for she said, let me not
see the death of the child. And she sat over against him and lift up her voice
and wept. Again, what a difficult situation. She didn't want to see the
death of Ishmael and no doubt if you can put yourself in this position you
wouldn't want to see the death of your child either. And we find here that as
that water was spent and as she wept, we find that an angel of God
spake unto her. In verse number 17, the Bible says in, it says, and God heard the
voice of the lad. And the angel of God called to Hagar out of heaven and said
unto her, what aileth thee, Hagar? Fear not, for God hath heard the voice of the
lad where he is. Notice in verse number 18 that God is going to provide once
again a promise that has been oft repeated with regard to Ishmael. It says,
Arise, lift up the lad, and hold him in thine hand, for I will make him a great
nation. As a side note, let me say this, God did. He fulfilled the promise that he
made with regard to Ishmael. And we find that he not only has made of him a great
nation, we do understand, and of course there's a bunch of confusion with
regard to the seed and so on and so forth, with regard to if you speak to
some within the Muslim faith and they believe that it's through Ishmael, not
through Isaac, but we understand without any controversy that God has explicitly
said in his word that the blessing would go through Isaac. But he said he would
bless Ishmael, and he has. Now we understand that there's much history
that could be looked at and so on and so forth, and we'll save that for another
discussion, but we find here that as we continue with this historical content in
the account that's given to us here, that not only is there a promise given
in verse number 18, but we find that provision is given in verse number 19.
The Bible says, And God opened her eyes, and she saw a well of water. And she went
and filled the bottle with water, and gave the lad drink. In verses 20 and 21,
the Bible tells us of the development and marriage of Ishmael. The Bible says
that God was with the lad, again Ishmael, and he grew and dwelt in the wilderness
and became an archer, and he dwelt in the wilderness of Paran, and his mother
took him a wife out of the land of Egypt. Now we understand that Hagar, remember,
she was an Egyptian, right? If you go all the way back and you find in Genesis
chapter number 12, during that time in which they had that great famine, that
difficulty that was faced, and the first time in which Abraham said that Sarah
was his sister to Pharaoh, and so on and so forth, when they come back, they come
back with Hagar, according to what we find in the portion of Scripture. And so
as we look at the the historical account that is given, we find that now Ishmael
is married, and he's married to an Egyptian. Now we understand that as we
look at the historical content, the account that is provided to us, much
discussion could be made. But instead of us making discussion with regard to the
content that is here, I'd rather let God's Word give us insight as to that
which is provided to us here in Genesis 21. And so we find that, yes, we know the
historical account, but number two, I want you to note the spiritual
application. In order to note the spiritual application, we must go to the
book of Galatians in chapter number four. In Galatians chapter number four, the
book of Galatians is just a power-filled book with so much wonderful truth with
regard to the the early church and all that was happening with the Judaizers
and all that was taking place. Of course, the book of Galatians is written to the
churches that are in the region of Galatia. These churches were planted,
established, if you will, during the first missionary journey of the Apostle Paul,
and we find that that could be recorded, or it is recorded, and can be reviewed in
Acts 13 and 14. And in these cities, Antioch and Pisidia, Iconium, Lystra, and
Derbe, these churches were established, and these Judaizers come in, and there's
all kinds of crazy teaching that's going on. And we understand that, really, as you
begin looking in the beginning of chapter number two, that it really points
us back to Acts chapter number 15, when they had that council at Jerusalem, and
there were some that were saying this, except you be circumcised after the
manner of Moses, you cannot be saved. And we know that's not true, and that was
something that these Judaizers were bringing into these churches in the
region of Galatia, and so Paul is seeking to provide them with instruction, and God
is faithful to give the truth of His Word to these believers in these
churches. And we find that in verses 21 through 31 of Galatians 4, that the
spiritual application is provided for us with regard to that account that we read
in Genesis 21. Notice what it says here in verse number 21,
tell me ye that desire to be under the law, do ye not hear the law? And then
notice this, he says, for it is written. Now he'll say for it is written again in
verse 27, and then he'll say in verse number 30, what saith the scripture? See,
Paul was well-versed within the Old Testament, he understood the teaching of
the Old Testament, he was well-versed in it, and we understand the Old Testament has
been given for our learning, for our admonition, and there are some today that
take the approach that we really don't need the Old Testament because we're
New Testament believers, and that's a bad approach because God Himself tells us
that the Old Testament has been given for our admonition, for our learning, and
no doubt there's great truth for us to understand. And so we find that Paul
makes an appeal to the scriptures, and he says this in verse 22, for it is
written that Abraham had two sons, the one by a bondmaid, the other by a free
woman. So we find immediately that Paul is going back to this passage of
scripture.
in Genesis chapter 21 where we see the birth of Isaac. Of course Ishmael was
born 16 years, 14 years earlier than the birth of Isaac and we find here that
that he's referring to these two sons Ishmael and Isaac. Ishmael from the
bondmaid and Isaac from the free woman. Notice in verse 23, but he who was of the
bondwoman was born, notice what it says, after the flesh but he of the free woman
was by promise or shall I say by faith. It says in verse number 24, notice this,
which things are an allegory, which things are an allegory for these are the
two covenants, the one from the Mount Sinai which gendereth to bondage which
is Hagar, for this Hagar is Mount Sinai in Arabia and answereth to Jerusalem
which now is and is in bondage with her children. But Jerusalem which is above
is free which is the mother of us all. For it is written, rejoice thou barren
that bearest not, break forth and cry thou that travailest not, for the
desolate hath many more children than she which hath not a husband. Notice
verse 28, now he says now we brethren as Isaac was are the children of promise.
Now you see how he's gonna make the application this allegory, he says these
things are an allegory, this passage of Scripture in Genesis 21, as you hold on
here in just a couple of more verses we're gonna see how we know exactly that
he's speaking about Genesis 21. He's mentioned the two sons, he's mentioned of
course Hagar and Sarah, and now we find that he says that we brethren as Isaac
was in verse 28 are the children of promise. He says this in verse 29, but as
then he that was born after the flesh, who's that? That's Ishmael, right? That's
who he's referring to. He says he that was born after the flesh persecuted him
that was born after the Spirit. Then notice these words, even so it is now. And
so he's making, he's unfolding for us this wonderful spiritual application
with regard to the historical account that is given to us in Genesis chapter
21. He goes on further and he says nevertheless, notice in verse 30, what
saith the Scripture? Again he's appealing back to the Word of God. Notice what he
says, cast out the bondwoman and her son. No doubt now that we're speaking
specifically about Genesis 21 in the historical account that we just read. He
says for the son of the bondwoman, notice, shall not be heir with the son of the
free woman. So then, here's the conclusion, so then brethren we are not children of
the bondwoman but of the free. See, the law cannot save. All the law can do is
condemn. That's all the law can do. In fact, if you look back in Galatians 3, he
says, is the law then, in verse number 21, is the law then against the promises of
God? God forbid. For if there had been a law given which could have given life,
verily righteousness should have been by the law. But what saith the Scripture? He
says, but the Scripture hath concluded all under sin that the promise by faith
of Jesus Christ might be given to them that believe. In chapter number 2, in
verse number 21, he says, I do not frustrate the grace of God, for if
righteousness came by the law, then Christ is dead in vain. And so he began
this passage of Scripture in Galatians 4, in verse number 21, by saying this,
tell me, ye that desire to be under the law, do ye not hear the law? And so there
were some that were trying to put themselves back under the law, these
Judaizers that were coming in and saying, hey, you got to be under the law, you got
to be under the law. Now, if you've read the law, you probably don't want to be
under the law. Amen? I'm glad to be in the dispensation, if you will, of grace. Amen?
I'm thankful that we're not under the law, that Christ has fulfilled the law.
I'm thankful for that. And we find that Paul is explaining this allegory that is
given to us. This historical account in Genesis chapter number 21 has this
wonderful, powerful spiritual application that is unfolded to us in Galatians
chapter number 4. And really, there's two aspects to this allegory. Number one is
this, there are two covenants. There's an old covenant, and there's a new covenant.
The old covenant is under Hagar, or after the flesh. You find that it says in
verse number 23, but he who was of the bondwoman was born after the flesh, but
he of the free woman was by promise. And so we see that this old
covenant, Hagar, of course he'll get into the law, we understand that no doubt
contextually, Paul has clear understanding that Abraham and Hagar
and Sarah, Ishmael and Isaac, they predate the law. We understand that. But the law
would come many years later, and it would show, it would be the revelation to the
people of God that there's no way you can keep this. It condemns. It
proves that we're guilty. And so we find here that he's showing us, he says in
verse number 24, which things are an allegory, for these are the two covenants.
The one for Mount Sinai, which gendereth to bondage, which is Hagar, and so we see
that being the flesh. And it only leads to bondage. Notice he says in verse 25,
for this Hagar is Mount Sinai in Arabian, answereth to Jerusalem which now is, and
is in bondage with her children. You know that before salvation, we're in bondage
to our sin. It's what the Word of God teaches in Romans chapter number 6, we
are bound by sin. And so we find that as we think about this old covenant that is
mentioned in this allegory that is being explained to us, that there are two
covenants, that this bondage that is mentioned, we find that it's there for us
in verses 24 and 25, we find that this old covenant, it brings death.
Ephesians chapter number 2 tells us that we were dead in our trespasses and sins
in Ephesians 2 and verse number 1. You know in Romans chapter number 8, I am so
thankful for the truth of just the fact that there is no condemnation. It says
this in Romans 8 and verse number 1, there is therefore now no condemnation
to them which are in Christ Jesus, who walk not after the flesh but after the
Spirit. But the reality is that for those that are not in Christ Jesus, there
is condemnation, right? Remember, we find that the Bible tells us and oftentimes we
quote, and rightly so, the truth of John 3, and so many people are familiar with
John 3 in verse number 16, and I'm so thankful that God did love the world. It
says, for God so loved the world that he gave his only begotten Son that whosoever
believeth in him should not perish but have everlasting life. It says, for God
sent not his Son into the world to condemn the world but that the world
through him might be saved. He that believeth on him is not condemned, verse
18, but he that believeth not is condemned already. Why? Because he hath
not believed in the name of the only begotten Son of God. Verse 36 of John 3
says, he that believeth on the Son hath everlasting life, and he that believeth
not the Son shall not see life, but the wrath of God abideth on him. I have not
ever personally used the gospel tract, but there was a gospel tract many years
ago that said something to the effect of, what do I have to do to go to hell? And
you opened it up and it said nothing. Nothing. Why? Because you're condemned
already. See, the allegory that is explained of this historical account in
Genesis 21 provides us with the understanding of this old covenant. He
says there are two covenants. The one from Mount Sinai, this old covenant, the
law, the flesh, the bondage, the death, the condemnation. But then we understand
that there's a new covenant. It says in verse 26, back in Galatians 4, but
Jerusalem which is above is free, which is the mother of us all. He said back in
verse number 23, but he who was of the bondwoman was born after the flesh, but
then notice, he of the free woman was by promise. He then says this in verse 28,
now we brethren, as Isaac was, are the children of promise. Now remember, we
looked at this last week as we looked at the first seven verses of Genesis 21,
this promise that had been made. I mentioned it by way of introduction this
evening. For 25 years before the promise was fulfilled, I mean from the time the
first giving of the promise to Abraham with regard to, I will give you a land
and I will give you a seed. And we find that God kept his word, but it was 25
years later, but he no doubt, Isaac, is the result of this promise that God
had made. And so we see in the new covenant, it's grace. It's grace. We find
it in the new covenant, it's freedom. As is mentioned in verse 26, that Jerusalem
which is above is free. Notice what he says in verse number 31, so then brethren,
Brethren, we are not children of the bondwoman, but of the free.
The truth shall make you free.
Right?
Remember, Jesus, as He makes that declaration, He's speaking to those Jews and they're saying,
we've not been in bondage to anybody.
They were in bondage at the time that they said that.
I mean, just look around and you can see the Romans all over the place, right?
I mean, that was what was going on.
No doubt, you don't have to go far into their history to see about the Babylonian captivity
and the Assyrian captivity and so on and so forth.
And certainly they had been in captivity, they'd been in bondage, and Jesus is making
this truth, of course, with regard to the freedom from sin, the power of sin, the bondage
of sin.
And so we find that this new covenant, as we look at this allegory and it provides this
truth of these two covenants and it being of grace and providing freedom, we understand
the life.
The Bible says that the wage of sin is death, but the gift of God is eternal life through
Jesus Christ our Lord.
I'm thankful for the life.
Remember what Jesus said in John chapter number 10, I've come to give them life, and He says
this, that they would have it more abundantly.
The abundant life through the Lord Jesus Christ.
The grace that He provides, we mentioned this morning about being forgiven, and we
find that this new covenant allows us to understand our acceptance.
It's a wonderful thing to be accepted by God, to know that we're accepted in the Beloved,
to know that we are the people of God, the children of God, that we are joint heirs with
Jesus Christ.
It's grace.
And so as we look at the truth that's given here, we find no doubt that there can be no
mixture of law and grace.
It will not work.
Law and grace cannot, they can't mix, it doesn't work.
He says in verse number 30, nevertheless, what saith the Scripture?
Cast out the bondwoman and her son, the flesh.
Cast that out.
Why?
For the law and the flesh, he says this, for the son of the bondwoman shall not be heir
with the son of the free woman.
And so we see that the mixture of law and grace, that first covenant and that second
covenant, the old is done away, Christ fulfilled the law, and we're so thankful for that.
Remember as you look in Hebrews chapter number 10, those priests, they came daily ministering
and offering the same sacrifices.
The Bible says that could never take away sin.
You make the offering today, you've got to come back and make the offering again tomorrow.
Basically it was a constant reminder of their sin.
But this man, after he made one sacrifice for sin forever, who is this man?
It's the Lord Jesus Christ.
He fulfilled it.
That's the second, or the new covenant, the grace that is given.
And we find this allegory explained, the allegory having the first aspect of the two covenants,
but I also want you to consider this evening from this passage of Scripture, not only the
two covenants, but the two natures.
We see the contrast between Hagar and Sarah.
We see the explanation between the bondwoman and the free woman.
We see the law and the grace, the flesh and the promise.
We see that.
But then we see the two natures.
Not necessarily explained by Hagar and Sarah, but seen through Ishmael and Isaac.
We think about those two natures as we think about what's happening here in the truth that
God has given, we find that Ishmael would best represent the flesh, right?
After Abraham and Sarah, at the time, Abram and Sarai, after they'd received the promise
and they wait ten years and there's no children, they begin to rely on their own understanding.
Sarai says, hey, go in, there's Hagar, marry her, go in and have seed, and so on and so
forth, and it's the result of their leaning on their own understanding and following in
that manner the birth of Ishmael, it no doubt represents for us the flesh.
But we find that Isaac would represent the spirit.
Now, as we look at this, we find that in verse 28 and verse number 31, it's so interesting
how that the application is made directly to us as the people of God today.
He says in verse number 28, now we, brethren, he's speaking to these believers in Galatia
that have been saved, now these ones that said, or at least that they were thinking
they'd been influenced by these Judaizers, ye that desire to be under the law.
He's saying, listen, why would you want to go, that's going backwards.
Why would you want to do that?
You've already been delivered, you've already been given the deliverance from that law and
that bondage that it represents, and you've been given the freedom through grace, and
this has been preached to you, and so he says, why would you want to do this?
But then he says in verse 28, now we, brethren, as Isaac was, are the children of promise.
Now, if you take out the parenthetical, if you will, he just says, now we are the children
of promise.
We are the children of promise.
Notice what he says back in chapter number, look in verse number, chapter number three
in verse number six.
It speaks about Abraham believing God, it being accounted to him for righteousness,
but look over at verse number 13, it says this, Christ hath redeemed us from the curse
of the law being made a curse for us, for it is written, cursed is everyone that hangeth
on a tree, that the blessing of Abraham might come on the Gentiles through Jesus Christ,
that we might receive the promise of the Spirit through faith.
He then says this, and as we're looking in chapter number four, he's speaking about this
truth that we, just as Isaac was, we are the children of promise.
This truth of redemption.
We've been dealing with this in Colossians, it's really interesting how God has brought
all these things together at this same time with what we've been looking at in Colossians
3, verses 5, now through verse number 14, with regard to the put off and the put on
and all that's going on and dealing with that conflict between the flesh and the Spirit,
and so we find that Paul is making this application directly to these believers, and he's saying,
listen, we are the children of promise, notice in verse 31, so then, brethren, we are not
children of the bondwoman, but of the free.
Why?
Because we've been born again.
So we have this new nature, no longer are we under that death and condemnation, but
now there is no condemnation for them that are in Christ Jesus.
Now we have the truth of eternal life, we've been accepted in the Beloved, and so we find
that there's now this flesh and this Spirit, these two natures, and we find that he tells
us in chapter number 5, in verse number 17, for the flesh lusteth against the Spirit and
the Spirit against the flesh, and these are contrary to one to the other, so that ye cannot
do the things that ye would.
Man, it makes full circle with what we've been dealing with in Colossians, and we find
that Paul is saying to these believers here in the region of Galatia, listen, this truth
of Genesis 21, this historical account that you're perhaps familiar with, many of us are
familiar with Genesis 21.
Of course, those that were Jewish, they would have been very familiar, no doubt, with the
account in Genesis 21.
Those that were Gentiles that had been saved, maybe not the same level of knowledge of that
passage of Scripture, and thus we find that Paul is making this application, he's explaining,
he says these things are an allegory, and so therefore, what is it that the Scripture says,
what is it that we follow, how is it that we behave?
Cast out the bondwoman and her son.
Not only are we casting out the old covenant, but we're casting out the flesh.
Does that make sense tonight?
And we find that, why, why do they have to be cast out?
Because they can't coexist.
They can't coexist.
Listen, you're either walking in the flesh or you're walking in the Spirit.
It's just, it's one or the other, I mean, you're either following God and obeying Him
or you're disobeying Him.
Remember, I said that when God spoke to Abraham there in Genesis chapter number 21, after
Sarah had said what she said, after her observance of Ishmael mocking, and God says to Abraham,
hearken unto her voice.
What was her voice?
Cast him out.
He has a decision to make.
Because Ishmael and Isaac could not be in the same house.
It just wasn't going to work.
And for us as the people of God, as Paul, through the inspiration of the Holy Spirit
of God, would give us the truth here in Galatians chapter number 4, which gives us great insight
to Genesis chapter number 21, we find this evening that we have to cast out the flesh.
How did Paul say it to the believers in Colossae?
Mortify therefore your members upon the earth, right?
Colossians 3 and verse number 5.
We started that two, three weeks ago now.
And so as we look at this passage of scripture in Genesis chapter 21, the Bible's awesome
by the way, isn't it?
I mean, it's amazing.
Listen, no scriptures have any private interpretation.
The best commentary on the Bible is the Bible.
It really is.
And I'm so thankful that as you look here in Galatians chapter number 4 and you begin
to read and understand, and now we get
some insight as to what's going on. He says, "'Cast out the bondwoman and her son, for the
son of the bondwoman shall not be heir with the son of the free woman.' So then, brethren,
we are not children of the bondwoman, but of the free.'" Why? Because we've been born again.
Because we've been born again. And so therefore, we've got to deal with the flesh.
And so I'm thankful this evening that we have not only the historical account of Genesis 21,
but the spiritual application of Galatians 4. And it helps us to understand how serious this
thing is. Listen, we can try to play the game and try to think that we can have them coexist,
but it just isn't going to work. It's just not going to work. And at some point in our lives,
we're going to get so frustrated trying to do the things that we ought to do and behave the
way that we ought to behave, but still feeding the flesh and still giving to the desires of the
flesh. And it's going to come to the point in our lives where we just are just fed up and we're
frustrated. We need to just wave that white flag of surrender and say, I got to mortify my members
which are upon the earth. I have to crucify my flesh. Because the flesh is contrary to the Spirit.
These two cannot coexist. I say they cannot coexist in the fact that we're not going to be
able to please God as we're walking in the flesh. Listen, the carnal man, he is not the spiritual
man, right? Why does Paul say to the believers in Corinth, I could not speak to you as unto
spiritual, as unto mature, but as babes, as immature, as carnal. And so this evening,
as we look at this great truth and this historical account in Genesis 21,
oh, we make wonderful application with regard to what God gives us in Galatians 4, and we make
that decision that we too must cast out the bond woman and her son. We must cast out that old
covenant. I'm so thankful I'm not under the law. So thankful. And we must cast out that old nature,
the flesh. But lest we misunderstand, and I do not have time to develop all of it,
but there are some today that misapply the truth of casting out we're not under the law anymore,
and they think, oh, well, then I can live however I want to live.
Well, so just in case you had that thought, just continue reading in Galatians 5,
because verse number one says, stand fast, therefore, in the liberty wherewith Christ
hath made us free, and be not entangled again with the yoke of bondage. If you skip over to
verse number 13, he says, for brethren, ye have been called unto liberty, notice this,
only use not liberty for an occasion to the flesh, but by love serve one another.
Too often today, we live in a time in which there are people that have peddled this idea
that we can live however we want to live because we're no longer under the law.
That's not true. Now, you may be able to live however you want to live,
but there are consequences for it. Amen? There are consequences for it. He says,
only use not liberty for an occasion to the flesh. You know, truly, our freedom in Christ
and our liberty that we have in Christ is a freedom and a liberty that allows us to serve Him.
That's what it is. It gives us that opportunity to serve Him and to walk with Him and to do all
that He's called us to do. It's not a freedom or a liberty that says, hey, man, I can do what I
want to do because I'm going to heaven when I die. If that's the approach, then we've grossly
misunderstood and misinterpreted what God tells us in His Word because He says that we're to
mortify our members upon the earth, we're to crucify the old man, we're to walk in the Spirit
so that we do not fulfill the lust of the flesh. Your flesh has desire. All of our flesh has desire,
has an appetite. The Bible tells us the flesh is contrary to the Spirit. And so, this evening,
we have to cast out. We have to understand that we're under that new covenant and that the flesh
and the Spirit are not going to be able to coexist. And so, therefore, we must crucify the
old man. What great truth that God gives us in Galatians 4 that helps us understand clearly
what happens back in Genesis 21. Next week, we'll continue with Genesis 21. Actually,
next week, we've got a missionary. And so, he'll be preaching in the evening. And so,
we'll be off from Genesis next week, but we look forward to finishing up Genesis 21.
Let's go to the Lord in prayer. Father, we love You, and we thank You for loving us. Thank You
for the content that You've given us in Your Word with regard to this account and this time in the
life of Abraham and Sarah. And we see the conflict there between Sarah and Hagar and between Ishmael
and Isaac. And God, we thank You for the spiritual insight, the application that is provided to us in
Galatians 4. And I'm so thankful to be born again. I'm so thankful to be saved. And God,
I pray that You'd help me to understand this allegory and help each of us to understand this
evening this, not only the two covenants, but the two natures and the flesh and the Spirit.
And God, I pray that even as we've heard many times in recent weeks, that You would help us to
walk in the Spirit so that we would not fulfill the lust of the flesh. Would You help us to
mortify our members which are upon the earth? Would You help us to live that crucified life?
Would You work in hearts and lives as only You can? We'll give You the glory for every
decision that's made. For it's in Christ's name we pray. Would You stand with us?