Continue, amen, continue, don't give up,
don't throw in the towel, continue.
And we have a great cause, we have a great savior,
and we are on the winning side, amen.
Continue, continue.
First Thessalonians chapter number five this evening.
This is our 15th lesson through this portion of scripture.
I've titled the series Walk Worthy, Please God.
And here on Wednesday evenings,
we've had the opportunity to go through this bullet point
if you will, type of instruction
that begins in verse number 12
and goes through the end of the chapter.
We do find that some of these verses
we'll look at in the next few weeks
have some greetings and so on and so forth.
We find that in second Thessalonians chapter number three,
there's also some similar type of instruction
at the end of the book.
And so once we finish here
in the fifth chapter of first Thessalonians,
we will go over to the third chapter of second Thessalonians
and continue our study of Walk Worthy, Please God.
I hope that your heart's desire is to please the Lord.
I hope that you desire in your life
that I want my life to count for Christ
and I want Christ to be pleased with me.
You know, it's interesting,
in the book of first Corinthians in the 10th chapter,
you read that God tells us
of the children of Israel in the Old Testament
that with many of them, God was not well pleased.
That's a statement of scripture that really frightens me
because I would not want it to be said of me
or of us corporately as a church
that God is not well pleased with us.
I want God to be pleased with me.
I hope that you have that same desire
and corporately as a church,
we desire God's blessing upon us.
We find that as we look at this passage of scripture,
the instruction that's been given as we've gone through it,
I've mentioned often that it's concise instruction,
it's bullet point type instruction.
And we find that with each of the pieces of instruction
that God gives us, there's a response of the hearer.
We often say that we ought to be doers of the word
and not hearers only.
And so this instruction is given to us
not so that we can answer a quiz question,
not so that we can say that we have,
no, it's so that we would apply it in our lives,
that we would be doers of the word and not hearers only.
Why do I say that?
Because we come to verse 23,
the verse that we'll be studying this evening,
and the subject matter that is before us
is that really of sanctification.
And I believe that as you look at the passage of scripture,
verses 12 down through verse 22,
that as God is giving all of this instruction,
it's pointing to this is the process,
if you will, of sanctification.
Now, it's interesting to me,
the subject of salvation is often discussed,
as it should be, amen?
I'm thankful to be saved by the grace of God, aren't you?
I'm thankful to know Christ as my savior, I'm heaven bound.
I'm thankful that I can have confidence.
I spoke about that on Sunday evening, and what a blessing.
And I'm so thankful for the subject of salvation
that we can regularly discuss the truth of God's salvation
and how we can be saved and know that we're saved
and how shall we escape if we neglect so great salvation,
the writer of Hebrews says,
and no doubt it's a precious subject.
But I would say to you this evening
that the subject of sanctification
is also of significant importance.
I would say that the subject of sanctification
must be understood,
but it's not one that we speak about maybe as often
as we speak about salvation.
God saved you, if you're saved this evening,
God saved you by his grace.
And as a new creature, we are to be sanctified.
Now, let me explain this evening
because it's important for us to understand
the biblical aspects of the subject
that is before us this evening of sanctification.
I've titled the message simply that, sanctification.
The Bible says in verse 23,
and the very God of peace sanctify you wholly, completely.
And I pray God, your whole spirit and soul and body
be preserved blameless unto the coming
of our Lord Jesus Christ.
As we look at this verse of scripture
and begin to think about the subject matter
of sanctification, we understand that the Bible
gives us really some aspects of sanctification
that are important for us to understand.
The first aspect of sanctification
that's important for us to understand
is that of positional sanctification.
The Bible says of the believers in Corinth,
now we know some things about the church in Corinth, right?
The church in Corinth is a carnal church, do you agree?
The Bible says that Paul says to them in the third chapter,
I can't speak unto you as unto spiritual,
but as unto carnal, why?
They were immature spiritually, they were babes,
they had divisions and contentions and so on and so forth.
So they were a people in the church in Corinth
that had some carnal issues, some problems,
but you know that God refers to them as being sanctified.
In 1 Corinthians chapter number one,
if you wanna run over there very quickly,
I want you to notice that as Paul was writing
the introduction unto the inspiration of the Holy Spirit
of God to these members of the church at Corinth,
we find here that God is saying to these individuals
in verse number two, unto the church of God,
which is at Corinth, to them that are sanctified
in Christ Jesus, called to be saints,
with all that in every place,
call upon the name of Jesus Christ our Lord,
both theirs and ours.
In chapter number six, he says this in verse number 11,
he says, and such were some of you.
What's he talking about?
Well, he goes through in verse nine and 10,
we don't have time to read all of it,
but he mentions a number of wicked lifestyles
and he says, and such were some of you,
but aren't you thankful for that great conjunction?
Ye are washed, but ye are sanctified,
but ye are justified in the name of the Lord Jesus
and by the Spirit of our God.
I would say of those in Corinth,
that the reality is that there were some,
all of the believers in Corinth
were sanctified positionally.
But not every believer in Corinth
was sanctified practically.
Sometimes we use the term progressive sanctification,
this ongoing process of becoming more like Christ.
We find in the book of Ephesians,
it's a great book to study
with regard to the subject matter of sanctification.
The first three chapters of the book of Ephesians
deal specifically with our position in Christ.
In fact, you find that in Christ is used repeatedly
in those first few chapters of the book of Ephesians, why?
Because that is our position in Christ.
Then you come to chapter number four and five and six,
and you start reading this word about walk.
Now that this is your position
and we've established your position in Christ,
here is practically what it's supposed to look like.
Does that make sense?
And so we find this evening,
if we were to look at some biblical phrases
in the book of Ephesians in the fourth chapter,
the book of Colossians in the third chapter,
in both of those chapters,
there's this put off and put on
that you'll read of.
Put off these things, what are these things?
The works of the flesh.
Put on, what are these things?
The fruit of the spirit, the obedience to Christ.
And you'll see this put off, put on
that you find in those two portions of scripture.
And that's what I would refer to
as being practical or progressive sanctification.
The word sanctify is a word
that means to cleanse or purify, to make holy,
but that could be referred to a number of different things.
You look in the Old Testament,
you talk about the furniture in the tabernacle,
it was sanctified, it was set apart for a sacred use.
But I want you to understand this definition.
I thought it was a great definition
from Noah Webster's 1828.
It says this, here's how he defined the word sanctify,
to make holy by detaching the affections
from the world and its defilements
and exalting them to a supreme love to God.
I think it's a great, great definition.
To then piggyback on sanctify, then sanctification,
he says it this way,
here's how he defines it in that dictionary,
the act of God's grace,
by which the affections of men are purified
or alienated from sin and the world
and exalted to a supreme love to God.
I said at the beginning of the message
that the subject of salvation is often discussed
as it should be,
but the subject matter of sanctification
sometimes isn't discussed as often.
Can I tell you that it's missing in our churches today
this understanding of sanctification
and what God's plan, and let me say it this way,
God's will is for every child of his to be sanctified.
To be sanctified.
Some people say, man, I'm saved
and I'm going to heaven
and I can just do whatever I want to do.
I can live however I want to live.
I can just whatever because, man, I'm going to heaven.
That's not the kind of salvation I got.
Amen, I'm just being honest with you.
When I got saved, the Bible says in Christ,
he's a new creature.
Old things are passed away.
Behold, all things are become new.
Do I still have the desires of the flesh?
All of us do.
But I'll tell you what,
when you start understanding the truth of this book
and the Holy Spirit of God
who indwells every child of God works in your life,
you understand the process of sanctification.
All of a sudden, the things that you did
before you got saved,
now the Holy Spirit of God is convicting you
for doing those things after you got saved.
Why?
Because you're a new creature, amen?
And we understand this.
And listen, we have,
in our world today, this situation where
this subject of sanctification is really foreign
to Christendom.
Man, just live how you wanna live.
I mean, God understands.
Listen, God wants you to be happy.
Where did you find that in the Bible?
I mean, honestly.
I've not read, no, I understand the Bible
used the word happy, used the word blessed,
but listen, your definition of what you think
makes you happy and what God talks about
being blessed or happy are different.
Amen?
It makes me happy to live in this promiscuous lifestyle.
That's not what God meant for you.
Amen, can we agree tonight?
And so we understand, listen, to be separate
from profane things and dedicated to God.
The same Greek word in the New Testament
is often translated, the same Greek word
that's translated sanctification
is often translated holiness.
It's the same Greek word.
They're synonymous.
As you read through the scriptures,
you'll see those words, you'll see that.
Someone said this, a preacher of yesteryear,
and he said it this way.
Salvation is the miracle of a moment.
Sanctification is the process of a lifetime.
I think it's a good quote.
I'm thankful to be saved.
I'm thankful that positionally I'm sanctified.
I'm seated in the heavenlies.
I mean, positionally.
But practically, it's a process of a lifetime.
You know what it is?
It is daily abiding in Christ.
It's walking in the spirit.
You know what it is?
It's crucifying the old man with its affections
and its lust, it's understanding,
as Paul says to the believers there in Colossae,
that we're to mortify our members.
If ye then be risen with Christ,
seek those things which are above, amen.
And it's that process of sanctification.
It's yielding to God's work in your life.
It's really the subject of surrender.
As we look at this passage of Scripture
in 1 Thessalonians chapter five and verse 23,
we find that the Apostle Paul, being used of God,
gives all of this instruction.
He's giving them instruction with regard
to how they can walk worthy,
how they can please God with their lives.
And he goes through all of this,
and we've studied it now for 14 weeks,
and we've gone through all of these pieces of instruction,
and we find that we come to verse 23,
and notice what he says,
and the very God of peace,
by the way, aren't you thankful for the peace of God?
He is the God of peace, as it says here.
Sanctify you wholly.
Notice, it's the entirety of us.
It's not to separate these,
but to talk about the whole of our being.
I pray, God, your whole spirit, soul, and body
be preserved blameless
under the coming of our Lord Jesus Christ.
On Sunday morning, I preached a message
about the qualifications for pastors and for deacons,
and I made this statement
in the introduction of that message
that though that passage of Scripture specifically
is addressing the qualifications for those two offices,
that the information, the qualifications listed therein
are really what every child of God should attain to be.
Amen?
It's not that we attain to be that
so that we can hold an office.
No, it's that that's what we should desire to be.
We should desire that what is said in those qualifications
would be true of every one of us.
Why? Because we're a child of God.
As we look at this passage of Scripture,
and we notice the subject of sanctification,
two thoughts for you this evening.
Number one, there is an example.
Number one, there's an example.
The greatest example in every area,
any area of your life or my life is the Lord Jesus Christ.
We're gonna deal with that last in this particular point
because the reality is that sometimes
as I've had interactions with people over the years,
and I've shown, listen, Peter says in 1 Peter
that Christ left us an example
that we should follow his steps.
But some would argue, well, he's God, he's perfect,
and I just can't attain to that, okay?
And I understand the argument,
but God is, he has given us an example
that we should follow his steps,
and the best example that we could ever go to in Scripture
is the Lord Jesus Christ.
But I find that even in the text of Scripture
that in here as we think about there's an example
that the apostle Paul was an example
of the truth that he's setting forth.
Notice what the Bible says a few chapters before
to the same that he's writing to
in 1 Thessalonians chapter two.
Notice what the Bible says.
In 1 Thessalonians chapter two, of course,
Paul was used of the Lord
during the second missionary journey
to see this church at Thessalonica established.
God allowed him, God called him, God equipped him,
and this church is established.
As best we can tell as you read through the book of Acts,
it was a short period of time that Paul was in Thessalonica.
They ran him out of town just as they did
in previous places where he ministered,
and we find that he's not there long,
but there's a church established.
Paul, as we mentioned at the very beginning
of our study here, he was yearning for these individuals,
concerned for them of how they're doing,
and notice what he says in the second chapter
in verse number 10.
He says, ye are witnesses.
Not only were they the members of the church
that he's writing to, but he says, and God also.
How wholly and justly and unblameably
we behaved ourselves among you that believe.
As ye know how we exhorted and comforted
and charged every one of you as a father doth his children
that ye would walk worthy of God
who hath called you unto his kingdom and glory.
Paul was not simply preaching a message
to a church about sanctification
that he himself was not applying in his own life.
That's important.
You've heard people say, I've said it
from the pulpit plenty of times,
the message of your lips is more powerful than the,
or excuse me, the message of your life is more powerful
than the message of your lips.
What you do is much more impactful than what you say.
You can say whatever you wanna say.
That's why Paul said when he was writing
to the believers in Philippi,
the things that you've heard,
but he says, and seen in me, do.
He didn't just preach a message, he lived a message.
In fact, he says it this way to the believers in Corinth
in 1 Corinthians 11, one, you don't need to turn there,
but he tells them to be followers of him,
but it's based upon the fact that he is a follower of God.
That's important.
You don't blindly follow someone
unless you know that that someone is following God.
Paul says this in 2 Timothy 3 in verse number 10,
again, with regard to his example,
he says, and we don't have time to look through all of it,
but he's talking about the last days
and the perilous times, and he's going through
and he's giving some examples,
and he comes to verse number 10,
and he says this, but thou hast fully known my doctrine,
but then notice what he says, matter of life.
You better know the doctrine of the spiritual leader,
but he says, you've not only known my doctrine,
but my matter of life.
Paul understood the importance of sanctification.
He understood that it was important that,
listen, he's the one that writes,
I am crucified with Christ, I die daily,
walk in the spirit so that you would not
fulfill the lust of the flesh.
He's living that, and he says that you have
fully known my doctrine, matter of life,
purpose, faith, long-suffering, charity,
patience, persecutions, afflictions,
which came unto me at Antioch, at Iconium,
at Lystra, what persecutions I endured,
but out of them all the Lord delivered me.
Hallelujah.
Paul says you've known.
See, Paul was an example as he writes to these believers
in Thessalonica about the importance of sanctification.
We understand that Paul was an example.
The greatest example, of course, the Lord Jesus Christ.
I mentioned that at the very beginning.
The Bible tells us that the just for the unjust,
there's no guile found in him.
He's perfect, he's sinless, he did the will of the Father.
We understand, the Bible says,
God says in the book of Leviticus,
we read it again in the book of 1 Peter,
that we are to be holy, why?
Because he is holy.
In fact, look at 1 Peter chapter one,
if you will, in verses 13 through 16,
and notice what the Bible says with regard
to this matter of holiness or sanctification.
Notice, Peter says in verse number 13,
1 Peter one and verse 13,
wherefore, gird up the loins of your mind,
be sober and hope to the end for the grace
that is to be brought unto you
at the revelation of Jesus Christ.
As obedient children,
not fashioning yourselves according to the former lust
in your ignorance,
but as he which hath called you is holy,
so be ye holy in all manner of conversation,
because it is written, be holy for I am holy.
What a great charge, what a great piece of instruction
with regard to holiness and sanctification.
And we understand again that there were false teachers
during the time of the writing of the New Testament,
and we understand that the false teacher
still exists to this very day,
and they would deny the truth of God's word,
and we find that they would creep in
and they would deny the grace,
they would turn.
excuse me, the grace of God into lasciviousness,
according to the book of Jude.
Unbridled lust.
Listen, you can find today, antinomianism is popular.
You can read of it.
Just, man, you're saved by grace.
You do what you wanna do.
We're not under the law.
Look, I'm glad that we're not under the law.
Christ fulfilled the law.
But I said this a few weeks ago.
The standard is actually higher.
In the Old Testament, remember, he said, do no evil.
But we come to 1 Thessalonians 5.22,
and he says, abstain from all appearance of evil.
It doesn't mean that we should engage in evil.
We understand the instruction to do no evil still stands,
but he takes it to a higher plane,
and he says, not only are you to do no evil,
but you're to abstain from all appearance of evil.
Wow.
There's an example.
Paul was not perfect.
He was a man like you and like me.
He was a human being.
There are times in which I've heard people say,
man, I wanna be used like Paul.
You better read what Paul did
in order to be used the way that he was used.
He was surrendered, he was yielded,
he was crucified with Christ.
He was a man that was fully surrendered to God,
and therefore God used him in the manner in which he did.
We can read of other missionaries
and preachers of yesteryear that God used in a great way.
God is no respecter of persons.
God will use you if you're usable.
Understand God doesn't use dirty vessels.
We're to be sanctified and meet for the master's use.
Sanctification is important.
Doesn't matter, man, just,
remember the girl that was saying
these are the servants of the Lord
that tell us about the way of salvation,
and Paul rebuked and caused that demon,
was it a right message?
It was the right message.
They were the servants of the most high God,
and they were speaking the way of salvation.
It was the right message, it was just the wrong vessel.
Amen.
So notice there's an example,
but notice number two, there's an expectation.
There's an expectation.
I believe that God expects for his children
to walk as children of light.
God expects for us to allow his word
and the Holy Spirit of God to work in us
and to conform us to the image of Jesus Christ,
his dear son.
In fact, Romans 8 and verse 29 tells us that very thing,
that this is really the understanding of the Christian life.
We often read verse 28, I mentioned on Sunday night,
and we know that all things work together for good
to them that love God,
to them who are the called according to his purpose.
Verse 29 says, for whom he did foreknow,
he also did predestinate to what?
To be conformed to the image of his son,
that he might be the firstborn among many brethren.
We find that as you continue to read,
and even as you think about the truth
of the book of Romans,
if you were to back up into the sixth chapter
and talk about how you were the servants of sin,
but now you're the servants of righteousness,
you can read in verse 19 and then again in verse 22
about the truth of holiness, fruits unto holiness.
Guess what that word is?
It's sanctification, it's the same word.
And we find this evening that there's been this change,
salvation brings this change, we're a new creature.
Listen, I'm thankful that Christianity,
the gospel, is not just about reformation.
It's about transformation.
Transformation, it's radical.
I'm a new creature in Christ.
Listen, I don't think like I used to think.
We shouldn't, why?
Because we had a worldview that was a void of God.
And there's a radical change
in this transforming gospel of Jesus Christ.
And his expectation is that his people
would be conformed to the image of his son,
that we'd be like Jesus.
Why did they call them Christians first at Antioch?
Well, they called them Christians
because they were like Christ.
A well-known leader of a former, another religion
said of Christians, I like your Christ,
but I don't like your Christians
because your Christians are nothing like your Christ.
What an indictment.
Because we're to be like Christ.
Notice what the Bible says in 1 Thessalonians chapter four.
We kept within this book to look at the example
of the apostle Paul when he talked about their behavior,
their own sanctification in chapter two.
But now look at what the Bible says in chapter four
with regard to this charge that he gives.
Notice in verse number one,
furthermore then we beseech you brethren
and exhort you by the Lord Jesus
that as you have received of us,
notice this phrase, how ye ought to walk and to please God
so ye would abound more and more.
It wasn't enough for them just to have the instruction.
They had to do something with it.
It's not enough for someone to just know about Jesus.
They got to accept him as their personal savior.
The conversation with someone recently
and I was talking about the Lord
and I asked her about heaven and I'm like,
oh yeah, man, I grew up in and he kind of went
on this whole rabbit trail of where he grew up
and the times he used to have
and he doesn't go to church anymore,
but I talk to God all the time and I cuss with God
and I do this with God and God seems to be okay with it.
And I'm like, I don't know what God you're talking to,
but that's not my God, amen?
What happened when Isaiah saw the glory of God?
He fell to his face.
My God, your God is a holy God.
We find that he says that you would abound more and more.
Look at verse two, for ye know what commandments
we gave you by the Lord Jesus.
Verse number three, for this,
you might want to underline this,
for this is the will of God,
even your sanctification,
that ye should abstain from fornication,
that every one of you should know how to possess his vessel
in sanctification and honor.
For God, skip down to verse number seven, if you will,
for God hath not called us unto uncleanness,
but unto holiness.
Praise the Lord.
And listen, here's the amazing thing.
It's not a work that you can do.
It's a work that God does in you.
As you yield yourself to him, as you get into this word,
as you hear the teaching and preaching of God's word,
as you apply the teaching and preaching of God's word,
God is doing this work.
Notice he says, and the very God of peace
sanctify you wholly.
I can't make myself sanctified,
but God working in me causes me to be sanctified.
It's amazing as we yield ourselves to him.
We find that, as I mentioned a moment ago,
and if you were to have the opportunity,
we're out of time this evening,
but if you look back to 1 Corinthians chapter six
and verses 19 and 20, what know ye not,
that your bodies are the temple of the Holy Ghost,
which is in you, which you have of God.
And we understand we're to glorify God
in our body and our spirit,
which are his, why we're bought with a price,
and we understand that truth.
And I said this in the beginning this evening,
but all the believers in Corinth,
positionally speaking, they were sanctified.
However, many of the believers in Corinth
were not practically sanctified.
They were carnal.
They were living how they wanted to live,
doing what they wanted to do.
I believe that even as we look at this truth
with regard to the church in Corinth,
Christendom, broadly speaking, is still guilty.
If you've truly been saved by the grace of God,
you're positionally sanctified.
But there are a lot of people that are living
like they're not saved.
I said this a while ago from the pulpit.
We're talking about praying for leaders.
Sometimes we have the expectation
that lost people are gonna act like saved people,
when it's hard enough to get saved people
to act like saved people.
Why in the world would we think that a lost person
is gonna act like a saved person?
Why would you think a lost person's gonna believe
the truth of the Bible that you believe?
They're lost.
The Bible tells us that the natural man
receiveth not the things of the Spirit of God,
for they're foolishness unto him,
neither can he know them
because they're spiritually discerned.
In 1 Corinthians chapter two.
As we look at this verse of Scripture
and we see the importance of sanctification,
as we reference once again that quote
from the preacher of yesteryear,
salvation is the miracle of the moment,
but sanctification is the process of a lifetime.
How much are we like Christ?
How much are we allowing the Holy Spirit of God
to conform us to the image of his dear Son?
See, what we understand as Christians
is that first and foremost, my identity is in Christ.
My identity is in Christ, first and foremost.
And when we understand that
and we understand that our citizenship is in heaven,
this world is not my home,
I'm just a passing through, as the songwriter said,
and we're to be like Christ.
We're not to be conformed to this world.
We see that in Romans chapter 12 in verse number one and two.
I beseech you therefore, brethren,
by the power vested in me by the Father and the Son
and the Holy Spirit, amen.
Amen.
the mercies of God that you present your body as a living sacrifice, holy, acceptable unto
God, which is your reasonable service.
And be not conformed to this world, but be ye transformed by the renewing of your mind."
How does that happen?
Listen, you had a worldview, I had a worldview that was contrary to the biblical worldview.
One of the greatest problems we have in America today is that we think that the worldview
out there, that we can adopt part of that worldview.
It's contrary, it's contrary.
As we look back in 1 Thessalonians 5 verse 23, we see the truth of sanctification, but
I'm also interested in seeing what Paul says to these believers, and very quickly you notice
that Paul says, I pray God your whole spirit and soul and body, and we see that Paul was
praying for them and what a valid thing to understand the power of prayer and the importance
of intercession and being involved in intercessory prayer.
But notice what he says, that you would be preserved, that you would be preserved blameless
unto the coming of our Lord Jesus Christ.
He reminds them, not only that he's praying for them, but he reminds them once again of
the truth that Jesus is coming again.
In fact, as you read through 1 Thessalonians, you see every chapter, 2 Thessalonians, the
same thing, in every chapter there's a reference to the return of Christ, and it's a theme
of both of these books.
There was some false teaching that was affecting them as it's dealt with in the second book
with regard to the day of the Lord, and it's set forth and straightened out because there
were some that were led astray.
They were given a counterfeit letter as if it came from Paul, and Paul instructs and
corrects.
You look at 2 Thessalonians 2 and you see specifically that being dealt with.
But when we understand unto the coming of the Lord Jesus Christ and the imminent return
of Christ, and we understand that John says, in the book of 1 John, that we would not be
ashamed of him at his appearing.
Then as you enter into the next portion of that scripture, that's at the end of chapter
2 of the book of 1 John, you get into chapter number 3, behold what manner of love the Father
hath bestowed upon us that we should be called the sons of God.
But then it talks about the truth there with regard to the coming of the Lord, and it says
this in chapter number 3, in verse number 3, talking about verse 2, when he shall appear,
but verse 3, and every man that hath this hope in him purifieth himself even as he is
pure.
Ephesians chapter number 5 talks about the church being presented, and obviously it's
talking about the members of the church being presented.
In fact, he says this in verse 26, that he might sanctify and cleanse it, the church,
with the washing of water by the word, that he might present it to himself a glorious
church, not having spot or wrinkle or any such thing, but that it should be holy and
without blemish.
There's an expectation that God's people would be sanctified.
We'd be serious about this thing of living for Christ.
Living for Jesus, we sing the song.
I want to be like Christ, and we make the statement.
This evening, sanctification, there's an example, there's an expectation.
How is our journey with Christ?
The believers in Hebrews, they're corrected for the fact that at the time they ought to
be teachers, they were in need that someone teach them.
The people in Corinth, their position practically, their practice did not align with their position.
Positionally sanctified, but practically they were carnal.
I hope that it would be said of us that we are seeking to walk worthy and please God,
that we're letting God have his way in and through our lives, that we would be sanctified.
As I mentioned, 2 Timothy, and meet for the master's use.
It would be a vessel that's clean and pure, and that God can use us for his honor and
for his glory.
Let's pray.
Father, we love you.
We thank you for loving us.
Thank you for the opportunity to study your Word tonight.
I pray, God, that you'd bless, help us, Lord, to draw closer to thee.
Help us to allow your Spirit to work in our lives, to have your will and way.
Help us to be doers of the Word and not hearers only.
Help us to walk as we ought to walk.
I pray that you'd bless our time of prayer.
We thank you for the privilege.
We give you the honor and glory for all that you'll do for us in Christ's name we pray.
Amen.