this evening, Matthew 15. I'm going to take a couple of verses of Scripture here from
this 15th chapter of the book of Matthew and look at these verses and then we're going
to spend much time in various portions of the Word of God this evening. And the Bible
speaks often about the heart of man. And we find that throughout the Scriptures there
are many references to the heart of man. In fact, we find many descriptive terms that
are used in order to address the heart of man. In our text of Scripture here in Matthew
15 in verse number 18, the Bible says, but those things which proceed out of the mouth
come forth from the heart and they defile the man. Now, you understand that as we look
through the passage of Scripture here that Jesus is speaking to these religious leaders
and they make a statement in verse number two. It says, why do thy disciples transgress
the tradition of the elders for they wash not their hands when they eat bread? How many
of you heard your parents say, wash your hands before you eat, right? And these religious
leaders, they're saying, hey, you're disciples, they're not washing their hands and so on
and so forth. And we see that the Lord begins to deal with them on the heart of the matter.
He starts discussing their heart and he goes through and he tells them various things.
He tells them in verse number, let's just pick it in verse number five, but you say,
whosoever shall say to his father, his mother, it is a gift by whatsoever thou mightest be
profited by me and honor not his father, his mother, he shall be free. Thus have you made
the commandment of God of none effect. How? By your tradition, ye hypocrites. Well, did
Isaiah the prophet say, or Isaiah prophesy of you saying this people draw nigh unto me
with their mouth and honoreth me with their lips. Notice this, but their heart is far
from me, but in vain they do worship me teaching for doctrines, the commandments of men. He
called the multitude and said unto them, hear and understand. We find that as Jesus
is teaching them, he says in verse number 13, but he answered and said, every plant
which my heavenly father hath not planted shall be rooted up. Let them alone, they be
blind leaders of the blind. And if the blind lead the blind, both shall fall into the ditch.
Then answered Peter and said unto him, declare unto us this parable. And Jesus said, are
you also yet without understanding? Do not ye yet understand that whatsoever entereth
in at the mouth goeth into the belly and is cast out into the drought. But those things
which proceed out of the mouth come forth from the heart and they defile the man. Notice
verse 19 for out of the heart proceed evil thoughts, murders, adulteries, fornications,
thefts, false witnesses, blasphemies. These are the things which defile a man. But to
eat with unwashing hands defileth not a man. Every young boy's favorite verse of scripture.
But look, as we look at the passage of scripture and we understand what Jesus is saying here
and as he's dealing with the heart of the matter, we find that it's interesting how
that we noticed the instruction of the Lord Jesus Christ and we couple it with what the
proverb declares in Proverbs four and verse number 23, the Bible says, keep thy heart
with all diligence. For out of it, out of the heart, what does the Bible say? Are the
issues of life, right? And so for out of it are the issues of life. And so we think about
keeping my heart with all diligence and the important aspect as we find here, I've often
said as I've interacted with people over the years that this is a heart issue. This is
a heart issue. I've had times in which I've spoken to individuals and they've shared things
with me that I would never repeat things of just gross immorality of just things that
they've been involved with and so on and so forth. And I've tried to explain to them that
there's a heart issue and they need in this particular or in these situations, what they
really need is salvation. Begin to deal with that. But see, they can go somewhere and they
can find someone that will diagnose them with some type of a situation and they just go
ahead and they just say, well, then this is just, I'm addicted to this, that or the other
because someone will say that. And I say, no, no, it's a heart issue. It's a heart issue.
And we find here that in the text of scripture that Jesus says out of the heart proceed.
Now, we are going to look at these things here in just a moment, but I want you to understand
that as we notice these verses of scripture here in Matthew 15, Proverbs 4 and verse 23,
it's very easy for us to look at a number of other verses of scripture that deal with
the heart and we can easily conclude that God is not speaking about the organ that beats
in my chest. Amen? That's what he's talking about. We find that as it would be a heart
can be defined by Webster in the 1828 Webster's dictionary, that what he's speaking of is
the seat of the affections and passions as of love, joy, grief, enmity, courage, pleasures,
et cetera. So we find that the scriptures, that's what's being referred to when he speaks
of the heart. This evening as we look at some Bible truth, I want to preach a message that
I've titled the heart of the matter. I said to you this morning, it is not something that
I coined as a phrase, but someone wisely said, the heart of the matter is a matter of the
heart. I tried to look that up to find out exactly who it was that said it and I found
some conflicting things. I had a Bible college professor that said, if you can't find out
who said it, just claim it that you said it. I don't think that's really good advice and
so I won't make that claim this evening because someone said it well before I was ever born.
But the reality is that what was said in that statement is so vitally true. You know the
reality is that as we think about that truth in Proverbs 4 and verse number 23, when the
wise man noted, keep thy heart with all diligence for out of it are the issues of life, we each
would conclude that there are many issues of life. Many things, problems. We spoke this
morning about the fact that our God is greater than any problem that we ever will face. And
does it matter if that problem is a personal problem or a global problem, our God is greater.
I'm thankful that while all those men were looking at the stature and the size and the
strength of Goliath, that David was almost just not even affected by it. Why? Because
he was so focused on his God. I know how that we would have that same perspective.
We find that there are many problems in our society. It's not hard for us to identify
problems that we see within our society. The problem is coming to the root of the problem.
The issue that we deal with in our society is how so many problems are going on and so
many issues that are raging in our society and the way in which people want to categorize
those problems or describe those problems and the solutions that would sought to be
given for those problems, they're avoiding the root of the problem. It's a hard issue.
It's a hard issue. And we find that there's a heart problem in our society. You say, Pastor,
how can you so boldly say there's a heart problem in our society? Because Jesus said
it. Notice again in our text of Scripture here in Matthew 15, I want you to look and
it's interesting, there are seven items that are mentioned here specifically that Jesus
deals with that these are those things which proceed out of the heart. Notice he says for
out of the heart proceed, number one, evil thoughts. Evil thoughts. We spent some time
not long ago in a message dealing with the truth of Philippians 4.8. What it is that
we're to think on. And we look at that passage of Scripture and we see the way in which those
thoughts are described and Paul concludes the verse by saying think on these things.
Well here we find that Jesus says that what proceed out of the mouth, the number one thing
he says for out of the heart proceed, I said mouth, excuse me, for out of the heart proceed
evil thoughts. Notice number two, murders. Murders. There's a lot of murder in our world.
Yeah? I read recently that in Chicago you're more likely to get shot than you are in Afghanistan.
That's sad. That's ridiculous. Amen? Twenty month old was shot yesterday and killed in
Chicago, drive-by shooting. And here's what they said, when is it going to stop? Almost
every weekend of this year there's been over 100 shootings in Chicago. I know we don't
live in Chicago. But murders? Yeah, we see it. Notice, adulteries. Yeah, it's a heart
issue. It's a heart issue. Fornications. Thefts.
False witness.
Blasphemies.
Blasphemies, often we think about
the word blasphemy and its relation to God
and dealing with the fact that we would
speak of the Lord in terms of impious irreverence.
We find here that this list that is provided
seven things that the Lord says
out of the heart proceed.
Evil thoughts, murders, adulteries,
fornications, thefts, false witness,
and blasphemies.
In just a little while, we'll go to Galatians
and notice how the Bible describes
the works of the flesh.
In that passage of Scripture,
there are 19 things that are mentioned.
The works of the flesh.
See, I want you to consider with me this evening,
take your Bible, go all the way back
to the book of Genesis.
I told you we'd go through some things.
And listen, I understand we could spend
a lot of time looking at a whole lot of things.
But I'm going to try to just go through
a few references this evening
to help you to understand that the heart
of the matter is a matter of the heart.
It's a heart issue.
We're dealing with a society.
Listen, we understand theologically
that man is not basically good.
Right?
The world wants to say,
oh man, they're basically good.
No.
There's none good.
No, not one.
You say, that's so harsh.
No, it's just Bible.
Amen?
It's just Bible.
There's none good.
No, not one.
Right?
All of your good works, Isaiah said,
it's like filthy rags.
Right?
And we find that, listen,
within the heart of man,
I mean, when we're born,
because of the sin that's recorded
in Genesis chapter number three,
sin entered into the world.
We understand that through that sin,
that sin and death has passed to all men,
apart from the Lord Jesus Christ,
because he's virgin born.
Amen?
Someone said, by the way,
something came across my desk this week.
Does the virgin birth of Christ really matter?
Absolutely it matters.
You've got to be kidding me.
From a church that says
that they're a Baptist church.
Anyway, I'm not preaching on that tonight.
Don't know why it came up.
All right?
But listen, the reality this evening
is that when we look at these subject matters
and we understand, listen,
man is not basically good.
What was going on in the book of Judges?
Every man did that was right in his own sight.
Right?
In his own eyes.
He became his own authority.
And here's the huge problem
that we deal with in our society today
that no one wants to address, by the way,
because we really don't want to deal with the truth.
But what we have done
is we have systematically removed God
from our culture.
And as we systematically remove God from our culture,
it really is following the pattern
of Romans chapter number one.
Right?
We don't want to have God.
We don't want God.
Why?
Because I don't want to be accountable to God.
And if I remove God,
somehow in my warped idea
that the God of this world, Satan,
has blinded the minds of them that believe not.
They come to this place.
They try to remove God.
Look at all of the attack on the record of Genesis.
Creation and the fall of man
and the flood and all of those things.
It's attacked, attacked, attacked.
Why?
We're trying to remove God.
And to remove God from society,
somebody or something has to be the authority.
And what happens is I become my own authority.
And we see that in the book of Judges.
In fact, the Bible says it this way
as the book of Judges is summarized.
In the very last chapter of the book,
in the very last verse,
here in Judges chapter number 21 and verse number 25,
in those days, there was no king in Israel.
Every man did that which was right in his own eyes.
There was no authority.
There was no king.
They did what was right in their own eyes.
See, the reality is that man is not basically good.
He is born a sinner, separated from God.
Amen?
We believe that biblically.
And therefore, we have a situation
with the sin of mankind that needs to be addressed.
And the only remedy, as we'll get to at the end of our message this evening,
is the blood of Jesus Christ.
It's the only cure for the problem.
And we find here, all the way back in Genesis chapter number 4,
I'll ask you some questions.
What was the first murder in human history?
We know.
Cain and Abel, right?
It's here in Genesis chapter number 4.
The first murder in human history.
What did Jesus say?
What was it that proceed out of the heart?
Evil thoughts.
Murders.
Right?
Now, notice in Genesis chapter number 4,
the Bible tells us in verse number 8,
and Cain talked with Abel as his brother.
His brother.
Amen?
It says this,
and it came to pass when they were in the field,
that Cain rose up against Abel,
his brother,
and slew him.
Two times in that verse of Scripture the Bible reminds us
that it's his brother.
Flesh and blood.
Brother.
What was it in Cain?
It's a heart issue.
Somehow or another, in his mind, he thought,
because of the offerings that were brought,
and the way in which his offering was not respected or received,
he then had anger towards his brother.
God plainly said to Cain,
Why art thou wroth?
He says,
Why is thy countenance fallen, if thou doest well?
Shalt thou not be accepted?
You can read it in verse number 7.
What is God saying to him?
If you come the right way,
if you come the prescribed way,
you'll be accepted.
But instead he just got angry.
And because of his heart,
he killed his brother.
God appears to him and says,
Where is Abel, thy brother?
Am I my brother's keeper?
Right? Is that what it says?
Yeah.
What was the problem with Cain?
Heart problem.
It was his brother.
Killed him.
Look over, if you will, in Genesis 6.
Let me ask you this.
How did God describe mankind before the flood
that's recorded here in Genesis 6-8?
Well, God said this,
in verse number 5 of Genesis 6,
And God saw that the wickedness of man was great in the earth,
that every imagination of the thoughts of his, what?
His heart,
was only evil continually.
It says in verse number 11,
the earth also was corrupt before God,
and the earth was filled with violence.
The Bible doesn't describe for us in complete detail
every single thing that was happening in these days prior to the flood,
but we understand even as Jesus would reference it in Matthew chapter 25,
we understand that the wickedness upon the earth
and the earth being filled with violence,
that it was at a point in which God brought divine judgment.
But we see that the Bible tells us in verse number 5 that
every imagination of the thoughts of his heart
was only evil continually.
Let me ask you this question as we kind of fast forward here
a number of generations and think about King David.
What were the two sins of King David as they're recorded in 2 Samuel chapter 11?
Adultery and murder.
What was the list?
What proceeds out of the heart?
Evil thoughts, murders, adulteries.
King David was guilty of two of the first three that are mentioned.
By the way, it all started with his look and his thoughts, right?
In fact, it's interesting to note that in 2 Samuel chapter 11,
I've often used this comparison as I think about what's going on here,
and you find that the Bible tells at the very beginning of the passage
that David tarried still at Jerusalem.
It was a time when kings went forth to battle.
David was the king, but he tarried in Jerusalem.
And he saw Bathsheba, and he inquired, he asked about her,
and he's told this,
"'Is not this Bathsheba the daughter of Eliam, the wife of Uriah the Hittite?'
Every time I read verse number 3, in fact, I have in the margin of my Bible,
the response from the servant included the fact that she was a married woman.
And the reality is that this warning that was given to the king
was something that he should have taken heed to.
But yet, he did not take heed to the warning.
His immediate response is, "'Bring her to me.'"
And we understand what happens.
We're familiar with the passage of Scripture.
He commits the transgression of adultery.
He finds that it's resulted in conception.
So what does he do?
We need to try to cover this thing up somehow.
Right?
Uriah, come back from the battle.
He tries to get Uriah to go home.
Uriah demonstrated more integrity
in this passage of Scripture
than most other examples of integrity
that you'll find throughout the Scriptures.
What a great level of integrity.
David went through a number of iterations
of trying to get Uriah to go home.
And eventually, David writes a letter
and hands that letter to Uriah
that contained his death sentence.
Yeah? Am I telling it right?
Do I need to read it all?
That's it.
Takes it to Joab, right?
What happens?
Joab then sends him to the place
where he knew he'd die.
And it's interesting when Joab
is going to tell the servant
to go back and to let the king know
how the battle fared,
he told him this at the end of v. 21.
Make sure you tell them,
thy servant Uriah the Hittite is dead also.
Because the news he was going to bring,
there were other casualties that were involved.
And unless the king would say,
well, didn't you know that this would happen?
I mean, you went to this place
and didn't you have this?
He said just make sure you let them know
that Uriah is dead.
And it's interesting,
when David hears that,
he says this in v. 25,
"'Let not this thing displease Thee,
for the sword devoureth one as well as another.
Make Thy battle more strong against the city
and overthrow it,
and encourage Thou him.'"
David had a heart problem.
Amen?
It's interesting to me
that one of the things that is recorded for us
in the Psalm of Confession,
turn over to Psalm 51 if you will,
one of the requests that is made
by David of course in the passage there
back in 2 Samuel,
we find that it's in chapter 12
when the Lord sends Nathan unto David.
And Nathan, the prophet, stands before him
and gives him a parable to start
and then lets him know,
thou art the man.
I'm thankful that David responded properly.
We read Psalm 51
and what a great psalm of repentance it is.
We find that he says,
"'Have mercy upon me.'"
In verse 1,
"'O God, according to Thy lovingkindness,
according unto the multitude of Thy tender mercies,
blot out my transgressions.'
Jared sang a song this morning."
What was the title of that song?
My Confession.
What a beautiful song.
I'd never heard that song before
until he started practicing it.
I'm so thankful that our God is
a loving, kind, compassionate God
who's ready to pardon and ready to forgive.
He says, "'Wash me throughly
from mine iniquity
and cleanse me from my sin.
For I acknowledge my transgressions.
My sin is ever before me.
Against Thee, Thee only have I sinned
and done this evil in Thy sight,
that Thou mightest be justified
when Thou speakest
and be clear when Thou judgest.'"
We don't have time to read the entirety of it,
but I want you to notice a specific request
that is made by David in this passage of Scripture,
this psalm of confession.
He says in verse 10,
"'Create in me a clean heart,
create in me a clean heart, O God,
and renew a right spirit within me.
Cast me not away from Thy presence
and take not Thy Holy Spirit from me.
Restore unto me the joy of Thy salvation
and uphold me with Thy free spirit.'"
If we were preaching an entire message
on this passage of Scripture,
we'd take each of these phrases apart
and deal with them.
Suffice it to say this evening
that he asks the question,
he makes the request,
create in me a clean heart, O God.
It's of interest that he says
and very important for us to understand
and as we have the entirety of the Scriptures
and we have the truth of the New Testament
and understanding the truth of eternal life,
he says, restore unto me the joy of Thy salvation.
He didn't say he needed to be saved again.
He lost his joy.
Everybody loses joy because of sin.
Sin will steal your joy.
It was D.L. Moody that said
sin will keep you from this book
or this book will keep you from sin.
The reality is that sin will steal your joy.
And David said, restore unto me
the joy of my salvation.
But before he says that,
he says, create in me a clean heart, O God.
On at least five occasions,
the exposure of Israel or really Judah in particular
during the ministry of the prophet Jeremiah,
there's many indictments against Judah
that are contained within the book of Jeremiah.
On at least five occasions
in the first several chapters of that great book,
it is said of the people of Judah
that they had an evil heart.
An evil heart.
And they were doing after the imaginations
of their evil heart.
If you were to understand and begin to study
and look at all that was taking place
during the time of Judah
on the eve of their captivity,
and you'd understand the sin and the idolatry
and the wickedness that they were involved in and engaged in,
you would see why God would indict them
by telling them that they had an evil heart.
It's interesting as you look at the book of Jeremiah
again on the eve of captivity,
and you understand what's going on,
and it's interesting if you go
and you take the truth of Jeremiah
here in chapter number two of the book,
and you think about what Jesus was dealing with
with those religious leaders back in Matthew 15.
Remember they were concerned about the washing of the hands,
eating without washing the hands and so on and so forth.
And Jesus is gonna direct them to the issue of their heart.
And he speaks about the prophecy of Isaiah,
which is extremely valid of them saying,
they draw near to me with their lips,
but their heart is far from me.
Listen, God is always concerned about your heart.
He's concerned about the heart.
We find here in the book of Jeremiah in chapter number two,
and again, we don't have time to read all of it,
but the indictment is given in verse number 11,
hath a nation changed their gods,
which are yet no gods,
but my people have changed their glory
for that which it doth not profit.
Be astonished, O ye heavens, at this,
and be horribly afraid.
Be very desolate, saith the Lord,
for my people have committed two evils.
They have forsaken me for the fountain of living waters
and hewed them out cisterns,
broken cisterns that can hold no water.
In verse 17, hast thou not procured this unto thyself
in that thou hast forsaken the Lord thy God
when He led thee by the way?
Notice verse 19, thine own wickedness shall correct thee
and thy backsliding shall reprove thee.
Know therefore and see that it is an evil thing
and bitter that thou hast forsaken the Lord thy God
and that my fear is not in thee,
saith the Lord God of hosts.
Skip down and look at verse 22.
For though thou wash thee with niter
and take thee much soap,
yet thine iniquity is marked before me,
saith the Lord God.
They couldn't just wash up and clean up
and look, no, no, they had a heart issue.
And there was nothing that could be done on the outward
that was gonna clean it up and fix it.
We understand from 1 Samuel 16, right?
Remember when Samuel goes,
he's gonna anoint the next king.
He'd been given the direction of the Lord
and God had told Samuel,
you go to the house of Jesse
and you're gonna anoint the next king, right?
Eliab is the first one that stands before him.
Surely this is he.
Is that not Samuel's response, right?
But God says, nope, not him.
Number two, number three, number four,
number five, number six.
No, no, no, no, no, no.
Jesse is there.
Samuel says, are these all your sons?
Well, there's another one.
He's out in the field.
They didn't even bring him.
What'd he say?
Send for him.
They didn't sit down until he came.
You find that there in 1 Samuel 16,
that as soon as David is coming,
that God lets Samuel know,
that's the one.
That's the one.
He's the one that you're to anoint
and he pours oil on him.
He anoints him.
It's interesting that within the text of Scripture,
right after he saw Eliab,
he looked on him and he said,
surely the Lord's anointed is before him.
But God showed Samuel a great lesson
and recorded it for us in His Word.
The Lord said unto Samuel in verse seven of 1 Samuel 16,
look not on his countenance
or on the height of his stature.
Why?
Because I have refused him.
For the Lord seeth not as man seeth.
For man looketh on the outward appearance,
but the Lord looketh on the heart.
There are two truths that we can take
from this passage of Scripture.
Number one, man can only see the outward,
so the outward is important.
We don't discount and just dismiss the outward
because when God sees the heart.
No, all other man can see is the outward, right?
So the outward's important.
But we understand that we don't make those decisions
that God makes because God looketh on the heart.
He says, you can try to clean it all up.
What are you talking about?
Jesus talked about the whited sepulchers, right?
Who are they?
They're filled with dead men's bones.
They look good on the outside, cleaned up.
Bunch of dead men's bones in there, right?
And so we find that as we look at the truth
of the Word of God and we see this.
various examples in the Old Testament
of this heart issue.
And we find that the works of the flesh,
as I mentioned a moment ago,
go over to Galatians 5, if you will.
And as you look in Galatians 5,
I want you to consider
these 19 things that are given to us
as the works of the flesh.
Now it's interesting, as we begin to see
that the Bible says the works of the flesh are manifest.
Here's how they are manifest.
Here's how they're known, right?
He goes through this list and he reveals it to us.
He says, these are the works of the flesh.
This is the natural man.
This is the wicked heart.
Remember what Paul said.
We studied through the book of Ephesians last year.
We went through the entire book in our morning services
and we preached and had the theme, be strong in the Lord.
Remember that Paul made this statement
in Ephesians chapter number two.
Stay there in Galatians.
But he said, where in time past
you walked according to the course of this world,
according to the prince of the power of the air,
the spirit that outworketh
and the children of disobedience,
among whom also we all had our conversation in time past
in the lust of our flesh,
fulfilling the desires of the flesh and of the mind
and were by nature the children of wrath, even as others.
Praise God for verse number four,
but God who is rich in mercy.
We don't have time to deal with all of Ephesians
chapter number two,
but you see the desires of the flesh, right?
Here we see the works of the flesh
as they're described to us in Galatians chapter number five.
I believe that this list that is provided to us
further proves the evil and wicked behavior of mankind
is a heart problem.
Paul starts out in verse number 16 by saying,
this I say then, walk in the spirit
and ye shall not fulfill the lust of the flesh.
We're gonna come back to that thought here
in just a few moments.
Notice it says the flesh lusteth against the spirit,
the spirit against the flesh,
and these are contrary the one to the other
so that you cannot do the things that you would.
But if you be led of the spirit, you're not under the law.
Now understand, before we get into verse number 19,
understand a very important truth
as we get into this passage.
The book of Galatians is written to whom?
It's written to the churches in the region of Galatia.
There were four churches that were planted
during the first missionary journey of the apostle Paul.
He left the church in Antioch.
He was sent out, first went to Antioch and Pisidia,
then he went to Iconium, Lystra, and Derbe.
And in those cities, churches were established.
He's now writing back to those churches.
Why?
Because there were some proselytes that came in,
there was all kinds of things going on,
excuse me, Judaizers that came in,
and these Judaizers, all the things that were going on,
legalism, so on and so forth,
and we find that here that the apostle Paul
is writing to these believers, right, these churches.
The church is, a church is made up of saved membership,
right, we believe that in order to be a member
of a local church that you have to be saved and baptized.
And so we find here that he says,
"'Walk in the Spirit, you shall not
"'fulfill the lust of the flesh.
"'The flesh lusteth against the Spirit.'"
For us this evening as saved people,
have we experienced this?
Have you experienced your flesh and your spirit
being enmity one against the other?
Have you experienced the way that Paul described it
in Romans when he said,
the things that I would, I do not,
the things that I would not, that I do,
that's the flesh and the spirit
contrary one to the other.
Have you experienced it?
Guess what?
If you're lost, you don't have the Spirit of God
living within you and you don't have that enmity.
Amen?
Amen.
The reality is that Ephesians 1
shares with us the plan of redemption
that before the foundation of the world,
God had a plan to redeem fallen mankind.
He shares with us what the price would be
for that redemption.
It's the precious blood of Jesus Christ.
And he tells us what the proof of our redemption is.
It's the Holy Spirit of God.
Amen?
We find that the Bible tells us
that we are the temple of the Holy Ghost,
which is in you.
What you have of God.
You're not your own.
You're bought with the price.
And the reality is that I have no Holy Spirit
until I get saved.
At the moment of conversion,
immediately, I didn't understand all of this
when I got saved 20 some years ago.
But at the moment of salvation,
the Holy Spirit of God indwelled me.
If you're saved this evening,
the Holy Spirit of God indwelled you.
And you have all the Holy Spirit you're ever going to get.
He doesn't have all of us,
but we have all of Him.
That's why Paul would say in there,
in the book of Ephesians,
to be filled with the Spirit.
The idea of that continual filling.
Why?
Because we get filled up of ourselves,
and we get filled up, right?
But we need to be filled with the Spirit.
We have all of Him when we're indwelled by Him.
That's the proof of our redemption.
But as we look at Galatians 5,
we have to understand something this evening
that as we look at this
and we understand these works of the flesh,
and we understand how they're going to be manifest
in the list that God's gonna give us here,
that the lost person, the unregenerate person,
they don't have the Spirit of God convicting them.
They don't have that enmity.
They just have a heart of unregenerate heart
that Ephesians chapter number two says
that they're going to simply fulfill
the lust and the desires of their flesh.
Why?
Because they're lost.
They're lost.
Galatians 5, look at the works of the flesh.
Verse number 19, it begins,
now the works of the flesh are manifest.
Which are these?
Adultery, fornication, uncleanness,
lasciviousness, idolatry, witchcraft,
hatred, variance, emulations,
wrath, strife, seditions, heresies.
Verse 21, envyings, murders,
drunkenness, revelings, and such like.
Of the witch I tell you before
as I have also told you in time past
that they which do such things
shall not inherit the kingdom of God.
Verse 22 starts with a conjunction,
but the fruit of the Spirit.
Oh, what a lovely list it is.
Amen?
The fruit of the Spirit, love, joy,
peace, longsuffering, gentleness,
goodness, faith, meekness, temperance.
Against such there is no law, right?
So we see the works of the flesh manifest.
I believe, again, as I mentioned,
that this list further proves
that the evil and wicked behavior of mankind
is a heart problem.
It was a heart problem in Genesis chapter number four.
It was a heart problem in Genesis chapter number six.
It was a heart problem in 2 Samuel chapter number 11.
It was a heart problem throughout the book of Judges.
A heart problem, I mean, we could go on
all sorts of illustrations this evening
of what we find is a heart problem
when Jesus was dealing with the religious leaders.
They were lost.
They had a hard heart.
They had a heart problem.
If we're not careful, even as believers,
we can have a heart problem.
And we understand that,
really kind of a situation we deal with in another context,
but this evening, as we think about these things
that have been given to us, I ask this question,
then what is the remedy?
There's only one remedy for the heart problem of mankind.
And that remedy is redemption
through the blood of Jesus Christ.
Transformation, not reformation.
Amen?
We're not trying to go through some kind of step process
of whatever and clean the man up.
No, we wanna have the truth of the gospel,
which is the power of God unto salvation.
And Paul declares, you think about the Apostle Paul
in Acts chapter nine, when he's still referred to as Saul,
before his conversion, he's got letters of authority
in his hands to go and to take any of that way,
which refers to those that would be believers,
followers of Jesus Christ, come to be called Christians
by the church in Antioch,
and we find that he has the authority, he has the letters,
he's done various things.
He's been consulting unto the death of many people,
taking them and all of these things.
He had a, I mean, people knew about him.
And then he's preaching Christ
by the end of the chapter.
What happened?
Here's what he declares in 2 Corinthians five,
if any man be in Christ, he's a new creature.
Old things are passed away,
behold, all things are become new.
You know what we need?
We need people to go out and preach the gospel.
It's amazing to me that the church,
you know, the church, Paul says this,
that the church is the pillar and ground of the truth.
Right?
We have the truth of God's word.
And we have the responsibility to take the truth
of the word of God and deliver that message
to a lost and dying world.
And we see all of these things.
We see the works of the flesh.
We see the heart of mankind being revealed to us
through all of the things that are going on in our society.
And we say, have people sitting around
and trying to figure out what is it that we can do?
How can we come up with new programs?
What new thing can we do?
What millions of dollars can we spend over here?
How can we do this?
Preach the book.
But guess what?
They removed the book.
As a society, we made decisions
in the Supreme Court.
Can't have prayer, Bible, in school.
Some of you grew up in school when you read the Bible.
in school. I didn't grow up at that era, but some of you remember being in school,
public school, reading the Bible. No, we want to remove God. You can't speak about
God. You can't. And then we got what we have today, right? If you read Romans 1,
you'll see it's the, I mean, it's just the devil has no new tricks, okay? That's just
the situation we're dealing with today really is laid out for us in Romans 1, and we see
that. But let me talk about the remedy. Let me read a few passages of scripture to you.
Romans 6. Romans 6, and I need to hurry. I just got a few passages to read to you. Romans
6. Begin looking at verse number, let's read verse 17. Verse 16, let's read there first.
Know ye not that to whom ye yield yourselves servants to obey, his servants ye are to
whom ye obey, whether of sin unto death or of obedience unto righteousness. But God be
thanked that ye were the servants of sin. Speaking about past tense, right? This is
what you were. You were the servants of sin. We all can identify there, right? What did
Paul say in Philippians chapter number two? Excuse me, Ephesians chapter number two. We
all had our conversation there. We all were lost. We're all in the same boat, right? But
thank God that he's rich in mercy. And we heard the gospel, we responded to the gospel,
and we trusted Christ our Savior. He says, but God be thanked that ye were the servants
of sin, but ye have obeyed from the heart that form of doctrine which was delivered
you being then made free from sin, ye became the servants of righteousness. See, sometimes
we get mad at a sinner because they sin. But we have to recognize this if we read the entirety
here of Romans chapter number six, the reality that they are bound by their sin. Amen? They
are bound by their sin. I am thankful that I have been set free. You notice it says in
verse number 14, for sin shall not have dominion over you for you're not under the law but
under grace. Listen, we've often said that at the moment of salvation that we are delivered
from the penalty of sin. What's the penalty of sin? Death. Amen? The wage of sin is death.
I'm thankful to be delivered from the penalty of sin, that second death, right? He says
this with regard to death and hell were cast in the lake of fire. This is the second death
in Revelation chapter 20. I've been delivered from that. I've been delivered from the power
of sin. Does it mean that we don't sin? No. But we should sin a whole lot less. I'm not
bound by sin anymore. I've been delivered by the power of the Holy Spirit of God that
lives within me, who gives me the opportunity to have victory that allows me to walk in
the Spirit so that I do not fulfill the lust of the flesh. Amen? I didn't have that when
I was lost. But I'm not yet delivered from the presence of sin. One day I'll be in heaven
and so will you. There'll be no more sin. Won't it be wonderful? But we find that here
are some that are still the servants of sin. And guess what? As a servant of sin with a
heart that is unregenerate, what proceeds out of that heart? We read it in Matthew 15.
Evil thoughts, murders, adulteries, fornications, right? You read it. The works of the flesh
are these, right? The works of the flesh are manifest, and here's what they are. So if
you're a servant of sin, if you're unregenerate, that's the behavior that you're going to expect.
But those that have believed from the heart, that have obeyed from the heart that form
of the doctrine which was delivered to you, what's that? The Gospel, right? What did Paul
say in the very beginning of this letter? I am not ashamed of the Gospel of Christ.
It was the power of God unto salvation, right? He said that he was ready to preach. He was
a debtor. And we understand that as he's speaking here, he says, you believe the Gospel, therefore
you were a servant of sin, but now you're a servant of righteousness. Isn't that wonderful
to be a servant of righteousness? No longer to have to be a servant of sin. To have that
chain and ball of sin attached to us and we can't help but just do this. No. But thanks
be to God which giveth us the victory through our Lord Jesus Christ. Now we can be a servant
of righteousness, not a servant of sin. 1 Corinthians chapter number 6, turn over there.
Who's Paul writing to? He's writing to some saved people, the church in Corinth. Oh, there's
some carnal people, but there's some saved people. Amen? The reality is that he writes
here in 1 Corinthians and as he's writing these people, I mean, there's divisions and
all sorts of things going on and what have you, but we find that he's writing to them.
Notice in verse number 9 in 1 Corinthians chapter number 6, know ye not that the unrighteous
shall not inherit the kingdom of God, be not deceived. Neither fornicators, nor idolaters,
nor adulterers, nor effeminate, nor abusers of themselves with mankind, nor thieves, nor
covetous, nor drunkards, nor revilers, nor extortioners shall inherit the kingdom of
God. And such were some of you. But, aren't you so thankful for that little conjunction?
But, ye are washed. We sing the song, Are You Washed? In the blood. In the soul-cleansing
blood of the Lamb. When we sing that song in the chorus, when it says, Are You Washed?
I like to say, Yes I am. Amen? I don't know how to sing another part and do the harmony
and all that stuff, but man, I like to say, Yes I am. It's a question, Are You Washed?
Paul says, Ye are washed. But, you're sanctified. But, you're justified. In the name of the
Lord Jesus, and by the Spirit of our God. Oh, thank God for redemption. How he changed
our lives. We can testify this evening that I'm not the man I used to be. My perfect
no. I'm so thankful for 1 John 2, that I have an advocate with the Father. Jesus Christ
the Righteous. Amen? What a blessing. Here in Galatians 5, we end here. We were here
earlier looking at the works of the flesh, but notice he says in verse 16, But this I
say. This I say then, walk in the Spirit and you shall not fulfill the lusts of the flesh.
The only person that can obey the instruction of verse 16 is a saved person. I cannot stand
up and preach a message to a lost crowd. If I receive an invitation, there are times in
which I've preached in settings where I have believed that apart from me and my wife on
one occasion, there were one other person here that I knew of, there were 3 saved people.
There was another occasion that I preached, and as far as I was aware, I was the only
saved person there. Holly wasn't there. I was by myself. As far as I knew, I was the
only saved person. I would never in that setting open up Galatians 5 and verse 16 and say,
walk in the Spirit. They can't. What's the message I need to deliver them? Ye must be
born again. Right? Ye must be born again. Is that what Jesus said to Nicodemus? Jesus
didn't say to Nicodemus, walk in the Spirit. Jesus didn't tell Nicodemus to do that. No.
He said, ye must be born again. When Paul went on his missionary journeys, did he preach
walk in the Spirit? No, he preached the Gospel. Then, after they were saved, he taught them
how to walk. Read the book of Ephesians, the first 3 chapters. He deals with their conversion,
their position in Christ. Then, beginning in chapter 4, 5 and 6, he talks about their
walk. Now that you're saved, here's how you walk. You don't tell a lost person how to
clean up their life and how to walk. They can't serve God. They're lost. So, what's
the problem in our society? A lot of lost people. It's always been that way, though.
What's the solution? Go buy a ranch somewhere in Idaho and hide under the hills? No. Preach
the Gospel. Amen? It's the power of God unto salvation. Did it work for you? It worked
for me. It worked for my dad. I only use that example because I was almost 13 years old
when he got saved. Guess what? As a 13 year old, you know when something happens. Amen?
I don't need to go into all the details. What I'm saying is that the Gospel worked in that
man's life. I saw it. I didn't understand it. I understand it a whole lot more today
than I did then. It worked in my life. It worked in your life. Why wouldn't we think
it would work in somebody else's life? It is the power of God unto salvation. That word
power is a nice word. It's a word that we get our word dynamite.
dynamite for, right?
The Greek word is the same Greek word that we get our word dynamite from.
Dynamite's pretty powerful.
Amen?
You want to blow something up, Dean?
Blow something up?
He's always talking about guns and bullets and all that kind of stuff.
Get some dynamite, amen?
Blow something up.
You understand what I'm saying, though?
Listen, we have the answer.
We have the remedy.
We have the cure.
And we run around and we look at all these things that are going on in our society, and
we're listening to all of these talking heads say all of the things that they're saying
on how they're going to fix this and fix that and do this and do that, and we need more
of this, and we need the gospel.
We're never going to clean up society apart from man being converted.
Why?
Because the heart of the matter is a matter of the heart.
We've got a heart problem.
And the only thing...
See, God made this promise in Ezekiel, really to the Jews, to Israel, that He would create
in them a clean heart, a new heart, a fleshly heart.
He will do that.
But see, the Jews, Israel rejected Jesus as Messiah.
They were set aside.
The Gentiles were grafted in.
And guess what?
Now, because of the beauty of salvation, when we get saved, we get that clean heart.
We get that new heart.
What a beautiful thing.
A servant of righteousness or a servant of sin?
Walk in the Spirit?
I can't expect a lost person to do that.
I need to give them the gospel.
This evening, I hope that we would be motivated to understand that it's a heart problem and
that as believers, we have the answer.
We just need to go and take the gospel.
I understand it's not the most popular thing.
People aren't ready to receive it.
I understand that.
But I don't think there's probably ever been a time in human history that they were ready
to receive it.
You know why?
It's a spiritual battle.
Brother, you're going to Uganda.
People ask missionaries all the time this question.
I've never been a missionary, but I've heard a lot of missionaries get asked questions.
Are the people in the field that you're going to receptive to the gospel?
I've heard that question I don't know how many times.
You'll receive that question, no doubt.
Are they receptive?
The reality is that the gospel's confrontational.
We can use a subjective scale to determine the openness and the receptivity of a certain
group of people versus another group of people and so on and so forth, and we can deal with
that.
But the reality at the end of the day is that the gospel is confrontational, and we must
be willing to confront somebody with their need for Christ.
I hope this evening that each and every person that's here knows the Lord Jesus Christ as
their personal Savior, that you've been born again, that you no longer are under the penalty
of sin.
You've understood that Jesus is the only Savior.
We sing the song with the kids, one way God said to get to heaven, Jesus is the only way.
No other way, no other way.
Not by works of righteousness which we have done, for by grace we are saved through faith,
not of works as any man should boast, right?
Thank God for his mercy and his grace.
If you're not saved this evening, let me take a Bible and show you how you can know for
sure that heaven's your home.
If you know the Lord Jesus Christ, your personal Savior tonight, I hope that we would be able
to walk away saying, there's a heart problem in our society, in our world, and the only
cure is Jesus, the only cure is Jesus.
And we have been allowed of God, to use the words of Paul, that he says to the church
in Thessalonica, we have been allowed of God to preach the gospel.
And what a unique privilege that is.
Don't misunderstand it, you have a responsibility as well.
Because Jesus said, go and preach the gospel to every creature.
We've been given a unique privilege.
We've been given a responsibility.
We have the answer, and the answer is Jesus.
Let's pray.
Father, we love you this evening.
We thank you for loving us.
Thank you for the Word of God.
This evening, as we've surveyed through many portions of Scripture, bounced back and forth,
I trust that there's been a level of continuity that's helped us to acknowledge this evening
there's a heart problem.
The only way to address that problem is with the gospel of Jesus Christ.
God if there's one here that's not sure of heaven, I pray that you would help them tonight
Lord, to understand their need for Christ.
They would not leave without knowing for sure, that if they were to die, that they'd go to heaven.
Lord, I pray that every believer would be challenged this evening to understand that
the greatest cause that we can be engaged in is the cause of preaching the gospel of
Jesus Christ.
It's the only hope for mankind.
God, I pray that we would be faithful, that we would acknowledge as the Apostle Paul did
as he's writing to the church there in Rome, the believers in Rome, that he was debtor,
he was ready, he was not ashamed.
Help us Lord, I pray.
Have your will and way in this moment of invitation.
Help us to respond.
Help us God to be doers of the Word and not hearers only.
We'll thank you for it.
In Christ's name we pray.
Amen.